<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by lcollins (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- Copyright Firaxis Games 2005 -->
<!-- Modified by strategyonly -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text - New -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_SOLOMON</Tag>
		<English>Solomon</English>
		<French>Salomon</French>
		<German>Salomo</German>
		<Italian>Salomone</Italian>
		<Spanish>Salomón</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_SOLOMON_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Solomon[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]King of Israel[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD]c.1000 - 928 BC[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:1][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]The time of the reigns of David and Solomon was a golden age for Israel.  David's military skill relieved Israel of its constant war threats from surrounding nations, and Solomon's diplomatic skill maintained this empire without the need for further war.  Solomon was productive in art and science.  He wrote the Song of Solomon, Ecclesiastes, and most of the Book of Proverbs, three books found in the Bible.  Early in Solomon's reign, God promised him great wisdom. [PARAGRAPH:1] When King David was aging, he lost his mental sharpness.  His oldest son, Adonijah, attempted to seize the throne from Solomon.  Despite the fact that God had promised Solomon the throne, David, in his declining mental health, did nothing to stop Adonijah and his preparations.  Eventually, the case was brought to the attention of David by Solomon's supporters.  David immediately made Solomon king, and retired.  Normally, Solomon would kill Adonijah.  However, in an attempt to spare his life, Adonijah stole the altar of God and refused to give it back until Solomon promised to spare his life. [PARAGRAPH:1] Solomon is described as surrounding himself with luxuries because of the government's success.  Solomon established an alliance with Hiram I, king of Tyre, who helped to give Solomon the supplies he needed for the construction of the Temple.  Hiram, and an architect also named Hiram, also helped Solomon complete the construction of the Ark of the Covenant. [PARAGRAPH:1] Solomon built many houses, palaces, gardens, parks, irrigations, and public works.  The most famous of his achievements is his construction of the Temple.  Because David was unable to build the temple, he accumulated materials for future use.  Solomon imported more supplies later.  The amount was so great that, to transport the materials, Solomon conscripted a labor force of nearly 200,000 of his own people, not counting the workers of the foreign exporters.  Solomon preached sermons and worshipped at the temple.  He also prayed to God to be present at the temple.  God spoke to Solomon again, and said that if his people were unfaithful, he would destroy them.  Even so, if they confessed and repented, he would bless them again. [PARAGRAPH:1] After the completion of the temple, Solomon built many other buildings of importance in Jerusalem.  For thirteen years, he was engaged in building the royal palace on Ophel.  Solomon is also described to rebuild major cities elsewhere in Israel.  Solomon is also attributed to supplying Israel with chariots and horsemen.  Solomon's reign in Israel also resulted in great trade and riches with other countries.  Solomon's fame spread to wide that it reached the Queen of Sheba, who immediately went to Jerusalem with a caravan full of gifts.  Once she arrived, she was very impressed at his immense wealth. [PARAGRAPH:1] Though Solomon remained devout to God for most of his early life, his late was different.  Solomon married 1,000 wives, some of which were foreign.  God forbade this for fear their religious practices would corrupt the true worship of God.  This is in fact what happened to Solomon.  Solomon, out of love for his wives, builds idols for them.  Building idols was a very bad sin in the eyes of God.  Because Solomon went against God's laws, he cursed Solomon's heir, Rehoboam who lost most of the kingdom.</English>
		<French>[H1]Salomon\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Roi d'Isra%C3%ABl[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Dates :[\BOLD]c.1000 - 928 BC[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:1][BOLD]Biographie :[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]La période des règnes de David et de Solomon était un âge d'or pour l'Israel. La compétence diplomatique de l'Israel soulagée par compétence militaire de ses menaces constantes de guerre des nations environnantes, et du Solomon de David a maintenu cet empire sans besoin davantage de de guerre. Solomon était productif dans l'art et la science. Il a écrit la chanson de Solomon, d'Ecclesiastes, et de la majeure partie du livre des proverbes, trois livres trouvés dans la bible. Tôt dans le règne de Solomon, Dieu lui a promis la grande sagesse. [PARAGRAPH : 1] Quand le Roi David vieillissait, il a perdu son acuité mentale. Son fils plus âgé, Adonijah, essayé pour saisir le trône de Solomon. Malgré le fait que Dieu avait promis à Solomon le trône, David, dans sa santé mentale en baisse, n'a fait rien à arrêter Adonijah et ses préparations. Par la suite, le cas a été porté à la connaissance de David par les défenseurs de Solomon's. Roi immédiatement fait de David Solomon, et retiré. Normalement, Solomon tuerait Adonijah. Cependant, afin d'essayer d'épargner sa vie, Adonijah a volé l'autel de Dieu et a refusé de le donner en arrière jusqu'à Solomon promis pour épargner sa vie. [PARAGRAPH : 1] Solomon est décrit en tant qu'entourage avec des luxes en raison du succès du gouvernement. Solomon a établi une alliance avec Hiram I, le roi du pneu, qui a aidé à donner à Solomon les approvisionnements qu'il a eus besoin pour la construction du temple. Hiram, et un architecte a également appelé Hiram, Solomon également aidé accomplissent la construction de l'arche de l'engagement. [PARAGRAPH : 1] Solomon a établi beaucoup de maisons, palais, jardins, parcs, irrigations, et travaux publics. Le plus célèbre de ses accomplissements est sa construction du temple. Puisque David ne pouvait pas construire le temple, il a accumulé des matériaux pour le futur usage. Solomon a importé plus d'approvisionnements plus tard. La quantité était si grande que, pour transporter les matériaux, Solomon ait enrôlé une main-d'oeuvre presque des 200.000 de ses propres personnes, ne comptant pas les ouvriers des exportateurs étrangers. Solomon a prêché des sermons et a adoré au temple. Il a également prié à Dieu pour être présent au temple. Dieu a parlé à Solomon encore, et a dit que si ses personnes étaient infidèles, il les détruirait. Néanmoins, s'ils admettaient et se repentissaient, il les bénirait encore. [PARAGRAPH : 1] Après l'accomplissement du temple, Solomon a construit beaucoup d'autres bâtiments d'importance à Jérusalem. Pendant treize années, il a été occupé à construire le palais royal sur Ophel. Solomon est également décrit pour reconstruire les villes principales ailleurs en Israel. Solomon est également attribué à fournir l'Israel des chars et des cavaliers. Le règne de Solomon en Israel a également eu comme conséquence le grands commerce et richesse avec d'autres pays. La renommée de Solomon s'est écartée au loin à cela qu'elle a atteint la reine de Sheba, qui est immédiatement allée à Jérusalem avec une caravane pleine des cadeaux. Une fois qu'elle arrivait, elle a été très impressionnée à son immense richesse. [PARAGRAPH : 1] Bien que Solomon soit resté dévot à Dieu pendant la majeure partie de sa vie tôt, sien était en retard différent. Solomon a épousé 1.000 épouses, certains dont étaient étrangers. Dieu a interdit ceci pour la crainte que leurs pratiques religieuses corrompraient le culte vrai de Dieu. C'est en fait ce qui est arrivé à Solomon. Solomon, hors de l'amour pour ses épouses, établit des idoles pour eux. Établir des idoles était un péché très mauvais aux yeux de Dieu. Puisque Solomon est allé à l'encontre les lois de Dieu, il a maudit l'héritier de Solomon, Rehoboam qui a perdu la majeure partie du royaume.</French>
		<German>[H1]Salomo[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]König von Israel[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lebte:[\BOLD]c.1000 - 928 BC[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:1][BOLD]Hintergrund:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Die Zeit der Herrschaften von David und von Solomon betrug ein goldenes Alter für Israel. Davids behielt militärische Fähigkeit entlastete Israel seiner konstanten Kriegdrohungen von umgebenden Nationen und Solomons diplomatische Fähigkeit dieses Reich ohne die Notwendigkeit am weiteren Krieg bei. Solomon war in der kunst und in der Wissenschaft produktiv. Er schrieb das Lied von Solomon, von Ecclesiastes und von die meisten des Buches von Sprichwörtern, drei Bücher, die in der Bibel gefunden wurden. Früh in der Herrschaft Solomons, versprach Gott ihm große Klugheit. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Als König David alterte, verlor er seine Geistesschärfe. Sein ältester Sohn, Adonijah, versucht, um den Thron von Solomon zu ergreifen. Obwohl Gott Solomon den Thron versprochen hatte, tat David, in seiner abfallenden Geistesgesundheit, nichts, Adonijah und seine Vorbereitungen zu stoppen. Schließlich wurde der Fall zur Aufmerksamkeit von David durch Verfechter Solomons geholt. David sofort gebildeter Solomon König und zurückgezogen. Normalerweise würde Solomon Adonijah töten. Jedoch um seinem Leben zu ersparen, stahl Adonijah den Altar des Gottes und lehnte ab, ihn bis Solomon zurück zu geben, der versprochen wurde, um seinem Leben zu ersparen. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Solomon wird als Umgeben mit Luxus wegen des Erfolges der Regierung beschrieben. Solomon stellte ein Bündnis mit Hiram I, König des Reifens her, der half, Solomon die Versorgungsmaterialien zu geben, die, er für den Aufbau des Bügels benötigte. Hiram und ein Architekt nannte auch Hiram, auch geholfener Solomon führen den Aufbau der Arche der Vereinbarung durch. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Solomon errichtete viele Häuser, Paläste, Gärten, Parks, Bewässerungen und Arbeiten. Das berühmteste seiner Ausführungen ist sein Aufbau des Bügels. Weil David nicht imstande war, den Bügel zu errichten, sammelte er Materialien für zukünftigen Gebrauch an. Solomon importierte mehr Versorgungsmaterialien später. Die Menge war so groß, daß, um die Materialien zu transportieren, Solomon Arbeitskräfte von fast 200.000 seiner eigenen Leute einzog und nicht die Arbeiter der fremden Exporteure zählte. Solomon predigte Predigten und betete am Bügel an. Er betete auch zum Gott, um am Bügel anwesend zu sein. Gott sprach mit Solomon wieder und sagte, daß, wenn seine Leute unfaithful waren, er sie zerstören würde. Allerdings wenn sie bekannten und repented, würde er sie wieder segnen. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Nach der Beendigung des Bügels, errichtete Solomon viele andere Gebäude des Wertes in Jerusalem. Für dreizehn Jahre nahm er an dem Errichten des königlichen Palastes auf Ophel teil. Solomon wird auch beschrieben, um Hauptstädte in Israel anderwohin umzubauen. Solomon wird auch dem Liefern von Israel mit chariots und Reitern zugeschrieben. Herrschaft Solomons in Israel ergab auch großen Handel und riches mit anderen Ländern. Ruhm Solomons verbreitete zu weit dem, den er die Königin von Sheba erreichte, die sofort nach Jerusalem mit einem Wohnwagen ging, der von den Geschenken voll ist. Sobald sie ankam, wurde sie sehr an seiner unermeßlichen Fülle beeindruckt. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Obwohl Solomon zum Gott für die meisten seines frühen Lebens fromm blieb, war seiner spät unterschiedlich. Solomon heiratete 1.000 Frauen, von denen einige fremd waren. Gott verbot dieses für Furcht, die ihre fromme Praxis die zutreffende Anbetung des Gottes verderben würde. Dieses ist tatsächlich, was Solomon geschah. Solomon, aus Liebe für seine Frauen heraus, errichtet Idole für sie. Idole zu errichten war eine sehr schlechte Sünde in den Augen des Gottes. Weil Solomon gegen Gesetze des Gottes ging, verfluchte er Erben Solomons, Rehoboam, das die meisten des Königreiches verlor.</German>
		<Italian>[H1]Salomone[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Re di Israele[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Vita:[\BOLD]c.1000 - 928 BC[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:1][BOLD]Informazioni:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Il periodo dei regni di David e di Solomon era un'età dorata per l'Israele. L'abilità diplomatica dell'Israele alleviata abilità militare delle relative minacce costanti di guerra dalle nazioni circostanti e del Solomon del David ha effettuato questo impero senza l'esigenza di ulteriore guerra. Solomon era produttivo nell'arte e nella scienza. Ha scritto la canzone di Solomon, di Ecclesiastes e di la maggior parte del libro dei proverbi, tre libri trovati nella bibbia. Presto nel regno del Solomon, il dio gli ha promesso la saggezza grande. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Quando il re David stava invecchiando, ha perso la sua acutezza mentale. Il suo figlio più anziano, Adonijah, tentato per grippare il throne da Solomon. Malgrado il fatto che il dio prometta a Solomon il throne, David, nella sua salute mentale declinante, non ha fatto niente arrestare Adonijah e le sue preparazioni. Finalmente, il caso è stato portato all'attenzione di David dai sostenitori del Solomon. Re immediatamente fatto di David Solomon e pensionato. Normalmente, Solomon ucciderebbe Adonijah. Tuttavia, nel tentativo di risparmiare la sua vita, Adonijah ha rubato il altar del dio ed ha rifiutato di darlo indietro fino a Solomon promesso per risparmiare la sua vita. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Solomon è descritto come circondarsi con i lussi a causa del successo del governo. Solomon ha stabilito un'alleanza con Hiram I, re del pneumatico, che ha contribuito a dare a Solomon i rifornimenti che ha avuto bisogno di per la costruzione del tempiale. Hiram e un architetto inoltre ha chiamato Hiram, Solomon anche aiutato completa la costruzione dell'arca del patto. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Solomon ha sviluppato molti case, palazzi, giardini, parchi, irrigazioni e lavori pubblici. Il più famoso dei suoi successi è la sua costruzione del tempiale. Poiché David non poteva costruire il tempiale, ha accumulato i materiali per uso futuro. Solomon ha importato più successivamente più rifornimenti. L'importo era così grande che, per trasportare i materiali, Solomon conscripted lle forze di lavoro di quasi 200.000 della sua propria gente, non contando gli operai degli esportatori stranieri. Solomon ha predicato i sermons ed ha adorato al tempiale. Inoltre ha pregato al dio per essere presente al tempiale. Il dio ha parlato ancora a Solomon ed ha detto che se la sua gente fosse unfaithful, li distruggerebbe. Nondimeno, se confessassero e repented, lo benedirebbe ancora. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Dopo il completamento del tempiale, Solomon ha costruito molte altre costruzioni di importanza a Gerusalemme. Per tredici anni, è stato agganciato nella costruire il palazzo reale su Ophel. Solomon inoltre è descritto per ricostruire le città importanti altrove nell'Israele. Solomon inoltre è attribuito a fornire all'Israele i chariots ed i horsemen. Il regno del Solomon nell'Israele inoltre ha provocato il commercio e i riches grandi con altri paesi. La fama del Solomon si è sparsa largamente a quella ch'ha raggiunto la regina di Sheba, che immediatamente è andato a Gerusalemme con un caravan pieno dei regali. Una volta che arrivasse, molto è stata impressionata alla sua ricchezza immensa. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Benchè Solomon rimanga devout al dio per la maggior parte della sua vita in anticipo, suo in ritardo era differente. Solomon ha sposato 1.000 mogli, alcuni di cui erano stranieri. Il dio ha proibito a questo per timore che le loro pratiche religiose corromperebbero il culto allineare del dio. Ciò è in effetti che cosa è accaduto a Solomon. Solomon, da amore per le sue mogli, sviluppa loro i idols per. Lo sviluppo dei idols era un sin molto difettoso secondo il dio. Poiché Solomon è andato contro le leggi del dio, cursed l'erede del Solomon, Rehoboam che ha perso la maggior parte del regno.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[H1]Salomón[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Rey de Israel[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]c.1000 - 928 BC.[\BOLD][NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:1][BOLD]Historia:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]La época de los reinados de David y de Solomon era una edad de oro para Israel. La habilidad diplomática relevada habilidad militar de Israel de sus amenazas constantes de la guerra de naciones circundantes, y de Solomon de David mantuvo este imperio sin la necesidad de la guerra adicional. Solomon era productivo en arte y ciencia. Él escribió la canción de Solomon, de Ecclesiastes, y la mayor parte de del libro de proverbios, tres libros encontrados en la biblia. Temprano en el reinado de Solomon, el dios te prometió la gran sabiduría. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Cuando rey David envejecía, él perdió su agudeza mental. Su más viejo hijo, Adonijah, procurado para agarrar el trono de Solomon. A pesar de que el dios había prometido a Solomon el trono, David, en su salud mental que declinaba, no hizo nada parar Adonijah y sus preparaciones. Eventual, el caso fue traído a la atención de David por los partidarios de Solomon. Rey inmediatamente hecho de David Solomon, y retirado. Normalmente, Solomon mataría a Adonijah. Sin embargo, en un intento por ahorrar su vida, Adonijah robó el altar del dios y rechazó darlo detrás hasta Solomon prometido para ahorrar su vida. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Describen a Solomon como rodearse con los lujos debido a el éxito del gobierno. Solomon estableció una alianza con Hiram I, el rey del neumático, que ayudó a dar a Solomon las fuentes que él necesitó para la construcción del templo. Hiram, y un arquitecto también nombró a Hiram, Solomon también ayudado termina la construcción de la arca del convenio. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Solomon construyó muchas casas, palacios, jardines, parques, irrigaciones, y obras públicas. El más famoso de sus logros es su construcción del templo. Porque David no podía construir el templo, él acumuló los materiales para el uso futuro. Solomon importó más fuentes más adelante. La cantidad era tan grande que, para transportar los materiales, Solomon reclutó una mano de obra de casi 200.000 de su propia gente, no contando a los trabajadores de los exportadores extranjeros. Solomon predicó sermones y se adoraba en el templo. Él también rogó al dios para estar presente en el templo. El dios habló a Solomon otra vez, y dijo que si su gente fuera unfaithful, él los destruiría. Sin embargo, si confesaran y repented, él lo bendeciría otra vez. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Después de la terminación del templo, Solomon construyó muchos otros edificios de la importancia en Jerusalén. Por trece años, lo contrataron a construir el palacio real en Ophel. Describen a Solomon también para reconstruir ciudades importantes a otra parte en Israel. Atribuyen a Solomon también a proveer Israel de los chariots y de los jinetes. El reinado de Solomon en Israel también dio lugar a grandes comercio y riquezas con otros países. La fama de Solomon se separó de par en par a ésa que alcanzó a reina de Sheba, que fue inmediatamente a Jerusalén con una caravana llena de regalos. Una vez que ella llegara, muy la impresionaron en su abundancia inmensa. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Aunque Solomon seguía siendo devoto al dios para la mayor parte de su vida temprana, el suyo era tarde diferente. Solomon casó a 1.000 esposas, algunas de quienes eran extranjeras. El dios prohibió esto para el miedo que sus prácticas religiosas corromperían la adoración verdadera del dios. Esto es de hecho qué sucedió a Solomon. Solomon, fuera del amor para sus esposas, construye los ídolos para ellos. La construcción de ídolos era un pecado muy malo a los ojos de dios. Porque Solomon fue contra los leyes del dios, él maldijo a heredero de Solomon, Rehoboam que perdió la mayor parte de el reino.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_SOLOMON_1</Tag>
		<English>Greetings, [CT_NAME].  Be good, and we shall be good.  But remember, there is always a time to love, and a time to hate; a time of war, and a time of peace.</English>
		<French>Salutations, [CT_NAME]. Être bon, et nous serons bons. Mais se rappeler, il y a toujours un temps d'aimer, et un temps de détester ; un moment de guerre, et un moment de paix.</French>
		<German>Grüße, [CT_NAME]. Gut sein und wir sind gut. Aber sich erinnern, gibt es immer eine Zeit zu lieben und eine Zeit zu hassen; eine Zeit des Krieges und eine Zeit des Friedens.</German>
		<Italian>Saluti, [CT_NAME]. Essere buono e saremo buoni. Ma ricordar di, ci è sempre un momento di amare e un momento di odiare; un momento della guerra e un momento di pace.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Saludos, [CT_NAME]. Sed amables, y nosotros seremos amables. Pero recordad, siempre hay un tiempo para amar, y un tiempo para odiar; un tiempo para la guerra, y un tiempo para la paz.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_REFUSE_TO_TALK_LEADER_SOLOMON_1</Tag>
		<English>Your words are like fire cups for the dead.</English>
		<French>Vos mots sont comme des tasses du feu pour les morts.</French>
		<German>Deine Wörter sind wie Feuerschalen für die Toten.</German>
		<Italian>Le vostre parole sono come le tazze del fuoco per i morti.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Tus palabras son como tazas de fuego para los muertos.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_NO_PEACE_LEADER_SOLOMON_1</Tag>
		<English>The wicked shall always be punished, [CT_NAME].</English>
		<French>Le mauvais sera toujours puni, [CT_NAME</French>
		<German>Das gemeine wird immer bestraft, [CT_NAME].</German>
		<Italian>Il cattivo sarà punito sempre, [CT_NAME].</Italian>
		<Spanish>Los malvados siempre deben ser castigados, [CT_NAME].</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FR_LEADER_SOLOMON_1</Tag>
		<English>My heart gives me joy when you present yourself.</English>
		<French>Mon coeur me donne la joie quand vous vous présentez.</French>
		<German>Mein Herz gibt mir Freude, wenn du dich darstellst.</German>
		<Italian>Il mio cuore mi dà la gioia quando vi presentate.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Mi corazón se regocija con tu presencia.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FUR_LEADER_SOLOMON_1</Tag>
		<English>You dug the pit that is your wickedness.  One day, you shall fall into it.</English>
		<French>Vous avez creusé le puits qui est votre méchanceté. Un jour, vous tomberez dans lui.</French>
		<German>Du grubst die Grube, die deine Gemeinheit ist. Ein Tag, fällst du in sie.</German>
		<Italian>Avete scavato il pozzo che è il vostro wickedness. Un giorno, cadrete in esso.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Cavaste el hoyo que es tu maldad. Un día, caerás en él.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_WEAKER_SOLOMON_1</Tag>
		<English>We two are better because when we fall, the other will lift the other up.  Lifting is helping.</English>
		<French>Nous deux sommes meilleurs parce que quand nous tombons, l'autre soulèvera l'autre vers le haut. Le levage aide.</French>
		<German>Wir zwei sind besser, weil, wenn wir fallen, das andere das andere anhebt. Das Anheben hilft.</German>
		<Italian>Due siamo migliori perché quando cadiamo, l'altro alzerà l'altro in su. Il sollevamento sta aiutando.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Dos somos mejores porque cuando nos caemos, el otro levantará a otro para arriba. La elevación está ayudando.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_EQUAL_SOLOMON_1</Tag>
		<English>We are in the same position I see, so please, give help to those who need it!</English>
		<French>Nous sommes en même position que je vois, ainsi satisfaisons, donnons l'aide à ceux qui a besoin de elle !</French>
		<German>Wir sind in der gleichen Position, die ich sehe, so gefallen, geben Hilfe zu denen, die sie benötigen!</German>
		<Italian>Siamo nella stessa posizione che vedo, così soddisfiamo, diamo l'aiuto a coloro che lo ha bisogno!</Italian>
		<Spanish>¡Estamos en la misma posición que veo, tan satisfacemos, damos ayuda a las que la necesiten!</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_STRONGER_SOLOMON_1</Tag>
		<English>Getting a good name is better than any precious ointment.  Providing for others will get you that name, [CT_NAME].</English>
		<French>Obtenir un bon nom est meilleur que n'importe quel onguent précieux. Prévoir d'autres vous obtiendra que nom, [CT_NAME].</French>
		<German>Einen guten Namen zu erhalten ist besser als jede kostbare Salbe. Das Zur Verfügung stellen für andere erhält dich daß Name, [CT_NAME].</German>
		<Italian>Ottenere un buon nome è migliore di tutto l'unguento prezioso. Provvedendo ad altri li otterrà che nome, [CT_NAME].</Italian>
		<Spanish>Conseguir un buen nombre es mejor que cualquier ungüento precioso. El prever otros te conseguirá que nombre, [CT_NAME].</Spanish>
	</TEXT>	
</Civ4GameText>