<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by lcollins (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- Copyright Firaxis Games 2005 -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text - New -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_SOBIESKI</Tag>
		<English>Sobieski</English>
		<French>Sobieski</French>
		<German>Sobieski</German>
		<Italian>Sobieski</Italian>
		<Spanish>Sobieski</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_SOBIESKI_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]John III Sobieski[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]King of Poland[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived:[\BOLD] 1629 - 1696[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Born in 1629 in the small town of Olesko, John III Sobieski was the member of a notable noble family of Sobieszyn Sobieski of Clan Janina.  After Sobieski graduated from Nowodworski College in Krakow, he graduated from the philosophical faculty of the Jagiellonian University. After completing his studies, John traveled with is brother Marek Sobieski through western Europe. During that time, he learned French German and Italian, in addition to Latin.  Knowing these languages would be proved an important asset in his later military career. [PARAGRAPH: 1] After returning to Poland in 1648, John Sobieski volunteered for the army during the Chmielnicki Uprising and founded his own banner of cavalry, commanding it in the rank of Rotamaster.  John fought with distinction in the Battle of Beresteczko much so that King John II Casimir sent him to the Ottoman Empire as an emissary.  There, Sobieski learned the Tatar language and studied the Turkish military traditions and tactics.  During the Swedish invasion of Poland, John Sobieski was a member of the Greater Polish regiments lead by Krzysztof Opalinski, Palatine of Poznan, swearing alliance to the Swedish king.  However, John returned to the Polish side and fought for the king. [PARAGRAPH: 1] John III Sobieski brilliantly commanded a regiment of Tatar cavalry in the three-day long battle of Warsaw that year.  After his success, he was promoted to the title Lord Standard-Bearer of the Crown.  His military career also benefited during the Lubomirski Rebellion, where Sobieski remained loyal to the King.  In 1655, he was promoted to rank of Grand Marshal of the Crown and later to the rank of Field Hetman of the Crown.  Also in that year, he married Marie Casimire Louise de la Grange d'Arquien.  After becoming a respected commander after his great victories in the Polish-Cossack-Tatar War, he achieved the highest military rank in the Polish-Lithuanian Commonwealth, Grand Hetman of the Crown, and thus became the commander-in-chief of the Polish Army. [PARAGRAPH: 1] During the Polish-Ottoman War, Sobieski defeated the Turks in the battle of Chocim.  News of this achievement spread throughout the country, making Sobieski the most popular personality since Michal I, King of Poland had died.  On May 19 of the following year, he was elected the new monarch of the Commonwealth.  John Sobieski was crowned John III on February 2, 1676. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Sobieski now faced the hardships of reviving the war-devastated Poland-Lithuania.  Sobieski introduced a peace treaty with the Ottomans to cease the war in the south.  In 1674, Sobieski called for war against the Turks and managed to capture several fortresses, now establishing a strong southern border for Poland in the Ukraine.  In 1675, the Tatars attempted to retake the strategic town of Zorawno, but were unsuccessful.  Thus, a peace treaty was signed soon after.  With the signing of peace treaties, focus was turned from war to the reparation of the country and strengthening the royal authority.  Although constantly stressed with Austria and Brandenburg, Sobieski reformed the Polish military.  The military was reorganized, infantry's pikes replaced with battle-axes, and Polish cavalry adopting the formations of hussars and dragoons.  Sobieski also increased the number of guns and developed new tactics for artillery. [PARAGRAPH: 1] At this time, Sobieski made several attempts to strengthen Poland against its enemies.  In the end, he decided to ally himself with Leopold I, Holy Roman Emperor.  He also joined the Holy League initiated by Pope Innocent XI to preserve Christendom.  The alliance, although aimed against the Turks, had the advantage of gaining support for the defense of Poland's southern borders.  After Polish spies uncovered Turkish preparations for a military campaign, Sobieski fortified the cities of Lwow and Krakow, which he feared were the targets of the Turkish campaigns. [PARAGRAPH: 1] One of Sobieski's greatest successes was in the victory at the Battle of Vienna, in joined command of Polish, Austrian, and German troops.  Together, they fought the invading Turks under Kara Mustafa.  He led a full attack of 81,000 men against 130,000 Turks which were divided between the attacking of the town and fighting of the united army.  Sobieski later led four hussar cavalry groups into a charge down the hillside.  Soon, the Turkish battle line was broken and the Battle of Vienna ended. [PARAGRAPH: 1] King John III Sobieski died in Wilanow, Poland on June 17, 1696.  He and his wife, who died in 1716 in France, are buried together in Wawel Cathedral in Krakow, Poland.  He was succeeded by Augustus II, whose death lead to a struggle for the crown of Poland, known as the War of the Polish Succession.</English>
		<French>[H1]Jean III Sobieski[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Roi de Pologne[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Régné:[\BOLD] 1629 - 1696[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Biographie:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Né en 1629 dans la petite ville de Olesko, Jean III Sobieski était le membre d'une remarquable famille noble de l'd'Sobieszyn Sobieski Clan Janina. Après Sobieski diplômé de Nowodworski College à Cracovie, il est diplômé de la faculté philosophique de l'Université Jagellon. Après avoir terminé ses études, John voyagé avec Marek Sobieski est frère à travers l'Europe occidentale. Pendant ce temps, il a appris le français en allemand et en italien, en plus de latine. Connaissant ces langues serait avéré un atout important dans ses dernières carrière militaire. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Après son retour en Pologne en 1648, Jean Sobieski porté volontaire pour l'armée pendant la Chmielnicki Uprising et a fondé sa propre bannière de la cavalerie, commandant dans le rang de Rotamaster. John combattu avec distinction dans la bataille de Beresteczko au point que le roi Jean II Casimir lui a envoyé à l'Empire ottoman comme un émissaire. Là, Sobieski appris la langue tatare et étudié les traditions militaires turcs et tactiques. Au cours de l'invasion de la Pologne suédois, Jean Sobieski a été membre de la Grande Pologne régiments de plomb par Krzysztof Opalinski, Palatin de Posnanie, jurant alliance pour le roi suédois. Toutefois, John retourné à la partie polonaise et lutté pour le roi. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Jean III Sobieski brillamment commandé un régiment de cavalerie tatare, dans les trois jours longue bataille de Varsovie cette année. Après son succès, il a été promu au titre Seigneur Standard - porteur de la Couronne. Sa carrière militaire a également bénéficié au cours de la rébellion Lubomirski, où Sobieski restés fidèles au Roi. En 1655, il a été promu au grade de Grand Maréchal de la Couronne et, plus tard, au rang de Hetman Champ de la Couronne. Toujours dans la même année, il épouse Marie Casimire Louise de La Grange d'Arquien. Devenu commandant respectée après sa grande victoire en polonais - Cosaques - Tartare de guerre, il a atteint le plus haut rang dans l'armée polonais-lituanien, Grand Hetman de la Couronne, et est ainsi devenu le commandant en chef de l'armée polonaise . [PARAGRAPH: 1] Au cours de la guerre polonais - ottomane, les Turcs Sobieski défaite dans la bataille de Chocim. Actualités de cette réalisation, réparties dans l'ensemble du pays, faisant de Sobieski personnalité la plus populaire depuis Michal I, Roi de Pologne avaient trouvé la mort. Le 19 mai de l'année suivante, il a été élu le nouveau monarque du Commonwealth. Jean Sobieski a été couronné Jean III, le 2 février 1676. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Sobieski maintenant faire face aux rigueurs de la relance de la guerre a dévasté la Pologne. Sobieski présenté un traité de paix avec les Turcs à mettre un terme à la guerre dans le sud. En 1674, Sobieski appelé à la guerre contre les Turcs et ont réussi à capturer plusieurs forteresses, actuellement en train de créer une forte frontière sud de la Pologne en Ukraine. En 1675, les Tatars tenté de reprendre la ville stratégique de Zorawno, mais en vain. Ainsi, un traité de paix a été signé peu de temps après. Avec la signature de traités de paix, l'accent a été transformé de la guerre à la réparation du pays et le renforcement de l'autorité royale. Bien que constamment souligné auprès de l'Autriche et de Brandebourg, le polonais Sobieski réforme militaire. Le militaire a été réorganisée, l'infanterie de piques remplacés par des haches de guerre, et l'adoption de la cavalerie polonaise formations de hussards et dragons. Sobieski également augmenté le nombre de fusils et mis au point de nouvelles tactiques de l'artillerie. [PARAGRAPH: 1] À l'heure actuelle, Sobieski tenté à plusieurs reprises de renforcer la Pologne contre ses ennemis. À la fin, il a décidé de s'allier avec Léopold Ier du Saint-Empire. Il a également rejoint la Sainte Ligue initiée par le pape Innocent XI de préserver la chrétienté. L'alliance, bien que dirigée contre les Turcs, avait l'avantage d'avoir le soutien pour la défense des frontières méridionales de la Pologne. Après avoir découvert des espions polonais turc préparation d'une campagne militaire, Sobieski fortifié les villes de Lwow et Cracovie, dont il craignait étaient les cibles des campagnes turques. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Sobieski Une des plus grandes réussites a été, lors de la victoire à la bataille de Vienne, est entré dans le commandement de polonais, autrichien, et les troupes allemandes. Ensemble, ils ont lutté contre les envahisseurs turcs sous Mustapha Kara. Il a dirigé une attaque de 81.000 hommes contre 130.000 Turcs, qui étaient partagés entre l'attaque de la ville et de la lutte contre l'armée unifiée. Sobieski plus tard conduit hussarde quatre groupes de cavalerie dans une redevance sur la colline. Bientôt, la bataille ligne turc a été rompu et de la bataille de Vienne clos. [PARAGRAPH: 1] roi Jean III Sobieski est décédé à Wilanow, de la Pologne le 17 juin 1696. Lui et son épouse, qui est mort en 1716 en France, sont enterrés ensemble dans la cathédrale de Wawel à Cracovie, Pologne. Il a été remplacé par Auguste II, dont la mort aboutir à une lutte pour la couronne de Pologne, connu sous le nom de la guerre de Succession de Pologne.</French>
		<German>[H1]Johann III Sobieski[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]K&#246;nig von Polen[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Angeordnet:[\BOLD] 1629 - 1696[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Hintergrund:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Geboren im 1629 in der kleinen Stadt Olesko, John III Sobieski war Mitglied einer bemerkenswerten Adelsfamilie Sobieszyn Sobieski der Clan Janina. Nach Sobieski absolvierte Nowodworski College in Krakau, er sein Studium an der philosophischen Fakultät der Jagiellonen-Universität. Nach Abschluss seines Studiums, John reiste mit Bruder ist Marek Sobieski durch Westeuropa. Während dieser Zeit hat er gelernt, Französisch und Italienisch, zusätzlich zu Latein. Wissen, diese Sprachen würde sich ein wichtiger Aktivposten in seinen späteren militärische Karriere. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Nach seiner Rückkehr nach Polen in 1648, John Sobieski freiwillig für die Armee während des Chmielnicki Aufstands und gründete seine eigene Fahne der Kavallerie, Kommandeur es in den Rang eines Rotamaster. John kämpfte mit Auszeichnung in der Schlacht von Beresteczko viel, so dass König Johann II. Kasimir schickte ihn zu dem Osmanischen Reich als ein Gesandter. Dort lernte Sobieski der tatarischen Sprache und studierte das türkische Militär Traditionen und Taktik. Während der schwedischen Invasion Polens, John Sobieski war ein Mitglied der Greater polnischen Regimenter der Leitung von Krzysztof Opalinski, Palatine von Poznan, Vereidigung Allianz für die schwedische König. Allerdings, John wieder auf der polnischen Seite und kämpfte für den König. [PARAGRAPH: 1] John III Sobieski brillant befehligte ein Regiment von Tataren Kavallerie in der drei Tage langen Schlacht von Warschau in diesem Jahr. Nach seinem Erfolg wurde er auf den Titel Lord Standard - Inhaberaktien der Krone. Seine militärische Karriere profitierte auch während der Lubomirski Rebellion, wo Sobieski blieb loyal zum König. In 1655 wurde er zum Rang eines Grand Marshal der Krone und später in den Rang eines Field Hetman der Krone. Auch in diesem Jahr heiratete er Marie Casimire Louise en la Grange d'Arquien. Nachdem sich ein geachteter Kommandeur nach seiner großen Siege in der polnischen - Kosaken - Tatarisch Krieges, erreichte er den höchsten militärischen Rang in der polnisch-litauischen Commonwealth, Grand Hetman der Krone, und so wurde der Kommandant in der Oberbefehlshaber der polnischen Armee . [PARAGRAPH: 1] In der polnischen Osmanischen Krieg, Sobieski besiegte die Türken in der Schlacht von Chocim. Nachrichten von diesem Erfolg auf der ganzen Land, wodurch Sobieski die beliebteste Persönlichkeit seit Michal I., König von Polen gestorben war. Am 19. Mai des folgenden Jahres wurde er zum neuen König des Commonwealth. John Sobieski wurde gekrönt Johannes III am 2. Februar 1676. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Sobieski nun die Nöte der Wiederbelebung der vom Krieg verwüsteten Polen - Litauen. Sobieski einen Friedensvertrag mit den Osmanen zu beenden den Krieg im Süden des Landes. In 1674, Sobieski fordert für den Krieg gegen die Türken und verwaltet werden, um mehrere Festungen, die jetzt zur Gründung einer starken südlichen Grenze für Polen in der Ukraine. In 1675, die Tataren versucht zu wiederholen, die strategische Stadt Zorawno, doch blieben erfolglos. So wird ein Friedensvertrag unterzeichnet wurde bald nach. Mit der Unterzeichnung der Friedensverträge, gefasst wurde vom Krieg zum Wiederaufbau des Landes und die Stärkung der königlichen Autorität. Obwohl stets betont, mit Österreich und Brandenburg, Sobieski Reform des polnischen Militärs. Das Militär wurde reorganisiert, die Infanterie Hechte ersetzt Schlacht Achsen, und polnische Kavallerie über die Verabschiedung der Formationen der Husaren und Dragoner. Sobieski auch die Zahl der Waffen und entwickelten neue Taktik für die Artillerie. [PARAGRAPH: 1] In dieser Zeit, Sobieski mehrere Versuche zur Stärkung der Polen gegen ihre Feinde. Am Ende entschied er sich zu verbünden sich mit Leopold I., Kaiser des Heiligen Römischen Reiches. Er trat auch der Heilige Liga, die von Papst Innozenz XI zur Erhaltung des Christentums. Die Allianz, obwohl die gegen die Türken, hatte den Vorteil, der sich für die Verteidigung der südlichen Grenzen Polens. Nach polnischen Spione aufgedeckt türkischen Vorbereitungen für eine militärische Kampagne, die Sobieski befestigten Städten Lemberg und Krakau, die er befürchtete, wurden die Ziele der türkischen Kampagnen. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Einer der größten Erfolge Sobieski wurde bei der Erringung des Sieges in der Schlacht von Wien, in den verbundenen Befehl der polnischen, österreichischen und deutschen Truppen. Gemeinsam kämpften sie Invasion der Türken unter Kara Mustafa. Er führte ein Angriff von 81.000 Männern gegen 130.000 Türken, die zwischen dem Angriff auf die Stadt und die Bekämpfung des vereinten Armee. Sobieski später führte vier Husaren Kavallerie Gruppen eine Gebühr in die Hügel. Bestellt, die türkische Schlacht wurde gebrochen und der Schlacht von Wien beendet. [PARAGRAPH: 1] König Johann III Sobieski starb in Wilanow, Polen am 17. Juni 1696. Er und seine Frau, die starb 1716 in Frankreich, begraben gemeinsam im Dom Wawel in Krakau, Polen. Er wurde von Augustus II, dessen Tosssd führen zu einem Kampf um die Krone von Polen, bekannt als der Krieg von der polnischen Erbfolgekrieg.</German>
		<Italian>[H1]Giovanni III Sobieski[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Re di Polonia[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Regolato:[\BOLD] 1629 - 1696[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Informazioni:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Nato nel 1629 nel piccolo comune di Olesko, Giovanni III Sobieski è stato il membro di una notevole nobile di Sobieszyn Sobieski famiglia di Clan Janina. Dopo Sobieski laureato da Nowodworski College di Cracovia, si è laureato alla Facoltà di filosofia dell'Università di Jagellonica. Dopo aver completato i suoi studi, viaggiò con Giovanni è fratello di Marek Sobieski attraverso l'Europa occidentale. Durante questo tempo, ha imparato francese tedesco e italiano, oltre al latino. La conoscenza di queste lingue sarebbe rivelata un importante patrimonio nella sua successiva carriera militare. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Dopo il ritorno in Polonia, nel 1648, Giovanni Sobieski volontari per l'esercito durante la Chmielnicki Uprising e fondato il suo vessillo di cavalleria, a comandare in grado di Rotamaster. Giovanni combattuto con distinzione nella Battaglia di Beresteczko molto in modo che il Re Giovanni II Casimiro lo inviò a ottomano come un emissario. Esiste, Sobieski imparato la lingua e tartaro studiato il turco tradizioni militari e tattiche. Durante l'invasione svedese di Polonia, Giovanni Sobieski è stato membro della Greater polacco reggimenti piombo da Krzysztof Opalinski, Palatine di Poznan, giurare alleanza per il re svedese. Tuttavia, Giovanni restituiti al polacco lato e lottato per il re. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Giovanni III Sobieski brillantemente comandato un reggimento di cavalleria Tataro nella tre giorni di lunga battaglia di Varsavia, che anno. Dopo il suo successo, è stato promosso per il titolo Signore - Standard portatore della Corona. La sua carriera militare anche beneficiato durante il Lubomirski Ribellione, dove Sobieski rimasta fedele al Re. Nel 1655 è stato promosso al rango di Grand Marshal della Corona e, successivamente, al rango di Campo Hetman della Corona. Inoltre, in tale anno, sposò Marie Casimire Luisa de la Grange d'Arquien. Dopo diventando un comandante rispettato dopo la sua grande vittorie in polacco - cosacco - Tataro guerra, ha raggiunto il più alto grado militare nella Polacco-Lituano, Grand Hetman della Corona, e quindi è diventato il comandante in capo dell 'esercito polacco . [PARAGRAPH: 1] Durante la guerra polacca - ottomano, Sobieski sconfitto i turchi nella battaglia di Chocim. Notizie di questo risultato diffusione in tutto il paese, rendendo più popolari Sobieski personalità dal Michal I, re di Polonia era morto. Il 19 maggio dell'anno successivo, è stato eletto il nuovo monarca del Commonwealth. Giovanni Sobieski è stato coronato Giovanni III il 2 febbraio 1676. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Sobieski ora di fronte alla difficoltà di ravvivare la guerra - devastato Polonia - Lituania. Sobieski introdotto un trattato di pace con gli ottomani, a cessare la guerra nel sud. Nel 1674, Sobieski chiamato per la guerra contro i turchi e sono riusciti a catturare numerose fortezze, ora che istituisce un forte frontiera meridionale per la Polonia in Ucraina. Nel 1675, i tartari tentato di riconquistare la strategica comune di Zorawno, ma non hanno avuto successo. Così, un trattato di pace è stato firmato subito dopo. Con la firma dei trattati di pace, focus è stato trasformato dalla guerra per il risarcimento del paese e di rafforzare il potere reale. Sebbene costantemente sottolineato con l'Austria e Brandeburgo, Sobieski riforma militare polacco. Il militare è stata riorganizzata, fanteria's pikes sostituito con assi di battaglia, e la cavalleria polacca adottando la formazioni di ussari e dragoons. Sobieski anche aumentato il numero delle armi e sviluppato nuove tattiche per artiglieria. [PARAGRAPH: 1] In questo momento, Sobieski fatto diversi tentativi di rafforzare la Polonia contro i suoi nemici. Alla fine, ha deciso di allearsi con se stesso Leopoldo I, Imperatore del Sacro Romano Impero. Ha aderito anche la Santa Lega avviato da Papa Innocenzo XI per preservare la cristianità. L'alleanza, anche se indirizzata contro i Turchi, ha avuto il vantaggio di un maggior sostegno per la difesa dei confini meridionali della Polonia. Dopo aver scoperto spie polacco turco preparativi per una campagna militare, Sobieski fortificato le città di Lwow e Cracovia, che egli teme che sono stati gli obiettivi del Turco campagne. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Sobieski Uno dei più grandi successi è stata la vittoria nella battaglia di Vienna, nella parte del comando polacco, austriaco, e le truppe tedesche. Insieme, hanno combattuto invasori turchi sotto Kara Mustafa. Egli ha portato a pieno attacco di 81.000 uomini contro 130.000 turchi, che sono stati ripartiti tra le attacco del comune e di lotta contro l'esercito unito. Sobieski successivamente portato ussaro cavalleria quattro gruppi in una tassa sulla collina. Presto, il turco era rotto linea di battaglia e la battaglia di Vienna si è concluso. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Re Giovanni III Sobieski morto in Wilanow, Polonia, il 17 giugno 1696. Lui e la moglie, che morì nel 1716 in Francia, sono sepolti insieme nella cattedrale del Wawel a Cracovia, in Polonia. Egli era riuscito da Augusto II, la cui morte condurre a una lotta per la corona di Polonia, conosciuto come la guerra di successione polacca.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[H1]Juan III Sobieski[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Rey de Polonia[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Gobernado:[\BOLD]  1629 - 1696[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Historia:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Nacido en 1629 en la pequeña ciudad de Olesko, Juan III Sobieski fue el miembro de una notable familia noble de Sobieszyn Sobieski Clan de Janina. Después de Sobieski se graduó de Nowodworski universidad de Cracovia, se graduó de la facultad de filosofía de la Universidad Jagellónica. Después de completar sus estudios, viajó con Juan es hermano Marek Sobieski a través de Europa occidental. Durante ese tiempo, él aprendió francés alemán e italiano, además del latín. Sabiendo estas lenguas sería demostrado ser un activo importante en su posterior carrera militar. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Después de regresar a Polonia en 1648, John Sobieski ofreció voluntariamente para el ejército durante la Chmielnicki Uprising y fundó su propia bandera de la caballería, al mando de ella en el rango de Rotamaster. John luchó con distinción en la Batalla de Beresteczko es así que el rey Juan II le envió a Casimir el Imperio Otomano como un emisario. Allí, Sobieski aprendido la lengua tártara y estudió las tradiciones militares turcos y las tácticas. Sin embargo, John regresó al lado polaco y luchó por el rey. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Juan III Sobieski brillantemente al mando de un regimiento de caballería en el tártaro de tres días de duración larga batalla de Varsovia ese año. Después de su éxito, fue promovido al título Lord Estándar - Portador de la Corona. Su carrera militar también se benefició durante la Rebelión Lubomirski, donde Sobieski permanecieron leales al rey. En 1655, fue promovido al rango de Gran Mariscal de la Corona y más tarde al rango de Hetman sobre el terreno de la Corona. También en ese año, se casó con Marie Casimire Luisa de la Grange de Arquien. Después de convertirse en un respetado comandante después de su gran victoria en el polaco - Cosacos - tártaro Guerra, que logró el más alto rango militar en la Comunidad de Polonia y Lituania, el Gran Hetman de la Corona, y, por tanto, se convirtió en el comandante en jefe del Ejército polaco . [PARAGRAPH: 1] Durante la Guerra polaco - otomano, Sobieski derrotó a los turcos en la batalla de Chocim. Noticias de este logro repartidos por todo el país, haciendo Sobieski la personalidad más popular desde Michal I, Rey de Polonia había muerto. El 19 de mayo del año siguiente, fue elegido como el nuevo monarca de la Comunidad. John John Sobieski III fue coronado el 2 de febrero de 1676. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Sobieski ahora enfrenta las dificultades de la guerra, la reactivación de la devastada Polonia - Lituania. Sobieski presentó un tratado de paz con los otomanos a poner fin a la guerra en el sur. En 1674, Sobieski llamado en favor de la guerra contra los turcos y lograron capturar varias fortalezas, ahora se establece una fuerte frontera meridional de Polonia en Ucrania. En 1675, los tártaros intentó retomar la ciudad estratégica de Zorawno, pero no tuvieron éxito. Por lo tanto, un tratado de paz se firmó poco después. Con la firma de los tratados de paz, se centra de la guerra a la reparación del país y el fortalecimiento de la autoridad real. Aunque subrayó constantemente con Austria y Brandeburgo, Sobieski reformado el militar polaco. Los militares se reorganizó, de la infantería de lucios reemplazado con hachas de batalla, la caballería polaca y la adopción de las formaciones de hussars y dragones. Sobieski también aumentó el número de cañones y desarrollado nuevas tácticas de la artillería. [PARAGRAPH: 1] En este momento, Sobieski hecho varios intentos de fortalecer Polonia contra sus enemigos. Al final, él decidió aliarse con Leopoldo I, rey de España. También se unió a la Liga Santa, iniciado por el Papa Inocencio XI de preservar la cristiandad. La alianza, aunque dirigidas contra los turcos, tuvo la ventaja de obtener apoyo para la defensa de la frontera meridional de Polonia. Después de espías polacos descubrieron los preparativos de Turquía para una campaña militar, Sobieski fortificada de las ciudades de Lwow y Cracovia, que temía que fueron el blanco de campañas de los turcos. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Sobieski Uno de los mayores éxitos fue en la victoria en la Batalla de Viena, se unió en el mando de polaco, austriaco, y las tropas alemanas. Juntos, ellos combatieron a los invasores turcos en virtud de Kara Mustafa. Dirigió un ataque de 81.000 hombres contra 130.000 turcos, que se dividieron entre el ataque de la ciudad y de la lucha contra el ejército unido. Sobieski más tarde la causa de que cuatro hussar caballería grupos en un cargo por la ladera. Pronto, la línea de batalla de Turquía tras la ruptura de la Batalla de Viena terminado. [PARAGRAPH: 1] El rey Juan III Sobieski murió en Wilanow, de Polonia el 17 de junio de 1696. Él y su esposa, que falleció en 1716 en Francia, están enterrados juntos en la catedral del Wawel en Cracovia, Polonia. Fue sucedido por Augusto II, cuya muerte conducir a una lucha por la corona de Polonia, conocida como la Guerra de Sucesión de Polonia.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_SOBIESKI_1</Tag>
		<English>Greetings! I am [OUR_NAME] of the [OUR_EMPIRE].  Before you come to me, always remember: no labour, no oilcakes.</English>
		<French>Bonjour! Je suis [OUR_NAME] de la [OUR_EMPIRE]. Avant de venir à moi, toujours se rappeler: pas de travail, pas de oilcakes.</French>
		<German>Greetings! Ich bin [OUR_NAME] der [OUR_EMPIRE]. Bevor Sie zu mir kommen, immer daran erinnern: keine Arbeit, keine oilcakes.</German>
		<Italian>Saluti! Sono [OUR_NAME] del [OUR_EMPIRE]. Prima di venire a me, ricordate sempre: nessun lavoro, nessuna panelli.</Italian>
		<Spanish>¡Saludos! Me [OUR_NAME] de la [OUR_EMPIRE]. Antes de venir a mí, recordar siempre: no hay trabajo, no se oilcakes.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>