<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by lcollins (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- Copyright Firaxis Games 2005 -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text - New -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_MEGARON</Tag>
		<English>Megaron</English>
		<French>Mégaron</French>
		<German>Megaron</German>
		<Italian>Megaron</Italian>
		<Spanish>Megaron</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
        <TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_MEGARON_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The megaron was the "Great Hall" in Minoan-Mycenaean society.  It was used for many purposes, including poetry, feasts, worshipping gods, sacrifice, and counsels of war.  A famous megaron is the reception hall of the king in the Palace of Tyrins.  The megaron is a rectangular hall with a two-collumned porch.</English>
		<French>[TAB]Le megaron était le « grand Hall » dans la société de Minoan-Mycenaean. Il a été employé pour beaucoup de buts, y compris la poésie, régals, dieux adorants, sacrifice, et avocats-conseils de guerre. Un megaron célèbre est le hall de réception du roi dans le palais de Tyrins. Le megaron est un hall rectangulaire avec a two-collumned le porche. </French>
		<German>[TAB]Das megaron war der „große Hall“ in der Minoan-Mycenaean Gesellschaft. Es wurde für viele Zwecke, einschließlich Poesie, Feste, anbetende Götter, Opfer und Ratschläge des Krieges verwendet. Ein berühmtes megaron ist die Aufnahmehalle des Königs im Palast von Tyrins. Das megaron ist eine rechteckige Halle mit a two-collumned Portal.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB]Il megaron era “il Corridoio grande„ nella società di Minoan-Mycenaean. È stato usato per molti scopi, compreso la poesia, le festività, i dii d'adorazione, il sacrificio ed i consulenti legali della guerra. Un megaron famoso è il corridoio di ricezione del re nel palazzo di Tyrins. Il megaron è un corridoio rettangolare con la a two-collumned il portico.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB]El megaron era el “gran Pasillo” en la sociedad de Minoan-Mycenaean. Fue utilizado para muchos propósitos, incluyendo poesía, los banquetes, los dioses que se adoraban, el sacrificio, y los consejos de la guerra. Un megaron famoso es el pasillo de la recepción del rey en el palacio de Tyrins. El megaron es un pasillo rectangular con a two-collumned el pórtico. </Spanish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>