<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<resources>
  <string name="TXT_KEY_LEADER_CIVILIS_PEDIA">[H1]Julius Civilis[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Leader of the Batavii[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD] 69 AD[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]  Gaius Julius Civilis was the leader of the Batavian rebellion against the Romans in 69. By his nomen, it can be told that he (or one of his male ancestors) was made a Roman citizen (and thus, the tribe a Roman vassal) by either Augustus or Caligula.[NEWLINE][TAB] He was twice imprisoned on a charge of rebellion, and narrowly escaped execution. During the disturbances that followed the death of Nero, he took up arms under pretence of siding with Vespasian and induced the inhabitants of his native country to rebel. The Batavians, who had rendered valuable aid under the early emperors, had been well treated in order to attach them to the cause of Rome. They were exempt from tribute, but were obliged to supply a large number of men for the army, and the burden of conscription and the oppressions of provincial governors were important incentives to revolt. The Batavians were immediately joined by several neighbouring German tribes, the most important of whom were the Frisians.[NEWLINE][TAB]  The Roman garrisons near the Rhine were driven out, and twenty-four ships captured. Two legions under Mummius Lupercus were defeated at Castra Vetera (near the modern Xanten) and surrounded. Eight cohorts of Batavian veterans joined their countrymen, and the troops sent by Vespasian to the relief of Vetera threw in their lot with them.[NEWLINE][TAB]The result of these accessions to the forces of Civilis was rising in Gaul.  Hordeonius Flaccus was murdered by his troops, and the whole Roman forces were induced by two commanders of the Gallic auxiliaries - Julius Classicus and Julius Tutor - to revolt from Rome and join Civilis.  The whole of Gaul thus practically declared itself independant, and the foundation of a new kingdom of Gaul was comptemplated.  The prophetess Veleda predicted the compelte success of Civilis and the fall of the Roman Empire.  But disputes broke out amoungst the different tribes and rendered co-operation impossible; Vespian, having successfully ended the civil war, called upon Civilis to lay down his arms, and on his refusal resolved to take strong measures for the suppression of the revolt.[NEWLINE][TAB]The arrival of Quintus Petillius Cerialis with a strong force awed the Gauls and mutinous troops into submission; Civilis was defeated at Augusta Treverorum (Trier, Trиves) and Castra Vetera, and forced to withdraw to the island of the Batavians. He finally came to an agreement with Cerialis whereby his countrymen obtained certain advantages, and resumed amicable relations with Rome. From this time Civilis disappears from history.</string>
  <string name="TXT_KEY_LEADER_CUZA_PEDIA">[H1]Alexandru Ioan Cuza[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Ruler of the Romanian Kingdom[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD] Born March 20 1820 - Died May 15 1873[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Alexandru Cuza belonged to the traditional noble (boier) class, the Orthodox Christian Romanian upper class that had come into control of the local governments of Wallachia and Moldavia, and retained traditional control of the country\'s land, the only key to pre-industrial wealth. Cuza received an urbane European education.  In 1848, the year of the European Revolutions, Moldovia and Wallachia fell into revolt.  In Moldavia the unrest was quickly suppressed, but in Wallachia the revolutionaries took power and governed during the summer. Young Cuza played a prominent enough part to establish his liberal credentials (compared to most nobility) and to be shipped to Vienna as a prisoner, where he soon made his escape.[NEWLINE][TAB]Afterwards however, following a brief career in the Moldavian army, he became minister of war in 1858, and represented Galati in the assembly at Iasi, acting under the guarantee of the European Powers in the wake of the Crimean war to nominate a prince for Moldavia. Cuza was a prominent speaker in the debates and strongly advocated the union of the two Danubian principalities, Moldavia and Walachia. In default of a foreign prince, he was himself elected prince of Moldavia (Moldova) on January 17, 1859 (January 5, Julian) and of Wallachia (Tara Romвneasca) on February 5, 1859.[NEWLINE][TAB]Thus Colonel A. I. Cuza achieved a de facto union of the two Romanian principalites. The Powers backtracked, Napoleon III of France remaining supportive, while the Austro-Hungarian ministry withheld approval of such a union at the Congress of Paris (October 18, 1858); partly as a consequence Cuza\'s authority was not recognized by his nominal suzerain, the sultan of Turkey, until the December 23, 1861.[NEWLINE]The Union was formally declared three years later, on February 5, 1862 (January 24, Julian), the new country bearing the name of Romania, with Bucharest as its capital city.[NEWLINE][TAB]Cuza was not a diplomatic politician, and lacked the traditional royal background, but he knew how to choose progressive ministers and had an intelligent ear for advice. Immediately he gained the sultan\'s assent to a single unified parliament and cabinet for his lifetime, in recognition of the complexity of the task. Thus he was the political embodiment of a unified Romania, for his lifetime.[NEWLINE][TAB]Assisted by his councilor Mihail Kogalniceanu, an intellectual leader of the 1848 revolution, Cuza initiated a series of reforms that contributed to the modernization of Romanian society and of state structures.The drastic reforms which he imposed to bring Romania fully into the 19th century impinged upon all classes and alienated his more influential subjects.[NEWLINE][TAB]Cuza failed in his effort to create an alliance of prosperous peasants and a strong liberal prince, ruling as a benevolent despot in the style of Napoleon III. Financial distress supervened, there was an awkward scandal that revolved around his mistress, and popular discontent culminated in revolution. Cuza was forced to abdicate by the so-called \"Monstrous Coalition\" of conservatives and radical liberals. At four o\'clock on the morning of February 22, 1866, a group of military conspirators broke into the palace, and compelled the prince to sign his abdication. On the following day they conducted him safely across the frontier.Cuza spent the remainder of his life in exile, chiefly in Paris, Vienna and Wiesbaden. He died at Heidelberg on May 15, 1873.</string>
  <string name="TXT_KEY_LEADER_EUCRATIDES_PEDIA">[H1]Eucratides I[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Greco-Bactrian King[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Ruled: [\BOLD] 171 BCE145 BCE[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Eucratides came to the throne by overthrowing the dynasty of Euthydemus I in Bactria, whose son Demetrius was conquering northwestern India. The king Eucratides dethroned in Bactria was probably Antimachus I.  It is unclear whether Eucratides was a Bactrian official who raised a rebellion, or, according to some scholars, a cousin of the Seleucid king Antiochus IV Epiphanes who was trying to regain the Bactrian territory. Justin explains that Eucratides acceeded to the throne at about the same time as Mithridates, whose rule is accurately known to have started in 171 BCE, thereby giving an approximate date for the accession of Eucratides.  Having become master of Bactria, Eucratides also conquered the western parts of the Indo-Greek kingdom. According to the single remaining source, Roman historian Justin, Eucratides defeated Demetrius of India, but the identity of this king is uncertain: he could be either Demetrius I, or Demetrius II.  Numismatic evidence suggests that Eucratides I was a contemporary of the Indo-Greek kings Apollodotus I, Antimachus II and Menander I. In any case, Eucratides\' advances into India are proved by his abundant bilingual coinage.  In the west the Parthian king Mithradates I began to enlarge his kingdom and attacked Eucratides; the city of Herat fell in 167 BC and the Parthians succeeded in conquering two provinces between Bactria and Parthia, called by Strabo the country of Aspiones and Turiua.Justin ends his account of Eucratides\' life by claiming that the warlike king was murdered on his way back from India by his own son (either Eucratides II or Heliocles I, although there are speculations that it could be his enemy\'s son Demetrius II), who hated his father so much that he dragged his dead body after his chariot.  The murder of Eucratides probably brought about a civil war amongst the members of the dynasty. The successors to Eucratides were Eucratides II and Heliocles I (145130 BCE), who was the last Greek king to reign in Bactria. Once the Yuezhi tribes overpowered Heliocles, the Greco-Bactrians lost control of the provinces north of the Hindu Kush.  However, the rule of the Indo-Greeks  over territories south of the Hindu Kush lasted for a further 150 years, ultimately collapsing under the pressure of the Yьeh-chih and Scythian (Saka) invasions in around 10 BCE.</string>
  <string name="TXT_KEY_LEADER_MACDONALD_PEDIA">[H1]Sir John A. MacDonald [\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Prime Minister of Canada[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD] 1815 - 1891[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]The Right Honourable Sir John Alexander MacDonald was the first Prime Minister of Canada from July 1, 1867 to November 5, 1873 and October 17, 1878 to June 6, 1891. BY 1864 he was the leader of arguably the largest British colony in the surrounding area and had the power to help enact agreements to confederate the British colonies. This would be done in an attempt to provide stability to the colonies, which were experiencing frequent government changes, to provide the basis for expansion into the West, and to create a unified country in order to guard against attacks from the Americans to the south.[PARAGRAPH:1]To prevent the frequent changes of government in the Province of Canada, George Brown, the leader of the Reformers (the forerunners to the Liberal Party of Canada) and an extremely vocal opponent of Macdonald\'s Conservatives, joined with Macdonald in 1864 to form the \"Great Coalition.\" This was an important step towards Confederation. Macdonald then spent 1864 to 1867 organizing the legislation needed to confederate the colonies into the country of Canada. In September 1864, he led the Canadian delegation at the Charlottetown Conference in Charlottetown,Prince Edward Island, to present his idea to the Maritime colonies, who were discussing a union of their own. In October 1864 delegates for confederation met in Quebec City, Quebec for the Quebec Conference where the Seventy-Two Resolutions were created -- the plan for confederation. By 1866, New Brunswick, Nova Scotia, and the Province of Canada had agreed to confederation. Newfoundland and Prince Edward Island were opposed. In the final conference of confederation held in 1866 in London, England the agreement to confederate was completed.[PARAGRAPH:1] As Prime Minister, Macdonald\'s vision was to enlarge the country and unify it. Accordingly, under his rule Canada bought Rupert\'s Land and the North-Western Territory from the Hudson\'s Bay Company for В£300,000 (about $11,500,000). This land became the Northwest Territories. In 1870 Parliament passed the Manitoba Act, creating the province of Manitoba out of a portion of the Northwest Territories in response to the Red River Rebellion led by Louis Riel.[PARAGRAPH:1] His career spanned 19 years, making Sir John A. Macdonald the second longest serving Prime Minister of Canada. He died while still Prime Minister, winning praise for having helped forge a nation of sprawling geographic size, with two diverse European colonial origins, and a multiplicity of cultural backgrounds and political views. Grieving Canadians turned out in the thousands to pay their respects while he lay in state in the Parliament Buildings in Ottawa and they lined the tracks to watch the train that returned his body to Kingston, Ontario where he was buried in the Cataraqui Cemetery.</string>
  <string name="TXT_KEY_LEADER_MURADBEY_PEDIA">[H1]Murad Bey[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD] Egyptian Mamluk Chieftain [\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD] c.1750 - 1801 [NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Murad Bey was an Egyptian Mamluk chieftain (Bey), cavalry commander and joint ruler of Egypt with Ibrahim Bey. He was of Georgian descent.  Following his defeat at the hands of Napoleon\'s armies at the Battle of the Pyramids, Murad fled to Upper Egypt, mounting a brief guerrilla campaign that staved off Desaix for a year. In 1800, Murad made peace with Jean Baptiste Klйber, and agreed to garrison Cairo, but died of bubonic plague on his journey there.</string>
</resources>
