<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by lcollins (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- Copyright Firaxis Games 2005 -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text - New -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_DAVID</Tag>
		<English>David</English>
		<French>David</French>
		<German>David</German>
		<Italian>Davide</Italian>
		<Spanish>David</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_DAVID_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]David[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]King of Israel[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD]c.1005 - 970 BC[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:1][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]David was the king of Judah and Israel.  He is described in the Bible in the books of Samuel and Kings.  David was the son of a landowner, Jesse, of the tribe of Judah.  He had eight brothers, of which David was the youngest.  He tended his father's sleep, whiling away many hours by playing the harp.  David lived about 1000 BC, when the Philistines pressed dangerously on the newly established Kingdom of Israel.  Israel's first king, Saul, had to fight almost constantly against the Philistines.  It is said that one of these battles, David killed Goliath, champion of the Philistines.  King Saul then appointed David as his armor bearer. [PARAGRAPH:1] The king's daughter fell in love with David, and they were married.  David became a popular hero, and because of this, the Judeans made him king of their tribe.  After King Saul and his son died in battle, David became king of Israel.  David's main goal was to unite the tribes of Israel into one kingdom.  There were many wars against the surrounding nations, and David proved to be a very good military leader. [PARAGRAPH:1] To bind the tribes closer together, David established on capital.  David conquered Jerusalem, to which he brought the ark of the law.  The ark contained two stone tablets on which the Ten Commandments were written.  King David was not only known for his military might, but his religious closeness to God.  David suffered many disappointments, but through it all, he remained a powerful leader. [PARAGRAPH:1] King David wrote many religious poems, or psalms, that are today included in many synogogues and churches.  David helped arrange services that would later be used in the temple build by his son, Solomon.  King David was so loved and admired, that some thought of him as the messiah.</English>
		<French>[H1]David\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Roi d'Isra%C3%ABl[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Dates :[\BOLD]c.1005 - 970 BC[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:1][BOLD]Biographie :[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]David était le roi de Judah et de l'Israel. Il est décrit dans le Bible dans les livres de Samuel et de rois. David était le fils d'un propriétaire foncier, Jesse, de la tribu de Judah. Il a eu huit frères, dont David était le plus jeune. Il a tendu le sommeil de son père, passant loin beaucoup d'heures en jouant l'harpe. David a vécu environ 1000 AVANT JÉSUS CHRIST, quand les philistins ont serré dangereusement sur le royaume nouvellement établi de l'Israel. Le premier roi de l'Israel, Saul, a dû lutter presque constamment contre les philistins. On lui dit qu'une de ces batailles, Goliath tué par David, champion des philistins. Le Roi Saul a alors nommé David en tant que son porteur d'armure. [PARAGRAPH : 1] La fille du roi est tombée amoureuse de David, et ils étaient mariés. David est allé bien à un héros populaire, et pour cette raison, le Judeans lui a fait le roi de leur tribu. Après le Roi Saul et son fils est mort dans la bataille, David est devenu roi de l'Israel. Le but principal de David était d'unir les tribus de l'Israel dans un royaume. Il y avait beaucoup de guerres contre les nations environnantes, et de David avérées être un chef militaire très bon. [PARAGRAPH : 1] Pour lier les tribus plus étroites ensemble, David établi sur le capital. David a conquis Jérusalem, auquel il a apporté l'arche de la loi. L'arche a contenu deux comprimés en pierre sur lesquels les Dix commandements ont été écrits. Le Roi David a été non seulement connu pour ses militaires pourrait, mais sa proximité religieuse à Dieu. David a souffert beaucoup de déceptions, mais par lui tout, il est resté un chef puissant. [PARAGRAPH : 1] Le Roi David a écrit beaucoup de poésies religieuses, ou psaumes, qui sont aujourd'hui inclus dans beaucoup de synogogues et églises. David aidé pour arranger les services qui plus tard seraient employés dans la construction de temple par son fils, Solomon. Le Roi David était ainsi a aimé et a admiré, une cette certaine pensée de lui en tant que Messie.</French>
		<German>[H1]David[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]König von Israel[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lebte:[\BOLD]c.1005 - 970 BC[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:1][BOLD]Hintergrund:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]David war der König von Judah und von Israel. Er wird im Bible in den Büchern von Samuel und von Königen beschrieben. David war der Sohn eines Grundbesitzers, Jesse, des Stammes von Judah. Er hatte acht Brüder, von denen David das jüngste war. Er neigte den Schlaf seines Vaters und weg verweilte viele Stunden, indem er die Harfe spielte. David lebte ungefähr 1000 BC, als die Philister sich gefährlich auf dem eben hergestellten Königreich von Israel betätigten. Israels erster König, Saul, mußte gegen die Philister fast ständig kämpfen. Es wird daß eine dieser Schlachten, David getöteter Goliath, Meister der Philister gesagt. König Saul ernannte dann David als seine Rüstung Stütze. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Die Tochter des Königs verliebte in David, und sie wurden verbunden. David stand einem populären Held, und wegen dieses, bildete das Judeans ihn König von ihrem Stamm. Nach König Saul und sein Sohn starb in der Schlacht, David wurde König von Israel. Davids Hauptziel war, die Stämme von Israel in ein Königreich zu vereinigen. Es gab viele Kriege gegen die umgebenden Nationen, und David gewesen ein sehr guter militärischer Führer. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Die Stämme genauer zusammen sind binden, David hergestellt auf Kapital. David eroberte Jerusalem, nach das er die Arche des Gesetzes holte. Die Arche enthielt zwei Steintabletten, auf denen die 10 Gebote geschrieben wurden. König David bekannt nicht nur für sein Militär konnte, aber seine fromme Nähe zum Gott. David erlitt viele Enttäuschungen, aber durch ihn aller, blieb er ein leistungsfähiger Führer. [PARAGRAPH: 1] König David schrieb viele fromme Gedichte oder Psalms, die heute in vielen synogogues und in Kirchen eingeschlossen sind. David geholfen, Dienstleistungen, die später im Bügelbau von seinem Sohn, verwendet würden Solomon zu ordnen. König David war, also liebte und bewunderte, dieser etwas Gedanke von ihm als der Messias.</German>
		<Italian>[H1]Davide[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Re di Israele[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Vita:[\BOLD]c.1005 - 970 BC[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:1][BOLD]Informazioni:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]David era il re di Judah e dell'Israele. È descritto nel Bible nei libri di Samuel e dei re. David era il figlio di un latifondista, Jesse, della tribù di Judah. Ha avuto otto fratelli, di cui David era il più giovane. Ha teso il sonno del suo padre, passante il tempo via molte ore giocando l'arpa. David ha vissuto BC circa 1000, quando i Philistines hanno premuto pericolosamente sul regno recentemente stabilito dell'Israele. Il primo re dell'Israele, Saul, ha dovuto combattere quasi costantemente contro i Philistines. Si dice che una di queste battaglie, Goliath ucciso David, campione dei Philistines. Il re Saul allora ha nominato David come suo elemento portante dell'armatura. [PARAGRAPH: 1] La figlia del re è caduto nell'amore con David e sono stati sposati. David ha stato bene ad un hero popolare ed a causa di questo, il Judeans gli ha reso il re della loro tribù. Dopo il re Saul ed il suo figlio è morto nella battaglia, David si è trasformato in in re dell'Israele. L'obiettivo principale del David era di unire le tribù dell'Israele in un regno. Ci era molte guerre contro le nazioni circostanti e David rivelate essere un capo militare molto buon. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Per legare insieme le tribù più vicine, David stabilito su capitale. David ha conquistato Gerusalemme, a cui ha portato l'arca della legge. L'arca ha contenuto due ridurre in pani di pietra su cui i dieci ordini sono stati scritti. Il re David non solo è stato conosciuto per i suoi militari potrebbe, ma la sua prossimità religiosa al dio. David ha sofferto molti disappunti, ma con esso tutto, è rimasto un capo potente. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Il re David ha scritto molti poems religiosi, o gli psalms, che oggi sono inclusi in molti synogogues e chiese. David contribuito per organizzare i servizi che più successivamente sarebbero usati nella configurazione del tempiale dal suo figlio, Solomon. Il re David era in modo da amava ed ammirato, un quel certo pensiero di lui come il messiah.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[H1]David[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Rey de Israel[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Vivi&#243;:[\BOLD]c.1005 - 970 BC.[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:1][BOLD]Historia:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]David era el rey de Judah y de Israel. Lo describen en el Bible en los libros de Samuel y de reyes. David era el hijo de un terrateniente, Jesse, de la tribu de Judah. Él tenía ocho hermanos, de quienes David era el más joven. Él tendió al sueño de su padre, pasando lejos muchas horas tocando la arpa. David vivió cerca de 1000 A.C., cuando los Philistines presionaron peligroso en el reino nuevamente establecido de Israel. Primer rey de Israel, Saul, tuvo que luchar casi constantemente contra los Philistines. Se dice que una de estas batallas, Goliath matado David, campeón de los Philistines. Rey Saul entonces designó David como su portador de la armadura. [PARAGRAPH: 1] La hija del rey cayó en amor con David, y fueron casados. David sintió bien a un héroe popular, y debido a esto, el Judeans te hizo a rey de su tribu. Después del rey Saul y su hijo murió en la batalla, David hizo rey de Israel. La meta principal de David era unir las tribus de Israel en un reino. Había muchas guerras contra las naciones circundantes, y David demostradas ser un líder militar muy bueno. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Para atar las tribus más cercanas juntas, David establecido en capital. David conquistó Jerusalén, a la cual él trajo la arca de la ley. La arca contuvo dos tabletas de piedra en las cuales los diez mandamientos fueron escritos. Conocían a rey David no sólo para sus militares pudo, solamente su proximidad religiosa al dios. David sufrió muchas decepciones, pero con él todo, él seguía siendo un líder de gran alcance. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Rey David escribió muchos poemas religiosos, o los salmos, que se incluyen hoy en muchos synogogues e iglesias. David ayudado para arreglar los servicios que serían utilizados más adelante en la estructura del templo por su hijo, Solomon. Rey David era así que amó y admiró, ese algún pensamiento de él como el messiah.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_DAVID_1</Tag>
		<English>Greetings.  I am [OUR_NAME], and I welcome you, with a hand on the heart, to the the land of [OUR_CIV_SHORT].</English>
		<French>Salutations. Je suis [OUR_NAME], et je te souhaite la bienvenue, avec une main sur le coeur, l'à la terre de [OUR_CIV_SHORT].</French>
		<German>Grüße. Ich bin [OUR_NAME], und ich begrüße dich, mit einer Hand auf dem Herzen, zum Land von [OUR_CIV_SHORT].</German>
		<Italian>Saluti. Sono [OUR_NAME] e li accolgo favorevolmente, con una mano sul cuore, alla terra di [OUR_CIV_SHORT].</Italian>
		<Spanish>Saludos. Soy [OUR_NAME], y te doy la bienvenida, con una mano en el corazón, el tierra de [OUR_CIV_SHORT].</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>