<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by lcollins (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- Copyright Firaxis Games 2005 -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text - New -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_DUSAN</Tag>
		<English>Dusan</English>
		<French>Dusan</French>
		<German>Dusan</German>
		<Italian>Dusan</Italian>
		<Spanish>Dusan</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_DUSAN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Stefan Uros IV Dusan[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]King of Serbia[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived:[\BOLD] 1308 - 1355[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Stefan Dusan was the eldest son of Stefan Uros III Decanski and Theodora of Bulgaria, the daughter of Emperor Smilets of Bulgaria.  He spent several years in Constantinople as a child, learning the culture and languages of Byzantium.  As a young soldier, he preformed exceptionally well in two battles, one in 1329 and another in 1330. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Because his father had not made an effort to expand Serbia, Dusan rebelled with the help of the nobles and crowned himself king in 1331.  In 1332, he married Helena of Bulgaria, who had a large influence on Dusan.  In the first years of his reign, Dusan fought against the Byzantine Empire.  He also found himself involved in large disagreements with the Hungarians.  However, these battles were primarily defensive and both times resulted in victory for the Serbs.  During this time, he received help from the Bulgarians, whom were allies of Serbia at the time. [PARAGRAPH: 1] At the time, a civil war occupied Byzantium and Dusan took advantage of this.  He extended Serbian territory into the western Balkans, his goal being to conquer Constantinople and replace the weakening Byzantine Empire with a Greco-Serbian Empire under his control.  After these successes, he proclaimed himself as "Emperor and Autocrat of Serbs and Greeks" in 1346.  He received help from the Serbian Orthodox Church to establish his power, which he had expanded in previous years. [PARAGRAPH: 1] With the increasing Serbian threat, the Byzantines found allies in the Turks.  The Turks had only recently entered the European scene, and the first conflict between the Serbs and Turks ended in defeat for Dusan.  In 1348 Dusan further expanded Serbian territory by conquering the regions of Thessaly and Epirus.  Dusan at this time saw the threat of the Turks and sought ways to delay their expansion.  However, he was disrupted by the Hungarians, who harassed Serbia.  He heavily defeated the Hungarians and their king.  Dusan's ambitions were cut short by his premature death in 1355, possibly resulting from poisoning by the Hungarians.  He was succeeded by his son, Stefan Uros V, who had been in power as king since 1346.  In addition to expanding Serbian territory significantly, Dusan made and enforced a new code of laws, known as Dusan's Code, in the years 1349 and 1354.</English>
		<French>[H1]Stefan Uros IV Dusan[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Roi de Serbie[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Régné:[\BOLD] 1308 - 1355[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Biographie:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Stefan Dusan était le fils le plus âgé de Stefan Uros III Decanski et Theodora de la Bulgarie, la fille de l'empereur Smilets de la Bulgarie.  Il a passé plusieurs années à Constantinople en tant qu'enfant, apprenant la culture et les langues de Byzance.  En tant que jeune soldat, il a particulièrement bien préformé dans deux batailles, dessus en 1329 et des autres en 1330. [PARAGRAPHE : 1] Puisque son père n'avait pas fait un effort d'augmenter la Serbie, Dusan s'est rebellé avec l'aide des nobles et s'est couronné roi en 1331.  En 1332, il a épousé Helena de la Bulgarie, qui a eu une grande influence sur Dusan.  En les premières années de son règne, Dusan a lutté contre l'empire bizantin.  Il s'est également trouvé impliqué dans de grands désaccords des Hongrois.  Cependant, ces batailles étaient principalement défensif et les deux fois ont eu comme conséquence la victoire pour les Serbes.  Pendant ce temps, il a reçu l'aide des Bulgares, qui étaient des alliés de la Serbie alors. [PARAGRAPHE : 1] Lorsque, une guerre civile Byzance occupée et Dusan a tiré profit de ceci.  Il a prolongé le territoire serbe en les Balkans occidentaux, son but devant conquérir Constantinople et remplacer l'empire bizantin de affaiblissement avec un empire Greco-Serbe sous sa commande.  Après ces succès, il s'est proclamé en tant que le « empereur et autocrate des Serbes et des Grecs » en 1346.  Il a reçu l'aide de l'église orthodoxe serbe pour établir sa puissance, qu'il avait augmentée en années précédentes. [PARAGRAPHE : 1] Avec la menace serbe croissante, le Byzantines alliés trouvés dans les Turcs.  Les Turcs avaient été introduits tout récemment dans l'Europe, et le premier conflit entre les Serbes et les Turcs finis dans la défaite pour Dusan.  En le territoire 1348 serbe augmenté encore de Dusan en conquérant les régions de Thessaly et d'Epirus.  Dusan actuellement a vu la menace des Turcs et a cherché des manières de retarder leur expansion.  Cependant, il a été perturbé par les Hongrois, qui ont harcelé la Serbie.  Il a fortement défait les Hongrois et leur roi.  Les ambitions de Dusan ont été coupées sous peu par sa mort prématurée en 1355, probablement résultant de l'empoisonnement par les Hongrois.  Il a été réussi par son fils, Stefan Uros V, qui avait été dans la puissance comme roi depuis 1346.</French>
		<German>[H1]Stefan Uros IV. Dusan[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]K&#246;nig von Serbien[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Angeordnet:[\BOLD] 1308 - 1355[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Hintergrund:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Stefan Dusan war der älteste Sohn von Stefan Uros III Decanski und Theodora von Bulgarien, die Tochter des Kaisers Smilets von Bulgarien.  Er verbrachte einige Jahre in Konstantinopolise als Kind und erlernte die Kultur und die Sprachen von Byzanz.  Als junger Soldat formte er außergewöhnlich gut in zwei Schlachten, an 1329 und andere 1330 vor. [PUNKT: 1] Weil sein Vater nicht eine Bemühung gebildet hatte, Serbien zu erweitern, lehnte sich Dusan mit Hilfe der Adligen auf und krönte sich König 1331.  1332 heiratete er Helena von Bulgarien, der einen großen Einfluß auf Dusan hatte.  In den ersten Jahren seiner Herrschaft, kämpfte Dusan gegen das byzantinische Reich.  Er fand sich auch mit einbezogen in große Widersprüche in die Ungarn.  Jedoch waren diese Schlachten hauptsächlich Defensive und beide Male ergaben Sieg für die Serben.  Während dieser Zeit empfing er Hilfe von den Bulgaren, die Verbündete von Serbien zu der Zeit waren. [PUNKT: 1] Zu der Zeit als, ein Bürgerkrieg besetzte, nutzten Byzanz und Dusan dieses.  Er verlängerte serbische Gegend in die Westbalkan, sein Ziel, das Konstantinopolis erobern und das schwächende byzantinische Reich mit einem Greco-Serbe Reich unter seiner Steuerung ersetzen soll.  Nach diesen Erfolgen proklamierte sich er als Kaiser und Autokrat von Serben und von Griechen 1346.  Er empfing Hilfe von der serbischen orthodoxen Kirche, um seine Energie herzustellen, die er in vorhergehende Jahre erweitert hatte. [PUNKT: 1] Mit der zunehmenden serbischen Drohung das Byzantines gefundene Verbündete in den Türken.  Die Türken waren erst vor kurzem in Europa geholt worden, und der erste Konflikt zwischen den Serben und den Türken beendete in der Niederlage für Dusan.  Dusan weitere erweiterte serbische Gegend 1348 durch das Erobern der Regionen von Thessaly und von Epirus.  Dusan diesmal sah die Drohung der Türken und suchte Weisen zu verzögert ihre Expansion.  Jedoch wurde er von den Ungarn gestört, die Serbien bedrängten.  Er besiegte schwer die Ungarn und ihren König.  Ehrgeiz Dusans wurde kurz durch seinen vorzeitigen Tod 1355 geschnitten, und das vielleicht resultiert aus der Vergiftung durch die Ungarn.  Er wurde von seinem Sohn, Stefan Uros V gefolgt, der in der Energie als König seit 1346 gewesen war.</German>
		<Italian>[H1]Stefano Uros IV Dusan[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Re di Serbia[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Regolato:[\BOLD] 1308 - 1355[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Informazioni:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Stefan Dusan era il figlio più anziano di Stefan Uros III Decanski e Theodora della Bulgaria, la figlia dell'imperatore Smilets della Bulgaria.  Ha speso parecchi anni a Constantinople come bambino, imparando la coltura e le lingue di Byzantium.  Come soldato giovane, ha preformato particolarmente bene in due battaglie, sopra in 1329 ed in un altro in 1330. [PARAGRAFO: 1] Poiché il suo padre non aveva fatto uno sforzo espandere la Serbia, Dusan si è ribellato con l'aiuto dei nobili e crowned re in 1331.  In 1332, ha sposato Helena della Bulgaria, che ha avuto una grande influenza su Dusan.  Durante i primi anni del suo regno, Dusan ha combattuto contro l'impero Byzantine.  Inoltre si è trovato coinvolgere nei grandi disaccordi con gli ungheresi.  Tuttavia, queste battaglie erano soprattutto difensivo ed entrambe le volte hanno provocato la vittoria per i serbi.  Durante questo tempo, ha ricevuto l'aiuto dai bulgari, quale erano allora alleati della Serbia. [PARAGRAFO: 1] Quando, una guerra civile ha occupato Byzantium e Dusan hanno approfittato di questo.  Ha esteso il territorio di Serbian in Balcani occidentali, il suo obiettivo che deve conquistare Constantinople e sostituire l'impero Byzantine d'indebolimento con un impero di Greco-Serbian sotto il suo controllo.  Dopo questi successi, si è affermato come l'imperatore e autocrate dei serbi e dei Greci in 1346.  Ha ricevuto l'aiuto dalla chiesa ortodossa di Serbian per stabilire la relativa alimentazione, che aveva espanso durante gli anni precedenti. [PARAGRAFO: 1] Con la minaccia aumentante di Serbian, il Byzantines alleati trovati nei Turchi.  I Turchi recentemente erano stati introdotti soltanto in Europa ed il primo conflitto fra i serbi ed i Turchi si è concluso nella sconfitta per Dusan.  In ulteriore Serbian territorio espanso 1348 di Dusan conquistando le regioni di Thessaly e di Epirus.  Dusan attualmente ha visto la minaccia dei Turchi ed ha cercato i sensi a fa ritardare la loro espansione.  Tuttavia, si è interrotto dagli ungheresi, che harassed la Serbia.  Ha sconfitto pesante gli ungheresi ed il loro re.  Le ambizioni del Dusan sono state tagliate bruscamente dalla sua morte prematura in 1355, possibilmente derivando dall'avvelenamento dagli ungheresi.  È stato riuscito dal suo figlio, Stefan Uros V, che era stato nell'alimentazione come re dal 1346.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[H1]Stefan Uros IV Dusan[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Rey de Serbia[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Gobernado:[\BOLD] 1308 - 1355[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Historia:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Stefan Dusan era el más viejo hijo de Stefan Uros III Decanski y Theodora de Bulgaria, la hija del emperador Smilets de Bulgaria.  Él pasó varios años en Constantinople como niño, aprendiendo la cultura y las idiomas de Byzantium.  Como soldado joven, él preformó excepcionalmente bien en dos batallas, encendido en 1329 y otro en 1330. [PÁRRAFO: 1] Porque su padre no había hecho un esfuerzo de ampliar Serbia, Dusan rebeló con la ayuda de los nobles y se coronó rey en 1331.  En 1332, él casó a Helena de Bulgaria, que tenía una influencia grande en Dusan.  En los primeros años de su reinado, Dusan luchó contra el imperio Byzantine.  Él también se encontró implicado en desacuerdos grandes con los húngaros.  Sin embargo, estas batallas eran sobre todo defensiva y ambas veces dieron lugar a la victoria para los servios.  Durante este tiempo, él recibió ayuda de los búlgaros, que eran aliados de Serbia en ese entonces. [PÁRRAFO: 1] Cuando, una guerra civil ocupó Byzantium y Dusan se aprovecharon de esto.  Él extendió el territorio servio en los Balcanes occidentales, su meta que debía conquistar Constantinople y substituir el imperio Byzantine de debilitamiento por un imperio del Greco-Servio bajo su control.  Después de estos éxitos, él se proclamó como emperador y Autocrat de servios y de Griegos en 1346.  Él recibió ayuda de la iglesia ortodoxa servia para establecer su energía, que él había ampliado en años anteriores. [PÁRRAFO: 1] Con la amenaza servia de aumento, el Byzantines aliados encontrados en los turcos.  Habían traído los turcos solamente recientemente en Europa, y el primer conflicto entre los servios y los turcos terminados en la derrota para Dusan.  En el territorio servio ampliado adicional 1348 de Dusan conquistando las regiones de Thessaly y de Epirus.  Dusan en este tiempo vio la amenaza de los turcos y buscó maneras a retrasa su extensión.  Sin embargo, a los húngaros lo interrumpió, que acosaron Serbia.  Él derrotó pesadamente a los húngaros y a su rey.  Las ambiciones de Dusan fueron cortadas brevemente por su muerte prematura en 1355, posiblemente resultando del envenenamiento de los húngaros.  A su hijo, Stefan Uros V lo tuvo éxito, que había estado en energía como rey desde 1346.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_DUSAN_1</Tag>
		<English>Greetings, [CT_NAME].  Remember, he who digs a trap for others ends up in it himself.</English>
		<French>Salutations, [CT_NAME]. N'oubliez pas que celui qui creuse un piège pour les autres, finit par tomber dedans.</French>
		<German>Greetings, [CT_NAME]. Denken Sie daran, dass er die Ausgrabungen eine Falle für die anderen endet es in sich.</German>
		<Italian>Saluti, [CT_NAME]. Ricordate, colui che scava una trappola per gli altri e si finisce per se stesso.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Saludos, [CT_NAME]. Recuerde, el que cava una trampa para otros termina en él mismo. </Spanish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>