<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by lcollins (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- Copyright Firaxis Games 2005 -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text - New -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_FOLWARK</Tag>
		<English>Folwark</English>
		<French>Folwark</French>
		<German>Folwark</German>
		<Italian>Folwark</Italian>
		<Spanish>Folwark</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
        <TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_FOLWARK_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Folwarks are giant Polish farms that were operated in the Polish-Lithuanian Commonwealth from the 14th century into the 20th.  They were used to produce a surplus of food.  The first folwarks were created on church and monastery owned grounds, but were later adopted by nobility and rich peasants.  The creation of folwarks was boosted by a growing demand for grain and its high profit. Folwark-based grain export was an important part of the economy of the Polish-Lithuanian commonwealth.  [PARAGRAPH: 1] The fall of agriculture goods prices in the end of the 17th century marked the start of a crisis for the folwark related economy.  The noble's attempt to increase use of folwarks only hurt the economic crisis more.  Until the 18th century, folwarks remained the basis for Polish noble's economic and political power.  After the abolition of serfdom in Poland, folwarks used paid labor.  Folwarks were abolished by the People's Republic of Poland with the PKWN decree of 6 September 1944 about agricultural reform</English>
		<French>[TAB]Folwarks sont géant polonais exploitations qui ont été opérés dans le polonais-lituanien du 14e siècle dans le 20ème. Ils ont servi à produire un excédent de nourriture. La première folwarks ont été créés sur l'église et le monastère appartenant motifs, mais ont par la suite été adopté par la noblesse et les paysans riches. La création de folwarks a été stimulée par une demande croissante de céréales et de sa forte rentabilité. Folwark fondée sur l'exportation de céréales a été une partie importante de l'économie de la polonais-lituanien Commonwealth. [PARAGRAPH: 1] La chute du prix des produits agricoles à la fin du 17e siècle ont marqué le début d'une crise pour la folwark liés économie. La noble tentative d'accroître l'utilisation des folwarks seulement blessé plus de la crise économique. Jusqu'au 18e siècle, folwarks demeure la base d'nobles polonais du pouvoir économique et politique. Après l'abolition du servage en Pologne, folwarks utilisé travail rémunéré. Folwarks ont été abolis par la République populaire de Pologne avec le PKWN décret du 6 septembre 1944 sur la réforme agricole.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Folwarks sind riesigen polnischen Bauernhöfen betrieben, die in der polnisch-litauischen Commonwealth aus dem 14. Jahrhundert in das 20. Jahrhundert. Sie wurden für die Herstellung von einem Überschuss von Lebensmitteln. Die erste folwarks wurden auf Kirche und Kloster im Besitz Gründen, sondern wurden später vom Adel und reichen Bauern. Die Schaffung von folwarks wurde durch eine wachsende Nachfrage nach Getreide und seiner hohen Gewinn. Folwark - auf der Grundlage Getreide exportieren war ein wichtiger Teil der Wirtschaft in der polnisch-litauischen Commonwealth. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Der Rückgang der Landwirtschaft Waren, die Preise in der Ende des 17. Jahrhunderts markiert den Beginn einer Krise für die folwark ähnliche Wirtschaft. Die edle Versuch zur Erhöhung der Nutzung von folwarks nur schaden, die wirtschaftliche Krise. Bis zum 18. Jahrhundert, folwarks blieb die Grundlage für die polnische edlen die wirtschaftliche und politische Macht. Nach der Abschaffung der Leibeigenschaft in Polen, folwarks verwendet Lohnarbeit. Folwarks abgeschafft wurden von der Volksrepublik Polen mit dem PKWN Dekret vom 6. September 1944 über die Agrarreform.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB]Folwarks sono gigante polacco aziende agricole che sono stati operati nel Polacco-Lituano dal 14 ° secolo in 20a. Essi sono stati utilizzati per la produzione di un surplus di cibo. Il primo folwarks sono stati creati sulla chiesa e del convento di proprietà motivi, ma sono stati in seguito adottati dalla nobiltà e ricchi contadini. La creazione di folwarks è stata incentivata da una crescente domanda di cereali e il suo alto profitto. Folwark a base di grano di esportazione è stato una parte importante dell 'economia di Stato polacco - lituano. [PARAGRAPH: 1] La caduta dei prezzi in agricoltura merci alla fine del 17 ° secolo ha segnato l'inizio di una crisi per il folwark connessi economia. Il nobile del tentativo di aumentare l'uso di folwarks solo male la crisi economica più. Fino al 18 ° secolo, folwarks rimasti la base per la nobile polacco potere economico e politico. Dopo l'abolizione della serfdom in Polonia, folwarks utilizzati pagato lavoro. Folwarks sono state abolite dalla Repubblica popolare di Polonia con il PKWN decreto del 6 settembre 1944 sulla riforma agricola.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB]Folwarks son gigantes granjas polacas que fueron operados en la Comunidad de Polonia - Lituania desde el siglo 14 en la 20. Estos recursos se utilizaron para producir un excedente de alimentos. La primera folwarks se crearon en la iglesia y el monasterio de propiedad de motivos, pero luego fueron aprobadas por la nobleza y los campesinos ricos. La creación de folwarks fue impulsada por una creciente demanda de cereales y su alto beneficio. Folwark basado en la exportación de cereales es una parte importante de la economía de la polaca y lituana ELA. [PARAGRAPH: 1] La caída de los precios de los bienes en la agricultura a finales del siglo 17 marcó el inicio de una crisis para la folwark relacionados con la economía. El noble intento de aumentar la utilización de folwarks sólo perjudican la crisis económica más. Hasta el siglo 18, folwarks sigue siendo la base de nobles polacos del poder económico y político. Después de la abolición de la servidumbre de la gleba en Polonia, folwarks utilizados trabajo remunerado. Folwarks fueron abolidas por la República Popular de Polonia con la PKWN decreto de 6 de septiembre de 1944 sobre la reforma agrícola.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
        <TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_FOLWARK_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Folwark[COLOR_REVERT], the Polish replacement for the [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Granary[COLOR_REVERT], offers bonus food.</English>
		<French>Le [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]folwark[COLOR_REVERT], équivalent polonais du [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]grenier[COLOR_REVERT], génère un bonus de nourriture.</French>
		<German>Die [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Folwark[COLOR_REVERT], die polnisch Ersatz für die [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Kornkammer[COLOR_REVERT], bietet bonus lebensmittel</German>
		<Italian>L'[COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Folwark[COLOR_REVERT], la sostituzione polacco per il [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Granaio[COLOR_REVERT], offre bonus di alimentare.</Italian>
		<Spanish> El [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Folwark[COLOR_REVERT], la sustitución de polaco para el [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Granero[COLOR_REVERT], ofrece bono de la alimentos. </Spanish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>