<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by lcollins (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- Copyright Firaxis Games 2005 -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text - New -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_POLAND_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Polish Empire</English>
		<French>Pologne</French>
		<German>Polnisch Reich</German>
		<Italian>Polacco Impero</Italian>
		<Spanish>Polaco Imperio</Spanish>
	</TEXT>	
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_POLAND_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Poland</English>
		<French>Polonais</French>
		<German>Polen</German>
		<Italian>Polonia</Italian>
		<Spanish>Polonia</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_POLAND_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Polish</English>
    <French>
	    <Text>polonais:polonaise:polonais:polonaises</Text>
	    <Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
	    <Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
    </French>
		<German>Polnisch</German>
		<Italian>Polacco</Italian>
		<Spanish>Polaco</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_POLAND_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Throughout Late Antiquity, many distinct ethnic groups occupied the regions of what is now Poland.  Many Slavic, Celtic, Baltic, and Germanic tribes were among the prominent groups.  The most famous archeological find from the prehistory of Poland is the Biskupin fortified settlement.  The fort has been dated to the early Iron Age, when the Lusatian culture occupied the area around 700 BC. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Poland began to take the form of a unified country around the middle of the tenth century under the Piast dynasty.  Catholic Christianity was the nation's first official religion.  In the twelfth century, Poland split into several smaller states.  Under the Jagiellon dynasty, Poland forged an alliance with its neighbor, the Grand Duchy of Lithuania.  Polish economy, military, and culture flourished in Poland-Lithuania and under the Jagiellons.  Poland was famous for its tolerance for all religions, and thus became a center for the migration of the Jewish people.  [PARAGRAPH: 2] A golden age resulted in the country from the newly established Polish-Lithuanian Commonwealth.  The nobility of Poland, which were more abundant than in other Western European countries, took pleasure in the parliamentary system.  During its Golden Age, Poland expanded its borders to become the largest country in Europe.  However, in the middle of the seventeenth century, a Swedish invasion and Cossack's Chmielnicki Uprising marked the end of its golden age.  Wars against Russia also marked the country's decline.  The reforms, specifically the Great Sejm, the second modern constitution of the world, were dissatisfied with the three partitions of Poland, which began Poland's being removed from the map and its territories being divided among Russia, Prussia, and Austria. [PARAGRAPH: 2] The Poles would resent their fate and would rebel several times against the partitioners.  In 1807, Napoleon created the Duchy of Warsaw, but after the Napoleonic wars, Poland was divided again.  The Russian Czars who ruled the country eventually reduced the Polish freedoms, and Russia captured the country.  After the invasions of Nazi Germany and the Soviet Union in 1939, Poland was split under Germany and the Soviet Union.  Poland lost much of its citizens in the war, six million and at least half Polish Jews.  After the borders were shifted following World War II, many people of Poland were forced to migrate. [PARAGRAPH: 2] The Soviet Union introduced a new Communist government in Poland.  The People's Republic of Poland was officially proclaimed in 1952.  However, in 1956, people received more freedoms and were freed from prisons after Poland became more liberal.  In 1980, an independent trade union overcame the Communist Party and bared the collapse of communism across Eastern Europe.  Following these changes, Poland made numerous improvements in human rights.  In May 1, 2004, Poland became a full member of the European Union.</English>
		<French>[TAB]Tout au long de la fin de l'Antiquité, de nombreux groupes ethniques distincts occupé les régions de ce qui est maintenant la Pologne. Beaucoup slaves, celtiques, baltes, et les tribus germaniques ont été parmi les éminents groupes. La plus célèbre site archéologique de trouver la préhistoire de la Pologne est le Biskupin fortifié. Le fort a été à la date du début de l'âge du fer, lorsque la culture de Lusace occupé la zone autour de 700 avant notre ère. [PARAGRAPH: 2] La Pologne a commencé à prendre la forme d'un pays unifié dans le milieu du Xe siècle sous la dynastie des Piast. Le christianisme catholique a été le premier religion officielle. Au XIIe siècle, la Pologne divisée en plusieurs petits Etats. Sous la dynastie des Jagellon, Pologne forgé une alliance avec son voisin, le Grand Duché de Lituanie. Économie polonaise, militaires, et de la culture florissante en Pologne, en Lituanie et en vertu de la Jagiellons. La Pologne est connue pour sa tolérance envers toutes les religions, et est ainsi devenu un centre pour la migration du peuple juif. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Un âge d'or a entraîné dans le pays de la nouvellement créée polonais-lituanien. La noblesse de la Pologne, qui ont été plus abondantes que dans les autres pays d'Europe occidentale, a pris plaisir dans le système parlementaire. Au cours de son âge d'or, de la Pologne a élargi ses frontières pour devenir le plus grand pays d'Europe. Toutefois, dans le milieu du XVIIe siècle, un suédois invasion et de Chmielnicki soulèvement cosaque a marqué la fin de son âge d'or. Guerres contre la Russie a également marqué le déclin du pays. Les réformes, en particulier de la Grande-Bretagne Sejm, la deuxième constitution moderne du monde, n'étaient pas satisfaits avec les trois partitions de la Pologne, qui a mis fin à la Pologne est retirée de la carte et de son territoire étant partagé entre la Russie, la Prusse et l'Autriche. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Les Polonais ressentent leur sort et se rebelle à plusieurs reprises contre le partitioners. En 1807, Napoléon a créé le Duché de Varsovie, mais après les guerres napoléoniennes, la Pologne est à nouveau divisé. Les tsars russes qui ont gouverné le pays finalement réduit le polonais libertés, et de la Russie capturé le pays. Après l'invasion de l'Allemagne nazie et l'Union soviétique en 1939, la Pologne a été scindée en vertu de l'Allemagne et de l'Union soviétique. La Pologne a perdu beaucoup de ses citoyens dans la guerre, six millions et au moins la moitié de juifs polonais. Après les frontières ont été déplacés après la Deuxième Guerre mondiale, de nombreuses personnes de la Pologne ont été forcés d'émigrer. [PARAGRAPHE: 2] L'Union soviétique a présenté un nouveau gouvernement communiste en Pologne. La République populaire de Pologne a été officiellement proclamée en 1952. Toutefois, en 1956, la population a reçu plus de libertés et ont été libérés de prison après la Pologne est devenue plus libérale. En 1980, un syndicat indépendant surmonté le Parti communiste et bared l'effondrement du communisme dans toute l'Europe de l'Est. Suite à ces changements, la Pologne a apporté de nombreuses améliorations dans les droits de l'homme. Au 1er mai 2004, la Pologne est devenue membre à part entière de l'Union européenne.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Überall in Late Antiquity, viele verschiedene ethnische Gruppen, die besetzten Gebiete von dem, was jetzt Polen. Viele slawische, keltische, Ostsee, und germanischen Stämme waren unter den prominenten Gruppen. Die berühmtesten archäologischen finden, von der Vorgeschichte der Polen ist die befestigte Siedlung Biskupin. Die Festung wurde vom bis in die frühen Eisenzeit, wenn die Lausitzer Kultur besetzten das Gebiet um 700 v. Chr.. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Polen begann, in der Form eines geeinten Landes etwa in der Mitte des zehnten Jahrhunderts unter der Piasten. Katholische Christentum wurde das Volk der ersten offiziellen Religion. In der zwölften Jahrhundert, Polen, unterteilt in mehrere kleinere Staaten. Unter der Jagiellonen, Polen gefälscht ein Bündnis mit seinen Nachbarn, das Großherzogtum Litauen. Polnischen Wirtschaft, Militär und Kultur blühten in Polen - Litauen und unter der Jagiellons. Polen war bekannt für seine Toleranz für alle Religionen, und wurde so zu einem Zentrum für die Migration des jüdischen Volkes. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Ein goldenes Zeitalter geführt, in dem Land, aus dem neu gegründeten polnisch-litauischen Commonwealth. Der Adel in Polen, die häufiger als in anderen westeuropäischen Ländern, erfreuten sich in der parlamentarischen System. Während seiner Golden Age, Polen erweitert seine Grenzen zu den größten in Europa. However, in der Mitte des siebzehnten Jahrhunderts, einem schwedischen Invasion und Kosaken's Chmielnicki Aufstands markiert das Ende seiner goldenen Zeitalter. Kriege gegen Russland auch im Land rückläufig. Die Reformen, insbesondere der Große Sejm, die zweite moderne Verfassung der Welt, unzufrieden waren mit den drei Partitionen mit Polen, das endete Polen, die beseitigt werden auf der Karte und ihre Territorien wird geteilt zwischen Russland, Preußen und Österreich. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Die Polen würden sich gegen ihr Schicksal und die Rebellen mehrere Male gegen den sichtbar. In 1807, Napoleon das Herzogtum Warschau, aber nach den napoleonischen Kriegen, Polen wurde erneut. Die russischen Zaren, die das Land schließlich reduziert die polnischen Freiheiten, und Russland erobert das Land. Nachdem die Invasionen der nationalsozialistischen Deutschland und der Sowjetunion 1939, Polen aufgeteilt wurde unter Deutschland und der Sowjetunion. Polen verlor viel von seiner Bürger in den Krieg, sechs Millionen und mindestens die Hälfte polnischen Juden. Nachdem die Grenzen verschoben wurden nach dem Zweiten Weltkrieg viele Menschen in Polen waren gezwungen zu migrieren. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Die Sowjetunion eine neue kommunistische Regierung in Polen. Der Volksrepublik Polen wurde offiziell verkündet im 1952. However, in der 1956 Menschen mehr Freiheiten und freigelassen wurden aus den Gefängnissen nach Polen wurde liberaler. In 1980, eine unabhängige Gewerkschaft gegen die Kommunistische Partei und entblößte dem Zusammenbruch des Kommunismus in Osteuropa. Nach diesen Änderungen, Polen, die zahlreiche Verbesserungen im Bereich der Menschenrechte. Im Mai 1, 2004, wurde Polen ein vollwertiges Mitglied der Europäischen Union.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB]Tutta Tarda Antichità, molti gruppi etnici distinti occupato le regioni di quella che è oggi la Polonia. Molti slavo, celtica, Mar Baltico, e tribù germaniche sono stati tra i gruppi di spicco. Il più famoso reperti dalla preistoria della Polonia è il Biskupin insediamento fortificato. Il forte è stata datata agli inizi età del ferro, quando la Lusatian cultura occupato l'area attorno 700 aC. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Polonia ha cominciato a prendere la forma di un unico paese, verso la metà del decimo secolo, sotto la dinastia Piast. Cattolica, il cristianesimo è stato il primo paese della religione ufficiale. Nel XII secolo, la Polonia suddivisi in diversi Stati più piccoli. Sotto la dinastia Jagellone, Polonia forgiato un'alleanza con il suo prossimo, il Granducato di Lituania. Economia polacca, militari, e la cultura fiorita in Polonia - Lituania e sotto la Jagiellons. La Polonia è stata famosa per la sua tolleranza per tutte le religioni, e, quindi, è diventato un centro per la migrazione del popolo ebraico. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Un epoca d'oro portato nel paese dal neoistituito Polacco-Lituano. La nobiltà di Polonia, che sono state più abbondanti che in altri paesi dell'Europa occidentale, ha avuto piacere nel sistema parlamentare. Nel corso della sua Golden Age, Polonia ampliato i suoi confini a diventare il più grande paese in Europa. Tuttavia, a metà del XVII secolo, una invasione svedese cosacco e di Chmielnicki Uprising segnato la fine della sua epoca d'oro. Guerre contro la Russia ha anche segnato il declino del paese. Le riforme, in particolare la Gran Sejm, la seconda moderna costituzione del mondo, non sono soddisfatti con le tre partizioni di Polonia, che si è conclusa la Polonia viene rimosso dalla mappa e il suo territorio è diviso tra la Russia, Prussia e Austria. [PARAGRAPH: 2] I polacchi sarebbe di nuovo il loro destino e ribelli avrebbero più volte contro il partitioners. Nel 1807, Napoleone creò il ducato di Varsavia, ma dopo le guerre napoleoniche, la Polonia è stata divisa. Zar russo, che ha governato il paese eventualmente ridotto il polacco libertà, e la Russia catturato il paese. Dopo l'invasione nazista della Germania e dell'Unione Sovietica nel 1939, la Polonia è stato diviso sotto la Germania e l'Unione Sovietica. Polonia perso gran parte dei suoi cittadini, in guerra, sei milioni di euro e almeno la metà ebrei polacchi. Dopo le frontiere sono state spostate dopo la seconda guerra mondiale, molte persone della Polonia sono stati costretti a migrare. [PARAGRAPH: 2] L'Unione Sovietica ha introdotto un nuovo governo comunista in Polonia. La Repubblica popolare di Polonia è stata ufficialmente proclamata nel 1952. Tuttavia, nel 1956, ha ricevuto più persone e la libertà sono stati liberati dalle carceri, dopo la Polonia è diventata più liberale. Nel 1980, un sindacato indipendente ha vinto il partito comunista e si scoprì il crollo del comunismo in tutta l'Europa orientale. A seguito di queste modifiche, la Polonia effettuati numerosi miglioramenti in materia di diritti umani. Nel 1 ° maggio 2004, la Polonia è diventata membro a pieno titolo dell'Unione europea.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB]Durante todo Antigüedad tardía, muchos grupos étnicos de las regiones ocupadas de lo que hoy es Polonia. Muchos eslavos, celtas, Báltico, y las tribus germánicas fueron algunos de los prominentes grupos. El más famoso de encontrar arqueológico de la prehistoria de Polonia es el Biskupin asentamiento fortificado. La fortaleza ha sido la fecha a principios de la Edad de Hierro, cuando la cultura lusaciana ocupó el área alrededor de 700 adC. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Polonia comenzó a tomar la forma de un país unificado alrededor de la mitad del siglo X bajo la dinastía Piast. El cristianismo católico era la nación la primera religión oficial. En el siglo XII, Polonia dividida en varios pequeños estados. En virtud de la Jagiellon dinastía, Polonia forjado una alianza con su vecino, el Gran Ducado de Lituania. Economía polaca, militar, y la cultura floreció en Polonia - Lituania, y en virtud de la Jagiellons. Polonia fue famoso por su tolerancia de todas las religiones, y se convirtió así en un centro de la migración del pueblo judío. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Una edad de oro en el país como resultado de la recién creada Comunidad de Polonia y Lituania. La nobleza de Polonia, que fueron más abundantes que en otros países de Europa occidental, con satisfacción, en el sistema parlamentario. Durante el Siglo de Oro, Polonia amplió sus fronteras para convertirse en el país más grande de Europa. Sin embargo, a mediados del siglo XVII, un sueco invasión y Cosacos del Chmielnicki Uprising marcó el final de su edad de oro. Las guerras contra Rusia también marcó el declive del país. Las reformas, en particular la Gran Sejm, la segunda constitución moderna del mundo, no estaban satisfechos con las tres particiones de Polonia, de Polonia, que terminó siendo eliminado del mapa y sus territorios está dividido entre Rusia, Prusia y Austria. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Los polacos se resienten de su suerte y los rebeldes en varias ocasiones por la partitioners. En 1807, Napoleón creó el Ducado de Varsovia, pero después de las guerras napoleónicas, Polonia fue dividida de nuevo. Los zares de Rusia, que gobernó el país eventualmente reducido el polaco libertades, y Rusia capturó el país. Después de la invasión de la Alemania nazi y la Unión Soviética en 1939, Polonia fue dividida en virtud de Alemania y la Unión Soviética. Polonia perdió gran parte de sus ciudadanos en la guerra, seis millones y por lo menos la mitad polaco Judios. Después de las fronteras se cambiaban después de la Segunda Guerra Mundial, muchos de los polacos se vieron obligados a emigrar. [PARAGRAPH: 2] La Unión Soviética introdujo un nuevo gobierno comunista en Polonia. La República Popular de Polonia fue proclamada oficialmente en 1952. Sin embargo, en 1956, la población recibió más libertades y fueron liberados de las cárceles después de Polonia se convirtió más liberal. En 1980, un sindicato independiente venció el Partido Comunista y bared el colapso del comunismo en Europa oriental. A raíz de estos cambios, Polonia hizo numerosas mejoras en los derechos humanos. En el 1 de mayo de 2004, Polonia se convirtió en miembro de pleno derecho de la Unión Europea.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>	