<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by lcollins (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- Copyright Firaxis Games 2005 -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text - New -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_CANADA_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Canadian Empire</English>
		<French>Canadien Empire</French>
		<German>Kanadisch Reich</German>
		<Italian>Canadese Impero</Italian>
		<Spanish>Canadiense Imperio</Spanish>
	</TEXT>	
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_CANADA_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Canada</English>
		<French>Canada</French>
		<German>Kanada</German>
		<Italian>Canada</Italian>
		<Spanish>Canad&#225;</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_CANADA_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Canadian</English>
		<French>Canadien</French>
		<German>Kanadisch</German>
		<Italian>Canadese</Italian>
		<Spanish>Canadiense</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_CANADA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Various groups of prehistoric peoples inhabited what is now Canada.  Europeans first arrived when the Vikings briefly settled in Canada around 1000 AD.  In the late 1400s and early 1500s, France and England began to send explorers to Canada.  French explorer Samuel de Champlain arrived in 1603 and set up the first enduring European settlements at Port Royal in 1605 and Quebec City in 1608.  These new colonies would come to be known as New France.  Various fur traders came to Canada to participate in the trade with the Native Americans.  When tensions grew, the French and Iroquois Wars broke out over control of the fur trade. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Once the English began settling in Canada and the Thirteen Colonies, several wars broke out resulting in much of the French lands in Canada to be ceded to England.  Canadian borders expanded, and it saw a high number of Irish and British immigrants in the early 1800s.  The timber industry would also surpass the fur trade in importance during this time.  The desire for Responsible Government resulted after the Rebellions of 1837.  The Act of Union in 1840 united all the Canadian lands into a United Province of Canada.  French and English Canadians worked together in the Assembly to restore French rights, which had long been overlooked after Britain's domination in the 1800s. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Canada expanded even more in the mid-1800s through a series of westward expeditions.  The move toward uniting Upper and Lower Canada into one country increased during this time of increased English Canadian nationalism.  Following several constitutional conferences, the British North America Act brought about a Confederation creating one country under the name Canada with four provinces: Ontario, Quebec, Nova Scotia, and New Brunswick.  In time, other provinces joined the Confederation. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Prime Minster John A. Macdonald's Conservative Party set up a National Policy of tariffs to protect emerging Canadian manufacturing industries.  The open the West, the government sponsored construction of three transcontinental railways.  Additionally, the government opened the prairies settlements and established its dominion over the territory.  After the Klondike Gold Rush in 1898, the government decided to create the Yukon Territory as a separate territory.  In 1905, Alberta and Saskatchewan became provinces as more immigrants settled in the prairies. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Canada entered World War I in 1914, sending volunteers to the Western Front.  In 1919, Canada joined the League of Nations independently of Britain.  In 1931, the Statute of Westminster asserted Canada's independence.  The Great Depression of 1929 brought economic hardship to Canada.  Canada declared war on Germany independently during World War II under Prime Minister William Lyon Mackenzie King, three days after Britain.  The Canadian economy boomed as industry manufactured military material for itself, Britain, China and the Soviet Union.  Canada finished the war with one of the largest armed forces in the world [PARAGRAPH: 1] Quebec experienced deep social and economic changes during the Quiet Revolution of the 1960s.  Under successive Liberal governments of Lester B. Pearson and Pierre Trudeau, a new Canadian identity emerged.  Canada adopted its current Maple Leaf Flag in 1965.  Various acts combating cultural discrimination were passed in the 1960s and 1970s as waves of non-European immigration changed the face of the country.  Social democratic programs such as Universal Healthcare, the Canada Pension Plan, and Canada Student Loans were passed during this time.  In the 1980s, the Canadian government pushed toward free trade and closer relations with the United States.  Because of these moves and others toward America, many Canadians worry about their cultural difference from the United States. However, Canadians take special pride in their system of universal healthcare and their commitment to multiculturalism.</English>
		<French>[TAB]Les divers groupes de peuples préhistoriques ont habité ce qui est maintenant le Canada.  Européens sont arrivés la première fois quand Vikings brièvement s'est établi au Canada autour de 1000 APRÈS JÉSUS CHRIST.  Vers la fin de 1400s et de 1500s tôt, la France et l'Angleterre ont commencé à envoyer des explorateurs au Canada.  L'explorateur français Samuel de Champlain est arrivé en 1603 et a établi les premiers règlements européens durables à la ville gauche royale en 1605 et du Québec en 1608.  Ces nouvelles colonies viendraient pour être connues en tant que nouvelle France.  Les divers commerçants de fourrure sont venus au Canada pour participer au commerce avec les Américains indigènes.  Quand les tensions se sont développées, les guerres de Français et d'Iroquois ont éclaté au-dessus de la commande du commerce de fourrure. [PARAGRAPH : 1] Par le passé l'anglais a commencé à s'établir au Canada et les treize colonies, plusieurs guerres ont éclaté ayant pour résultat une grande partie des terres françaises au Canada à céder en Angleterre.  Les frontières canadiennes ont augmenté, et il a vu un nombre élevé d'immigrés irlandais et britanniques dans le 1800s tôt.  L'industrie de bois de construction surpasserait également le commerce de fourrure dans l'importance pendant ce temps.  Le désir pour le gouvernement responsable a résulté après les rébellions de 1837.  La Loi de l'union dans 1840 a uni toutes terres de Canadien dans une province unie du Canada.  Les Canadiens français et anglais ont travaillé ensemble dans l'Assemblée pour reconstituer les droites françaises, qui avaient été longtemps négligées après la domination de la Grande-Bretagne dans le 1800s. [PARAGRAPH : 1] Le Canada augmenté encore plus dans le mid-1800s par une série d'expéditions à l'ouest.  Le mouvement vers unir le Canada supérieur et inférieur dans un pays a augmenté pendant cette période du nationalisme canadien anglais accru.  Après plusieurs conférences constitutionnelles, l'acte des Anglais Amérique du Nord a provoqué une confédération créant un pays sous le nom du Canada avec quatre provinces : Ontario, le Québec, Nouvelle-Écosse, et le Nouveau Brunswick.  À temps, d'autres provinces ont joint la confédération. [PARAGRAPH : 1] Minster principal John A. La partie conservatrice de Macdonald a établi une politique nationale des tarifs pour protéger des industries canadiennes naissantes.  L'ouvert l'ouest, la construction commanditée par le gouvernement de trois chemins de fer transcontinentaux.  En plus, le gouvernement a ouvert les règlements de prairies et a établi son dominion au-dessus du territoire.  Après que les précipitations d'or de Klondike en 1898, le gouvernement aient décidé de créer le territoire de Yukon comme territoire séparé.  En 1905, Alberta et Saskatchewan sont devenus des provinces en tant que plus d'immigrés arrangés dans les prairies. [PARAGRAPH : 1] Le Canada a écrit la Première Guerre Mondiale en 1914, envoyant offre à l'avant occidental.  En 1919, le Canada a adhéré à la ligue des nations indépendamment de la Grande-Bretagne.  En 1931, le statut de Westminster a affirmé l'indépendance du Canada.  La grande dépression de 1929 a apporté des difficultés économiques au Canada.  Le Canada a déclaré la guerre sur l'Allemagne indépendamment pendant la deuxième guerre mondiale sous le roi de William Lyon Mackenzie de premier ministre, trois jours après la Grande-Bretagne.  L'économie canadienne a grondé en tant que matériel militaire construit par industrie pour elle-même, la Grande-Bretagne, la Chine et l'Union Soviétique.  Le Canada a fini la guerre avec une des plus grandes forces armées dans le monde [PARAGRAPH : 1] Changements sociaux du Québec et économiques profonds expérimentés pendant la révolution tranquille des années 60.  Sous des gouvernements libéraux successifs de Lester B. Pearson et Pierre Trudeau, une nouvelle identité canadienne ont émergé.  Le Canada a adopté son drapeau courant de feuille d'érable en 1965.  De divers actes combattant la discrimination culturelle ont été passés dans les années 60 et les années 70 comme les vagues de l'immigration non-européenne ont changé le visage du pays.  Des programmes démocratiques sociaux tels que des soins de santé universels, le plan de retraite de retraite du Canada, et des prêts d'étudiant du Canada ont été passés pendant ce temps.  Dans les années 80, le gouvernement canadien a poussé vers le libre échange et les relations plus étroites avec les Etats-Unis.  En raison de ces mouvements et de d'autres vers l'Amérique, beaucoup de Canadiens s'inquiètent de leur différence culturelle des Etats-Unis. Cependant, les Canadiens prennent la fierté spéciale dans leur système des soins de santé universels et de leur engagement au multiculturalisme.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Verschiedene Gruppen der prähistorischen Völker bewohnten, was jetzt Kanada ist.  Europäer kamen zuerst an, als das Vikings kurz in Kanada um 1000 V. CHR. vereinbarte.  Ende 1400s und frühen 1500s fingen Frankreich und England an, Forscher nach Kanada zu schicken.  Französischer Forscher Samuel de Champlain kam 1603 an und stellte die ersten aushaltenen europäischen Regelungen an der königlicher 1605 und Quebec Portstadt 1608 auf.  Diese neuen Kolonien würden kommen, als neues Frankreich bekannt.  Verschiedene Pelzhändler kamen nach Kanada, am Handel mit den gebürtigen Amerikanern teilzunehmen.  Als Spannungen wuchsen, brachen die Franzose-und Irokese-Kriege über Steuerung des Pelzhandels aus. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Einmal fing Englisch an, in Kanada zu vereinbaren und die dreizehn Kolonien, einige Kriege brachen mit dem Ergebnis viel der französischen nach England überlassen zu werden Länder in Kanada, aus.  Kanadische Ränder erweiterten und es sah eine hohe Anzahl von irischen und britischen Immigranten im frühen 1800s.  Die Bauholzindustrie würde auch den Pelzhandel im Wert während dieser Zeit übertreffen.  Der Wunsch nach verantwortlicher Regierung resultierte nach den Aufständen von 1837.  Die Tat des Anschlußes in 1840 vereinigte alle Kanadierländer in eine vereinigte Provinz von Kanada.  Französische und englische Kanadier arbeiteten zusammen in der Versammlung, um französische Rechte wieder herzustellen, die lang nach Herrschaft Großbritanniens im 1800s übersehen worden waren. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Kanada sogar erweitert in das mid-1800s durch eine Reihe nach Westen gerichtete Expeditionen.  Die Bewegung in Richtung zum Vereinigen von oberem und untererem Kanada in ein Land erhöhte sich während dieser Zeit des erhöhten englischen kanadischen Nationalismus.  Nach einigen konstitutionellen Konferenzen holte die Briten Nordamerika Tat ein ungefähr Bündnis, das ein Land unter dem Namen Kanada mit vier Provinzen herstellt: Ontario, Quebec, Neuschottland und New-Brunswick.  In der Zeit verbanden andere Provinzen das Bündnis. [PARAGRAPH: 1] HauptMinster John A. Macdonalds konservative Partei stellte eine nationale Politik von Tarifen auf, um auftauchende kanadische Fertigungsindustrien zu schützen.  Das geöffnete der Westen, der staatlich geförderte Aufbau von drei transkontinentalen Gleisen.  Zusätzlich öffnete die Regierung die Graslandregelungen und stellte seine Herrschaft über der Gegend her.  Nachdem die Klondike Goldanstürme 1898, die Regierung entschieden, die Yukon Gegend als unterschiedliche Gegend herzustellen.  1905 wurden Alberta und Saskatchewan Provinzen als mehr Immigranten, die im Grasland vereinbart wurden. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Kanada trug den Ersten Weltkrieg 1914 ein und sendete sich freiwillig erbietet zur westlichen Frontseite.  1919 verband Kanada die Liga von Nationen unabhängig von Großbritannien.  1931 erklärte das Gesetz von Westminster Unabhängigkeit Kanadas.  Der große Tiefstand von 1929 holte ökonomische Härte nach Kanada.  Kanada erklärte Krieg auf Deutschland unabhängig während des Zweiten Weltkrieges unter Premierminister-William Lyon Mackenzie König, drei Tage nach Großbritannien.  Die kanadische Wirtschaft dröhnte als Industrie hergestelltes militärisches Material für sich, Großbritannien, China und die Sowjetunion.  Kanada beendete den Krieg mit einer der größten bewaffneten Kräfte in der Welt [PARAGRAPH: 1] Quebec erfahrene tiefe Sozial- und ökonomische änderungen während der ruhigen Revolution der sechziger Jahre.  Unter aufeinanderfolgenden liberalen Regierungen von Lester B. Pearson und Pierre Trudeau, eine neue kanadische Identität tauchten auf.  Kanada nahm seine gegenwärtige Ahornholz-Blatt-Markierungsfahne 1965 an.  Die verschiedenen Taten, die kulturelle Unterscheidung bekämpfen, wurden in die sechziger Jahre und in die siebziger Jahre geführt, wie Wellen der außereuropäischen Immigration das Gesicht des Landes änderten.  Demokratische sozialprogramme wie UniversalHealthcare, die Kanada Rentenversicherung und Kanada Kursteilnehmer-Darlehen wurden während dieser Zeit geführt.  Die achtziger Jahre drückte sich die kanadische Regierung in Richtung zum Freihandel und zu den genaueren Relationen mit den Vereinigten Staaten ein.  Wegen dieser Bewegungen und anderer in Richtung zu Amerika, sorgen sich viele Kanadier um ihren kulturellen Unterschied von den Vereinigten Staaten. Jedoch nehmen Kanadier speziellen Stolz in ihrem System von Universalhealthcare und von ihrer Verpflichtung zum Multikulturalismus.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB]I vari gruppi della gente prehistoric hanno abitato che cosa ora è il Canada.  Europei in primo luogo sono arrivato quando il Vikings brevemente si è depositato nel Canada intorno all'ANNUNCIO 1000.  Verso la fine di 1400s e di 1500s iniziale, la Francia e l'Inghilterra hanno cominciato a trasmettere gli esploratori nel Canada.  L'esploratore francese Samuel de Champlain è arrivato in 1603 ed ha installato i primi stabilimenti europei duraturi nei porti la città della Quebec e in 1605 reale in 1608.  Queste nuove colonie verrebbero essere conosciute come nuova Francia.  I vari commercianti della pelliccia sono venuto nel Canada partecipare al commercio con gli Americani natali.  Quando i tensionamenti si sono sviluppati, le guerre del Iroquois e del francese hanno scoppiato sopra controllo del commercio della pelliccia. [PARAGRAPH: 1] L'inglese ha cominciato una volta a depositarsi nel Canada e le tredici colonie, parecchie guerre hanno scoppiato con conseguente gran parte delle terre francesi nel Canada da cedere in Inghilterra.  I bordi canadesi espansi ed esso hanno visto un alto numero di immigranti irlandesi e britannici nel 1800s iniziale.  L'industria del legname inoltre sorpasserebbe il commercio della pelliccia nell'importanza durante questo tempo.  Il desiderio per il governo responsabile ha risultato dopo le ribellioni di 1837.  La Legge dell'unione in 1840 ha unito tutte le terre del canadese in una provincia unita del Canada.  I canadesi francesi ed inglesi hanno lavorato insieme nell'Assemblea per ristabilire i diritti francesi, che lungamente erano stati trascurati dopo la dominazione della Gran-Bretagna nel 1800s. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Il Canada espanso ancor più nel mid-1800s con una serie di spedizioni westward.  Il movimento verso unire il Canada superiore e più basso in un paese è aumentato durante questo periodo di nazionalismo canadese inglese aumentato.  A seguito di parecchi congressi costituzionali, la Legge dei Britannici America del Nord ha determinato una confederazione che genera un paese sotto il nome del Canada con quattro province: Ontario, la Quebec, Nuova Scozia ed il Nuovo Brunswick.  A tempo, altre province hanno unito la confederazione. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Minster principale John A. Il partito conservatore del Macdonald ha installato una politica nazionale delle tariffe per proteggere le industrie manufatturiere canadesi d'emersione.  L'aperto l'ovest, il governo ha patrocinato una costruzione di tre ferrovie transcontinentali.  Ulteriormente, il governo ha aperto gli stabilimenti dei prairies ed ha stabilito il relativo dominion sopra il territorio.  Dopo che gli sbalzi dell'oro di Klondike in 1898, il governo decidano generare il territorio di Yukon come territorio separato.  In 1905, Alberta e Saskatchewan si sono trasformati in in province come più immigranti depositati nei prairies. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Il Canada ha fornito la guerra mondiale I di 1914, trasmettendo si offre volontariamente alla parte anteriore occidentale.  In 1919, il Canada ha fatto parte indipendentemente della lega delle nazioni dalla Gran-Bretagna.  In 1931, lo statuto di Westminster ha asserito l'indipendenza del Canada.  La depressione grande di 1929 ha portato le difficoltà economiche nel Canada.  Il Canada ha dichiarato indipendentemente la guerra con Germania durante la seconda guerra mondiale sotto il re del William Lione Mackenzie del Primo Ministro, tre giorni dopo la Gran-Bretagna.  L'economia canadese ha cresciuto come materiale militare prodotto industria per se, la Gran-Bretagna, la Cina e l'Unione Sovietica.  Il Canada ha rifinito la guerra con una di più grandi forze munite nel mondo [PARAGRAPH: 1] Cambiamenti sociali della Quebec ed economici profondi con esperienza durante la rivoluzione calma degli anni 60.  Sotto i governi liberali successivi di Lester B. Pearson e Pierre Trudeau, una nuova identità canadese sono emerso.  Il Canada ha adottato la relativa bandierina corrente del foglio dell'acero in 1965.  I vari atti che combattono la distinzione culturale sono stati passati negli anni 60 e negli anni 70 come le onde dell'immigrazione non-European hanno cambiato la faccia del paese.  I programmi democratici sociali quali Healthcare universale, il programma di pensione del Canada ed i prestiti di allievo del Canada sono stati passati durante questo tempo.  Negli anni 80, il governo canadese ha spinto verso libero scambio e rapporti più vicini con gli Stati Uniti.  A causa di questi movimenti e di altri verso l'America, molti canadesi si preoccupano per la loro differenza culturale dagli Stati Uniti. Tuttavia, i canadesi prendono l'orgoglio speciale nel loro sistema di healthcare universale e del loro impegno al multiculturalism.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB]Los varios grupos de gente prehistórica habitaron cuál ahora es Canadá.  Europeos primero llegaron cuando el Vikings colocó brevemente en Canadá alrededor del ANUNCIO 1000.  En el último 1400s y el 1500s temprano, Francia e Inglaterra comenzaron a enviar a exploradores a Canadá.  El explorador francés Samuel de Champlain llegó en 1603 e instaló los primeros establecimientos europeos que aguantaban en la ciudad real en 1605 y de Quebec portuaria en 1608.  Estas nuevas colonias vendrían ser conocidas como Francia nueva.  Los varios comerciantes de la piel vinieron a Canadá participar en el comercio con los americanos nativos.  Cuando las tensiones crecieron, las guerras del francés y del Iroquois explotaron sobre el control del comercio de la piel. [PARAGRAPH: 1] El inglés comenzó una vez a colocar en Canadá y las trece colonias, varias guerras explotaron dando por resultado mucha de las tierras francesas en Canadá que se cederán a Inglaterra.  Las fronteras canadienses se ampliaron, y vio un alto número de inmigrantes irlandeses y británicos en el 1800s temprano.  La industria de la madera también sobrepasaría el comercio de la piel en importancia durante este tiempo.  El deseo para el gobierno responsable resultó después de las rebeliones de 1837.  El acto de la unión en 1840 unió todas las tierras del canadiense en una provincia unida de Canadá.  Los canadienses franceses e ingleses trabajaron juntos en la asamblea para restaurar las derechas francesas, que habían sido pasadas por alto de largo después de la dominación de Gran Bretaña en el 1800s. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Canadá ampliado aún más en el mid-1800s con una serie de expediciones que va hacia el oeste.  El movimiento hacia la unión de Canadá superior y más bajo en un país aumentó durante esta época del nacionalismo canadiense inglés creciente.  Después de varias conferencias constitucionales, el acto de Británicos Norteamérica trajo alrededor de una confederación que creaba un país bajo el nombre de Canadá con cuatro provincias: Ontario, Quebec, Nueva Escocia, y Nuevo Brunswick.  A tiempo, otras provincias ensamblaron la confederación. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Minster primero Juan A. El partido conservador de Macdonald instaló una política nacional de tarifas para proteger industrias fabriles canadienses que emergían.  El abierto el oeste, el gobierno patrocinó la construcción de tres ferrocarriles transcontinentales.  Además, el gobierno abrió los establecimientos de las praderas y estableció su dominio sobre el territorio.  Después de que las acometidas del oro de Klondike en 1898, el gobierno decidieran a crear el territorio de Yukon como territorio separado.  En 1905, Alberta y Saskatchewan se convirtieron en provincias como más inmigrantes colocados en las praderas. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Canadá incorporó Primera Guerra Mundial a 1914, enviando se ofrece voluntariamente al frente occidental.  En 1919, Canadá ensambló la liga de naciones independientemente de Gran Bretaña.  En 1931, el estatuto de Westminster afirmó la independencia de Canadá.  La gran depresión de 1929 trajo dificultad económica a Canadá.  Canadá declaró guerra en Alemania independientemente durante la Segunda Guerra Mundial debajo del rey de Guillermo Lyon Mackenzie del primer ministro, tres días después de Gran Bretaña.  La economía canadiense creció como material militar fabricado industria para sí mismo, Gran Bretaña, China y la Unión Soviética.  Canadá acabó la guerra con una de las fuerzas armadas más grandes del mundo [PARAGRAPH: 1] Cambios sociales y económicos profundos experimentados Quebec durante la revolución reservada de los años 60.  Bajo gobiernos liberales sucesivos de Lester B. Pearson y Pierre Trudeau, una nueva identidad canadiense emergieron.  Canadá adoptó su bandera actual de la hoja del arce en 1965.  Los varios actos que combatían la discriminación cultural fueron pasados en los años 60 y los años 70 como las ondas de la inmigración no europea cambiaron la cara del país.  Los programas democráticos sociales tales como Healthcare universal, el plan de jubilación de Canadá, y préstamos de estudiante de Canadá fueron pasados durante este tiempo.  En los años 80, el gobierno canadiense empujado hacia libre cambio y relaciones más cercanas con los Estados Unidos.  Debido a estos movimientos y otros hacia América, muchos canadienses se preocupan de su diferencia cultural de los Estados Unidos. Sin embargo, los canadienses llevan orgullo especial en su sistema del healthcare universal y de su comisión el multiculturalismo.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>	