<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by lcollins (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- Copyright Firaxis Games 2005 -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text - New -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
        <TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_HEAVY_HUSSAR</Tag>
		<English>Winged Hussar</English>
		<French>Winged Hussar</French>
		<German>Winged Hussar</German>
		<Italian>Winged Hussar</Italian>
		<Spanish>Húsar Alado</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_HEAVY_HUSSAR_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The first hussar units in the Kingdom of Poland were formed by the Sejm, the Polish Parliament, in 1503 which hired three banners of Hungarian mercenaries.  Soon, recruitment also began among Polish and Lithuanian citizens.  The Hussars proved vital to Poland because they were more maneuverable than the previously used lancers.  But the reign of King Stefan Batory, the hussars formed the bulk of the Polish and Lithuanian cavalry.  Over many years, hussars in Hungary became heavier.  When Stefan Batory was elected king of Poland, he reorganized the Polish-Lithuanian hussars of his Royal Guard making them a heavy formation, and equipping lancers as their main weapon. These Polish 'heavy' hussars were known in their homeland as "husaria" [PARAGRAPH: 1] With the Battle of Lubiszew in 1577, the "Golden Age" of the hussar began.  Until the Battle of Vienna, Polish-Lithuanian hussars rarely lost in battle.  Throughout many battles the Polish-Lithuanian hussars would prove to be an important factor against overwhelming odds. [PARAGRAPH: 1] The primary battle tactic of the Polish-Lithuanian hussars was the charge.  They also tended to repeat the charge until the enemy formation broke.  The hussars fought with a long lance, a szabla, one or two pistols, and a carbine or arquebus, known in Polish as a "bandolet".  Polish hussars were also famous for the wings they wore on their backs.  According to some theories, they were designed to foil attacks by Tatar lassos, another theory being that the vibrating of feathers made a strange sound that frightened enemy horses.  However, experiments carried out by re-enactors and movie-makers since the 1970s and more recently by Polish historians in 2001 contradict such ideas. Possibly the wings were worn only during parades and not during combat, but this explanation is also disputed.</English>
		<French>[TAB]La première hussarde unités dans le Royaume de Pologne ont été formés par le Sejm, le Parlement polonais, en 1503, qui a engagé trois bannières de mercenaires hongrois. Bientôt, le recrutement a commencé entre les citoyens polonais et lituaniens. Les Hussards avérée vitale pour la Pologne, parce qu'ils étaient plus manoeuvrable que les lanciers précédemment utilisés. But le règne du roi Stefan Batory, les hussards formaient le gros de la cavalerie polonaise et lituanienne. Depuis de nombreuses années, hussards en Hongrie est devenue plus lourde. Lorsque Stefan Batory est élu roi de Pologne, il a réorganisé le polonais-lituanien hussards de sa garde royale rendant une lourde formation et l'équipement des lanciers comme leur principale arme. Ces polonais "lourds" hussards étaient connus dans leur pays comme "husaria" [PARAGRAPH: 1] Avec la bataille de Lubiszew en 1577, l'âge d'or "de la hussarde a commencé. Jusqu'à la bataille de Vienne, polonais-lituanien hussards rarement perdu dans la bataille. Tout au long de nombreuses batailles l'polonais-lituanien hussards se révéler être un important facteur écrasante contre chances. [PARAGRAPH: 1] La principale bataille tactique de la polonais-lituanien hussards a la charge. Ils ont également tendance à répéter les frais jusqu'à la formation ennemie a éclaté. Les hussards combattu avec une longue Lance, un szabla, un ou deux pistolets, et un mousqueton ou arquebuse, connue en polonais comme un "bandolet". Hussards polonais étaient reconnus pour les ailes, ils portaient sur leur dos. Selon certaines théories, mais ils ont été conçus pour déjouer les attaques menées par des lassos tatare, une autre théorie est que la vibration de plumes fait une étrange que le son ennemi effrayé les chevaux. Toutefois, les expériences menées par la réorientation enactors et film décideurs depuis les années 1970 et, plus récemment, par les historiens polonais en 2001 contredisent de telles idées. Eventuellement les ailes ont été portées seulement pendant les parades et non pas pendant le combat, mais cette explication est également contesté.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Die ersten Husaren in das Königreich Polen wurden durch den Sejm, das polnische Parlament, in der 1503 die drei gemietet Banner der ungarischen Söldnern. Bald begann auch die Einstellung der polnischen und litauischen Bürger. Die Husaren als entscheidend für Polen, weil sie mehr wendiger als die bisher verwendeten Speerträger. But der Regierungszeit von König Stefan Batory, die Husaren bilden den größten Teil der polnischen und litauischen Kavallerie. Über viele Jahre, Husaren in Ungarn wurde schwerer. Wenn Stefan Batory gewählt wurde König von Polen, er hat die Polnisch Husaren seiner Royal Guard und machen sie zu einer schweren Ausbildung, Ausrüstung und Speerträger als ihre wichtigste Waffe. Diese polnischen "schwere" Husaren bekannt waren, in ihrer eigenen Heimat als "husaria" [PARAGRAPH: 1] Mit der Schlacht von Lubiszew im 1577, das "Goldene Zeitalter" der Husaren begann. Bis in die Schlacht von Wien, Polnisch Husaren selten verloren in der Schlacht. In vielen Schlachten der polnischen Husaren - Litauisch würde sich als ein wichtiger Faktor gegen die überwältigende Quoten. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Der primäre Kampf Taktik der polnisch-litauischen Husaren war. Darüber hinaus neigten die Gebühr zu wiederholen, bis der Feind Bildung pleite. Die Husaren kämpften mit einer langen Lanze, ein szabla, ein oder zwei Pistolen, und einem Karabiner oder arquebus, die in der polnischen als "bandolet." Polnischen Husaren waren auch berühmt für die Flügel trugen sie auf dem Rücken. Nach einigen Theorien, sie wurden so gestaltet, dass Folie Angriffe von Tataren Lassos, eine andere Theorie ist, dass die Vibrationen von Federn, die ein seltsames Geräusch, Angst Feind Pferde. Allerdings, Experimente durchgeführt erneut enactors und Film Entscheidungsträger seit den 1970er Jahren und in jüngster Zeit von den polnischen Historiker in der 2001 im Widerspruch zu solchen Ideen. Möglicherweise die Flügel getragen wurden nur während der Paraden und nicht während des Kampfes, aber diese Erklärung ist auch umstritten.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB]La prima unità ussaro nel Regno di Polonia si sono formati dal Sejm, il parlamento polacco, nel 1503, che noleggiati tre bandiere ungheresi di mercenari. Presto, ha iniziato il reclutamento anche tra i cittadini polacchi e lituani. Il Ussari rivelato fondamentale per la Polonia perché erano più manovrabile da quella usata in precedenza lance. Ma il regno di Stefan Batory, la ussari formata la maggior parte della cavalleria polacco e lituano. Nel corso di molti anni, ussari in Ungheria è diventata più pesante. Stefan Batory, quando è stato eletto re di Polonia, ha riorganizzato il Polacco-Lituana ussari del suo Royal Guard rendendoli un pesante formazione, e di dotare le lance come loro principale arma. Questi polacco 'pesanti' ussari erano conosciuti in patria come "husaria" [N: 1] Con la Battaglia di Lubiszew nel 1577, il "Golden Age" del ussaro iniziato. Fino alla battaglia di Vienna, polacco - lituano ussari raramente perso in battaglia. In molti battaglie polacco - lituano ussari sarebbe rivelato un fattore importante contro la stragrande quota. [PARAGRAPH: 1] La principale battaglia tattica del Polacco-Lituana ussari era l'accusa. Essi hanno anche la tendenza a ripetere la carica fino a quando il nemico formazione rotto. Il ussari combattuto con una lunga lancia, un szabla, uno o due pistole, e di una carabina o arquebus, in polacco noto come "bandolet". Ussari polacchi sono stati anche famosa per le ali che indossavano sulle loro spalle. Secondo alcune teorie, che sono stati progettati per sventare attacchi da Tataro lassos, un'altra teoria è che la vibrazione di piume fatto uno strano suono che spaventati nemico cavalli. Tuttavia, gli esperimenti effettuati da ristabilire enactors movie e responsabili dal 1970 e, più recentemente, dal polacco storici nel 2001 in contrasto con tali idee. Eventualmente, le ali sono stati indossati solo durante parate, e non durante il combattimento, ma questa spiegazione è anche contestato.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB]La primera hussar unidades en el Reino de Polonia se formaron por el Sejm, el Parlamento polaco, en 1503, que contrató a tres pancartas húngaro de los mercenarios. En breve, también se inició la contratación entre los ciudadanos polacos y lituanos. El Hussars resultó vital para Polonia, ya que fueron más maniobrable que los utilizados anteriormente lancers. But el reinado del rey Stefan Batory, la hussars forman el grueso de la caballería polaco y lituano. Durante muchos años, hussars en Hungría se convirtió en más pesadas. Cuando Stefan Batory fue elegido rey de Polonia, se reorganizó el polaco - lituano hussars de su Guardia Real convierten en una pesada formación, y el equipamiento lancers como su principal arma. Estos polaco 'pesadas' hussars eran conocidos en su tierra natal como "husaria" [PARAGRAPH: 1] Con la Batalla de Lubiszew en 1577, la "Edad de Oro" de la hussar comenzó. Hasta la Batalla de Viena, polaco, lituano hussars rara vez perdió en la batalla. Muchas batallas en todo el polaco - lituano hussars resultaría ser un factor importante en contra de enormes dificultades. [PARAGRAPH: 1] La principal batalla de la táctica polaca y lituana hussars era el cargo. También tienden a repetir el cargo hasta que el enemigo rompió la formación. El hussars luchó con una larga lanza, un szabla, una o dos pistolas, y una carabina o arquebus, conocido en Polonia como una "bandolet". Polish hussars también famoso por las alas que llevaban en sus espaldas. Según algunas teorías, que estaban diseñadas para frustrar los ataques de tártaro lassos, otra teoría es que la vibración de plumas hizo un extraño sonido que asustados caballos enemigo. Sin embargo, los experimentos llevados a cabo por volver a enactors y de la película de la formulación desde el decenio de 1970 y más recientemente por historiadores de Polonia en 2001 contradice esas ideas. Posiblemente las alas se usaron sólo durante los desfiles y no durante el combate, pero esta explicación es también controvertida.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_HEAVY_HUSSAR_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>This powerful mounted unit (the Polish replacement for the [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Cuirassier[COLOR_REVERT]) is excellent against seige weapons and melee infantry, because of its Charge I and Shock I promotions.</English>
		<French>Cette puissante unité de montage (la Pologne pour le remplacement [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Cuirassier[COLOR_REVERT]) est excellent contre les armes de siège à cause de son chargé I et Shock I de promotions. </French>
		<German>Dieses leistungsfähige Einheit montiert (die polnische Ersatz für die [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Cuirassier[COLOR_REVERT]) ist hervorragend gegen die Belagerung Waffen wegen seiner Charge I und Shock I Förderung. </German>
		<Italian>Questa potente unità montate (il polacco sostituzione per il[COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Cuirassier[COLOR_REVERT]), è eccellente contro assedio armi a causa della sua carica di promozione.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Esta potente unidad montada (el reemplazo polaco para el [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Coracero[COLOR_REVERT]) es excelente contra las armas de asedio y la infanteria de mele debido a las promociones Carga I y Shock I.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_A1</Tag>
		<English>AA</English>
		<French>
			<Text>AA</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>AA</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>AA</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>AA</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_A2</Tag>
		<English>BB</English>
		<French>
			<Text>BB</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>BB</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>BB</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>BB</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_A3</Tag>
		<English>CC</English>
		<French>
			<Text>CC</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>CC</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>CC</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>CC</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_A4</Tag>
		<English>DD</English>
		<French>
			<Text>DD</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>DD</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>DD</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>DD</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_A5</Tag>
		<English>EE</English>
		<French>
			<Text>EE</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>EE</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>EE</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>EE</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_A6</Tag>
		<English>FF</English>
		<French>
			<Text>FF</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>FF</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>FF</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>FF</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_A7</Tag>
		<English>GG</English>
		<French>
			<Text>GG</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>GG</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>GG</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>GG</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_A8</Tag>
		<English>HH</English>
		<French>
			<Text>HH</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>HH</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>HH</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>HH</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_A9</Tag>
		<English>II</English>
		<French>
			<Text>II</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>II</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>II</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>II</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_A0</Tag>
		<English>JJ</English>
		<French>
			<Text>JJ</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>JJ</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>JJ</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>JJ</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_B1</Tag>
		<English>KK</English>
		<French>
			<Text>KK</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>KK</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>KK</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>KK</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_B2</Tag>
		<English>LL</English>
		<French>
			<Text>LL</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>LL</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>LL</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>LL</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_B3</Tag>
		<English>MM</English>
		<French>
			<Text>MM</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>MM</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>MM</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>MM</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_B4</Tag>
		<English>NN</English>
		<French>
			<Text>NN</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>NN</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>NN</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>NN</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_B5</Tag>
		<English>OO</English>
		<French>
			<Text>OO</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>OO</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>OO</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>OO</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_B6</Tag>
		<English>PP</English>
		<French>
			<Text>PP</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>PP</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>PP</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>PP</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_B7</Tag>
		<English>QQ</English>
		<French>
			<Text>QQ</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>QQ</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>QQ</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>QQ</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_B8</Tag>
		<English>RR</English>
		<French>
			<Text>RR</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>RR</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>RR</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>RR</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_B9</Tag>
		<English>SS</English>
		<French>
			<Text>SS</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>SS</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>SS</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>SS</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_B0</Tag>
		<English>TT</English>
		<French>
			<Text>TT</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>TT</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>TT</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>TT</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_C1</Tag>
		<English>UU</English>
		<French>
			<Text>UU</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>UU</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>UU</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>UU</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_C2</Tag>
		<English>VV</English>
		<French>
			<Text>VV</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>VV</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>VV</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>VV</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_C3</Tag>
		<English>WW</English>
		<French>
			<Text>WW</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>WW</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>WW</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>WW</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_C4</Tag>
		<English>XX</English>
		<French>
			<Text>XX</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>XX</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>XX</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>XX</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_C5</Tag>
		<English>YY</English>
		<French>
			<Text>YY</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>YY</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>YY</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>YY</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_C6</Tag>
		<English>ZZ</English>
		<French>
			<Text>ZZ</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>ZZ</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>ZZ</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>ZZ</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_C7</Tag>
		<English>AAA</English>
		<French>
			<Text>AAA</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>AAA</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>AAA</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>AAA</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_C8</Tag>
		<English>BBB</English>
		<French>
			<Text>BBB</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>BBB</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>BBB</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>BBB</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_C9</Tag>
		<English>CCC</English>
		<French>
			<Text>CCC</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>CCC</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>CCC</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>CCC</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_C0</Tag>
		<English>DDD</English>
		<French>
			<Text>DDD</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>DDD</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>DDD</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>DDD</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>