<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by lcollins (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- Copyright Firaxis Games 2005 -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text - New -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_VECHE</Tag>
		<English>Veche Hall</English>
		<French>Assemblée vétché</French>
		<German>Wetsche Saal</German>
		<Italian>Veche Femminile</Italian>
		<Spanish>Veche Feminino</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
        <TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_VECHE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The word "veche" refers to popular assemblies in medieval Slavic countries.  In the Kievan Rus, a medieval Ukrainian kingdom is known to be the origin of many of the other veches throughout Slavic countries.  The earliest mentions of veches in Russian chronicles refer to examples in Belgorod, a city on the Dnieper in 977, the Novgorod Republic in 1016, and in Kiev in 1068.  The assemblies discussed matters of war and peace, adopted laws, and called for and expelled rulers.</English>
		<French>[TAB]Le mot « veche » se rapporte aux assemblées populaires dans les pays slaves médiévaux.  Dans le Kievan Rus, un royaume ukrainien médiéval est connu pour être l'origine de plusieurs des autres veches dans tous les pays slaves.  Les mentions les plus tôt des veches en chroniques russes se rapportent à des exemples dans Belgorod, à une ville sur le Dnieper dans 977, à la République de Novgorod en 1016, et à Kiev en 1068.  Les assemblées ont discuté des points de guerre et de paix, ont adopté des lois, et ont appelé pour et ont expulsé des règles.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Das Wort „veche“ bezieht sich auf populäre Versammlungen in den mittelalterlichen Slavic Ländern.  Im Kievan Rus, bekannt ein mittelalterliches ukrainisches Königreich, um der Ursprung von vielen der anderen veches in Slavic Ländern zu sein.  Die frühesten Erwähnungen von veches in den russischen Chroniken beziehen sich Beispiele in Belgorod, eine Stadt auf dem Dnieper in 977, die auf Novgorod Republik 1016 und in Kiew 1068.  Die Versammlungen berieten über Sachen des Krieges und des Friedens, nahmen Gesetze an und verlangten und trieben Lehren weg.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB]La parola “veche„ si riferisce ai complessivi popolari nei paesi medioevali di Slavic.  Nel Kievan Rus, un regno ucraino medioevale è conosciuto per essere l'origine di molti degli altri veches durante i paesi di Slavic.  Le menzioni più iniziali dei veches in chronicles russi si riferiscono agli esempi in Belgorod, ad una città sul Dnieper in 977, alla Repubblica di Novgorod in 1016 ed a Kiev in 1068.  I complessivi hanno discusso sugli argomenti della guerra e della pace, hanno adottato le leggi ed hanno richiesto ed hanno espulso i righelli.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB]La palabra “veche” refiere a las asambleas populares en los países medievales de Slavic.  En el Kievan Rus, un reino ucraniano medieval se conoce para ser el origen de muchos de los otros veches a través de los países de Slavic.  Las menciones más tempranas de veches en los chronicles rusos refieren a ejemplos en Belgorod, a una ciudad en el Dnieper en 977, a la república de Novgorod en 1016, y en Kiev en 1068.  Las materias discutidas asambleas de la guerra y paz, leyes adoptados, y llamado para y reglas expelidas.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
        <TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_VECHE_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Veche[COLOR_REVERT], the Ukrainian replacement for the [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Courthouse[COLOR_REVERT], offers additional food.</English>
		<French>[TAB]L'[COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]assemblée vétché[COLOR_REVERT], équivalent ukrainien du [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]tribunal[COLOR_REVERT], procure davantage de nourriture.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Die [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Wetsche[COLOR_REVERT], die Ukrainisch Ersatz für die [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Gerichtsgeb&#228;ude[COLOR_REVERT], bietet Bonus Food.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB]L'[COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Veche[COLOR_REVERT], la sostituzione Ucraino per il [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Palazzo di giustizia[COLOR_REVERT], offre bonus di food.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB]El [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Veche[COLOR_REVERT], la sustitución de Ucraniano para el [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Delegaci&#243;[COLOR_REVERT], ofrece bonificación de la food. </Spanish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>