<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by lcollins (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- Copyright Firaxis Games 2005 -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text - New -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_PIYE</Tag>
		<English>Piye</English>
		<French>Piankhy</French>
		<German>Pije</German>
		<Italian>Piye</Italian>
		<Spanish>Pianjy</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_PIYE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Piye[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Pharaoh of Egypt[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Reigned: [\BOLD]752 BC - 721 BC.[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH: 1][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]At the beginning of his reign, Piye took advantage of the bickering Egyptian rulers by expanding the power of Nubia beyond Thebes into central Egypt.  Tefnakht of Sais, in reaction against the increasing Kushite pressure in Upper Egypt, formed an alliance between the local kings of the Delta Region and lured King Nimlot of Hermopolis, Piye's apparent ally, into defecting to his side.  Tefnakht then sent his union's army south and besieged Herakleopolis, where its king appealed to Piye for help.  Piye assembled an army to invade Middle and Lower Egypt. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Piye marched north and achieved complete victory at Herakleopolis, conquering the cities of Hermopolis, Memphis, and others.  He also received the submission of several kings of the Nile Delta.  Tefnakht took refuge in an island in the Delta and accepted defeat in a letter to Piye, though refused to pay homage to the Kushite king.  Satisfied with these successes, Piye sailed to his homeland in Nubia.  Despite Piye's success, his authority only extended north of Thebes to the western desert oasis and Herakleopolis.  Therefore, the local kings of Lower Egypt, especially Tefnakht, were free to do as they pleased without Piye's oversight. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Piye was more passionate about the worship of the god Amun more than other kings of Nubia.  He improved the declining Great Temple of Amun at Gebel Barkal.  Piye was buried in a pyramid at elKurru near Hebel Barkal, a site that would be occupied by the tombs of several later members of the dynasty.</English>
		<French>[H1]Piankhy[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Pharaon de Egypte[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Régné: [\BOLD]752 BC - 721 BC.[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH: 1][BOLD]Fond:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Au début de son règne, Piye a profité de la bisbille dirigeants égyptiens par l'expansion de la puissance audelà de la Nubie Thèbes en Égypte centrale. Tefnakht de Sais, en réaction contre l'augmentation Kushite pression en Haute Égypte, a formé une alliance entre les rois de la région du delta et attirés Roi Nimlot d'Hermopolis, Piye semble allié, en défection de son côté. Tefnakht alors envoyé son armée au sud du syndicat et assiégé Herakleopolis, où son roi Piye lancé un appel à l'aide. Piye assemblé une armée d'envahir Moyenne et Basse Égypte. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Piye marcha vers le nord et atteint complète victoire à Herakleopolis, de la conquête des villes de Hermopolis, de Memphis et d'autres. Il a également reçu la présentation de plusieurs rois du Delta du Nil. Tefnakht se réfugier dans une île du Delta et accepté la défaite dans une lettre adressée à Piye, mais a refusé de rendre hommage au Kushite roi. Satisfait de ces succès, Piye navigué dans sa patrie en Nubie. Piye Malgré son succès, son autorité ne s'étendait vers le nord de Thèbes à l'ouest du désert oasis et Herakleopolis. Par conséquent, les rois de la Basse Egypte, surtout Tefnakht, étaient libres de faire comme ils voulaient sans Piye l'oubli. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Piye était plus passionné par le culte du dieu Amon de plus que les autres rois de Nubie. Il a amélioré la baisse du Grand Temple d'Amon à Gebel Barkal. Piye a été enterré dans une pyramide à el Kurru près Hebel Barkal, un site qui serait occupé par les tombes de plusieurs membres du coté de la dynastie.</French>
		<German>[H1]Pije[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Pharao von Ägypten[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Regierte:[\BOLD]752 BC - 721 BC..[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH: 1][BOLD]Hintergrund:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Zu Beginn seiner Regierungszeit, Piye nutzten die Kabbeleien ägyptischen Herrscher durch die Erweiterung der Leistung von Nubien über Theben in zentralen Ägypten. Tefnakht von Sais, in der Reaktion auf die wachsende Kushite Druck in Oberägypten, eine Allianz zwischen der lokalen Könige der Delta Region gelockt und König Nimlot von Hermopolis, Piye der scheinbaren Verbündeten, in defecting auf seiner Seite. Tefnakht dann seiner Gewerkschaft Armee Süden und belagert Herakleopolis, wo seine König appellierte an Piye um Hilfe zu erhalten. Piye montiert eine Armee, um in Mittel und Niederösterreich Ägypten. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Piye marschierten Norden und erreicht vollständigen Sieg bei Herakleopolis, erobern die Städte Hermopolis, Memphis, und andere. Er erhielt außerdem die Vorlage von mehreren Könige des Nildeltas. Tefnakht Zuflucht auf einer Insel im Delta und akzeptiert Niederlage in einem Brief an Piye, obwohl sich geweigert, eine Hommage an die Kushite König. Zufrieden mit diesen Erfolgen, Piye fuhr in seine Heimat in Nubien. Trotz Piye Erfolg, seine Behörde nur verlängert nördlich von Theben auf der westlichen Wüste Oase und Herakleopolis. Daher ist die lokale Könige von Niederösterreich Ägypten, vor allem Tefnakht, frei zu tun, wie sie froh, ohne Piye Aufsicht. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Piye war leidenschaftlich über die Verehrung des Gottes Amun mehr als andere Könige von Nubien. Er verbesserte die rückläufigen Großer Tempel des Amun in Gebel Barkal. Piye wurde in einer Pyramide auf el Kurru nahe Hebel Barkal, eine Website, wäre besetzten durch die Gräber von mehreren später Mitglieder der Dynastie.</German>
		<Italian>[H1]Piye[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Pharaoh di Egitto[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Regnato:[\BOLD]752 BC - 721 BC.[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH: 1][BOLD]Priorità bassa:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]All'inizio del suo regno, Piye ha approfittato della bickering egiziano governanti ampliando il potere di Nubia centrali al di là di Tebe in Egitto. Tefnakht di Sais, in reazione contro la crescente Kushite pressione in Egitto, formata un'alleanza tra il re locale del Delta Regione e attirato re Nimlot di Hermopolis, Piye's apparente alleato, in defecting al suo fianco. Tefnakht poi inviato il suo sindacato l'esercito del sud e assediata Herakleopolis, dove il suo re appello a Piye per chiedere aiuto. Piye assemblato un esercito di invadere il Medio e Basso Egitto. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Piye marciato nord e completa vittoria ottenuta a Herakleopolis, la conquista delle città di Hermopolis, Memphis, e di altri. Egli ha anche ricevuto la presentazione di diversi re del Delta del Nilo. Tefnakht si sono rifugiati in un isola nel Delta e accettato la sconfitta in una lettera a Piye, anche se ha rifiutato di rendere omaggio alla Kushite re. Soddisfatto di questi successi, Piye navigato in patria nel Nubia. Nonostante Piye il successo, la sua autorità solo esteso a nord di Tebe alle oasi del deserto occidentale e Herakleopolis. Pertanto, il re locale del Basso Egitto, soprattutto Tefnakht, erano liberi di fare come hanno soddisfatto senza Piye la svista. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Piye era più passione per il culto del dio Amon più di altri re di Nubia. Ha migliorato il declino Grande Tempio di Amon a Gebel Barkal. Piye fu seppellito in una piramide a El Kurru vicino Hebel Barkal, un sito che potrebbe essere occupato da tombe di più tardi membri della dinastia.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[H1]Pianjy[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Pharaoh de Egipto[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Reinó:[\BOLD]752 BC - 721 BC.[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH: 1][BOLD]Fondo:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Al comienzo de su reinado, Piye se aprovecharon de la disputa gobernantes de Egipto por la ampliación de la potencia de Nubia más allá de Tebas en el centro de Egipto. Tefnakht de Sais, en reacción contra el creciente kushita presión en el Alto Egipto, formaron una alianza entre los reyes locales de la Región y atraídos Delta King Nimlot de Hermopolis, Piye la aparente aliado, en la de desertar a su lado. Tefnakht y luego envió a su ejército al sur del sindicato y sitiado Herakleopolis, donde su rey hizo un llamamiento a Piye de ayuda. Piye reunido un ejército para invadir el Medio y el Bajo Egipto. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Piye marcharon al norte y logró la victoria completa en Herakleopolis, conquistando las ciudades de Hermopolis, Memphis, y otros. También recibió la presentación de varios reyes de la Delta del Nilo. Tefnakht se refugió en una isla del Delta y aceptó la derrota en una carta a Piye, aunque se negó a rendir homenaje a la kushita rey. Satisfecho con estos éxitos, Piye navegó a su patria en Nubia. A pesar de Piye del éxito, su autoridad sólo se extendió al norte de Tebas a los oasis en los desiertos occidentales y Herakleopolis. Por lo tanto, el local de los reyes del Bajo Egipto, en especial Tefnakht, son libres de hacer lo que complace sin Piye de supervisión. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Piye era más pasión por el culto del dios Amón más de otros reyes de Nubia. He mejorado la disminución de Gran Templo de Amón en Gebel Barkal. Piye fue enterrado en una pirámide en el Hebel  Kurru cerca de Barkal, un sitio que sería ocupado por las tumbas de varios miembros después de la dinastía.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_PIYE_1</Tag>
		<English>Greetings o' traveler, [OUR_NAME] is my name, welcome to the [OUR_EMPIRE].  Please, make yourself at home!</English>
		<French>Salutations voyageur, [OUR_NAME] est mon nom, bienvenue aux [OUR_EMPIRE]. Je vous en prie, faites comme chez vous !</French>
		<German>Grüße o Reisender, [OUR_NAME] ist mein Name, Willkommen zu [OUR_EMPIRE]. Bitte zu Hause sich bilden!</German>
		<Italian>Il viaggiatore del o di saluti, [OUR_NAME] è il mio nome, benvenuto al [OUR_EMPIRE]. Per favore, far nel paese!</Italian>
		<Spanish>El viajero del o de los saludos, [OUR_NAME] es mi nombre, recepción a [OUR_EMPIRE]. ¡Por favor, hacerte en el país!</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>