<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by lcollins (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- Copyright Firaxis Games 2005 -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text - New -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_AGAMEMNON</Tag>
		<English>Agamemnon</English>
		<French>Agamemnon</French>
		<German>Agamenon</German>
		<Italian>Agamennone</Italian>
		<Spanish>Agamenón</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_AGAMEMNON_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Agamemnon[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Prince of Mycenae[\BOLD][NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH: 1][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Agamemnon's father, Atreus, the king of Mycenae, was murdered by Aegistheus and his wife.  The two took possession of the thrown of Mycenae, and so Agamemnon and his brother, Menelaus, went to the king of Sparta.  There, Agamemnon married Clytemnestra, the daughter of Tyndareus, king of Sparta, and had five children.[PARAGRAPH: 1]Agamemnon is known for his role in the Trojan War.  Much of Agamemnon's life is encompassed by myth, so some of the information about the Trojan War is unreliable.  Agamemnon gathered Greek soldiers to sail for Troy.  Agamemnon was the Commander-in-Chief for the Greek Army, and had slain many important people from the Trojan Army.  He killed Antiphus, and Helaesus.  After the war, Cassandra, daughter of Priam, was given to Agamemnon as a prize.[PARAGRAPH: 1]Agamemnon returned to Greece with Cassandra and landed in Argolis.  Agamemnon's wife Clytemnestra had taken a lover, Aegistheus, and invited Agamemnon to a banquet.  There, Agamemnon was slain and died.  Clytemnestra then ruled Agamemnon's kingdom for a time, but the murder of Agamemnon was eventually avenged by his son Orestes with the help of his daughter Electra.</English>
		<French>[H1]Agamemnon[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Prince de Mycènes[\BOLD][NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH: 1][BOLD]Fond:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Le père d'Agamemnon, Atreus, roi de Mycenae, a été assassiné par Aegistheus et son épouse. Les deux ont pris la possession du jetée de Mycenae, et ainsi Agamemnon et son frère, Menelaus, sont allés au roi de Sparta. Là, Clytemnestra marié par Agamemnon, la fille de Tyndareus, roi de Sparta, et a eu cinq enfants. [PARAGRAPH : 2] Agamemnon est connu pour son rôle dans la guerre de Trojan. Beaucoup de la vie d'Agamemnon est entourée par mythe, ainsi certaines d'informations sur la guerre de Trojan sont incertaines. Agamemnon a recueilli les soldats grecs pour naviguer pour Troie. Agamemnon était le Commander-in-Chief pour l'armée grecque, et avait massacré beaucoup de personnes importantes de l'armée de Trojan. Il a tué Antiphus, et Helaesus. Après la guerre, Cassandra, fille de Priam, a été donné à Agamemnon comme prix. [PARAGRAPH : 3] Agamemnon retourné en Grèce avec Cassandra et débarqué dans Argolis. L'épouse Clytemnestra d'Agamemnon avait pris un amoureux, un Aegistheus, et un Agamemnon invité à un banquet. Là, Agamemnon a été massacré et mort. Clytemnestra a alors régné le royaume d'Agamemnon pendant un certain temps, mais le meurtre d'Agamemnon a été par la suite vengé par son fils Orestes avec l'aide de sa fille Electra. </French>
		<German>[H1]Agamenon[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Prinz von Mykene[\BOLD][NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH: 1][BOLD]Hintergrund:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Vater Agamemnons, Atreus, der König von Mycenae, wurde von Aegistheus und von seiner Frau ermordet. Die zwei nahmen den Besitz von geworfen von Mycenae und also gingen Agamemnon und sein Bruder, Menelaus, zum König von Sparta. Dort hatte Agamemnon verbundenes Clytemnestra, die Tochter von Tyndareus, König von Sparta und fünf Kinder. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Agamemnon bekannt für seine Rolle im Trojan Krieg. Viel von Leben Agamemnons wird durch Mythus umgegeben, also ist etwas von den Informationen über den Trojan Krieg unzuverlässig. Agamemnon erfaßte griechische Soldaten, um für Troy zu segeln. Agamemnon war der Commander-in-Chief für die griechische Armee und hatte viele wichtige Leute von der Trojan Armee getötet. Er tötete Antiphus und Helaesus. Nach dem Krieg Agamemnon wurde Cassandra, Tochter von Priam, als Preis gegeben. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Agamemnon zurückgebracht nach Griechenland mit Cassandra und in Argolis gelandet. Frau Clytemnestra Agamemnons hatte einen Geliebten, ein Aegistheus und ein eingeladenes Agamemnon zu einem Bankett genommen. Dort wurde Agamemnon getötet und gestorben. Clytemnestra ordnete dann Königreich Agamemnons während einer Zeit an, aber der Mord an Agamemnon avenged schließlich von seinem Sohn Orestes mit Hilfe seiner Tochter Electra.</German>
		<Italian>[H1]Agamennone[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Principe di Micene[\BOLD][NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH: 1][BOLD]Priorità bassa:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Il padre del Agamemnon, Atreus, il re di Mycenae, è stato assassinato da Aegistheus e dalla sua moglie. I due hanno preso il possesso del gettato di Mycenae ed in modo da Agamemnon ed il suo fratello, Menelaus, sono andato al re di Sparta. Là, Clytemnestra sposato Agamemnon, la figlia di Tyndareus, re di Sparta ed ha avuto cinque bambini. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Agamemnon è conosciuto per il suo ruolo nella guerra di Trojan. Molta di vita del Agamemnon è compresa dal mito, in modo da alcune delle informazioni sulla guerra di Trojan sono non fidate. Agamemnon ha riunito i soldati greci per navigare per Troy. Agamemnon era il Commander-in-Chief per l'esercito greco e slain molta gente importante dall'esercito del Trojan. Ha ucciso Antiphus e Helaesus. Dopo la guerra, Cassandra, figlia di Priam, è stato dato a Agamemnon come premio. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Agamemnon restituito in Grecia con Cassandra ed atterrato in Argolis. La moglie Clytemnestra del Agamemnon aveva preso un amante, un Aegistheus e un Agamemnon invitato ad un banquet. Là, Agamemnon slain e morto stato. Clytemnestra allora ha regolato il regno del Agamemnon per un certo tempo, ma l'omicidio di Agamemnon finalmente avenged dal suo figlio Orestes con l'aiuto della sua figlia Electra. </Italian>
		<Spanish>[H1]Agamenón[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Príncipe de Micenas[\BOLD][NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH: 1][BOLD]Fondo:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]A su esposa asesinó al padre de Agamemnon, Atreus, el rey de Mycenae, Aegistheus y. Los dos tomaron la posesión del lanzada de Mycenae, y así que Agamemnon y su hermano, Menelaus, fueron al rey de Sparta. Allí, Clytemnestra casado Agamemnon, la hija de Tyndareus, rey de Sparta, y tenía cinco niños. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Agamemnon se conoce para su papel en la guerra de Trojan. Mucha de la vida de Agamemnon es abarcada por mito, así que algo de la información sobre la guerra de Trojan es no fiable. Agamemnon recolectó a soldados griegos para navegar para Troy. Agamemnon era el comandante en jefe para el ejército griego, y había matado a mucha gente importante del ejército de Trojan. Él mató a Antiphus, y a Helaesus. Después de la guerra, dieron Cassandra, hija de Priam, a Agamemnon como premio. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Agamemnon vuelto a Grecia con Cassandra y aterrizado en Argolis. La esposa Clytemnestra de Agamemnon había llevado un amante, un Aegistheus, y un Agamemnon invitado un banquete. Allí, Agamemnon fue matado y muerto. Clytemnestra entonces gobernó el reino de Agamemnon por una época, pero el asesinato de Agamemnon fue vengado eventual por su hijo Orestes con la ayuda de su hija Electra.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_AGAMEMNON_1</Tag>
		<English>Greetings.  I am [OUR_NAME], Prince of [OUR_EMPIRE], and defeater of all enemies.  Tell me, are you a friend, or enemy?</English>
		<French>Salutations. Je suis [OUR_NAME], prince de Mycènes, et défait tous mes ennemis. Dites moi, êtes-vous un ami ou un ennemi ?</French>
		<German>Grüße. Ich bin [OUR_NAME], Prinz von [OUR_EMPIRE] und defeater aller Feinde. Erkläre mir, bin du ein Freund oder Feind?</German>
		<Italian>Saluti. Sono [OUR_NAME], principe di [OUR_EMPIRE] e defeater di tutti i nemici. Mi dico, sono voi un amico, o nemico?</Italian>
		<Spanish>Saludos. Soy [OUR_NAME], príncipe de [OUR_EMPIRE], y defeater de todos los enemigos. ¿Me dice, es tú un amigo, o enemigo?</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>