<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by lcollins (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- Copyright Firaxis Games 2005 -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text - New -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_MYCENAE_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Mycenaean Empire</English>
		<French>Empire de Mycénienne</French>
		<German>Mykenische Reich</German>
		<Italian>Impero di Micenea</Italian>
		<Spanish>Imperio de Micénica</Spanish>
	</TEXT>	
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_MYCENAE_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Mycenae</English>
		<French>Mycènes</French>
		<German>Mykene</German>
		<Italian>Micene</Italian>
		<Spanish></Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_MYCENAE_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Mycenaean</English>
		<French>Mycénienne</French>
		<German>Mykenische</German>
		<Italian>Micenea</Italian>
		<Spanish>Micénica</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_MYCENAE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The Mycenaeans were warlike people who first entered the Greek peninsula around 1600 B.C.  Their culture evolved around Minoan culture because of their close trade relations.  Some Mycenaeans became seafaring traders, while some others remained warriors like their ancestors. [PARAGRAPH: 2]The Mycenaeans were organized into small kingdoms, each of which had its own hilltop fortress commanding the rest of the land.  The most impressive of these strongholds was Mycenae.  The fortress was contained a 40 foot stone wall that was over 26 feet thick.  This made the fortress virtually invincible.  Like Knossos of the Minoans, Mycenae might have been the seat of an overlord to whom the other rulers deferred.  Mycenaean fortresses were smaller than Minoan palaces but resembled them in other ways.  Within the fortress were workshops.  The king watched over ceremonies in the megaron.  The kings of Mycenae were buried in tombs with their important belongings.[PARAGRAPH: 2]The Mycenaeans are famous for their role in the downfall of Troy under the leadership of Agamemnon.  By 1450 B.C., the Mycenaeans were dominant in trading and raiding throughout the Mediterranean.  But by 1200 B.C., the Mycenaean civilization was on a decline.  Drought, civil war, invasions, or any combination of the three may have caused the collapse.  A dark age was upon the Aegean world, and seafarers from other places in the Mediterranean began to succeed Mycenae.</English>
		<French>[TAB]Le Mycenaeans étaient les personnes guerrières qui sont entrées dans la première fois la péninsule grecque autour de 1600 B.C. Leur culture a évolué autour de la culture de Minoan en raison de leurs relations commerciales étroites. Un certain Mycenaeans est allé bien à des commerçants de vie de marin, alors que quelques autres restaient des guerriers comme leurs ancêtres. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Le Mycenaeans ont été organisés en petits royaumes, qui ont eu sa propre forteresse de sommet commander le reste de la terre. Le plus impressionnant de ces bastions était Mycenae. La forteresse a été contenue un mur de pierre de 40 pieds qui était plus de 26 pieds d'épaisseur. Ceci a rendu la forteresse pratiquement invincible. Comme Knossos du Minoans, Mycenae pourrait avoir été le siège d'un suzerain à qui les autres règles ont reporté. Les forteresses de Mycenaean étaient plus petites que des palais de Minoan mais ressemblées leur d'autres manières. Dans la forteresse étaient les ateliers. Les cérémonies finies observées par roi dans le megaron. Les rois de Mycenae ont été enterrés en tombeaux avec leurs affaires importantes. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Le Mycenaeans sont célèbre pour leur rôle dans la chute de Troie sous la conduite d'Agamemnon. Par 1450 B.C., le Mycenaeans étaient dominant dans le commerce et le pillage dans tous le méditerranéen. Mais par 1200 B.C., la civilisation de Mycenaean était sur un déclin. La sécheresse, la guerre civile, les invasions, ou n'importe quelle combinaison des trois ont pu avoir causé l'effondrement. Un âge foncé était sur le monde égéen, et les marins d'autres endroits dans le méditerranéen ont commencé à réussir Mycenae.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Das Mycenaeans waren kriegerische Leute, die zuerst die griechische Halbinsel um 1600 B.C. betraten. Ihre Kultur entwickelte um Minoan Kultur wegen ihrer nahen Geschäftsrelationen. Irgendein Mycenaeans stand Seafaringhändlern, während einige andere Krieger wie ihre Vorfahren blieben. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Das Mycenaeans wurden in kleine Königreiche organisiert, von denen jedes seine eigene Gipfelfestung hatte, den Rest des Landes zu beherrschen. Das eindrucksvollste dieser Festungen war Mycenae. Der Festung wurde eine 40-Fuss-Steinwand enthalten, die über 26 Fuß stark war. Dieses bildete die Festung praktisch unbesiegbar. Wie Knossos des Minoans, konnte Mycenae der Sitz eines overlord gewesen sein, zu dem die anderen Lehren aufschoben. Mycenaean Festungen waren kleiner als Minoan Paläste aber ihnen in anderen Weisen geähnelt. Innerhalb der Festung waren Werkstätten. Die König aufgepaßten überzeremonien im megaron. Die Könige von Mycenae wurden in den Gräbern mit ihrem wichtigen Eigentum begraben. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Das Mycenaeans sind für ihre Rolle im Sturz von Troy unter der Führung von Agamemnon berühmt. Durch 1450 B.C. waren das Mycenaeans beim dem Handeln und Überfallen während des Mittelmeer dominierend. Aber durch 1200 B.C., war die Mycenaean Zivilisation auf einer Abnahme. Dürre, Bürgerkrieg, Invasionen oder irgendeine Kombination der drei können den Einsturz verursacht haben. Ein dunkles Alter war nach der ägäischen Welt, und Seafarers von anderen Plätzen im Mittelmeer fingen an, Mycenae zu folgen.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB]Il Mycenaeans era gente warlike che in primo luogo ha entrato nella penisola greca intorno a 1600 B.C. La loro coltura si è evoluta intorno alla coltura di Minoan a causa dei loro rapporti commerciali vicini. Un certo Mycenaeans ha stato bene ai commercianti di seafaring, mentre alcuni altri sono rimasto guerrieri come i loro antenati. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Il Mycenaeans è stato organizzato nei piccoli regni, di cui ciascuno hanno avuti relativo proprio fortress del hilltop comandare il resto della terra. L'più impressionante di questi strongholds era Mycenae. Il fortress è stato contenuto una parete della pietra dai 40 piedi che era oltre spesso 26 piedi. Ciò ha reso il fortress virtualmente invincible. Come Knossos del Minoans, Mycenae potrebbe essere la sede di un overlord a quale gli altri righelli hanno rinviato. I fortresses di Mycenaean erano più piccoli dei palazzi di Minoan ma assomigliati a loro in altri sensi. All'interno del fortress erano le officine. Le cerimonie eccessive guardate re nel megaron. I re di Mycenae sono stati sepolti in tombe con i loro effetti personali importanti. [PARAGRAFO: 1] Il Mycenaeans è famoso per il loro ruolo nella rovina di Troy sotto la direzione di Agamemnon. Da 1450 B.C., il Mycenaeans era dominante nel commercio e nel raiding durante il Mediterraneo. Ma da 1200 B.C., la civilizzazione di Mycenaean era su un declino. La siccità, la guerra civile, le invasioni, o qualsiasi combinazione dei tre possono causare il crollo. Un'età scura era sul mondo Aegean ed i marinai da altri posti nel Mediterraneo hanno cominciato a riuscire Mycenae.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB]El Mycenaeans era la gente guerrera que primero entró en la península griega alrededor de 1600 B.C. Su cultura se desarrolló alrededor de la cultura de Minoan debido a sus relaciones comerciales cercanas. Algún Mycenaeans sintió bien a comerciantes del seafaring, mientras que algunos otros seguían siendo guerreros como sus antepasados. [PÁRRAFO: 1] El Mycenaeans fue organizado en los reinos pequeños, que tenían su propia fortaleza del hilltop el ordenar del resto de la tierra. El más impresionante de estas plazas fuertes era Mycenae. La fortaleza fue contenida una pared de la piedra de 40 pies que estaba sobre 26 pies de grueso. Esto hizo la fortaleza virtualmente invencible. Como Knossos del Minoans, Mycenae pudo haber sido el asiento de un overlord a el cual las otras reglas difirieron. Las fortalezas de Mycenaean eran más pequeñas que los palacios de Minoan pero asemejadas os de otras maneras. Dentro de la fortaleza estaban los talleres. Las ceremonias excesivas miradas rey en el megaron. Enterraron a los reyes de Mycenae en tumbas con sus pertenencia importantes. [PÁRRAFO: 1] El Mycenaeans es famoso por su papel en la caída de Troy bajo dirección de Agamemnon. Por 1450 B.C., el Mycenaeans era dominante en negociar y el ataque a través del mediterráneo. Pero por 1200 B.C., la civilización de Mycenaean estaba en una declinación. La sequía, la guerra civil, las invasiones, o cualquier combinación de los tres pudieron haber causado el derrumbamiento. Una edad oscura estaba sobre el mundo egeo, y los navegantes de otros lugares en el mediterráneo comenzaron a tener éxito Mycenae.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>	