<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by lcollins (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- Copyright Firaxis Games 2005 -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text - New -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_SHAUSHTATAR</Tag>
		<English>Shaushtatar</English>
		<French>Shaushtatar</French>
		<German>Shaushtatar</German>
		<Italian>Shaushtatar</Italian>
		<Spanish>Shaushtatar</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_SHAUSHTATAR_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Shaushtatar[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]King of Mitanni[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Reigned:[\BOLD] c. 1410 - 1440 BC[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Shaushtatar was a king of the Hurrian kingdom of Mitanni in the fifteenth century BC.  He was born to Barattarna, the previous king of Mitanni.  Barattarna had established control over northern Mesopotamia.  Here, he installed several client kings with Hurrian names in various cities.  It was left however for Shaushtatar to complete the conquest of the region and establish the Mitanni as a world power. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Now freed from the constant threat undergone by Mitanni of the Egyptians, Shaushtatar turned his attention toward Assyria.  He invaded Assyria and sacked and looted its capital, Assur.  He then turned westward across the Euphrates, along the way gathering beneath his sway all the northern Syrian states as he brought his army to the Mediterranean coast.  He was looking to extend Mitanni's power further south, possibly into Palestine.  However, much of southern Syria still lay within the Egyptian sphere of influence, which had long been a threat to Mitanni. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Shaushtatar wished to now increase Mitanni's territory by conquering Palestine, which already had a significant Hurrian population.  The consequence to his actions was, however, a war against Egypt.  Although the Mitanni military successes against Egyptian forces in the region may have been successful, the long term risks were substantial.  Earlier in his reign, when he had invaded Assyria, neither Assyria nor Kassite Babylon posed a serious threat to Mitanni expansion.  The only major state likely to oppose him was Hatti.  However, the Hittite Kingdom had not yet fully regained its former strength, but did once again expand into many Anatolian territories lost to it after Mursili's assassination.  It was only a matter of time before the Hittites once again turned to Mitanni, which would pose a serious threat.  If at that time Mitanni was at war with Egypt, it would be caught in a conflict between two powerful enemies.  However, it would not be Shaushtatar who would confront these problems, but his son, Artatama I, who would negotiate with the pharaoh Amenhotep II over an alliance.</English>
		<French>[H1]Shaushtatar[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Roi de Mitanni[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Regna :[\BOLD] 1410 approx.- 1440 av. J.C.[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Biographie :[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Shaushtatar fut un roi du royaume de hourrite Mitaniens au XVe siècle av. Il est né à Barattarna, l'ancien roi de Mitaniens. Barattarna avaient établi un contrôle sur le nord de la Mésopotamie. Ici, il a installé plusieurs clients rois avec hourrite noms dans différentes villes. Il a été cependant laissé pour Shaushtatar pour achever la conquête de la région et d'établir les Mitaniens comme une puissance mondiale. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Maintenant, libérée de la constante threat Mitaniens subis par des Égyptiens, Shaushtatar tourné son attention vers l'Assyrie. Il a envahi et saccagé une Assyrie pillé sa capitale, Assur. Il s'est ensuite tourné vers l'ouest à travers l'Euphrate, le long du chemin rassemblement sous son emprise tout le nord syrien affirme que son armée, qu'il a prise à la côte méditerranéenne. Il cherchait à étendre son pouvoir Mitaniens plus au sud, peut-être en Palestine. Cependant, une grande partie du sud de la Syrie reste relève de la sphère d'influence égyptienne, qui a longtemps été une menace pour Mitaniens. [PARAGRAPH 1] Shaushtatar souhaite maintenant accroître Mitaniens du territoire par la conquête de la Palestine, qui avait déjà une importante population hourrite. La conséquence de son action a été, cependant, une guerre contre l'Égypte. Bien que les Mitaniens succès militaires contre les forces égyptiennes dans la région ont été très bons, les risques à long terme sont importants. Plus tôt au cours de son règne, lorsqu'il avait envahi l'Assyrie, ni l'Assyrie ni Kassite de Babylone constituent une grave menace pour Mitaniens expansion. Le seul grand État susceptibles de s'opposer à lui est Hatti. Toutefois, le royaume hittite n'a pas encore pleinement retrouvé son ancienne force, mais il n'a une fois de plus à conquérir de nombreux territoires perdus à anatolienne après l'assassinat de Mursili. Ce n'était qu'une question de temps avant que les Hittites une nouvelle fois tournés vers Mitaniens, ce qui constituerait une grave menace. Si, à ce moment Mitaniens était en guerre avec l'Égypte, il serait pris dans un conflit entre deux ennemis puissants. Toutefois, il ne serait pas Shaushtatar qui seraient confrontés à ces problèmes, mais son fils, Artatama I, qui va négocier avec le pharaon Aménophis II sur une alliance.</French>
		<German>[H1]Shaushtatar[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]K&#246;nig von Mitanni[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Regierte:[\BOLD] ca. 1410 - 1440 v. Chr. [NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Hintergrund:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Shaushtatar war ein König der Hurrian Reich von Mitanni im fünfzehnten Jahrhundert v. Chr.. Er wurde geboren, um Barattarna, den früheren König von Mitanni. Barattarna hatte die Kontrolle über nördlichen Mesopotamien. Hier hat er mehrere Client installiert Hurrian Könige mit Namen in verschiedenen Städten. Es blieb jedoch für Shaushtatar um die Eroberung der Region und die Mitanni als Weltmacht. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Nun befreit von der ständigen Diskussion unterzogen von Mitanni der Ägypter, Shaushtatar wandte seine Aufmerksamkeit auf Assyrien. Er erobert Assyrien und entließ ein geplündert seine Hauptstadt Assur. Er drehte dann westwärts über den Euphrat, auf dem Weg sammelt unter seiner Herrschaft alle syrischen nördlichen Staaten gebracht, als er seine Armee an der Mittelmeerküste. Er war auf der Suche zu erweitern Mitanni Macht weiter südlich, möglicherweise in Palästina. Ein Großteil der südlichen Syrien lag noch in der ägyptischen Einflussbereich, die schon lange eine Bedrohung für die Mitanni. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Shaushtatar wollte jetzt erhöhen Mitanni-Gebiet durch Eroberung Palästina, die bereits einen erheblichen Hurrian Bevölkerung. Die Konsequenz für sein Handeln war aber ein Krieg gegen Ägypten. Obwohl die Mitanni militärische Erfolge gegen die ägyptischen Truppen in der Region wurden sehr gut, die langfristigen Risiken waren beträchtlich. Zu Beginn seiner Regierungszeit, als er Assyrien erobert hatte, weder noch Kassite Assyrien Babylon, die eine ernsthafte Bedrohung für Mitanni Expansion. Der einzige große Staat wahrscheinlich gegen ihn wurde Hatti. Allerdings ist die hethitischen Königreich noch nicht in vollem Umfang zu seiner ehemaligen Stärke, aber haben noch einmal erweitern in viele anatolischen Territorien verloren die ihm nach der Ermordung Muršili. Es war nur eine Frage der Zeit, bis die Hethiter wieder wandte sich Mitanni, die eine ernsthafte Bedrohung. Wenn zu diesem Zeitpunkt Mitanni war im Krieg mit Ägypten, es wäre gefangen in einem Konflikt zwischen zwei mächtige Feinde. Aber es wäre nicht Shaushtatar konfrontieren, würde diese Probleme, aber sein Sohn, Artatama ich, die würden Verhandlungen mit dem Pharao Amenophis II. über eine Allianz.</German>
		<Italian>[H1]Shaushtatar[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Re di Mitanni[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Regnava:[\BOLD] ca. 1410 - 1440 a.C. [NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Informazioni:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Shaushtatar era un re del regno di Mitanni Hurrian nel XV secolo aC. Egli è nato per Barattarna, il precedente re di Mitanni. Barattarna aveva stabilito il controllo su Mesopotamia settentrionale. Qui, ha installato vari client di re con Hurrian nomi in varie città. E 'stato tuttavia sinistra per Shaushtatar per completare la conquista della regione e creare le Mitanni come una potenza mondiale. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Ora liberato dalla costante filo da subito Mitanni degli Egiziani, Shaushtatar rivolto la sua attenzione verso l'Assiria. Ha invaso l'Assiria e saccheggiata uno saccheggiato la sua capitale, Assur. Egli ha quindi rivolto ad ovest attraverso l'Eufrate, lungo il percorso di raccolta sotto la sua influenza tutti gli stati del nord siriano come egli ha portato il suo esercito per la costa mediterranea. Egli stava cercando di estendere il potere Mitanni più a sud, possibilmente in Palestina. Tuttavia, gran parte del sud della Siria ancora laici all'interno della sfera di influenza egiziana, che era stata a lungo una minaccia per la Mitanni. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Shaushtatar voluto adesso Mitanni aumento del territorio da conquistare la Palestina, che già ha avuto un significativo Hurrian popolazione. La conseguenza per le sue azioni è stata, comunque, una guerra contro l'Egitto. Sebbene il Mitanni successi militari contro le forze egiziane nella regione potrebbe essere stato molto buono, a lungo termine, i rischi sono notevoli. Anteriore e il suo regno, quando aveva invaso Assiria, né Assiria, né Kassite Babylon posta una grave minaccia per la Mitanni espansione. L'unico grande stato in grado di opporsi a lui è stato Hatti. Tuttavia, il Regno ittita non era ancora pienamente recuperato il suo ex forza, ma ancora una volta ha fatto espandere in molti territori perduti Anatolian ad essa dopo l'assassinio Mursili. Era solo una questione di tempo prima che il Ittiti, ancora una volta si è rivolto a Mitanni, che potrebbe rappresentare una seria minaccia. Se a quel tempo Mitanni era in guerra con l'Egitto, sarebbe stato catturato in un conflitto tra due potenti nemici. Tuttavia, non sarebbe Shaushtatar che affrontare questi problemi, ma il suo figlio, Artatama I, che sarebbe negoziare con il faraone Amenhotep II, in una alleanza.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[H1]Shaushtatar[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Rey de Mitanni[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Reino:[\BOLD] c. 1410 - 1440 a. C. [NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Historia:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Shaushtatar fue un rey de los hurritas reino de Mitanni en el siglo XV aC. Él nació a Barattarna, el anterior rey de Mitanni. Barattarna ha establecido el control sobre el norte de Mesopotamia. Aquí, el cliente instalado varios reyes con nombres hurritas en varias ciudades. Se dejó sin embargo de Shaushtatar para completar la conquista de la región y establecer el Mitanni como potencia mundial. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Ahora liberados de la constante hilo de Mitanni sufrido por los egipcios, Shaushtatar dirigió su atención hacia Asiria. Asiria invadió y saqueó un saquearon su capital, Assur. Se dirigió hacia el oeste a través del Eufrates, a lo largo del camino de reunión bajo su dominio todos los estados del norte de Siria como él trajo a su ejército a la costa mediterránea. Él estaba buscando ampliar el poder de Mitanni más al sur, posiblemente en Palestina. Sin embargo, gran parte del sur de Siria todavía quedaban dentro de la esfera de influencia egipcia, que ha sido durante mucho tiempo una amenaza para Mitanni. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Shaushtatar desea ahora aumentar Mitanni por la conquista del territorio de Palestina, que ya tenía una importante población hurritas. La consecuencia de sus acciones es, sin embargo, una guerra contra Egipto. Aunque el Mitanni éxitos militares contra fuerzas egipcias en la región puede haber sido muy buena, a largo plazo, los riesgos son considerables. A comienzos de su reinado, cuando había invadido Asiria, ni Asiria ni Kassite Babilonia que plantean una grave amenaza para la expansión de Mitanni. El único gran estado probable que se le oponen Hatti. Sin embargo, el Reino hitita aún no ha recuperado plenamente su antigua fuerza, pero una vez más expandir en muchos territorios de Anatolia perdido a él después del asesinato de Mursili. Es sólo una cuestión de tiempo antes de los hititas, una vez más, recurrió a Mitanni, que constituiría una grave amenaza. Si en ese momento Mitanni estaba en guerra con Egipto, que se ven atrapados en un conflicto entre dos enemigos poderosos. Sin embargo, no sería Shaushtatar que enfrentar estos problemas, pero su hijo, Artatama I, que negociar con el faraón Amenhotep II más de una alianza.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_SHAUSHTATAR_1</Tag>
		<English>Greetings, [CT_NAME].  I hope we will be there are many who throw stones at a red apple.</English>
		<French>Salutations, [CT_NAME]. Nombreux sont ceux qui jettent des pierres sur les pommes rouges, ne soyons pas de ceux-là.</French>
		<German>Greetings, [CT_NAME]. Ich hoffe, wir werden es gibt viele, werfen Steine auf einem roten Apfel.</German>
		<Italian>Saluti, [CT_NAME]. Spero che saremo in molti ci sono pietre che passi a una mela rossa.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Saludos, [CT_NAME]. Espero que seamos muchos son los que tiran piedras en una manzana roja.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>