<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by lcollins (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- Copyright Firaxis Games 2005 -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text - New -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_SWEDEN_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Swedish Empire</English>
		<French>Sue&#232;ois Empire</French>
		<German>Schwedish Reich</German>
		<Italian>Svedese Impero</Italian>
		<Spanish>Suevo Imperio</Spanish>
	</TEXT>	
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_SWEDEN_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Sweden</English>
		<French>Sue&#232;e</French>
		<German>Schweden</German>
		<Italian>Svezia</Italian>
		<Spanish>Suecia</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_SWEDEN_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Swedish</English>
		<French>Sue&#232;ois</French>
		<German>Schwedish</German>
		<Italian>Svedese</Italian>
		<Spanish>Suevo</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_SWEDEN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Little is known of Swedish history before the Viking period of the late 8th century.  Two related peoples, the Svear and the G&#246;tar, then lived in south central Sweden.  Almost incessantly at war with each other, they united in the 9th century under the control of Svear.  The Swedish name for Sweden, Sverige, means "realm of the Svear."  Swedish Vikings sailed eastward across the Baltic Sea and into the rivers of Russia.   By the 9th and 10th centuries they were doing business as far east as Constantinople.  According to legend, a Swedish Viking chieftain, Rurik, was the creator of the first Russian monarchy.  Finland came under Swedish rule in the 12th century.  In 1397 the Union of Kalmar joined the kingdoms of Sweden, Denmark, and Norway under the Danish monarchy.  The Swedes opposed Danish command, which ended in 1523, when Gustavus Vasa came to the Swedish throne as King Gustav I. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Under Gustav I and his successors, Sweden became a martial power.  Two Swedish monarchs were famed as warrior kings.  Gustav II, also known as Gustavus Adolphus, won great triumphs in the Thirty Years' War.  As an effect of this war, Sweden increased land in northern Germany and became master of the Baltic region.  In 1638, Sweden founded a brief colony in America called New Sweden.  Continually challenged by its neighbors, Sweden fought a series of wars with Denmark, Russia, Poland, and Saxony during the early 18th century.  The Swedish king Charles XII won first impressive victories.  But his devastating defeat by the Russian Tsar Peter the Great in 1709 commenced Sweden's decline as a European power. [PARAGRAPH: 1] The loss of Finland to Russia in 1809 led to the deposition of King Gustav IV.  A new constitution was adopted and a Frenchman, Jean Baptiste Bernadotte, was chosen as the Swedish crown prince.  After Napoleon's defeat in 1814, Norway was taken from Denmark and given to Sweden to substitute its loss of Finland.  The union of Sweden and Norway lasted until 195,, when Norway peacefully gained its independence.  Bernadotte came to the throne in 1818 as King Charles XIV John and was the founder of the present Swedish royal house. [PARAGRAPH: 1] The constant years of war impoverished Sweden.  A lack of financial prospects caused a large number of Swedes to emigrate from the country.  Sweden was never again to go to war, adopting the policy of neutrality and nonalignment that continues today.  The growth of Swedish industry in the early 20th century restored its economy.  Sweden also developed its social welfare system that guaranteed the needs of existence to every Swedes.  Sweden was able to uphold its neutrality in both World War I and II, establishing itself as a haven for refugees escaping the damage of both these wars.  Sweden has also sought to promote peace in not only itself, but in all countries.  Many of Sweden's troops served in the United Nations peacekeeping forces.</English>
		<French>[TAB]On sait peu de choses de l'histoire de la Suède avant la période viking de la fin du 8e siècle. Deux peuples liés, les Svear et les Götar, puis vécu dans le centre-sud de la Suède. Presque sans cesse en guerre les uns avec les autres, ils ont uni au 9e siècle sous le contrôle de Svear. Le suédois nom de la Suède, Sverige, et signifie «royaume des Svear." Les Vikings suédois navigué vers l'est à travers la mer Baltique et dans les fleuves de la Russie. À la 9 e et 10 e siècles, ils faisaient des affaires l'Est jusqu'à Constantinople. Selon la légende, un chef viking suédois, Rurik, est le créateur de la première monarchie russe. Finlande relèvent suédois règle dans le 12ème siècle. En 1397 l'Union de Kalmar a rejoint le royaume de Suède, le Danemark et la Norvège en vertu de la monarchie danoise. Les Suédois Danois opposés commandement, qui a pris fin en 1523, quand Gustave Vasa est arrivé à la trône comme roi suédois Gustav I. [PARAGRAPH: 1] En vertu de Gustav Ier et ses successeurs, la Suède est devenue une puissance martiale. Deux monarques étaient suédois célèbre guerrier comme des rois. Gustav II, également connu sous le nom de Gustavus Adolphus, a remporté un grand triomphe dans la guerre de Trente Ans. Comme un effet de cette guerre, la Suède a augmenté terres dans le nord de l'Allemagne et devint maître de la région de la Baltique. En 1638, la Suède a fondé une colonie en Amérique brève appelé New Suède. Sans cesse contestée par ses voisins, la Suède a mené une série de guerres avec le Danemark, la Russie, la Pologne et la Saxe au début du 18ème siècle. Le roi Charles XII de Suède, a remporté le premier impressionnantes victoires. Mais sa défaite dévastatrice par le tsar russe Pierre le Grand en 1709 la Suède a commencé à décliner en tant que puissance européenne. [PARAGRAPH 1] La perte de la Finlande à la Russie en 1809 a abouti à la déposition du roi Gustav IV. Une nouvelle constitution a été adoptée et un Français, Jean-Baptiste Bernadotte, a été choisi comme prince héritier suédois. Après la défaite de Napoléon en 1814, la Norvège a été prise compte tenu du Danemark et de Suède, de substituer sa perte de la Finlande. L'union de la Suède et la Norvège ont duré jusqu'en 195, lorsque la Norvège a obtenu son indépendance pacifiquement. Bernadotte monta sur le trône en 1818 que le roi Charles XIV Jean et fut le fondateur de la maison royale suédoise. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Les années de guerre constante appauvri Suède. Le manque de perspectives financières causé un grand nombre de Suédois à émigrer du pays. La Suède a été plus jamais à faire la guerre, adoptant la politique de neutralité et nonalignment qui continue aujourd'hui. La croissance de l'industrie suédoise au début du 20ème siècle restaurée de son économie. La Suède a également mis au point son système de protection sociale qui garantit l'existence de besoins à tous les Suédois. La Suède a été en mesure de défendre sa neutralité dans les deux guerre mondiale I et II, en train de s'affirmer comme un havre pour les réfugiés fuyant les dégâts de ces deux guerres. La Suède a également cherché à promouvoir la paix, non seulement en soi, mais dans tous les pays. Beaucoup de Suède servi dans les troupes de la force de maintien de la paix des Nations Unies.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Wenig bekannt von der schwedischen Geschichte vor der Viking Periode des späten 8. Jahrhunderts.  Zwei bezogen Völker, das Svear und das Gö Teer, dann gewohnt in zentralem Südschweden.  Fast incessantly am Krieg mit einander, vereinigten sie im 9. Jahrhundert unter der Steuerung von Svear.  Der schwedische Name für Schweden, Sverige und Mittel „Reich des Svear.“  Schwedisches Vikings segelte ostwärts über die Ostsee und in die Flüsse von Rußland.   Bis zum den 9. und 10. Jahrhunderten taten sie Geschäft als Ferner Osten als Konstantinopolis.  Entsprechend Legende war ein schwedischer Viking Häuptling, Rurik, der Schöpfer der ersten russischen Monarchie.  Finnland kam unter schwedische Richtlinie im 12. Jahrhundert.  In 1397 verband der Anschluß von Kalmar die Königreiche von Schweden, von Dänemark und von Norwegen unter der dänischen Monarchie.  Die Schweden setzten dänischem Befehl entgegen, der 1523 beendete, als Gustavus Vasa zum schwedischen Thron als König Gustav I. kam. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Unter Gustav wurden I und seine Nachfolger, Schweden eine kriegerische Energie.  Zwei schwedische Monarchen waren als Kriegerkönige berühmt.  Gustav II, alias Gustavus Adolphus, gewonnene große Triumphe im dreißig Krieg der Jahre.  Als Effekt dieses Krieges, erhöhte Schweden Land in Norddeutschland und wurde Meister der baltischen Region.  1638 gründete Schweden eine kurze Kolonie in Amerika angerufenem New Schweden.  Fortwährend herausgefordert durch seine Nachbarn, kämpfte Schweden eine Reihe Kriege mit Dänemark, Rußland, Polen und Sachsen während des frühen 18. Jahrhunderts.  Der schwedische König Charles XII gewann erste eindrucksvolle Siege.  Aber seine verheerende Niederlage durch das russische Tsar Peter das große in der Abnahme 1709 begonnenen Schwedens als europäischer Energie. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Der Verlust von Finnland nach Rußland in 1809 zur Absetzung des Königs Gustav IV. geführt.  Eine neue Beschaffenheit wurde angenommen und ein Franzose, Jean Baptiste Bernadotte, wurde als der schwedische Kronprinz gewählt.  Nach Niederlage Napoleons 1814, wurde Norwegen von Dänemark genommen und gegeben nach Schweden, um seinen Verlust von Finnland zu ersetzen.  Der Anschluß von Schweden und von Norwegen dauerte bis 195, als Norwegen friedlich seine Unabhängigkeit gewann.  Bernadotte kam zum Thron in 1818 als König Charles XIV John und war der Gründer des anwesenden schwedischen königlichen Hauses. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Die konstanten Jahre des Krieges verarmtes Schweden.  Ein Mangel an finanziellen Aussichten veranlaßte viele Schweden, aus dem Land auszuwandern.  Schweden war nie wieder in den Krieg zu gehen und nahm die Neutralitätspolitik und nonalignment an, das heute fortfährt.  Das Wachstum der schwedischen Industrie im frühen - Jahrhundert des Th 20 stellte seine Wirtschaft wieder her.  Schweden entwickelte auch sein Sozialwohlfahrt System, das den Notwendigkeiten des Bestehens zu jedem Schweden garantierte.  Schweden war in der Lage, seine Neutralität im Ersten Weltkrieg und in II zu unterstützen und stellte sich als Hafen für die Flüchtlinge her, die der Beschädigung beider dieser Kriege entgehen.  Schweden hat auch gesucht, Frieden in nicht nur selbst, aber in allen Ländern zu fördern.  Viele von Truppen Schwedens dienten in den Nationen Friedenssicherungkräften.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB]Piccolo è conosciuto di storia svedese prima del periodo di Viking dell'ottavo secolo tardo.  Due hanno collegato la gente, lo Svear e il Gö catrame, allora vivo in Svezia centrale del sud.  Quasi incessantly alla guerra con a vicenda, hanno unito nel nono secolo sotto il controllo di Svear.  Il nome svedese per la Svezia, Sverige ed i mezzi “regno dello Svear.„  Vikings svedese ha navigato verso l'est attraverso il Mar Baltico e nei fiumi della Russia.   Entro i noni e decimi secoli stavano facendo il commercio come Estremo-Oriente come Constantinople.  Secondo la leggenda, un capo svedese di Viking, Rurik, era il creatore del primo monarchy russo.  La Finlandia è rientrato nella regola svedese nel dodicesimo secolo.  In 1397 l'unione di Kalmar ha unito i regni della Svezia, della Danimarca e della Norvegia sotto il monarchy danese.  Gli Svedesi hanno opposto l'ordine danese, che si è concluso in 1523, quando Gustavus Vasa è venuto al throne svedese come re Gustav I. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Sotto Gustav I ed i suoi successori, Svezia si sono trasformati in in un'alimentazione martial.  Due monarchi svedesi erano famed come re del guerriero.  Gustav II, anche conosciuto come Gustavus Adolphus, trionfi grandi vinti nella guerra dei trenta anni.  Come effetto di questa guerra, la terra aumentata la Svezia in Germania del Nord e si è trasformata in in padrone della regione baltica.  In 1638, la Svezia ha fondato una breve colonia in New denominato l'America Svezia.  Sfidato continuamente dai relativi vicini, la Svezia ha combattuto una serie di guerre con la Danimarca, la Russia, la Polonia e la Sassonia durante il diciottesimo secolo in anticipo.  Il re svedese Charles XII ha vinto le prime vittorie impressionanti.  Ma la sua sconfitta devastating dal Tsar russo Peter il grande in un declino delle 1709 Svezie cominciate come alimentazione europea. [PARAGRAPH: 1] La perdita della Finlandia in Russia in 1809 ha condotto al deposito del re Gustav IV.  Una nuova costituzione è stata adottata e un francese, Jean Baptiste Bernadotte, è stato scelto come il principe di parte superiore svedese.  Dopo la sconfitta del Napoleon in 1814, la Norvegia è stata presa dalla Danimarca ed è stata data in Svezia per sostituire la relativa perdita della Finlandia.  L'unione della Svezia e della Norvegia ha durato fino a 195, quando la Norvegia ha guadagnato pacificamente la relativa indipendenza.  Bernadotte è venuto al throne in 1818 come re Charles XIV John ed era il fondatore della casa reale svedese attuale. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Gli anni costanti della guerra Svezia impoverita.  Una mancanza di prospetti finanziari ha indotto tantissimi Svedesi ad emigrare dal paese.  La Svezia non era mai ancora di andare fare la guerra, adottando la politica di neutralità e del nonalignment che continua oggi.  Lo sviluppo di industria svedese nell'inizio del 20esimo secolo ha ristabilito la relativa economia.  La Svezia inoltre ha sviluppato il relativo sistema di assistenza sociale sociale che ha garantito i bisogni dell'esistenza all'ogni Svedesi.  La Svezia poteva sostenere la relativa neutralità sia nelle guerre mondiali I che II, stabilendosi come porto per i rifugiati che fuoriescono danni di entrambe queste guerre.  La Svezia inoltre ha cercato di promuovere la pace in non solo in se, ma in tutti i paesi.  Molte delle truppe della Svezia hanno servito nelle forze di mantenimento della pace delle Nazioni Unite.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB]Poco se sabe de historia sueca antes del período de Viking del último 8vo siglo.  Dos relacionaron la gente, el Svear y el Gö alquitrán, entonces vivido en Suecia central del sur.  Casi incesantemente en la guerra con uno a, unieron en el 9no siglo bajo control de Svear.  El nombre sueco para Suecia, Sverige, y los medios “reino del Svear.”  Vikings sueco navegó hacia el este a través del mar báltico y en los ríos de Rusia.   Por los 9nos y 10mos siglos hacían negocio como Extremo Oriente como Constantinople.  Según leyenda, un cacique sueco de Viking, Rurik, era el creador de la primera monarquía rusa.  Finlandia vino bajo regla sueca en el 12mo siglo.  En 1397 la unión de Kalmar ensambló los reinos de Suecia, de Dinamarca, y de Noruega bajo monarquía danéa.  Los sueco opusieron el comando danés, que terminó en 1523, cuando Gustavus Vasa vino al trono sueco como rey Gustav I. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Debajo de Gustav I y sus sucesores, Suecia se convirtió en una energía marcial.  Dos monarcas suecos eran famosos como reyes del guerrero.  Gustav II, también conocido como Gustavus Adolphus, grandes triunfos ganados en la guerra de los treinta años.  Como efecto de esta guerra, la tierra creciente Suecia en Alemania norteña y se convirtió en amo de la región báltica.  En 1638, Suecia fundó a breve colonia en New llamado América Suecia.  Desafiado continuamente por sus vecinos, Suecia luchó una serie de guerras con Dinamarca, Rusia, Polonia, y Sajonia durante el décimo octavo siglo temprano.  El rey sueco Charles XII ganó las primeras victorias impresionantes.  Pero su derrota devastadora por el Tsar ruso Peter el grande en la declinación de 1709 Suecia comenzadas como energía europea. [PARAGRAPH: 1] La pérdida de Finlandia a Rusia en 1809 condujo a la deposición de rey Gustav IV.  Una nueva constitución fue adoptada y eligieron a un francés, Jean Baptiste Bernadotte, como el príncipe de corona sueco.  Después de la derrota de Napoleon en 1814, Noruega fue tomada de Dinamarca y dada a Suecia para substituir su pérdida de Finlandia.  La unión de Suecia y de Noruega duró hasta 195, cuando Noruega ganó pacífico su independencia.  Bernadotte vino al trono en 1818 como rey Charles XIV Juan y era el fundador de la actual casa real sueca. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Los años constantes de la guerra Suecia empobrecida.  Una carencia de perspectivas financieras hizo a una gran cantidad de sueco emigrar del país.  Suecia nunca era otra vez ir a guerrear, adoptando la política de la neutralidad y del nonalignment que continúa hoy.  El crecimiento de la industria sueca en el siglo a principios de siglo 20 restauró su economía.  Suecia también desarrolló su sistema de la asistencia social que garantizó las necesidades de la existencia a cada sueco.  Suecia podía mantener su neutralidad en Primera Guerra Mundial e II, estableciéndose como asilo para los refugiados que escapaban el daño de ambas estas guerras.  Suecia también ha intentado promover la paz en no sólo sí mismo, pero en todos los países.  Muchas de las tropas de Suecia desempen'aron servicios en las fuerzas del mantenimiento de la paz de Naciones Unidas.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>	