<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by lcollins (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- Copyright Firaxis Games 2005 -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text - New -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_HUNGARY_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Hungarian Empire</English>
		<French>Hongrois Empire</French>
		<German>Ungarische Reich</German>
		<Italian>Ungherese Impero</Italian>
		<Spanish>Húngaro Imperio</Spanish>
	</TEXT>	
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_HUNGARY_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Hungary</English>
		<French>Hongrie</French>
		<German>Ungarn</German>
		<Italian>Ungheria</Italian>
		<Spanish>Hungría</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_HUNGARY_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Hungarian</English>
		<French>Hongrois</French>
		<German>Ungarische</German>
		<Italian>Ungherese</Italian>
		<Spanish>Húngaro</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_HUNGARY_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB] Before the birth of Christ, Hungary belonged to the Roman Empire.  In the 5th century A.D., the Huns swept in from the east.  Later, Slavic and Germanic people settled in the region.  Hungarians usually trace their history to the Magyars, who under Arpad, arrived at the Danube basin.  A nomadic tribe of expert horsemen, the Magyars were excellent warriors who dominated the entire region, going as far as laying siege to German cities and Byzantium. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Under the Hungarian king Saint Stephen, Hungary was united under powerful nobles.  Hungary and Croatia were joined in 1091 and became the strongest state in east central Europe.  However, the power declined, and was forced to go under the power of the nobles.  In 1242, the Mongols invaded and devastated the land.  Most of Hungary's rulers were foreigners, with one distinguished king.  Under the king Louis the Great, Hungary reached its greatest territorial expansion.  However, the Ottoman Empire posed a threat to Hungary, who began slowly pushing on Hungary's borders.  Under Matthias Corvinus and his father Janos Hunyadi, the Ottomans were pushed from Hungary and order was restored. [PARAGRAPH: 2] With the death of Matthias, Hungary fell once again into disorder, and went under the control of the Turks.  In the 17th century, the Turks were driven out by Austria, who ruled harshly against the Hungarians.  Thus, they revolted several times, one of the most prominent being that under Lajos Kossuth.  This rebellion attempt was crushed when the Austrians received aid from Russia. The Compromise of 1867 created the Dual Monarchy of Austria-Hungary, which gave Hungary its own parliament.  However, it was ruled by the Austrian emperor Francis Joseph I, who was crowned King of Hungary. [PARAGRAPH: 2] In World War I, Hungary fought on the side of Austria and Germany, and a revolution after the war made Hungary a republic.  After World War I, Hungary lost much of its land that it hoped to regain in World War II.  However, it was under German occupation in 1944, which were driven out by the Soviet troops.  Following the elections in 1945, Hungary became a republic.  However, under the influence of the Soviets, Hungary became Communist that ruled the country harshly.  After several successful attempts to take over the government and make reforms, Soviet troops entered Hungary to restore Communism.  By 1989, Hungary was seeing major governmental reforms.  In 1990, Soviet troops began their departure from Hungary, ending the era and starting a new one.</English>
		<French>[TAB] Avant la naissance du Christ, la Hongrie appartenait à l'Empire romain. Dans le 5ème siècle A.D., les Huns envahirent depuis l'est. Plus tard, slave et germanique personnes installées dans la région. Hongrois généralement retracer leur histoire pour les Magyars, qui sous Arpad, sont arrivés sur le bassin du Danube. Une tribu de nomades cavaliers experts, les Magyars étaient excellents guerriers qui ont dominé l'ensemble de la région, allant jusqu'à jeter le siège de villes allemandes et de Byzance. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Sous le roi hongrois Saint Stephen, de la Hongrie a été réunis sous les nobles puissants. La Hongrie et la Croatie ont été rejoints en 1091 et est devenu l'État le plus puissant dans l'est de l'Europe centrale. Toutefois, le pouvoir a baissé, et a été contrainte de passer sous le pouvoir de la noblesse. En 1242, l'invasion mongole qui a dévasté le pays. La plupart des dirigeants de la Hongrie étaient des étrangers, dont un éminent roi. Sous le roi Louis le Grand, la Hongrie a atteint sa plus grande expansion territoriale. Cependant, l'Empire ottoman constituait une menace pour la Hongrie, qui a commencé lentement, poussant sur les frontières de la Hongrie. En vertu de Matthias Ier et son père de Janos Hunyadi, les Turcs ont été poussés à partir de la Hongrie et de l'ordre a été rétabli. [PARAGRAPH: 2] À la mort de Matthias, de la Hongrie a chuté à nouveau dans le désordre, et sont passées sous le contrôle des Turcs. Au 17e siècle, les Turcs ont été chassés par l'Autriche, qui gouvernait durement contre les Hongrois. Ainsi, ils se révoltèrent à plusieurs reprises, l'une des plus importantes étant que, en vertu de Lajos Kossuth. Cette tentative de rébellion a été écrasée quand les Autrichiens reçu de l'aide de la Russie. Le compromis de 1867 a créé la double monarchie d'Autriche-Hongrie, qui a donné la Hongrie son propre parlement. Toutefois, il a été jugé par l'empereur autrichien François Joseph Ier, qui a été couronné roi de Hongrie. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Dans la première guerre mondiale, la Hongrie a combattu du côté de l'Autriche et l'Allemagne, et la révolution, après la guerre, la Hongrie a fait une république. Après la Première Guerre mondiale, la Hongrie a perdu une grande partie de ses terres qu'il espérait retrouver dans la Seconde Guerre mondiale. Toutefois, il a été sous occupation allemande en 1944, qui ont été chassés par les troupes soviétiques. Après la sélection en 1945, la Hongrie est devenue une république. Cependant, sous l'influence de l'Union soviétique, la Hongrie est devenue communiste qui a gouverné le pays sévèrement. Après plusieurs tentatives réussies de prendre sur le gouvernement et de faire des réformes, les troupes soviétiques entrés Hongrie pour rétablir le communisme. En 1989, la Hongrie a vu grandes réformes gouvernementales. En 1990, les troupes soviétiques ont commencé leur départ de la Hongrie, de la fin de l'ère de départ et un nouveau.</French>
		<German>[TAB] Vor der Geburt Jesu Christi, Ungarn gehörte zu den Römischen Reiches. Im 5. Jahrhundert A.D., fegte die Hunnen aus dem Osten. Später, slawischen und germanischen Menschen, die in der Region. Ungarn normalerweise den Spuren ihrer Geschichte, die Magyaren, die unter Arpad, kam an der Donau Becken. Ein nomadischen Stamm von Experten Reiter, die Magyaren waren hervorragende Krieger, die dominiert in der gesamten Region gehen so weit wie mit der Belagerung der deutschen Städte und Byzanz. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Unter dem ungarischen König St. Stephan, Ungarn, war unter mächtigen Adel. Ungarn und Kroatien waren sich in der 1091 und war der stärkste Staat im östlichen Mitteleuropa. Allerdings ist die Macht ging, und war gezwungen, unter der Macht des Adels. In 1242, die Mongolen erobert, die das Land verwüstet. Die meisten der ungarischen Herrscher waren Ausländer, mit einem König unterscheiden. Unter König Ludwig dem Großen, Ungarn erreichte seine größte territoriale Expansion. Allerdings, das Osmanische Reich, die eine Gefährdung nach Ungarn, die begannen langsam drängt auf Ungarns Grenzen. Unter Matthias Corvinus und sein Vater Janos Hunyadi, die Osmanen gedrängt wurden aus Ungarn und Ordnung wiederhergestellt. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Mit dem Tod von Matthias, Ungarn fiel erneut in Unordnung, und ging unter der Kontrolle der Türken. Im 17. Jahrhundert, die Türken wurden von Österreich, die entschieden, hart gegen die Ungarn. So revoltierten sie mehrere Male, eine der prominentesten, dass unter Lajos Kossuth. Diese Rebellion Versuch wurde zerdrückt, wenn die Österreicher erhalten Hilfe aus Russland. Der Kompromiss von 1867 schuf die Dual Monarchie Österreich - Ungarn, die Ungarn hat sein eigenes Parlament. Es wurde jedoch von den österreichischen Kaiser Franz Joseph I., der König von Ungarn gekrönt. [PARAGRAPH: 2] In World War I, Ungarn kämpfte auf der Seite von Österreich und Deutschland, und eine Revolution nach dem Krieg aus Ungarn eine Republik. Nach dem Ersten Weltkrieg, Ungarn verloren viel von ihrem Land zu hoffen, dass es wieder im Zweiten Weltkrieg. Allerdings war es unter deutschen Besetzung im 1944, die sich aus der sowjetischen Truppen. Nach der Auswahl in 1945, Ungarn wurde eine Republik. Doch unter dem Einfluss der Sowjets, kommunistischen Ungarn wurde entschieden, dass das Land hart. Nach mehreren erfolgreichen Versuche, die über die Regierung und die Reformen, sowjetischen Truppen in Ungarn zur Wiederherstellung des Kommunismus. Nach 1989 war Ungarn bedeutende staatliche Reformen. In 1990, sowjetischen Truppen begann ihre Abreise aus Ungarn, endet die Ära und eine neue ein.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB] Prima della nascita di Cristo, Ungheria apparteneva a Romano. Nel 5 ° secolo A.D., gli Unni travolto da est. Più tardi, slava e germanica persone costante nella regione. Ungheresi traccia di solito la loro storia ai magiari, che, a norma di Arpad, arrivati al bacino del Danubio. Una tribù di nomadi cavalieri esperti, il magiari sono stati eccellenti guerrieri, che domina l'intera regione, in quanto recante assedio alla città tedesche e di Bisanzio. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Ai sensi del re ungherese Santo Stefano, l'Ungheria è stata unita sotto potenti nobili. Ungheria e la Croazia sono state riunite nel 1091 e divenne il più forte Stato in est Europa centrale. Tuttavia, il potere è diminuito, e fu costretto a passare sotto il potere dei nobili. Nel 1242, i Mongoli invaso che ha devastato la terra. La maggior parte di Ungheria sono stati governanti stranieri, con un illustre re. Sotto il re Luigi il Grande, l'Ungheria ha raggiunto la sua massima espansione territoriale. Tuttavia, l'impero ottomano poste una minaccia per l'Ungheria, che ha iniziato lentamente spingendo sul Ungheria frontiere. Pagina Matthias Corvinus e suo padre Janos Hunyadi, gli ottomani erano spinti da Ungheria e la fine è stata restaurata. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Con la morte di Mattia, l'Ungheria è sceso ancora una volta in disordine, e si è recato sotto il controllo dei turchi. Nel 17 ° secolo, i turchi sono stati scacciati da Germania, Austria, che ha dichiarato duramente contro gli ungheresi. Così, si sono ribellati più volte, uno dei più importanti è che sotto Lajos Kossuth. Questo tentativo di ribellione è stato schiacciato quando gli austriaci ricevuto aiuti dalla Russia. Il compromesso del 1867 ha creato il doppio Monarchia d'Austria - Ungheria, Ungheria, che ha dato il proprio parlamento. Tuttavia, è stato stabilito dalla austriaca imperatore Francesco Giuseppe I, che è stato incoronato re d'Ungheria. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Nella prima guerra mondiale, l'Ungheria ha combattuto sul lato di Austria e Germania, e di una rivoluzione dopo la guerra fatta una repubblica Ungheria. Dopo la prima guerra mondiale, l'Ungheria ha perso gran parte della sua terra che si spera di ritrovare nella seconda guerra mondiale. Tuttavia, è stato sotto occupazione tedesca nel 1944, che sono stati cacciati dalle truppe sovietiche. In seguito le selezioni nel 1945, l'Ungheria è diventata una repubblica. Tuttavia, sotto l'influenza dei sovietici, l'Ungheria è diventata comunista, che ha governato il paese duramente. Dopo vari tentativi di successo di assumere il governo e fare le riforme, le truppe sovietiche l'Ungheria è entrata a ripristinare il comunismo. Dal 1989, l'Ungheria è stata quella di vedere grandi riforme governative. Nel 1990, le truppe sovietiche iniziato la loro partenza da Ungheria, finisce l'epoca e di iniziare una nuova.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB] Antes del nacimiento de Cristo, Hungría pertenecía al Imperio Romano. En el 5 º siglo A.D., barrió en la hunos desde el este. Más tarde, germánicas y eslavas pueblo asentado en la región. Húngaros suelen rastrear su historia a los magiares, que en virtud de Arpad, llegó a la cuenca del Danubio. Una tribu nómada de jinetes expertos, los magiares eran excelentes guerreros que dominaron toda la región, hasta que, por el que se asedio a las ciudades y Bizancio. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Bajo el rey San Esteban de Hungría, Hungría fue unida en virtud de los nobles poderosos. Hungría y Croacia se unió en 1091 y se convirtió en el más fuerte del Estado en la región central del este de Europa. Sin embargo, el poder disminuido, y se vio obligado a pasar bajo el poder de los nobles. En 1242, los mongoles invadieron que devastó la tierra. La mayoría de los gobernantes de Hungría eran extranjeros, con un distinguido rey. Bajo el rey Luis el Grande, Hungría alcanzó su mayor expansión territorial. Sin embargo, el Imperio Otomano, que plantean una amenaza a Hungría, que comenzó lentamente empujando las fronteras de Hungría. En virtud de Matthias Corvinus y su padre Janos Hunyadi, los otomanos fueron empujados de Hungría y el orden fue restablecido. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Con la muerte de Matías, Hungría, una vez más, cayó en el desorden, y pasó bajo el control de los turcos. En el siglo 17, los turcos fueron expulsados por Alemania, Austria, que gobernó con dureza contra los húngaros. Por lo tanto, se sublevaron en varias ocasiones, una de las más destacadas es que en virtud de Lajos Kossuth. Este intento de rebelión fue aplastada cuando los austríacos recibieron ayuda de Rusia. La transacción de 1867 creó la doble monarquía de Austria - Hungría, que dio Hungría su propio parlamento. Sin embargo, es gobernada por el emperador austriaco Francisco José I, quien fue coronado Rey de Hungría. [PARAGRAPH: 2] En la Primera Guerra Mundial, Hungría luchó en el lado de Austria y Alemania, y una revolución después de la guerra hizo una república Hungría. Después de la Primera Guerra Mundial, Hungría perdió gran parte de sus tierras que esperaba recuperar en la Segunda Guerra Mundial. Sin embargo, fue ocupada por Alemania en 1944, que fueron expulsados por las tropas soviéticas. Después de la selección en 1945, Hungría se convirtió en una república. Sin embargo, bajo la influencia de los soviéticos, Hungría se convirtió en comunista que gobernó el país con dureza. Después de varios intentos para tener éxito en el gobierno y hacer las reformas, las tropas soviéticas entraron en Hungría para restablecer el comunismo. En 1989, Hungría fue ver grandes reformas gubernamentales. En 1990, las tropas soviéticas iniciaron su salida de Hungría, que terminó la era y el comienzo de uno nuevo.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>	