<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by lcollins (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- Copyright Firaxis Games 2005 -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text - New -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_LOMBARD_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Langobard Empire</English>
		<French>Langobard Empire</French>
		<German>Langobard Reich</German>
		<Italian>Langobard Impero</Italian>
		<Spanish>Impero Langobard</Spanish>
	</TEXT>	
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_LOMBARD_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Langobardia</English>
		<French>Langobardia</French>
		<German>Langobardia</German>
		<Italian>Langobardia</Italian>
		<Spanish>Langobardia</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_LOMBARD_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Langobard</English>
		<French>Langobard</French>
		<German>Langobard</German>
		<Italian>Langobard</Italian>
		<Spanish>Langobard</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_LOMBARD_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The history of the Langobards begins with a small tribe known as the Winniler.  The Winniler dwelled on a Nordic Island called Scanan.  The Winniler were split into three groups, and the third moved out of the original land.  The departing people were lead by brother Ybor and Aio and their mother Gambara.  They arrived on the lands of Scoringa, which was ruled by Wandals.  At the moment, the people of Scoringa were forced to either pay tribute, or go to war.  The Winniler chose to go to war, and because they had such few numbers, women were forced to fight alongside men.  The women tied their hair in front of their faces.  When they were spotted, many noticed their long beards.  From this moment on, the Winniler were known as the Langobard, which is Latinized to Langobards. [PARAGRAPH: 2] The Langobard dwelt near the river Elbe next to the Chauci.  Archaeological finds show that early Langobard society revolved around agriculture.  The first mention of the Langobards occurred between 9 and 16 AD.  They were mentioned by the Roman court historian Velleius Paterculus.  Paterculus described them as being "fiercer than normal German savagery."  The Langobards were assumed as a Seubian tribe, subjects of King Marobod of the Marcomanni.  The Marcomanni at the time made peace with the Romans, and that is why the Langobards were not part of the German confederacy. [PARAGRAPH: 2] In the second century, the Langobards appear in Rhineland.  The Langobard had greatly expanded during this time.  Just before the year 166, the Langobards and Obii crossed the Danube and invaded Pannonia.  The Langobards lost the war, and returned back to their homes on the river Elbe.  After this time, the Langobards seem to disappear from history.  One reason is that the Langobards could have delved deeper into the Germanic lands.  While some Langobard migrated, others were absorbed by the surrounding Saxons.  Shortly after, the Langobards rose up against the Saxons with their king Agelmund.  The Langobards began on another migration. [PARAGRAPH: 2] The crossing into Mauringa was difficult because the Usipetes denied the Langobards passage.  Because of this, a fight was arranged between the strongest men of each tribe.  The Langobards left the fight as victors, and their passage was granted.  The Langobards reached Mauringa, and the first king, Agelmund, ruled for thirty years.  The Langobards then departed from Mauringa and arrived at Golanda.  The Golanda was a land on the bank of the Oder.  Leaving Golanda, the Langobards passed through Anthaib and Banthaib until they at last reached Vurgundaib.  The Huns attacked the Langobards, and killed their King Agelmund.  The Langobards rose up against the Huns under the new king Laimicho.  [PARAGRAPH: 2] In the year 560, a new king emerged who would mark a turning point in Langobard history, Alboin.  Alboin defeated the Gepids, made them his subjects and led the Langobards and a federation of other tribes across the Julian Alps to invade Italy.  The first important city to fall was Forum Iulii, in which he created the first Langobard duchy.  His nephew, Gisulph, was to be the duke.  In the summer of 569, the Langobards conquered Milan, which at the time was in terrible condition because of the Gothic Wars.  Pavia fell under siege after three years, becoming the first capital of the new Langobard kingdom.  In the upcoming years, the Langobards established two duchies further south, Spoleto and Benevento.  The Byzantines managed to retain control of Ravenna and Rome. [PARAGRAPH: 2] The Langobard territory was divided into 36 duchies.  The king ruled over them and administered the land through representatives called gastaldi.  This unity was however weak, and the Langobards lost control over Spoleto and Benevento to the Franks over time.  The deaths of Alboin and his son Cleph resulted in a ten year interregnum known as the "Rule of the Dukes".  The dukes, threatened by the Franks, elected the son of Cleph, Authari, their next king.  Authari tried to reorganize the royal administration, and manage to end the dangerous alliance between the Byzantines and the Franks.  After Authari's death in 590, Agilulf, duke of Turin, ruled.  He successfully fought the rebels from Northern Italy and conquered Padua and Mantua. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Rothari, the next ruler, extended the kingdom by conquering Ligura and the remaining part of the Byzantine territories of Veneto.  Rothari also wrote the laws of his people in Latin.  Rothari's son, Rodoald, succeeded him but was killed by the Catholic party.  After the death of Aripert in 661, the kingdom was divided between his children.  The capitals were in Milan and Pavia.  Gromoald overthrew Perctarit, ruler of the Milan-centered Langobardia, and defeated the Franks and conquered southern Italy. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Religious troubles remained the source of struggle in the following years.  The Langobards managed to gain control over Spoleto and Benevento. They also helped the Frankish Marshall Charles Martel drive back the Arabs.  Aistulf conquered Ravenna for the first time, but was defeated by the king of the Franks, Pippin III.  The last Langobard king to rule was Desiderius, duke of Tuscany.  He attempted to prevent the Pope from attacking, and entered Rome for the first time.  Charlemagne continued to defeat the Langobards on countless occasions to follow.  Charlemagne took the title "King of the Langobards". [PARAGRAPH: 2] The Langobards of Southern Italy had not yet been conquered by Charlemagne, and made several attempts to produce a king with little success.  The Langobards of Sothern Italy were now claimed by two empires, the Carolingian and Byzantine.  Benevento at this time grew to it greatest extent. Langobard culture became embedded in formerly Greek Apulia.  A civil war spread throughout Langobard lands for ten years after Emperor Louis II, the only Frankish king to exercise power over the Langobard states, imposed a peace treaty.  The kingdom was divided into two states into the Principalities of Benevento of Salerno.  Arabs began conquering Langobard cities and lands.  The papacy began absorbing the remaining Langobard lands, which over time was losing their power.  The remnants of the Langobards can still be seen in the modern Langobardy region of Italy.</English>
		<French>[TAB]L'histoire du Langobards commence par une petite tribu connue sous le nom de Winniler. Le Winniler a demeuré sur une île nordique appelée Scanan. Le Winniler ont été coupés en trois groupes, et le tiers ont été déplacés hors de la terre originale. Les personnes partantes étaient fil par le frère Ybor et Aio et leur mère Gambara. Elles sont arrivées sur les terres de Scoringa, qui a été régné par Wandals. Au moment où, les personnes de Scoringa ont été forcées ou à l'hommage de salaire, ou aller faire la guerre. Le Winniler a choisi d'aller faire la guerre, et parce qu'elles ont eu de tels quelques nombres, des femmes ont été forcées de combattre à côté des hommes. Les femmes ont attaché leurs cheveux devant leurs visages. Quand elles ont été repèrées, beaucoup ont noté leurs longues barbes. À partir de ce moment dorénavant, le Winniler ont été connus comme Langobard, qui est Latinized à Langobards. [PARAGRAPH : 1] Le Langobard a demeuré près du fleuve Elbe à côté du Chauci. Les trouvailles archéologiques prouvent que la première société de Langobard a tourné autour de l'agriculture. La première mention du Langobards s'est produite entre 9 et 16 APRÈS JÉSUS CHRIST. Ils ont été mentionnés par l'historien romain Velleius Paterculus de cour. Paterculus les a décrits en tant qu'étant « une sauvagerie allemande plus féroce que normalement. » Le Langobards ont été assumés comme tribu de Seubian, sujets du Roi Marobod du Marcomanni. Le Marcomanni a alors fait la paix avec le Romans, et c'est pourquoi le Langobards n'étaient pas une partie de la confédération allemande. [PARAGRAPH : 1] Au deuxième siècle, le Langobards apparaissent en Rhénanie. Le Langobard avait considérablement augmenté pendant ce temps. Juste avant l'année 166, le Langobards et l'Obii ont croisé le Danube et ont envahi Pannonia. Le Langobards a perdu la guerre, et est retourné de nouveau à leurs maisons sur le fleuve Elbe. Après ce temps, le Langobards semblent disparaître de l'histoire. Une raison est que le Langobards pourrait avoir fouillé plus profond dans les terres germaniques. Tandis qu'un certain Langobard émigrait, d'autres ont été absorbés par le Saxons environnant. Peu de temps après, le Langobards s'est levé vers le haut contre le Saxons avec leur Roi Agelmund. Le Langobards a commencé sur une autre migration. [PARAGRAPH : 1] Le croisement dans Mauringa était difficile parce que l'Usipetes a nié le passage de Langobards. Pour cette raison, un combat a été arrangé entre les hommes les plus forts de chaque tribu. Le Langobards a laissé le combat comme vainqueurs, et leur passage a été accordé. Par Langobards le Mauringa atteint, et le premier roi, Agelmund, régné pendant trente années. Le Langobards est alors parti de Mauringa et est arrivé chez Golanda. Le Golanda était une terre sur la banque de l'Oder. Laissant Golanda, le Langobards a traversé Anthaib et Banthaib jusqu'à ce qu'ils aient enfin atteint Vurgundaib. Les huns ont attaqué le Langobards, et ont tué leur Roi Agelmund. Le Langobards s'est levé vers le haut contre les huns sous le nouveau Roi Laimicho. [PARAGRAPH : 1] En l'année 560, un nouveau roi a émergé qui marquerait un tournant en histoire de Langobard, Alboin. Alboin a défait le Gepids, leur a fait ses sujets et a mené le Langobards et une fédération d'autres tribus à travers les Alpes de Julian pour envahir l'Italie. La première ville importante à tomber était un forum Iulii, dans lequel il a créé le premier duché de Langobard. Son neveu, Gisulph, devait être le duc. En été de 569, le Langobards a conquis Milan, qui était alors en état terrible en raison des guerres gothiques. Pavie est tombé sous le siège après trois ans, devenant le premier capital du nouveau royaume de Langobard. En années prochaines, le Langobards a établi encore deux sud, Spoleto et Bénévent de duchés. Le Byzantines est parvenu à garder la main de Ravenne et de Rome. [PARAGRAPH : 1] Le territoire de Langobard a été divisé en 36 duchés. Le roi a régné au-dessus de eux et a administré la terre par des représentants appelés le gastaldi. Cette unité était cependant faible, et le Langobards a perdu le contrôle de Spoleto et Bénévent au temps fini de contreseings. Les décès d'Alboin et de son fils Cleph ont eu comme conséquence un interregnum de dix ans connu sous le nom de « règle des ducs ». Les ducs, menacés par les contreseings, ont élu le fils de Cleph, Authari, leur prochain roi. Authari a essayé de réorganiser l'administration royale, et parvient à finir l'alliance dangereuse entre le Byzantines et les contreseings. Après la mort d'Authari dans 590, Agilulf, duc de Turin, a régné. Il a avec succès combattu les rebelles d'Italie nordique et a conquis Padoue et Mantua. [PARAGRAPH : 1] Rothari, la prochaine règle, a prolongé le royaume en conquérant Ligura et la partie restante des territoires bizantins de Veneto. Rothari a également écrit les lois de ses personnes dans le latin. Le fils de Rothari, Rodoald, réussi lui mais a été tué par la partie catholique. Après la mort d'Aripert dans 661, le royaume a été divisé entre ses enfants. Les capitaux étaient à Milan et à Pavie. Gromoald a renversé Perctarit, règle du Langobardia Milan-centré, et a défait les contreseings et a conquis l'Italie méridionale. [PARAGRAPH : 1] Les ennuis religieux sont demeurés la source de lutte en années suivantes. Le Langobards est parvenu à gagner le contrôle de Spoleto et de Bénévent. Ils également ont aidé la commande franche de Charles Martel de maréchal en arrière les Arabes. Aistulf a conquis Ravenne pour la première fois, mais a été défait par le roi des contreseings, la reinette III. Le dernier roi de Langobard à r ule was Desiderius, duke of Tuscany. He attempted to prevent the Pope from attacking, and entered Rome for the first time. Charlemagne continued to defeat the Langobards on countless occasions to follow. Charlemagne took the title "King of the Langobards". [PARAGRAPH: 2] The Langobards of Southern Italy had not yet been conquered by Charlemagne, and made several attempts to produce a king with little success. The Langobards of Sothern Italy were now claimed by two empires, the Carolingian and Byzantine. Benevento at this time grew to it greatest extent. Langobard culture became embedded in formerly Greek Apulia. A civil war spread throughout Langobard lands for ten years after Emperor Louis II, the only Frankish king to exercise power over the Langobard states, imposed a peace treaty. The kingdom was divided into two states into the Principalities of Benevento of Salerno. Arabs began conquering Langobard cities and lands. The papacy began absorbing the remaining Langobard lands, which over time was losing their power. The romance of the Langobards can still be seen in the modern Langobardy region of Italy.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Die Geschichte des Langobards fängt mit einem kleinen Stamm an, der als das Winniler bekannt ist. Das Winniler blieb auf einer nordischen Insel, die Scanan genannt wurde. Das Winniler wurden in drei Gruppen aufgespaltet und der Third verschoben aus dem ursprünglichen Land heraus. Die abreisenleute waren Leitung durch Bruder Ybor und Aio und ihre Mutter Gambara. Sie kamen auf den Ländern von Scoringa an, das von Wandals angeordnet wurde. In dem Augenblick als, die Leute von Scoringa entweder zum Bezahlung Tribut gezwungen wurden oder in den Krieg gehen. Das Winniler beschloß in den Krieg zu gehen, und weil sie solche wenige Zahlen hatten, wurden Frauen gezwungen, neben Männern zu kämpfen. Die Frauen banden ihr Haar vor ihren Gesichtern. Als sie beschmutzt wurden, beachteten viele ihre langen Bärte. Von diesem Moment an, bekannt das Winniler als das Langobard, das Latinized zu Langobards ist. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Der Langobard blieb nahe dem Fluß Elbe nahe bei dem Chauci. Archäologische Entdeckungen zeigen, daß frühe Langobard Gesellschaft um Landwirtschaft rotierte. Die erste Erwähnung des Langobards trat zwischen 9 und 16 V. CHR. auf. Sie wurden vom römischen Gerichthistoriker Velleius Paterculus erwähnt. Paterculus beschrieb sie als seiend „heftigeres als normale deutsche Unzivilisiertheit.“ Das Langobards wurden als Seubian Stamm, Themen des Königs Marobod des Marcomanni angenommen. Das Marcomanni bildete zu der Zeit Frieden mit dem Romans, und das ist, warum das Langobards nicht Teil der deutschen Konföderation waren. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Im zweiten Jahrhundert erscheinen das Langobards in Rheinland. Der Langobard hatte groß während dieser Zeit erweitert. Kurz vor dem Jahr 166, kreuzten das Langobards und das Obii die Donau und drangen Pannonia ein. Das Langobards verlor den Krieg und ging zurück zu ihren Häusern auf dem Fluß Elbe zurück. Nach dieser Zeit scheinen das Langobards, von der Geschichte zu verschwinden. Ein Grund ist, daß das Langobards tieferes in die germanischen Länder geforscht haben könnte. Während irgendein Langobard abwanderte, wurden andere durch das umgebende Saxons aufgesogen. Kurz nach, stieg das Langobards oben gegen das Saxons mit ihrem König Agelmund. Das Langobards fing auf einer anderen Migration an. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Die überfahrt in Mauringa war schwierig, weil das Usipetes den Langobards Durchgang verweigerte. Wegen dieses wurde ein Kampf zwischen den stärksten Männern jedes Stammes geordnet. Das Langobards ließ den Kampf als Victors, und ihr Durchgang wurde bewilligt. Das Langobards erreichte Mauringa und der erste König, Agelmund, angeordnet für dreißig Jahre. Das Langobards dann reiste von Mauringa ab und kam bei Golanda an. Das Golanda war ein Land auf der Bank des Oder. Golanda lassend, überschritt das Langobards durch Anthaib und Banthaib, bis sie schließlich Vurgundaib erreichten. Die Hunnen nahmen das Langobards in Angriff und töteten ihren König Agelmund. Das Langobards stieg oben gegen die Hunnen unter den neuen König Laimicho. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Im Jahr 560, tauchte ein neuer König wem einen Drehpunkt in der Langobard Geschichte kennzeichnen würde, Alboin auf. Alboin besiegte das Gepids, bildete sie seine Themen und führte das Langobards und eine Vereinigung anderer Stämme über den julianischen Alpen, um Italien einzudringen. Die erste wichtige Stadt zum zu fallen war Forum Iulii, in dem er das erste Langobard Herzogtum herstellte. Sein Neffe, Gisulph, sollte der Herzog sein. Am Sommer von 569, eroberte das Langobards Mailand, das zu der Zeit in schrecklichem Zustand wegen der gotischen Kriege war. Pavia fiel unter Belagerung nach drei Jahren und wurde das erste Kapital des neuen Langobard Königreiches. In den upcoming Jahren stellte das Langobards zwei Herzogtümer den weiteren Süden, Spoleto und Benevento her. Das Byzantines handhabte, Steuerung von Ravenna und von Rom zu behalten. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Die Langobard Gegend wurde in 36 Herzogtümer geteilt. Der König ordnete über ihnen an und übte das Land durch die Repräsentanten aus, die gastaldi genannt wurden. Diese Einheit war jedoch schwach, und das Langobards verlor Steuerung über Spoleto und Benevento zur Freivermerküberzeit. Die Todesfälle von Alboin und von seinem Sohn Cleph ergaben einen zehnjährigen Interregnum, der als die „Richtlinie der Herzöge“ bekannt ist. Die Herzöge, bedroht durch die Freivermerke, wählten den Sohn von Cleph, Authari, ihr folgender König. Authari versuchte, die königliche Leitung zu reorganisieren und handhabt, das gefährliche Bündnis zwischen dem Byzantines und den Freivermerken zu beenden. Nach Tod Autharis in 590, ordnete Agilulf, Herzog von Turin, an. Er kämpfte erfolgreich die Aufrührer aus Norditalien und eroberte Padua und Mantua. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Rothari, die folgende Lehre, verlängerte das Königreich, indem er Ligura und das restliche Teil der byzantinischen Gegenden von Veneto eroberte. Rothari schrieb auch die Gesetze seiner Leute in Latein. Sohn Rotharis, Rodoald, gefolgt ihm aber wurde von der katholischen Partei getötet. Nach dem Tod von Aripert in 661, wurde das Königreich zwischen seine Kinder geteilt. Die Kapitalien waren in Mailand und in Pavia. Gromoald besiegte Perctarit, Lehre des Mailand-zentrierten Langobardia und besiegte die Freivermerke und eroberte Süditalien. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Fromme Mühen blieben die Quelle des Kampfes in den folgenden Jahren. Das Langobards handhabte, Steuerung über Spoleto und Benevento zu gewinnen. Sie halfen auch dem Frankish Marschall-Charles Martel Antrieb zurück die Araber. Aistulf eroberte Ravenna zum ersten Mal, aber wurde vom König der Freivermerke, Pippinapfel III. besiegt. Der letzte Langobard König zu r ule was Desiderius, duke of Tuscany. He attempted to prevent the Pope from attacking, and entered Rome for the first time. Charlemagne continued to defeat the Langobards on countless occasions to follow. Charlemagne took the title "King of the Langobards". [PARAGRAPH: 2] The Langobards of Southern Italy had not yet been conquered by Charlemagne, and made several attempts to produce a king with little success. The Langobards of Sothern Italy were now claimed by two empires, the Carolingian and Byzantine. Benevento at this time grew to it greatest extent. Langobard culture became embedded in formerly Greek Apulia. A civil war spread throughout Langobard lands for ten years after Emperor Louis II, the only Frankish king to exercise power over the Langobard states, imposed a peace treaty. The kingdom was divided into two states into the Principalities of Benevento of Salerno. Arabs began conquering Langobard cities and lands. The papacy began absorbing the remaining Langobard lands, which over time was losing their power. The romance of the Langobards can still be seen in the modern Langobardy region of Italy.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB]La storia del Langobards comincia con una piccola tribù conosciuta come il Winniler. Il Winniler ha abitato su un'isola nordica denominata Scanan. Il Winniler è stato tagliato in tre gruppi ed il terzo è stato spostato dalla terra originale. La gente partente era cavo dal fratello Ybor e Aio e la loro madre Gambara. È arrivato sulle terre di Scoringa, che è stato regolato da Wandals. Dal momento che, la gente di Scoringa è stata forzata o a tributo di paga, o andare fare la guerra. Il Winniler ha scelto andare fare la guerra e perché hanno avute tali pochi numeri, le donne sono state costrette a combattere accanto agli uomini. Le donne hanno legato i loro capelli davanti le loro facce. Quando sono state macchiate, molte hanno notato le loro barbe lunghe. Da questo momento in poi, il Winniler è stato conosciuto come il Langobard, che è Latinized a Langobards. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Il Langobard ha abitato vicino al fiume Elbe vicino al Chauci. I ritrovamenti Archaeological indicano che la società in anticipo del Langobard ha girato intorno all'agricoltura. La prima menzione del Langobards si è presentata fra l'ANNUNCIO 9 e 16. Sono stati accennati dallo storico romano Velleius Paterculus della corte. Paterculus li ha descritti come essendo “savagery tedesco più feroce del normale.„ Il Langobards è stato presupposto come tribù di Seubian, argomenti di re Marobod del Marcomanni. La pace allora fatta di Marcomanni con il Romans e ecco perché il Langobards non facevano parte del confederacy tedesco. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Nel secondo secolo, il Langobards compare in Renania. Il Langobard notevolmente si era espanso durante questo tempo. Appena prima l'anno 166, il Langobards e il Obii hanno attraversato il Danubio ed hanno invaso Pannonia. Il Langobards ha perso la guerra ed ha rinviato di nuovo alle loro sedi sul fiume Elbe. Dopo questo tempo, il Langobards sembra sparire da storia. Un motivo è che il Langobards potrebbe ricercare più profondo nelle terre germaniche. Mentre un certo Langobard ha migrato, altri sono stati assorbiti dal Saxons circostante. Subito dopo, il Langobards è aumentato in su contro il Saxons con il loro re Agelmund. Il Langobards ha cominciato su un'altra espansione. [PARAGRAPH: 2] L'incrocio in Mauringa era difficile perché il Usipetes ha negato il passaggio di Langobards. A causa di questa, una lotta è stata organizzata fra gli uomini più forti di ogni tribù. Il Langobards ha lasciato la lotta come victors ed il loro passaggio è stato assegnato. Langobards il Mauringa raggiunto ed il primo re, Agelmund, regolato per trenta anni. Il Langobards allora ha partito da Mauringa ed è arrivato a Golanda. Il Golanda era una terra sulla banca del Oder. Lasciando Golanda, il Langobards ha attraversato Anthaib e Banthaib fino a che infine non raggiungessero Vurgundaib. I Huns hanno attacato il Langobards ed hanno ucciso il loro re Agelmund. Il Langobards è aumentato in su contro i Huns sotto il nuovo re Laimicho. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Durante l'anno 560, un nuovo re ha emerso chi contrassegnerebbe una svolta nella storia del Langobard, Alboin. Alboin ha sconfitto il Gepids, ha reso loro i suoi oggetti ed ha condotto il Langobards e una federazione di altre tribù attraverso le alpi Julian per invadere l'Italia. La prima città importante da cadere era tribuna Iulii, in cui ha generato il primo ducato del Langobard. Il suo nipote, Gisulph, doveva essere il duca. di estate di 569, il Langobards ha conquistato Milano, che allora era nello stato terribile a causa delle guerre gotiche. Pavia è rientrato nel siege dopo tre anni, trasformantesi nel primo capitale di nuovo regno del Langobard. Durante gli anni imminenti, il Langobards ha stabilito ulteriore sud, Spoleto e Benevento dei due ducati. Il Byzantines è riuscito a mantenere il controllo di Ravenna e di Roma. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Il territorio del Langobard è stato diviso in 36 ducati. Il re ha regolato sopra loro ed ha amministrato la terra attraverso i rappresentanti denominati gastaldi. Questa unità era comunque, debole e il Langobards ha perso il controllo sopra Spoleto e Benevento a col tempo di firme di franchigia. Le morti di Alboin e del suo figlio Cleph hanno provocato un interregnum di dieci anni conosciuto come “la regola dei duchi„. I duchi, minacciati dalle firme di franchigia, hanno scelto il figlio di Cleph, Authari, il loro re seguente. Authari ha provato a riorganizzare la gestione reale e riesce a concludere l'alleanza pericolosa fra il Byzantines e le firme di franchigia. Dopo la morte del Authari in 590, Agilulf, duca di Torino, ha regolato. Ha combattuto con successo i ribelli dall'Italia del Nord ed ha conquistato Padova e Mantua. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Rothari, il righello seguente, ha esteso il regno conquistando Ligura e la parte restante dei territori Byzantine di Veneto. Rothari inoltre ha scritto le leggi della sua gente nel Latino. Il figlio del Rothari, Rodoald, riuscito lui ma è stato ucciso dal partito cattolico. Dopo la morte di Aripert in 661, il regno è stato diviso fra i suoi bambini. I capitali erano a Milano e Pavia. Gromoald overthrew Perctarit, righello del Langobardia Milano-centrato ed ha sconfitto le firme di franchigia ed ha conquistato l'Italia del sud. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Le difficoltà religiose sono rimasto la fonte di lotta durante i seguenti anni. Il Langobards è riuscito a guadagnare il controllo sopra Spoleto e Benevento. Inoltre hanno aiutato l'azionamento Frankish del Charles Martel del Marshall indietro gli arabi. Aistulf ha conquistato per la prima volta Ravenna, ma è stato sconfitto dal re delle firme di franchigia, renetta III. L'ultimo re del Langobard alla r ule was Desiderius, duke of Tuscany. He attempted to prevent the Pope from attacking, and entered Rome for the first time. Charlemagne continued to defeat the Langobards on countless occasions to follow. Charlemagne took the title "King of the Langobards". [PARAGRAPH: 2] The Langobards of Southern Italy had not yet been conquered by Charlemagne, and made several attempts to produce a king with little success. The Langobards of Sothern Italy were now claimed by two empires, the Carolingian and Byzantine. Benevento at this time grew to it greatest extent. Langobard culture became embedded in formerly Greek Apulia. A civil war spread throughout Langobard lands for ten years after Emperor Louis II, the only Frankish king to exercise power over the Langobard states, imposed a peace treaty. The kingdom was divided into two states into the Principalities of Benevento of Salerno. Arabs began conquering Langobard cities and lands. The papacy began absorbing the remaining Langobard lands, which over time was losing their power. The romance of the Langobards can still be seen in the modern Langobardy region of Italy.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB]La historia del Langobards comienza con una tribu pequeña conocida como el Winniler. El Winniler moró en una isla nórdica llamada Scanan. El Winniler estuvo partido en tres grupos, y el tercero fue movido de la tierra original. La gente que salía era plomo de hermano Ybor y Aio y su madre Gambara. Ella llegó en las tierras de Scoringa, que fue gobernado por Wandals. En el momento que, forzaron a la gente de Scoringa o al tributo de la paga, o ir a guerrear. El Winniler eligió ir a guerrear, y porque tenían tales pocos números, forzaron a las mujeres luchar junto a hombres. Las mujeres ataron su pelo delante de sus caras. Cuando los mancharon, mucha notaron sus barbas largas. A partir de este momento encendido, el Winniler era conocido como el Langobard, que es Latinized a Langobards. [PARAGRAPH: 2] El Langobard moró cerca del río Elbe al lado del Chauci. Los hallazgos arqueológicos demuestran que la sociedad temprana de Langobard giró alrededor de agricultura. La primera mención del Langobards ocurrió entre el ANUNCIO 9 y 16. Fueron mencionados por el historiador romano Velleius Paterculus de la corte. Paterculus los describió como siendo “más feroz del salvajismo alemán normal.” El Langobards fue asumido como tribu de Seubian, temas de rey Marobod del Marcomanni. El Marcomanni hizo las paces en ese entonces con el Romans, y ése es porqué el Langobards no era parte del confederacy alemán. [PARAGRAPH: 2] En el segundo siglo, el Langobards aparece en Renania. El Langobard se había ampliado grandemente durante este tiempo. Momentos antes del año 166, el Langobards y el Obii cruzaron el Danubio e invadieron Pannonia. El Langobards perdió la guerra, y volvió de nuevo a sus hogares en el río Elbe. Después de este tiempo, el Langobards se parece desaparecer de historia. Una razón es que el Langobards habría podido cavar más profundo en las tierras germánicas. Mientras que emigró algún Langobard, otros fueron absorbidos por el Saxons circundante. Poco después, el Langobards se levantó para arriba contra el Saxons con su rey Agelmund. El Langobards comenzó por otra migración. [PARAGRAPH: 2] La travesía en Mauringa era difícil porque el Usipetes negó el paso de Langobards. Debido a esto, una lucha fue arreglada entre los hombres más fuertes de cada tribu. El Langobards dejó la lucha como vencedores, y su paso fue concedido. Langobards el Mauringa alcanzado el primer rey, y, Agelmund, gobernado por treinta años. El Langobards después salió de Mauringa y llegó Golanda. El Golanda era una tierra en el banco del Oder. Dejando Golanda, el Langobards pasó con Anthaib y Banthaib hasta ellos en Vurgundaib alcanzado pasado. Los Huns atacaron el Langobards, y mataron a su rey Agelmund. El Langobards se levantó para arriba contra los Huns debajo del nuevo rey Laimicho. [PARAGRAPH: 2] En el año 560, un nuevo rey emergió quién marcaría un momento crucial en la historia de Langobard, Alboin. Alboin derrotó el Gepids, os hizo sus temas y condujo el Langobards y una federación de otras tribus a través de las montan@as Julian para invadir Italia. La primera ciudad importante a caer era el foro Iulii, en el cual él creó el primer ducado de Langobard. Su sobrino, Gisulph, debía ser el duque. En el verano de 569, el Langobards conquistó Milano, que estaba en ese entonces en condiciones terribles debido a las guerras góticas. Pavía cayó bajo sitio después de tres años, convirtiéndose en el primer capital del nuevo reino de Langobard. En los años próximos, el Langobards estableció el sur adicional, Spoleto y Benevento de dos ducados. El Byzantines manejó conservar el control de Ravena y de Roma. [PARAGRAPH: 2] El territorio de Langobard fue dividido en 36 ducados. El rey gobernó sobre ellos y administró la tierra a través de los representantes llamados gastaldi. Esta unidad era sin embargo débil, y el Langobards perdió control sobre Spoleto y Benevento en un cierto plazo las cartas francas. Las muertes de Alboin y de su hijo Cleph dieron lugar a un interregnum de diez años conocido como la “regla de los duques”. Los duques, amenazados por las cartas francas, eligieron a hijo de Cleph, Authari, su rey siguiente. Authari intentó reorganizar la administración real, y maneja terminar la alianza peligrosa entre el Byzantines y las cartas francas. Después de la muerte de Authari en 590, Agilulf, duque de Turín, gobernó. Él luchó con éxito a rebeldes de Italia norteña y conquistó Padua y Mantua. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Rothari, la regla siguiente, amplió el reino conquistando Ligura y la parte restante de los territorios Byzantine de Veneto. Rothari también escribió los leyes de su gente en latín. El partido católico mató al hijo de Rothari, Rodoald, tenido éxito te pero. Después de la muerte de Aripert en 661, el reino fue dividido entre sus niños. Los capitales estaban en Milano y Pavía. Gromoald derrocó Perctarit, regla del Langobardia Milano-centrado, y derrotó las cartas francas y conquistó Italia meridional. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Los apuros religiosos seguían siendo la fuente de la lucha en los años siguientes. El Langobards manejó ganar control sobre Spoleto y Benevento. También ayudaron a la impulsión Frankish de Charles Martel del ordenar detrás los árabes. Aistulf conquistó Ravena por primera vez, pero fue derrotado por el rey de las cartas francas, reineta III. El rey pasado de Langobard a r ule was Desiderius, duke of Tuscany. He attempted to prevent the Pope from attacking, and entered Rome for the first time. Charlemagne continued to defeat the Langobards on countless occasions to follow. Charlemagne took the title "King of the Langobards". [PARAGRAPH: 2] The Langobards of Southern Italy had not yet been conquered by Charlemagne, and made several attempts to produce a king with little success. The Langobards of Sothern Italy were now claimed by two empires, the Carolingian and Byzantine. Benevento at this time grew to it greatest extent. Langobard culture became embedded in formerly Greek Apulia. A civil war spread throughout Langobard lands for ten years after Emperor Louis II, the only Frankish king to exercise power over the Langobard states, imposed a peace treaty. The kingdom was divided into two states into the Principalities of Benevento of Salerno. Arabs began conquering Langobard cities and lands. The papacy began absorbing the remaining Langobard lands, which over time was losing their power. The romance of the Langobards can still be seen in the modern Langobardy region of Italy.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>	