<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by lcollins (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- Copyright Firaxis Games 2005 -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text - New -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
        <TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_GRENZER_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]In various Austrian Empires, Grenzers were troops who came from the Croatian and Transylvanian Military Frontier.  The troops were originally founded to defend Austria from the Ottomans, however when no danger lurked, the Grenzers were employed by the Habsburgs in other frontiers of war.  Still, at least one battalion of each regiment would remain guarding the border from invasion threats. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Grenzers were successors of the irregular army of Pandurs, which were also raised by the Habsburgs to defend the border and serve as skirmishers in the Seven Years' War.  By the time of the Napoleonic Wars, the troops formed more regular line infantry regiments.  They were given training in marksmanship, linear tactics, and skirmishing.  At the start of the war, 18 Grenzer regiments formed about a quarter of the Austrian Army. [PARAGRAPH: 1] However, because the Grenzers were not as good in the role of line infantry as the regular regiments, the Austrian military command never gave them much credit, and following a mutiny in 1800, their numbers were reduced.  Despite these setbacks, Grenzers preformed exceptionally well at Marengo and Austerlitz, earning them respect from the French.  Napoleon even considered them the only warlike troops in the entire Austrian Army.  Grenzer troops served for Napoleon until his defeat after the Austrians ceded territories in the War of the Fifth Coalition. [PARAGRAPH: 1] During the 19th century, the Ottoman thread diminished and thus there was less need for troops defending the Frontier.  Additionally, with rise of Slav nationalism and self-determination, the Austrian high command grew suspicious of the Grenzers and a possible revolt.  With these factors, the number of Grenzers was steadily reduced, although they remained in service in the Austrian and later Austro-Hungarian army until the World War II.</English>
		<French>[TAB]Dans divers Empires autrichien, Grenzers étaient soldats venus de la Croatie et de Transylvanie militaire aux frontières. Les troupes ont été initialement fondée pour la défense de l'Autriche Ottomans, mais quand aucun danger m'attendait, le Grenzers étaient employés par les Habsbourg dans d'autres frontières de la guerre. Pourtant, au moins sur le bataillon de chaque régiment resterait protégeant la frontière de l'invasion de menaces. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Grenzers étaient successeurs de l'armée irrégulière de Pandurs, qui ont également été soulevés par les Habsbourg pour défendre la frontière et de servir de tirailleurs dans la guerre de Sept Ans. Au moment des guerres napoléoniennes, les troupes formé plus régulier régiments d'infanterie de ligne. Ils ont reçu une formation en aptitudes, linéaire tactiques, et escarmouches. Au début de la guerre, 18 Grenzer régiments forment environ un quart de l'armée autrichienne. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Toutefois, parce que le Grenzers n'étaient pas aussi bien dans le rôle de l'infanterie de ligne que les régiments réguliers, le commandement militaire autrichien ne leur a donné beaucoup de crédit, et la suite d'une mutinerie en 1800, leur nombre a été réduit. Malgré ces revers, Grenzers préformés exceptionnellement bien à la bataille de Marengo et Austerlitz, qui lui a valu le respect de la société française. Napoléon même envisagé eux la seule guerrière des troupes dans l'ensemble de l'armée autrichienne. Grenzer troupes servi de Napoléon jusqu'à sa défaite après les Autrichiens cédée territoires de la guerre de la Cinquième Coalition. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Au cours du 19e siècle, les ottomans fil diminué et il n'y avait donc moins besoin de troupes de la défense des frontières. En outre, avec montée du nationalisme slave et de l'autodétermination, le haut commandement autrichien a crû suspectes de la Grenzers et d'une éventuelle révolte. Compte tenu de ces facteurs, le nombre de Grenzers a été réduite progressivement, mais ils sont restés en service dans la autrichienne et, plus tard, l'armée austro-hongroise jusqu'à la Seconde Guerre mondiale.</French>
		<German>[TAB]In verschiedenen österreichischen Empires, Grenzers waren Soldaten, die aus dem kroatischen und siebenbürgischen Military Frontier. Die Truppen waren ursprünglich gegründet zu verteidigen Österreich von den Osmanen, aber, wenn keine Gefahr drohte, die Grenzers wurden von den Habsburgern in anderen Grenzen des Krieges. Noch, zumindest auf jedes Bataillon Regiment bleiben würde Bewachung der Grenze von Invasion bedroht. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Grenzers wurden Nachfolger der irregulären Armee von Panduren-Oberst, die auch von den Habsburgern zur Verteidigung der Grenze und dienen als skirmishers in der Siebenjährigen Krieges. Nach der Zeit der Napoleonischen Kriege, die Truppen aus mehr regelmäßige Linie Infanterie Regimenter. Sie erhielten Ausbildung in Schießkunst, lineare Taktik, und plänkelnd. Zu Beginn des Krieges, 18 Grenzer Regimenter bildeten etwa ein Viertel der österreichischen Armee. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Da die Grenzers waren nicht so gut, in der Rolle der Linie Infanterie als die regelmäßigen Regimenter, der österreichischen militärischen Befehl nie gab ihnen viel Kredit, und nach einer Meuterei im 1800, ihre Zahl reduziert wurden. Trotz dieser Rückschläge, Grenzers vorgeformte außergewöhnlich gut bei Marengo und Austerlitz, verdienen sie Respekt von den französischen. Napoleon selbst als sie die einzige militärische Truppen in die gesamte österreichische Armee. Grenzer Truppen diente Napoleon bis zu seiner Niederlage, nachdem die Österreicher abgetretenen Gebiete, in dem Krieg des Fünften Koalition. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Im Verlauf des 19. Jahrhunderts, des Osmanischen Faden verringert und damit gab es weniger Aufwand für die Truppen der Verteidigung der Grenzen. Darüber hinaus steigt mit der slawischen Nationalismus und Selbstbestimmung, der österreichischen hohe Befehl wuchs verdächtige des Grenzers und eine mögliche Revolte. Mit diesen Faktoren, die Zahl der Grenzers wurde stetig reduziert, obwohl sie noch im Dienst in der österreichischen und später österreichisch-ungarischen Armee bis zum Zweiten Weltkrieg.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB]In vari imperi austriaco, Grenzers erano truppe che è venuto dalla Transilvania militare croato e di frontiera. Le truppe sono state originariamente fondata per difendere l'Austria dal ottomani, tuttavia quando nessun pericolo lurked, il Grenzers sono stati impiegati dal Asburgo in altre frontiere della guerra. Ancora, almeno sul battaglione di ogni reggimento sarebbero rimasti a guardia della frontiera da minacce di invasione. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Grenzers sono stati successori degli irregolari esercito di Pandurs, che sono state sollevate anche dalla Asburgo per difendere il confine e servire come skirmishers nel Sette Anni 'guerra. Con il tempo della guerre napoleoniche, il formato più truppe regolari linea reggimenti di fanteria. Esse sono state date formazione in marksmanship, lineare tattiche, e skirmishing. All'inizio della guerra, 18 Grenzer reggimenti costituito circa un quarto del esercito austriaco. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Tuttavia, poiché il Grenzers non erano così bene nel ruolo di fanteria di linea regolari reggimenti, il comando militare austriaco non ha dato loro molto credito, e a seguito di una rivolta nel 1800, il loro numero è stato ridotto. Nonostante questi contrattempi, Grenzers preformata eccezionalmente bene a Marengo e di Austerlitz, guadagnandosi loro confronti dal francese. Napoleone, anche in considerazione solo le loro truppe in guerra l'intero esercito austriaco. Grenzer truppe servito per Napoleone fino alla sua sconfitta dopo gli austriaci ceduto territori in guerra della Quinta Coalizione. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Nel corso del 19 ° secolo, il filo ottomano diminuita e, quindi, non vi è meno bisogno di truppe per difendere la frontiera. Inoltre, con il sorgere del nazionalismo slavo e di autodeterminazione, l'alto comando austriaco sospette è cresciuto del Grenzers e di una possibile rivolta. Con questi fattori, il numero di Grenzers era costantemente ridotta, anche se è rimasto in servizio in Austria e, successivamente, l'esercito austro-ungarico fino alla seconda guerra mondiale.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB]En diversos imperios de Austria, Grenzers fueron las tropas que vinieron de los croatas y Transilvania Militar Frontier. Las tropas fueron originalmente a la defensa de Austria de los otomanos, sin embargo, cuando se escondían ningún peligro, la Grenzers fueron empleados por los Habsburgo en otras fronteras de la guerra. Sin embargo, por lo menos en cada batallón del regimiento se mantendrá la vigilancia de la frontera de la invasión amenazas. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Grenzers eran sucesores de los irregulares ejército de Pandurs, que también fueron planteadas por los Habsburgo para defender la frontera y servir de jabalina en el Seven Years' War. En la época de las guerras napoleónicas, las tropas regulares formadas más regimientos de infantería de línea. Se les dio capacitación en tiro, la táctica lineal, y skirmishing. Al comienzo de la guerra, el 18 Grenzer regimientos formado alrededor de la cuarta parte del ejército austriaco. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Sin embargo, debido a que el Grenzers no eran tan buenas en el papel de infantería de línea regular como regimientos, de Austria mando militar nunca les dio mucho crédito, y después de un motín en 1800, su número es reducido. A pesar de estos reveses, Grenzers preformados excepcionalmente bien en Marengo y Austerlitz, ellos ganan el respeto de los franceses. Napoleón incluso consideraba el único militar que las tropas en todo el Ejército austríaco. Grenzer tropas de Napoleón sirvió hasta su derrota después de los austriacos cedió territorios en la Guerra de la Quinta Coalición. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Durante el siglo 19, el otomano hilo disminuido y, por lo tanto hay menos necesidad de que tropas de la defensa de la frontera. Además, con el aumento del nacionalismo eslavo y de la libre determinación, el alto mando de Austria creció sospechosas de la Grenzers y una posible rebelión. Con estos factores, el número de Grenzers fue reducido de manera constante, a pesar de que permaneció en servicio en la de Austria y más tarde Austrohúngaro hasta que el ejército de la Segunda Guerra Mundial.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_GRENZER</Tag>
		<English>Grenzer</English>
		<French>Grenzer</French>
		<German>Grenzer</German>
		<Italian>Grenzer</Italian>
		<Spanish>Grenzer</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_GRENZER_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>This powerful gundpowder unit (the Austrian replacement for the [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Rifleman[COLOR_REVERT]) is an excellent defender against Riflemen.</English>
		<French>Cette puissante unité à poudre à canon (le remplacement autrichien pour l'[COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]infanterie[COLOR_REVERT]), est un très bon défenseur contre l'infanterie classique.</French>
		<German>Dieses leistungsfähige gundpowder unit (der österreichischen Ersatz für die [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Rifleman[COLOR_REVERT]), ist ein ausgezeichneter Verteidiger gegen Schützenzug.</German>
		<Italian>Questo potente gundpowder unit (austriaco per la sostituzione[COLOR_UNIT_TEXT] Rifleman[COLOR_REVERT]), è un eccellente difensore contro Riflemen.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Esta potente gundpowder unit (la sustitución de Austria para la[COLOR_UNIT_TEXT] Rifleman[COLOR_REVERT]), es un excelente defensor contra Riflemen.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_A1</Tag>
		<English>AA</English>
		<French>
			<Text>AA</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>AA</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>AA</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>AA</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_A2</Tag>
		<English>BB</English>
		<French>
			<Text>BB</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>BB</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>BB</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>BB</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_A3</Tag>
		<English>CC</English>
		<French>
			<Text>CC</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>CC</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>CC</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>CC</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_A4</Tag>
		<English>DD</English>
		<French>
			<Text>DD</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>DD</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>DD</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>DD</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_A5</Tag>
		<English>EE</English>
		<French>
			<Text>EE</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>EE</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>EE</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>EE</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_A6</Tag>
		<English>FF</English>
		<French>
			<Text>FF</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>FF</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>FF</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>FF</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_A7</Tag>
		<English>GG</English>
		<French>
			<Text>GG</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>GG</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>GG</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>GG</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_A8</Tag>
		<English>HH</English>
		<French>
			<Text>HH</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>HH</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>HH</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>HH</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_A9</Tag>
		<English>II</English>
		<French>
			<Text>II</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>II</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>II</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>II</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_A0</Tag>
		<English>JJ</English>
		<French>
			<Text>JJ</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>JJ</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>JJ</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>JJ</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_B1</Tag>
		<English>KK</English>
		<French>
			<Text>KK</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>KK</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>KK</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>KK</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_B2</Tag>
		<English>LL</English>
		<French>
			<Text>LL</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>LL</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>LL</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>LL</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_B3</Tag>
		<English>MM</English>
		<French>
			<Text>MM</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>MM</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>MM</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>MM</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_B4</Tag>
		<English>NN</English>
		<French>
			<Text>NN</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>NN</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>NN</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>NN</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_B5</Tag>
		<English>OO</English>
		<French>
			<Text>OO</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>OO</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>OO</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>OO</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_B6</Tag>
		<English>PP</English>
		<French>
			<Text>PP</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>PP</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>PP</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>PP</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_B7</Tag>
		<English>QQ</English>
		<French>
			<Text>QQ</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>QQ</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>QQ</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>QQ</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_B8</Tag>
		<English>RR</English>
		<French>
			<Text>RR</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>RR</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>RR</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>RR</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_B9</Tag>
		<English>SS</English>
		<French>
			<Text>SS</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>SS</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>SS</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>SS</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_B0</Tag>
		<English>TT</English>
		<French>
			<Text>TT</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>TT</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>TT</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>TT</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_C1</Tag>
		<English>UU</English>
		<French>
			<Text>UU</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>UU</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>UU</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>UU</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_C2</Tag>
		<English>VV</English>
		<French>
			<Text>VV</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>VV</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>VV</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>VV</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_C3</Tag>
		<English>WW</English>
		<French>
			<Text>WW</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>WW</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>WW</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>WW</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_C4</Tag>
		<English>XX</English>
		<French>
			<Text>XX</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>XX</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>XX</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>XX</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_C5</Tag>
		<English>YY</English>
		<French>
			<Text>YY</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>YY</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>YY</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>YY</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_C6</Tag>
		<English>ZZ</English>
		<French>
			<Text>ZZ</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>ZZ</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>ZZ</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>ZZ</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_C7</Tag>
		<English>AAA</English>
		<French>
			<Text>AAA</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>AAA</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>AAA</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>AAA</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_C8</Tag>
		<English>BBB</English>
		<French>
			<Text>BBB</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>BBB</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>BBB</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>BBB</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_C9</Tag>
		<English>CCC</English>
		<French>
			<Text>CCC</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>CCC</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>CCC</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>CCC</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_C0</Tag>
		<English>DDD</English>
		<French>
			<Text>DDD</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>DDD</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>DDD</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>DDD</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>