<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by lcollins (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- Copyright Firaxis Games 2005 -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text - New -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_CHORTEN</Tag>
		<English>Chorten</English>
		<French>Chorten</French>
		<German>Chorten</German>
		<Italian>Chorten</Italian>
		<Spanish>Chorten</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
        <TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_CHORTEN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]In early India, mounds of earth, brick, and stone were used to house holy Buddhist relics.  These structures became known as stupas.  Their housing of Buddhist relics lead to the stupas as being seen as a symbol of Buddha's final liberation known as nirvana.  As their use spread across Asia with Buddhism, stupas retained their basic function as relic holders.  In Tibet, where they are known as chortens, the form was employed not only for sacred burial monuments, but also for metal reliquaries that are kept on Buddhist temple altars.  Tibetan chortens are overcome by elaborate tiered finials, often decorated with streamers and flags. [PARAGRAPH: 1] As well as ornate reliquaries set with precious stones and grand temples, such as the Pango Chorten in Gyantse, chortens can take the form of simple wayside markers made from little more than piles of rocks on the circuit around Mount Kailas.  They can be seen throughout the Tibetan countryside.  They offer weary pilgrims and other travelers the spiritual reassurance that, wherever they may find themselves, the Buddha is all around.</English>
		<French>[TAB]Au début de l'Inde, des monticules de terre, la brique et la pierre sont utilisés pour abriter les reliques saintes bouddhistes. Ces structures que l'on a appelé stupas. Leur logement de reliques bouddhiques conduire à la stupas comme étant perçue comme un symbole de la libération finale de Bouddha connu sous le nirvana. Comme leur utilisation répandre dans toute l'Asie avec le bouddhisme, stupas conservé leur fonction de base comme relique titulaires. Au Tibet, où ils sont connus comme chortens, le formulaire a été utilisé non seulement pour les monuments funéraires sacrés, mais aussi pour que le métal reliquaires sont gardées sur temple bouddhiste autels. Tibétain chortens sont surmontés par paliers élaborer embouts, souvent décorée de banderoles et drapeaux. [PARAGRAPHE 1] En plus de fixer des reliquaires orné de pierres précieuses, et les grands temples, tels que le Pango Chorten à Gyantse, chortens peuvent prendre la forme de simples marqueurs de voie de faits peu plus que des amas de roches sur le circuit autour du Mont Kailas . Ils peuvent être vus à travers le paysage tibétain. Ils offrent las pèlerins et autres voyageurs spirituels rassurer que, partout où ils se trouvent, le Bouddha est partout.</French>
		<German>[TAB]In frühen Indien, Hügel der Erde, Ziegel und Steine wurden verwendet, um Haus heiligen buddhistischen Reliquien. Diese Strukturen wurde bekannt als Stupas. Ihr Gehäuse von buddhistischen Reliquien führen zu den Stupas als als ein Symbol für die endgültige Befreiung Buddha bekannt als Nirvana. Da ihre Verwendung in ganz Asien mit dem Buddhismus, Stupas behalten ihre grundlegende Funktion als Relikt Inhaber. In Tibet, wo sie sind bekannt als Chörten, die Form war nicht nur für die heiligen Begräbnisstätte Denkmal, sondern auch für die Metall-Reliquien aufbewahrt, die auf buddhistischen Tempel Altäre. Tibetischen Chörten sind durch aufwändige Tiered finials, oft verziert mit Luftschlangen und Fahnen. [ABSATZ: 1] Neben Reliquienschreine verziert mit Edelsteinen und großen Tempel, wie der Pango Chorten in Gyantse, Chörten können in Form von einfachen Strecke Marker aus nicht viel mehr als Haufen von Felsen auf der Rennstrecke um den Berg Kailas . Sie können sich in der gesamten tibetischen Landschaft. Sie bieten müden Pilger und andere Reisende die spirituelle Zusicherung, dass, wo immer sie sich finden, die Buddha ist rund um die Uhr.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB]Ai primi di India, montagne di terra, di mattoni, pietra, e sono stati utilizzati per casa santa reliquie buddiste. Queste strutture divenne noto come stupa. I loro alloggi di reliquie buddiste portare alla stupa ad essere visto come un simbolo di liberazione finale di Buddha conosciuto come il nirvana. Come il loro uso diffuso in tutta l'Asia con il buddismo, stupa conservato la loro funzione di base, come reliquia titolari. In Tibet, dove sono noti come chortens, il modulo è stato impiegato non solo per la sepoltura dei monumenti sacri, ma anche per metallo reliquiari, che sono tenuti al tempio buddista altari. Tibetano chortens sono superate da elaborare livelli finials, spesso decorata con striscioni e bandiere. [PARAGRAFO: 1] Oltre a impostare reliquiari ornato con pietre preziose, e grandi templi, come il Pango Chorten e Gyantse, chortens può assumere la forma di un semplice marcatori strada fatta da poco più di cumuli di pietra sul circuito attorno al monte Kailas . Essi possono essere visti in tutto il paesaggio tibetano. Essi offrono stanchi pellegrini e altri viaggiatori spirituale rassicurazione che, ovunque si trovino, il Buddha è tutto intorno.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB]A principios de la India, montículos de tierra, ladrillo, piedra y fueron utilizados para albergar las reliquias sagradas budistas. Estas estructuras se conoció como stupas. Su vivienda de reliquias budistas llevar a la stupas de ser visto como un símbolo de la liberación definitiva de Buda conocida como nirvana. Como su uso extendido a través de Asia con el budismo, stupas conservado su función básica como reliquia titulares. En el Tíbet, en los que se conoce como chortens, fue la forma empleada no sólo para el entierro monumentos sagrados, pero también de metal relicarios que se mantienen en templo budista altares. Chortens tibetano se superen por elaborar en niveles terminaciones, a menudo decorada con banderas y serpentinas. [APARTADO: 1] Además de relicarios conjunto adornado con piedras preciosas, y grandes templos, como el Pango Chorten en Gyantse, chortens puede adoptar la forma de marcadores camino simple hecho de poco más de pilas de rocas en el circuito de todo el monte Kailas . Que se puede ver todo el paisaje tibetano. Ofrecen cansados peregrinos y otros viajeros de la tranquilidad espiritual de que, dondequiera que se encuentren, el Buda está por todas partes.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
        <TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_CHORTEN_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Chorten[COLOR_REVERT], the Tibetan replacement for the [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Monument[COLOR_REVERT], offers bonus happiness.</English>
		<French>Le [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]chorten[COLOR_REVERT], équivalent tibétain du [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]monument[COLOR_REVERT], offre un supplément de bonheur.</French>
		<German>Die [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Chorten[COLOR_REVERT], der Tibetische Ersatz für die [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Denkmal[COLOR_REVERT], bietet bonus Glück.</German>
		<Italian>L'[COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Chorten[COLOR_REVERT], il Tibetana sostituzione per il [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Monumento[COLOR_REVERT], offre bonus di felicità.</Italian>
		<Spanish>El [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Chorten[COLOR_REVERT], el Tibetano reemplazo para el [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Monumento[COLOR_REVERT], ofrece bono de la felicidad.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>