<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by lcollins (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- Copyright Firaxis Games 2005 -->
<!-- Modified by strategyonly -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text - New -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_SOLOMON</Tag>
		<English>Solomon</English>
		<French>Salomon</French>
		<German>Salomo</German>
		<Italian>Salomone</Italian>
		<Spanish>SalomÛn</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_SOLOMON_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Solomon[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]King of Israel[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD]c.1000 - 928 BC[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:1][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]The time of the reigns of David and Solomon was a golden age for Israel.  David's military skill relieved Israel of its constant war threats from surrounding nations, and Solomon's diplomatic skill maintained this empire without the need for further war.  Solomon was productive in art and science.  He wrote the Song of Solomon, Ecclesiastes, and most of the Book of Proverbs, three books found in the Bible.  Early in Solomon's reign, God promised him great wisdom. [PARAGRAPH:1] When King David was aging, he lost his mental sharpness.  His oldest son, Adonijah, attempted to seize the throne from Solomon.  Despite the fact that God had promised Solomon the throne, David, in his declining mental health, did nothing to stop Adonijah and his preparations.  Eventually, the case was brought to the attention of David by Solomon's supporters.  David immediately made Solomon king, and retired.  Normally, Solomon would kill Adonijah.  However, in an attempt to spare his life, Adonijah stole the altar of God and refused to give it back until Solomon promised to spare his life. [PARAGRAPH:1] Solomon is described as surrounding himself with luxuries because of the government's success.  Solomon established an alliance with Hiram I, king of Tyre, who helped to give Solomon the supplies he needed for the construction of the Temple.  Hiram, and an architect also named Hiram, also helped Solomon complete the construction of the Ark of the Covenant. [PARAGRAPH:1] Solomon built many houses, palaces, gardens, parks, irrigations, and public works.  The most famous of his achievements is his construction of the Temple.  Because David was unable to build the temple, he accumulated materials for future use.  Solomon imported more supplies later.  The amount was so great that, to transport the materials, Solomon conscripted a labor force of nearly 200,000 of his own people, not counting the workers of the foreign exporters.  Solomon preached sermons and worshipped at the temple.  He also prayed to God to be present at the temple.  God spoke to Solomon again, and said that if his people were unfaithful, he would destroy them.  Even so, if they confessed and repented, he would bless them again. [PARAGRAPH:1] After the completion of the temple, Solomon built many other buildings of importance in Jerusalem.  For thirteen years, he was engaged in building the royal palace on Ophel.  Solomon is also described to rebuild major cities elsewhere in Israel.  Solomon is also attributed to supplying Israel with chariots and horsemen.  Solomon's reign in Israel also resulted in great trade and riches with other countries.  Solomon's fame spread to wide that it reached the Queen of Sheba, who immediately went to Jerusalem with a caravan full of gifts.  Once she arrived, she was very impressed at his immense wealth. [PARAGRAPH:1] Though Solomon remained devout to God for most of his early life, his late was different.  Solomon married 1,000 wives, some of which were foreign.  God forbade this for fear their religious practices would corrupt the true worship of God.  This is in fact what happened to Solomon.  Solomon, out of love for his wives, builds idols for them.  Building idols was a very bad sin in the eyes of God.  Because Solomon went against God's laws, he cursed Solomon's heir, Rehoboam who lost most of the kingdom.</English>
		<French>[H1]Salomon\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Roi d'Isra%C3%ABl[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Dates :[\BOLD]c.1000 - 928 BC[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:1][BOLD]Biographie :[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]La p√©riode des r√®gnes de David et de Solomon √©tait un √¢ge d'or pour l'Israel. La comp√©tence diplomatique de l'Israel soulag√©e par comp√©tence militaire de ses menaces constantes de guerre des nations environnantes, et du Solomon de David a maintenu cet empire sans besoin davantage de de guerre. Solomon √©tait productif dans l'art et la science. Il a √©crit la chanson de Solomon, d'Ecclesiastes, et de la majeure partie du livre des proverbes, trois livres trouv√©s dans la bible. T√¥t dans le r√®gne de Solomon, Dieu lui a promis la grande sagesse. [PARAGRAPH : 1] Quand le Roi David vieillissait, il a perdu son acuit√© mentale. Son fils plus √¢g√©, Adonijah, essay√© pour saisir le tr√¥ne de Solomon. Malgr√© le fait que Dieu avait promis √† Solomon le tr√¥ne, David, dans sa sant√© mentale en baisse, n'a fait rien √† arr√™ter Adonijah et ses pr√©parations. Par la suite, le cas a √©t√© port√© √† la connaissance de David par les d√©fenseurs de Solomon's. Roi imm√©diatement fait de David Solomon, et retir√©. Normalement, Solomon tuerait Adonijah. Cependant, afin d'essayer d'√©pargner sa vie, Adonijah a vol√© l'autel de Dieu et a refus√© de le donner en arri√®re jusqu'√† Solomon promis pour √©pargner sa vie. [PARAGRAPH : 1] Solomon est d√©crit en tant qu'entourage avec des luxes en raison du succ√®s du gouvernement. Solomon a √©tabli une alliance avec Hiram I, le roi du pneu, qui a aid√© √† donner √† Solomon les approvisionnements qu'il a eus besoin pour la construction du temple. Hiram, et un architecte a √©galement appel√© Hiram, Solomon √©galement aid√© accomplissent la construction de l'arche de l'engagement. [PARAGRAPH : 1] Solomon a √©tabli beaucoup de maisons, palais, jardins, parcs, irrigations, et travaux publics. Le plus c√©l√®bre de ses accomplissements est sa construction du temple. Puisque David ne pouvait pas construire le temple, il a accumul√© des mat√©riaux pour le futur usage. Solomon a import√© plus d'approvisionnements plus tard. La quantit√© √©tait si grande que, pour transporter les mat√©riaux, Solomon ait enr√¥l√© une main-d'oeuvre presque des 200.000 de ses propres personnes, ne comptant pas les ouvriers des exportateurs √©trangers. Solomon a pr√™ch√© des sermons et a ador√© au temple. Il a √©galement pri√© √† Dieu pour √™tre pr√©sent au temple. Dieu a parl√© √† Solomon encore, et a dit que si ses personnes √©taient infid√®les, il les d√©truirait. N√©anmoins, s'ils admettaient et se repentissaient, il les b√©nirait encore. [PARAGRAPH : 1] Apr√®s l'accomplissement du temple, Solomon a construit beaucoup d'autres b√¢timents d'importance √† J√©rusalem. Pendant treize ann√©es, il a √©t√© occup√© √† construire le palais royal sur Ophel. Solomon est √©galement d√©crit pour reconstruire les villes principales ailleurs en Israel. Solomon est √©galement attribu√© √† fournir l'Israel des chars et des cavaliers. Le r√®gne de Solomon en Israel a √©galement eu comme cons√©quence le grands commerce et richesse avec d'autres pays. La renomm√©e de Solomon s'est √©cart√©e au loin √† cela qu'elle a atteint la reine de Sheba, qui est imm√©diatement all√©e √† J√©rusalem avec une caravane pleine des cadeaux. Une fois qu'elle arrivait, elle a √©t√© tr√®s impressionn√©e √† son immense richesse. [PARAGRAPH : 1] Bien que Solomon soit rest√© d√©vot √† Dieu pendant la majeure partie de sa vie t√¥t, sien √©tait en retard diff√©rent. Solomon a √©pous√© 1.000 √©pouses, certains dont √©taient √©trangers. Dieu a interdit ceci pour la crainte que leurs pratiques religieuses corrompraient le culte vrai de Dieu. C'est en fait ce qui est arriv√© √† Solomon. Solomon, hors de l'amour pour ses √©pouses, √©tablit des idoles pour eux. √âtablir des idoles √©tait un p√©ch√© tr√®s mauvais aux yeux de Dieu. Puisque Solomon est all√© √† l'encontre les lois de Dieu, il a maudit l'h√©ritier de Solomon, Rehoboam qui a perdu la majeure partie du royaume.</French>
		<German>[H1]Salomo[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]K√∂nig von Israel[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lebte:[\BOLD]c.1000 - 928 BC[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:1][BOLD]Hintergrund:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Die Zeit der Herrschaften von David und von Solomon betrug ein goldenes Alter f√ºr Israel. Davids behielt milit√§rische F√§higkeit entlastete Israel seiner konstanten Kriegdrohungen von umgebenden Nationen und Solomons diplomatische F√§higkeit dieses Reich ohne die Notwendigkeit am weiteren Krieg bei. Solomon war in der kunst und in der Wissenschaft produktiv. Er schrieb das Lied von Solomon, von Ecclesiastes und von die meisten des Buches von Sprichw√∂rtern, drei B√ºcher, die in der Bibel gefunden wurden. Fr√ºh in der Herrschaft Solomons, versprach Gott ihm gro√üe Klugheit. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Als K√∂nig David alterte, verlor er seine Geistessch√§rfe. Sein √§ltester Sohn, Adonijah, versucht, um den Thron von Solomon zu ergreifen. Obwohl Gott Solomon den Thron versprochen hatte, tat David, in seiner abfallenden Geistesgesundheit, nichts, Adonijah und seine Vorbereitungen zu stoppen. Schlie√ülich wurde der Fall zur Aufmerksamkeit von David durch Verfechter Solomons geholt. David sofort gebildeter Solomon K√∂nig und zur√ºckgezogen. Normalerweise w√ºrde Solomon Adonijah t√∂ten. Jedoch um seinem Leben zu ersparen, stahl Adonijah den Altar des Gottes und lehnte ab, ihn bis Solomon zur√ºck zu geben, der versprochen wurde, um seinem Leben zu ersparen. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Solomon wird als Umgeben mit Luxus wegen des Erfolges der Regierung beschrieben. Solomon stellte ein B√ºndnis mit Hiram I, K√∂nig des Reifens her, der half, Solomon die Versorgungsmaterialien zu geben, die, er f√ºr den Aufbau des B√ºgels ben√∂tigte. Hiram und ein Architekt nannte auch Hiram, auch geholfener Solomon f√ºhren den Aufbau der Arche der Vereinbarung durch. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Solomon errichtete viele H√§user, Pal√§ste, G√§rten, Parks, Bew√§sserungen und Arbeiten. Das ber√ºhmteste seiner Ausf√ºhrungen ist sein Aufbau des B√ºgels. Weil David nicht imstande war, den B√ºgel zu errichten, sammelte er Materialien f√ºr zuk√ºnftigen Gebrauch an. Solomon importierte mehr Versorgungsmaterialien sp√§ter. Die Menge war so gro√ü, da√ü, um die Materialien zu transportieren, Solomon Arbeitskr√§fte von fast 200.000 seiner eigenen Leute einzog und nicht die Arbeiter der fremden Exporteure z√§hlte. Solomon predigte Predigten und betete am B√ºgel an. Er betete auch zum Gott, um am B√ºgel anwesend zu sein. Gott sprach mit Solomon wieder und sagte, da√ü, wenn seine Leute unfaithful waren, er sie zerst√∂ren w√ºrde. Allerdings wenn sie bekannten und repented, w√ºrde er sie wieder segnen. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Nach der Beendigung des B√ºgels, errichtete Solomon viele andere Geb√§ude des Wertes in Jerusalem. F√ºr dreizehn Jahre nahm er an dem Errichten des k√∂niglichen Palastes auf Ophel teil. Solomon wird auch beschrieben, um Hauptst√§dte in Israel anderwohin umzubauen. Solomon wird auch dem Liefern von Israel mit chariots und Reitern zugeschrieben. Herrschaft Solomons in Israel ergab auch gro√üen Handel und riches mit anderen L√§ndern. Ruhm Solomons verbreitete zu weit dem, den er die K√∂nigin von Sheba erreichte, die sofort nach Jerusalem mit einem Wohnwagen ging, der von den Geschenken voll ist. Sobald sie ankam, wurde sie sehr an seiner unerme√ülichen F√ºlle beeindruckt. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Obwohl Solomon zum Gott f√ºr die meisten seines fr√ºhen Lebens fromm blieb, war seiner sp√§t unterschiedlich. Solomon heiratete 1.000 Frauen, von denen einige fremd waren. Gott verbot dieses f√ºr Furcht, die ihre fromme Praxis die zutreffende Anbetung des Gottes verderben w√ºrde. Dieses ist tats√§chlich, was Solomon geschah. Solomon, aus Liebe f√ºr seine Frauen heraus, errichtet Idole f√ºr sie. Idole zu errichten war eine sehr schlechte S√ºnde in den Augen des Gottes. Weil Solomon gegen Gesetze des Gottes ging, verfluchte er Erben Solomons, Rehoboam, das die meisten des K√∂nigreiches verlor.</German>
		<Italian>[H1]Salomone[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Re di Israele[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Vita:[\BOLD]c.1000 - 928 BC[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:1][BOLD]Informazioni:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Il periodo dei regni di David e di Solomon era un'et√† dorata per l'Israele. L'abilit√† diplomatica dell'Israele alleviata abilit√† militare delle relative minacce costanti di guerra dalle nazioni circostanti e del Solomon del David ha effettuato questo impero senza l'esigenza di ulteriore guerra. Solomon era produttivo nell'arte e nella scienza. Ha scritto la canzone di Solomon, di Ecclesiastes e di la maggior parte del libro dei proverbi, tre libri trovati nella bibbia. Presto nel regno del Solomon, il dio gli ha promesso la saggezza grande. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Quando il re David stava invecchiando, ha perso la sua acutezza mentale. Il suo figlio pi√π anziano, Adonijah, tentato per grippare il throne da Solomon. Malgrado il fatto che il dio prometta a Solomon il throne, David, nella sua salute mentale declinante, non ha fatto niente arrestare Adonijah e le sue preparazioni. Finalmente, il caso √® stato portato all'attenzione di David dai sostenitori del Solomon. Re immediatamente fatto di David Solomon e pensionato. Normalmente, Solomon ucciderebbe Adonijah. Tuttavia, nel tentativo di risparmiare la sua vita, Adonijah ha rubato il altar del dio ed ha rifiutato di darlo indietro fino a Solomon promesso per risparmiare la sua vita. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Solomon √® descritto come circondarsi con i lussi a causa del successo del governo. Solomon ha stabilito un'alleanza con Hiram I, re del pneumatico, che ha contribuito a dare a Solomon i rifornimenti che ha avuto bisogno di per la costruzione del tempiale. Hiram e un architetto inoltre ha chiamato Hiram, Solomon anche aiutato completa la costruzione dell'arca del patto. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Solomon ha sviluppato molti case, palazzi, giardini, parchi, irrigazioni e lavori pubblici. Il pi√π famoso dei suoi successi √® la sua costruzione del tempiale. Poich√© David non poteva costruire il tempiale, ha accumulato i materiali per uso futuro. Solomon ha importato pi√π successivamente pi√π rifornimenti. L'importo era cos√¨ grande che, per trasportare i materiali, Solomon conscripted lle forze di lavoro di quasi 200.000 della sua propria gente, non contando gli operai degli esportatori stranieri. Solomon ha predicato i sermons ed ha adorato al tempiale. Inoltre ha pregato al dio per essere presente al tempiale. Il dio ha parlato ancora a Solomon ed ha detto che se la sua gente fosse unfaithful, li distruggerebbe. Nondimeno, se confessassero e repented, lo benedirebbe ancora. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Dopo il completamento del tempiale, Solomon ha costruito molte altre costruzioni di importanza a Gerusalemme. Per tredici anni, √® stato agganciato nella costruire il palazzo reale su Ophel. Solomon inoltre √® descritto per ricostruire le citt√† importanti altrove nell'Israele. Solomon inoltre √® attribuito a fornire all'Israele i chariots ed i horsemen. Il regno del Solomon nell'Israele inoltre ha provocato il commercio e i riches grandi con altri paesi. La fama del Solomon si √® sparsa largamente a quella ch'ha raggiunto la regina di Sheba, che immediatamente √® andato a Gerusalemme con un caravan pieno dei regali. Una volta che arrivasse, molto √® stata impressionata alla sua ricchezza immensa. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Bench√® Solomon rimanga devout al dio per la maggior parte della sua vita in anticipo, suo in ritardo era differente. Solomon ha sposato 1.000 mogli, alcuni di cui erano stranieri. Il dio ha proibito a questo per timore che le loro pratiche religiose corromperebbero il culto allineare del dio. Ci√≤ √® in effetti che cosa √® accaduto a Solomon. Solomon, da amore per le sue mogli, sviluppa loro i idols per. Lo sviluppo dei idols era un sin molto difettoso secondo il dio. Poich√© Solomon √® andato contro le leggi del dio, cursed l'erede del Solomon, Rehoboam che ha perso la maggior parte del regno.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[H1]Salom%C3%B3n[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Rey de Israel[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Vivi&#243;:[\BOLD]c.1000 - 928 BC.[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:1][BOLD]Historia:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]La √©poca de los reinados de David y de Solomon era una edad de oro para Israel. La habilidad diplom√°tica relevada habilidad militar de Israel de sus amenazas constantes de la guerra de naciones circundantes, y de Solomon de David mantuvo este imperio sin la necesidad de la guerra adicional. Solomon era productivo en arte y ciencia. √âl escribi√≥ la canci√≥n de Solomon, de Ecclesiastes, y la mayor parte de del libro de proverbios, tres libros encontrados en la biblia. Temprano en el reinado de Solomon, el dios te prometi√≥ la gran sabidur√≠a. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Cuando rey David envejec√≠a, √©l perdi√≥ su agudeza mental. Su m√°s viejo hijo, Adonijah, procurado para agarrar el trono de Solomon. A pesar de que el dios hab√≠a prometido a Solomon el trono, David, en su salud mental que declinaba, no hizo nada parar Adonijah y sus preparaciones. Eventual, el caso fue tra√≠do a la atenci√≥n de David por los partidarios de Solomon. Rey inmediatamente hecho de David Solomon, y retirado. Normalmente, Solomon matar√≠a a Adonijah. Sin embargo, en un intento por ahorrar su vida, Adonijah rob√≥ el altar del dios y rechaz√≥ darlo detr√°s hasta Solomon prometido para ahorrar su vida. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Describen a Solomon como rodearse con los lujos debido a el √©xito del gobierno. Solomon estableci√≥ una alianza con Hiram I, el rey del neum√°tico, que ayud√≥ a dar a Solomon las fuentes que √©l necesit√≥ para la construcci√≥n del templo. Hiram, y un arquitecto tambi√©n nombr√≥ a Hiram, Solomon tambi√©n ayudado termina la construcci√≥n de la arca del convenio. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Solomon construy√≥ muchas casas, palacios, jardines, parques, irrigaciones, y obras p√∫blicas. El m√°s famoso de sus logros es su construcci√≥n del templo. Porque David no pod√≠a construir el templo, √©l acumul√≥ los materiales para el uso futuro. Solomon import√≥ m√°s fuentes m√°s adelante. La cantidad era tan grande que, para transportar los materiales, Solomon reclut√≥ una mano de obra de casi 200.000 de su propia gente, no contando a los trabajadores de los exportadores extranjeros. Solomon predic√≥ sermones y se adoraba en el templo. √âl tambi√©n rog√≥ al dios para estar presente en el templo. El dios habl√≥ a Solomon otra vez, y dijo que si su gente fuera unfaithful, √©l los destruir√≠a. Sin embargo, si confesaran y repented, √©l lo bendecir√≠a otra vez. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Despu√©s de la terminaci√≥n del templo, Solomon construy√≥ muchos otros edificios de la importancia en Jerusal√©n. Por trece a√±os, lo contrataron a construir el palacio real en Ophel. Describen a Solomon tambi√©n para reconstruir ciudades importantes a otra parte en Israel. Atribuyen a Solomon tambi√©n a proveer Israel de los chariots y de los jinetes. El reinado de Solomon en Israel tambi√©n dio lugar a grandes comercio y riquezas con otros pa√≠ses. La fama de Solomon se separ√≥ de par en par a √©sa que alcanz√≥ a reina de Sheba, que fue inmediatamente a Jerusal√©n con una caravana llena de regalos. Una vez que ella llegara, muy la impresionaron en su abundancia inmensa. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Aunque Solomon segu√≠a siendo devoto al dios para la mayor parte de su vida temprana, el suyo era tarde diferente. Solomon cas√≥ a 1.000 esposas, algunas de quienes eran extranjeras. El dios prohibi√≥ esto para el miedo que sus pr√°cticas religiosas corromper√≠an la adoraci√≥n verdadera del dios. Esto es de hecho qu√© sucedi√≥ a Solomon. Solomon, fuera del amor para sus esposas, construye los √≠dolos para ellos. La construcci√≥n de √≠dolos era un pecado muy malo a los ojos de dios. Porque Solomon fue contra los leyes del dios, √©l maldijo a heredero de Solomon, Rehoboam que perdi√≥ la mayor parte de el reino.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_SOLOMON_1</Tag>
		<English>Greetings, [CT_NAME].  Be good, and we shall be good.  But remember, there is always a time to love, and a time to hate; a time of war, and a time of peace.</English>
		<French>Salutations, [CT_NAME]. Soyez bon, et nous serons bon. Mais rappelez-vous, il y a un temps pour aimer, et un temps pour haÔr; un temps pour la guerre et un temps pour la paix.</French>
		<German>Gr¸ﬂe, [CT_NAME]. Gut sein und wir sind gut. Aber sich erinnern, gibt es immer eine Zeit zu lieben und eine Zeit zu hassen; eine Zeit des Krieges und eine Zeit des Friedens.</German>
		<Italian>Saluti, [CT_NAME]. Essere buono e saremo buoni. Ma ricordar di, ci Ë sempre un momento di amare e un momento di odiare; un momento della guerra e un momento di pace.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Saludos, [CT_NAME]. Sed amables, y nosotros seremos amables. Pero recordad, siempre hay un tiempo para amar, y un tiempo para odiar; un tiempo para la guerra, y un tiempo para la paz.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_REFUSE_TO_TALK_LEADER_SOLOMON_1</Tag>
		<English>Your words are like fire cups for the dead.</English>
		<French>Vos mots sont comme des tasses de feu pour les morts.</French>
		<German>Deine W√∂rter sind wie Feuerschalen f√ºr die Toten.</German>
		<Italian>Le vostre parole sono come le tazze del fuoco per i morti.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Tus palabras son como tazas de fuego para los muertos.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_NO_PEACE_LEADER_SOLOMON_1</Tag>
		<English>The wicked shall always be punished, [CT_NAME].</English>
		<French>Le mauvais sera toujours puni, [CT_NAME</French>
		<German>Das gemeine wird immer bestraft, [CT_NAME].</German>
		<Italian>Il cattivo sar‡ punito sempre, [CT_NAME].</Italian>
		<Spanish>Los malvados siempre deben ser castigados, [CT_NAME].</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FR_LEADER_SOLOMON_1</Tag>
		<English>My heart gives me joy when you present yourself.</English>
		<French>Mon coeur me procure de la joie quand vous vous prÈsentez.</French>
		<German>Mein Herz gibt mir Freude, wenn du dich darstellst.</German>
		<Italian>Il mio cuore mi d‡ la gioia quando vi presentate.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Mi corazÛn se regocija con tu presencia.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FUR_LEADER_SOLOMON_1</Tag>
		<English>You dug the pit that is your wickedness.  One day, you shall fall into it.</English>
		<French>Vous avez creusÈ la fosse de votre mÈchancetÈ. Un jour, vous tomberez dedans.</French>
		<German>Du grubst die Grube, die deine Gemeinheit ist. Ein Tag, f√§llst du in sie.</German>
		<Italian>Avete scavato il pozzo che √® il vostro wickedness. Un giorno, cadrete in esso.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Cavaste el hoyo que es tu maldad. Un d√≠a, caer√°s en √©l.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_WEAKER_SOLOMON_1</Tag>
		<English>We two are better because when we fall, the other will lift the other up.  Lifting is helping.</English>
		<French>Nous sommes plus forts ‡† deux, car quand l'un tombe, l'autre le relËve. Relever, c'est aider.</French>
		<German>Wir zwei sind besser, weil, wenn wir fallen, das andere das andere anhebt. Das Anheben hilft.</German>
		<Italian>Due siamo migliori perch√© quando cadiamo, l'altro alzer√† l'altro in su. Il sollevamento sta aiutando.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Dos somos mejores porque cuando nos caemos, el otro levantar√° a otro para arriba. La elevaci√≥n est√° ayudando.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_EQUAL_SOLOMON_1</Tag>
		<English>We are in the same position I see, so please, give help to those who need it!</English>
		<French>Je vois que nous sommes dans la mÍme position, donc s'il vous plait, aidez ce qui en ont besoin !</French>
		<German>Wir sind in der gleichen Position, die ich sehe, so gefallen, geben Hilfe zu denen, die sie ben√∂tigen!</German>
		<Italian>Siamo nella stessa posizione che vedo, cos√¨ soddisfiamo, diamo l'aiuto a coloro che lo ha bisogno!</Italian>
		<Spanish>¬°Estamos en la misma posici√≥n que veo, tan satisfacemos, damos ayuda a las que la necesiten!</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_STRONGER_SOLOMON_1</Tag>
		<English>Getting a good name is better than any precious ointment.  Providing for others will get you that name, [CT_NAME].</English>
		<French>Se faire un nom juste est mieux que le meilleur des onguents. Donner aux autres fera de vous un nom juste, [CT_NAME].</French>
		<German>Einen guten Namen zu erhalten ist besser als jede kostbare Salbe. Das Zur Verf√ºgung stellen f√ºr andere erh√§lt dich da√ü Name, [CT_NAME].</German>
		<Italian>Ottenere un buon nome √® migliore di tutto l'unguento prezioso. Provvedendo ad altri li otterr√† che nome, [CT_NAME].</Italian>
		<Spanish>Conseguir un buen nombre es mejor que cualquier ung√ºento precioso. El prever otros te conseguir√° que nombre, [CT_NAME].</Spanish>
	</TEXT>	
</Civ4GameText>