<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by lcollins (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- Copyright Firaxis Games 2005 -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text - New -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_CLOISTER</Tag>
		<English>Cloister</English>
		<French>Cloître</French>
		<German>Kreuzgang</German>
		<Italian>Chiostro</Italian>
		<Spanish>Claustro</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_CLOISTER_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Cloister[COLOR_REVERT], the Lombard replacement for the [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Colosseum[COLOR_REVERT], adds a free priest.</English>
		<French>Le [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]cloître[COLOR_REVERT], équivalent lombard du [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]colisée[COLOR_REVERT], ajoute un prêtre gratuit.</French>
		<German>Das [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Kreuzgang[COLOR_REVERT], der Lombard Wiedereinbau für das [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT] Colosseum [COLOR_REVERT], adds a free priest.</German>
		<Italian>Il [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Chiostro[COLOR_REVERT], il rimontaggio del Lombard per [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT] il Colosseum [COLOR_REVERT], adds a free priest.</Italian>
		<Spanish>El [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Claustro[COLOR_REVERT], el reemplazo de Lombard para [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT] el Colosseum [COLOR_REVERT], adds a free priest.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_CLOISTER_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Monastacism grew greatly during the twelfth century, and its reflection in architecture can be found in cloisters.  Before the twelfth century, cloisters were rarely seen.  The earliest visible cloister in Lombardy is the clositer at S. Alberto di Pizzo Como.  Lombard cloisters commonly possessed features like single colonnettes, central doorways, and archivolts of an unmoulded order.  These features were replaced with features native to Provence.  Cloisters with coupled colonnettes had been built in Lombardy as early as 1100.  These clositers show characteristics of those of Provence, Languedoc, and Spain.  The Lombard cloister is perhaps best represented at S. Zeno of Verona, which was built between 1175 and 1200.  The first vaulted cloisters could be found at Vezzolano.  The cloisters here date from 1180 to 1189.  The vault and decorations of these cloisters commonly contained French influence.  This style of cloister was reproduced in the thirteenth century by the Goths at Chiaravelle.</English>
		<French>Monastacism s'est développé considérablement pendant le douzième siècle, et sa réflexion dans l'architecture peut être trouvée dans les cloîtres. Avant le douzième siècle, des cloîtres ont été rarement vus. Le cloître évident le plus tôt en Lombardie est le clositer chez S. Alberto di Pizzo Como. Lombard cloître les dispositifs généralement possédés comme des colonnettes simples, portes centrales, et les archivolts de l'unmoulded l'ordre. Ces dispositifs ont été remplacés avec des dispositifs indigènes en Provence. Des cloîtres avec des colonnettes couplés avaient été construits en Lombardie dès 1100. Ces clositers montrent des caractéristiques de ceux de la Provence, du Languedoc, et de l'Espagne. Le cloître de Lombard peut-être mieux est représenté à S. Zeno de Vérone, qui a été construit entre 1175 et 1200. Les premiers cloîtres sautés ont pu être trouvés chez Vezzolano. Les cloîtres ici datent de 1180 à 1189. La chambre forte et les décorations de ces cloîtres ont généralement contenu l'influence de Français. Ce modèle de cloître a été reproduit au treizième siècle par le Goths chez Chiaravelle.</French>
		<German>Monastacism wuchs groß während des twelfth Jahrhunderts, und seine Reflexion in der Architektur kann in den Klöstern gefunden werden. Vor dem twelfth Jahrhundert wurden Klöster selten gesehen. Das früheste sichtbare Kloster in Lombardei ist das clositer bei S. Alberto di Pizzo Como. Lombard kapselt allgemein besessene Eigenschaften wie einzelne colonnettes, zentrale Eingänge ab, und archivolts von unmoulded Auftrag. Diese Eigenschaften wurden mit den Eigenschaften ersetzt, die nach Provence gebürtig sind. Klöster mit verbundenen colonnettes waren in Lombardei schon in 1100 errichtet worden. Diese clositers zeigen Eigenschaften von denen von Provence, von Languedoc und von Spanien. Das Lombard Kloster wird möglicherweise gut an S. Zeno von Verona dargestellt, das zwischen 1175 und 1200 errichtet wurde. Die ersten vaulted Klöster konnten bei Vezzolano gefunden werden. Die Klöster hier datieren von 1180 bis 1189. Die Wölbung und die Dekorationen dieser Klöster enthielten allgemein Franzoseeinfluß. Diese Art des Klosters wurde im dreizehnten Jahrhundert durch das Goths bei Chiaravelle reproduziert.</German>
		<Italian>Monastacism si è sviluppato notevolmente durante il twelfth secolo e la relativa riflessione nell'architettura può essere trovata in cloisters. Prima del twelfth secolo, i cloisters sono stati visti raramente. Il cloister visibile più in anticipo in Lombardia è il clositer a S. Alberto di Pizzo Como. Lombard cloisters le caratteristiche comunemente possedute come i singoli colonnettes, porte centrali e i archivolts dell'unmoulded l'ordine. Queste caratteristiche sono state sostituite con le caratteristiche natali in Provenza. I Cloisters con i colonnettes coppia erano stati costruiti in Lombardia fin da 1100. Questi clositers mostrano le caratteristiche di quelli della Provenza, di Languedoc e della Spagna. Il cloister del Lombard forse è rappresentato il più bene allo S. Zeno di Verona, che è stata costruita fra 1175 e 1200. I primi cloisters vaulted hanno potuto essere trovati a Vezzolano. I cloisters qui datano da 1180 a 1189. La volta e le decorazioni di questi cloisters hanno contenuto comunemente l'influenza del francese. Questo stile del cloister è stato riprodotto nel tredicesimo secolo dal Goths a Chiaravelle.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Monastacism creció grandemente durante el twelfth siglo, y su reflexión en arquitectura se puede encontrar en cloisters. Antes del twelfth siglo, los cloisters fueron vistos raramente. El cloister visible más temprano de Lombardía es el clositer en S. Alberto di Pizzo Como. Lombard cloisters características comúnmente poseídas como los solos colonnettes, umbrales centrales, y los archivolts del unmoulded orden. Estas características fueron substituidas por las características nativas a Provence. Los Cloisters con colonnettes juntados habían sido construidos en Lombardía desde 1100. Estos clositers demuestran características de los de Provence, de Languedoc, y de España. El cloister de Lombard quizás se representa lo más mejor posible en S. Zeno de Verona, que fue construida entre 1175 y 1200. Los primeros cloisters saltados se podían encontrar en Vezzolano. Los cloisters aquí fechan a partir de 1180 a 1189. La cámara acorazada y las decoraciones de estos cloisters contuvieron comúnmente influencia del francés. Este estilo del cloister fue reproducido en el décimotercer siglo por el Goths en Chiaravelle.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>