<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by lcollins (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- Copyright Firaxis Games 2005 -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text - New -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_HUNG_VEGVAR</Tag>
		<English>Végvár</English>
		<French>
			<Text>Végvár</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>Végvár</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>1</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>Végvár</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>Végvár</Text>
			<Gender>Female</Gender>
			<Plural>0:1</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_HUNG_VEGVAR_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>After the Turks conquered much of southern Hungary, a new defensive line inside the country was strongly needed. Out of castles, mansions, churches and monasteries a new defensive line was built with the efforts of the bondsmen of the surrounding area within a short time. A new system of castles was created, which began at the Adriatic Sea, ended at the lower Danube River and enclosed the area that was controlled by the Turks. The most important places were Kanizsa, Györ and Komárom, in the north Érsekújvár, Kassa, Szatmár and in the east Várad, Gyula, Lippa and Temesvár, these fortresses observed every Turkish movement. [PARAGRAPH:1]From the 1550s on, the Vienna council sent some military engineers to Hungary, that rebuilt the most important Végvárs to a modern standard. The most important functions of the Végvárs were to defend the borders, secure the roads and the river crossings, the prevention of the enemy troop supplies and the security of the people and their goods in the surrounding area. [PARAGRAPH:1]Towers were built from where the defenders could fire at the attacking enemies that wanted to climb the walls, whereas the defenders where protected from enemy bombardments. After 1556 the military council took control over the Végvárs, thus they were under a uniform and competent command. Furthermore, smart defenders invented new military equipment and in peaceful times the wine supply didn't only delight the castles crew.  [PARAGRAPH:2]</English>
		<French>After the Turks conquered much of southern Hungary, a new defensive line inside the country was strongly needed. Out of castles, mansions, churches and monasteries a new defensive line was built with the efforts of the bondsmen of the surrounding area within a short time. A new system of castles was created, which began at the Adriatic Sea, ended at the lower Danube River and enclosed the area that was controlled by the Turks. The most important places were Kanizsa, Györ and Komárom, in the north Érsekújvár, Kassa, Szatmár and in the east Várad, Gyula, Lippa and Temesvár, these fortresses observed every Turkish movement. [PARAGRAPH:1]From the 1550s on, the Vienna council sent some military engineers to Hungary, that rebuilt the most important Végvárs to a modern standard. The most important functions of the Végvárs were to defend the borders, secure the roads and the river crossings, the prevention of the enemy troop supplies and the security of the people and their goods in the surrounding area. [PARAGRAPH:1]Towers were built from where the defenders could fire at the attacking enemies that wanted to climb the walls, whereas the defenders where protected from enemy bombardments. After 1556 the military council took control over the Végvárs, thus they were under a uniform and competent command. Furthermore, smart defenders invented new military equipment and in peaceful times the wine supply didn't only delight the castles crew.  [PARAGRAPH:2]</French>
		<German>Nachdem die Türken sich in Ungarn einrichteten, wurde dringend eine neue Verteidigungslinie im Inneren des Landes benötigt. Aus Ritterburgen und Schlössern, Herrenhäusern, Kirchen und Klöstern wurde mit großen Anstrengungen seitens der Leibeigenen aus der Umgebung in kurzer Zeit eine neue Verteidigungslinie erschaffen. Ein komplettes Burgensystem entstand das beginnend an der Adria bis zur unteren Donau verlief und das von Türken besetzte Gebiet einschloss. Die bedeutendsten Orte waren Kanizsa, Gyor und Komárom; im Norden außerdem Érsekújvár, Kassa, Szatmár und im Osten Várad, Gyula, Lippa und Temesvár, welche jede türkische Bewegung überwachten. [PARAGRAPH:1]Ab Mitte der 1550er Jahre sandte der Wiener Rat einige italienische Militäringenieure nach Ungarn, die die wichtigsten Végvár gemäß den damaligen Ansprüchen umbauten. Die wichtigsten Aufgaben der Végvár waren die Verteidigung der Grenzen, die Sicherung der Straßen und der Flussübergänge, die Unterbindung des feindlichen Truppennachschubs und der Schutz der Bevölkerung der jeweiligen Umgebung und deren Eigentum. [PARAGRAPH:1]Aus den Mauerfluchten wurden schmucke fünfseitige Türme gebaut. Von dort aus konnten die Verteidiger die Angreifer die die Mauern erstürmen wollten, unter Feuer nehmen, sie selbst waren vor feindlichem Beschuss geschützt. Ab 1556 gerieten die Végvár unter die Kontrolle des Militärrates und damit eröffnete sich die Möglichkeit das Burgensystem unter ein einheitliches und fähiges Kommando zu stellen. Zudem erfanden einige gewiefte Verteidiger neue Kriegsmaschinerie und der Weinvorrat der Burgen erfreute in friedlicheren Zeiten nicht nur die Burgbesatzung. [PARAGRAPH:2]</German>
		<Italian>Dopo che i turchi conquistarono larga parte dell'Ungheria meridionale si rese fortemente necessaria una nuova linea di difese sul territorio. Grazie agli sforzi dei vassalli delle aree vicine, in poco tempo ne fu costruita una che correva esternamente alle dimore dei cavalieri e dei signori, ai castelli, alle chiese e ai monasteri. La nuova linea difensiva era costituita da una serie di castelli che partiva dal mar Adriatico e terminava sulle rive del basso Danubio, delimitando cosi il territorio controllato dai turchi. Le postazioni piu importanti furono Kanizsa, Györ e Komárom, a nord Érsekújvár, Kassa e Szatmár e ad est Várad, Gyula, Lippa e Temesvár; da queste fortezze era possibile tenere sotto controllo tutti i movimenti delle truppe turche. [PARAGRAPH:1]Dalla meta del XVI secolo, il consiglio di Vienna invio in Ungheria alcuni ingegneri militari che ristrutturarono i piu importanti végvár secondo standard moderni. Le funzioni piu importanti dei vegvár furono di sorvegliare i confini, di garantire un passaggio sicuro sulle strade e sul fiume, di intercettare i rifornimenti delle truppe nemiche e di difendere la popolazione e i loro beni nelle aree circostanti. [PARAGRAPH:1]Furono edificate delle torri da cui i soldati posti a difesa, ben protetti dai bombardamenti nemici, potevano far fuoco sui soldati che cercavano di arrampicarsi lungo le mura. Dopo il 1556 il consiglio militare prese il controllo dei végvár che, di conseguenza, furono amministrati da un comando uniforme e competente. Inoltre, dei soldati brillanti inventarono un nuovo equipaggiamento militare mentre in tempo di pace le abbondanti risorse di vino non deliziarono unicamente gli abitanti dei castelli.</Italian>
		<Spanish>After the Turks conquered much of southern Hungary, a new defensive line inside the country was strongly needed. Out of castles, mansions, churches and monasteries a new defensive line was built with the efforts of the bondsmen of the surrounding area within a short time. A new system of castles was created, which began at the Adriatic Sea, ended at the lower Danube River and enclosed the area that was controlled by the Turks. The most important places were Kanizsa, Györ and Komárom, in the north Érsekújvár, Kassa, Szatmár and in the east Várad, Gyula, Lippa and Temesvár, these fortresses observed every Turkish movement. [PARAGRAPH:1]From the 1550s on, the Vienna council sent some military engineers to Hungary, that rebuilt the most important Végvárs to a modern standard. The most important functions of the Végvárs were to defend the borders, secure the roads and the river crossings, the prevention of the enemy troop supplies and the security of the people and their goods in the surrounding area. [PARAGRAPH:1]Towers were built from where the defenders could fire at the attacking enemies that wanted to climb the walls, whereas the defenders where protected from enemy bombardments. After 1556 the military council took control over the Végvárs, thus they were under a uniform and competent command. Furthermore, smart defenders invented new military equipment and in peaceful times the wine supply didn't only delight the castles crew.  [PARAGRAPH:2]</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_HUNG_VEGVAR_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>[COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Végvárs[COLOR_REVERT] replace [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]castles[COLOR_REVERT]; they increase city defense, espionage, science and culture. It also exerts a zone of control around your city to guard your borders. Happiness also rises if wine is available. Build végvárs near your empire's borders where your cities are in danger of attack by your enemies.</English>
		<French>[COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Végvárs[COLOR_REVERT] replace [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]castles[COLOR_REVERT]; they increase city defense, espionage, science and culture. It also exerts a zone of control around your city to guard your borders. Happiness also rises if wine is available. Build végvárs near your empire's borders where your cities are in danger of attack by your enemies.</French>
		<German>[COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Végvárs[COLOR_REVERT] replace [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]castles[COLOR_REVERT]; they increase city defense, espionage, science and culture. It also exerts a zone of control around your city to guard your borders. Happiness also rises if wine is available. Build végvárs near your empire's borders where your cities are in danger of attack by your enemies.</German>
		<Italian>[COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Végvárs[COLOR_REVERT] replace [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]castles[COLOR_REVERT]; they increase city defense, espionage, science and culture. It also exerts a zone of control around your city to guard your borders. Happiness also rises if wine is available. Build végvárs near your empire's borders where your cities are in danger of attack by your enemies.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Végvárs[COLOR_REVERT] replace [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]castles[COLOR_REVERT]; they increase city defense, espionage, science and culture. It also exerts a zone of control around your city to guard your borders. Happiness also rises if wine is available. Build végvárs near your empire's borders where your cities are in danger of attack by your enemies.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>