<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by lcollins (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- Copyright Firaxis Games 2005 -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text - New -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_AUSTRIA_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Austrian Empire</English>
		<French>Autriche</French>
		<German>Kaisertum Osterreich</German>
		<Italian>Impero Austriaco</Italian>
		<Spanish>Imperio Austriaco</Spanish>
	</TEXT>	
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_AUSTRIA_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Austria</English>
		<French>Autrichiens</French>
		<German>Osterre</German>
		<Italian>Austria</Italian>
		<Spanish>Austria</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_AUSTRIA_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Austrian</English>
    <French>
      <Text>autrichien:autrichienne:autrichiens:autrichiennes</Text>
      <Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
      <Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
    </French>
		<German>Osterreichische</German>
		<Italian>Austriaco</Italian>
		<Spanish>Austriaco</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_AUSTRIA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Austria was first settled by various Celtic tribes.  Noricum, a Celtic kingdom, was claimed by the Roman Empire and made a province.  After the Roman Empire's fall, Austria was invaded by Bavarians, Slavs, and Avars.  When Charlemagne conquered the land in 788, he encouraged colonization and Christianity.  Austria, now part of Eastern Francia, was under the control of the house of Babenberg.  In 976, the area known as Marchia Orientalis was given to Leopold of Babenberg in 976. [PARAGRAPH: 2] The first record of the land being known as Austria is in 966 when referring to the territory of the Babenberg March.  The following centuries are characterized by the early settlements of the country.  In 1156, the Privilegium Minus elevated Austria to the duchy statues.  The Babenbergs also gained the Duchy of Styria in 1192. [PARAGRAPH: 2] With the death of Frederick II in 1246, the Barenberg line ended.  Otakar II of Bohemia effectively controlled the duchies of Austria.  After his defeat and Durnkrut by Rudolf I of Germany in 1278, his reign came to an end.  The following centuries would mark a time of Austrian prosperity, under the ruling dynasty, the Habsburgs.  In the fourteenth and fifteenth centuries, the Habsburgs accumulated provinces in the area of the Duchy of Austria.  In 1438, Duke Albert V of Austria was chosen as the successor to his father-in-law, Emperor Sigismund.  Although Albert ruled for only a year, from that time on, every emperor of the Holy Roman Empire was a Habsburg, with one exception. [PARAGRAPH: 2] The Habsburgs began to accumulate lands over the years, and in 1477 the Archduke Maximilian acquired most of the Low Countries after marrying the heiress of Burgundy.  His son Philip the Fair married the heiress of Castile and Aragon, and acquired Spain and its Italian, African, and New World adjuncts for the Habsburgs. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Following the Battle of Mohacs, Austrian rulers expanded their territories.  However, the Ottoman expansion into Hungary led to frequent conflicts between the two powers.  The long reign of Leopold I ended the Austrian conflict with the Turks.  Following the defense of Vienna in 1628, a series of campaigns resulted in the return of Hungary to Austrian Control in 1699.  However, during the latter part of the reign of Emperor Charles VI, Austria surrendered some of these gains.  After this time, the age of Austrian-Prussian dualism began in Hungary. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Various defeats against Napoleon spelled the end of the old Holy Roman Empire in 1806, and in 1804 the Austrian Empire was founded.  In 1867, it was transformed into the dual-monarchy of Austria-Hungary.  Following the Napoleonic wars, Austria emerged as one of Europe's dominant powers along with Prussia and Russia.  In 1815, the German Confederation was founded under the presidency of Austria.  Austria and Prussia were one of the two leading powers.  After Germany wished to become a unified country, Austria was unwilling to become part of it and grew out of Germany, while Prussia grew into it.  Following the defeat of Prussia at the battle of Koniggratz in Bohemia, Austria had to leave the German Confederation and was subsequently no longer permitted to take part in German politics. [PARAGRAPH: 2] The Austro-Hungarian Compromise of 1867 provided a dual sovereignty under Franz Joseph I, who ruled until his death.  The diversity of the empire made it difficult to control in an age of emerging nationalist movements.  The assassination of Archduke Franz Ferdinand in 1914 was the probable cause of World War I, which led to the downfall of the Austro-Hungarian Empire. [PARAGRAPH: 2] In 1918 and 1919, Austria was known as the Republic of German Austria.  The monarchy was, however, dissolved in 1919 and a parliamentary democracy was set up in 1920.  In 1922, Austria was given a loan to improve the general economic condition.  With the granting of the loan, Austria passed from an independent state to the control exercised by the League of Nations. At the time, the real ruler of Austria became the League, through its commissioner in Vienna. [PARAGRAPH: 2] The First Austrian Republic lasted until 1933.  The two major parties fought each other within the parliament.  After the Austrian Civil War in 1934, several members of the Schutzbund Party were executed and the Social Democratic Party was outlawed.  In 1936, German troops occupied the country and Hitler, a native of Austria himself, lost citizenship in 1925.  Just before the collapse of the Third Reich, Karl Renner set up a Provisional Government in Vienna.  Much like Germany, Austria, too, was divided into a British, French, a Soviet and an American Zone and governed by the Allied Commission for Austria. [PARAGRAPH: 2] On May 1955, Austria regained independence and declared itself permanently neutral, which it remains today. The political system of the Second Republic came to be characterized by the system of Proporz, meaning that most posts of some political importance were split evenly between members of the Social Democrats and the People's Party.  Today, Austria has five major parties: the SPO (Labour Party), the OVP (Conservatives), the Greens (Environmentalists), and FPO (nationalists).  Austria became a member of the European Union in 1995, and has retained its constitutional neutrality.</English>
		<French>[TAB]L'Autriche a été d'abord colonisée par diverses tribus celtes. Norique, un royaume celtique, a été revendiqué par l'Empire romain et a fait une province. Après la chute de l'empire romain, l'Autriche a été envahie par les Bavarois, les Slaves, et les Avars. Lorsque Charlemagne a conquis les terres de 788, il a encouragé la colonisation et le christianisme. Autriche, qui fait maintenant partie de l'Est Francia, était sous le contrôle de la maison de Babenberg. En 976, la région connue sous le nom de Marchia Orientalis a été donnée à Léopold de Babenberg à 976. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Le premier album de la terre étant connue sous le nom de l'Autriche est en 966 lorsqu'il se réfère au territoire de la Babenberg mars. Les siècles suivants, se caractérisent par des premiers établissements du pays. En 1156, le Privilegium Moins élevée à l'Autriche le duché de statues. Les Babenberg également obtenu le duché de Styrie en 1192. [PARAGRAPH: 2] À la mort de Frédéric II en 1246, a pris fin le Barenberg ligne. Otakar II de Bohême effectivement contrôlé les duchés de l'Autriche. Après sa défaite et Durnkrut par Rudolf I de l'Allemagne en 1278, son règne a pris fin. Les siècles suivants, va marquer une époque de prospérité autrichienne, sous la dynastie au pouvoir, les Habsbourg. Au quatorzième et quinzième siècles, les Habsbourg accumulé provinces dans le domaine de la Duché de l'Autriche. En 1438, le duc Albert V de l'Autriche a été choisi pour succéder à son père dans la loi, l'empereur Sigismond. Bien que Albert a statué que pour un an, à partir de ce moment, chaque empereur du Saint Empire romain était un Habsbourg, à une exception près. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Les Habsbourg ont commencé à accumuler des terres au fil des ans, et en 1477 l'archiduc Maximilien acquis la plupart des pays à faible marient après l'héritière de la Bourgogne. Son fils Philippe le Bel mariée l'héritière de Castille et d'Aragon et de l'acquisition de l'Espagne et de ses italienne, africaine et du Nouveau Monde compléments pour les Habsbourg. [PARAGRAPH: 2] À la suite de la bataille de Mohacs, autrichien dirigeants élargi leur territoire. Toutefois, l'expansion ottomane en Hongrie a conduit à de fréquents conflits entre les deux pouvoirs. Le long règne de Léopold Ier d'Autriche a mis fin au conflit avec les Turcs. Suite à la défense de Vienne en 1628, une série de campagnes abouti au retour de la Hongrie à autrichien de contrôle en 1699. Toutefois, au cours de la dernière partie du règne de l'empereur Charles VI, Autriche annulé certains de ces gains. Après cette période, l'âge du dualisme austro-hongrois de Prusse a débuté en Hongrie. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Divers défaites contre Napoléon fut la fin de l'ancien Saint Empire romain germanique en 1806, et en 1804 l'Empire autrichien a été fondée. En 1867, il a été transformé en la double monarchie austro-hongroise. Suivant les guerres napoléoniennes, l'Autriche est apparue comme l'une des puissances dominantes de l'Europe avec la Prusse et la Russie. En 1815, la Confédération allemande a été fondé sous la présidence de l'Autriche. L'Autriche et la Prusse étaient l'une des deux principales puissances. Après l'Allemagne souhaitait devenir un pays unifié, l'Autriche n'était pas disposée à devenir une partie de celui-ci et est née de l'Allemagne, tandis que la Prusse a grandi dans lui. Après la défaite de la Prusse à la bataille de Koniggratz la Bohême, l'Autriche a dû quitter la Confédération allemande et a été par la suite ne sont plus autorisés à prendre part à la politique allemande. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Le compromis austro-hongrois de 1867 a fourni une double souveraineté sous Franz Joseph I, qui a gouverné jusqu'à sa mort. La diversité de l'empire fait qu'il est difficile de maîtriser à l'âge de l'émergence des mouvements nationalistes. L'assassinat de l'archiduc Franz Ferdinand en 1914 a été la cause la plus probable de la première guerre mondiale, qui a conduit à la chute de l'Empire austro-hongrois. [PARAGRAPH: 2] En 1918 et 1919, l'Autriche a été connu sous le nom de la République de l'Autriche allemande. La monarchie a cependant été dissous en 1919 et une démocratie parlementaire a été créée en 1920. En 1922, l'Autriche a reçu un prêt pour améliorer la situation économique générale. Avec l'octroi du prêt, de l'Autriche transmise d'un État indépendant pour le contrôle exercé par la Société des Nations. À l'époque, le véritable souverain de l'Autriche est devenue la Ligue, par l'intermédiaire de son commissaire à Vienne. [PARAGRAPH: 2] La Première République autrichienne a duré jusqu'en 1933. Les deux principaux partis se sont battues au sein du parlement. Après la guerre civile autrichienne en 1934, plusieurs membres de la Schutzbund Parti ont été exécutés et le Parti social démocrate a été proscrit. En 1936, les troupes allemandes occupent le pays et Hitler, natif de l'Autriche a lui-même perdu la citoyenneté en 1925. Juste avant l'effondrement du IIIe Reich, Karl Renner, mettre en place un gouvernement provisoire à Vienne. Tout comme l'Allemagne, l'Autriche, elle aussi, été divisé en un britannique, le français, l'un soviétique et une zone américaine et qui sont régies par la Commission alliée de l'Autriche. [PARAGRAPH: 2] En mai 1955, l'Autriche a retrouvé l'indépendance et s'est déclaré perpétuellement neutre, dont il demeure aujourd'hui. Le système politique de la Deuxième République est venu à être caractérisée par le système de Proporz, ce qui signifie que la plupart des postes de certaines politiques importantes ont été répartis de manière égale entre les membres de la sociaux-démocrates et le Parti populaire. Aujourd'hui, l'Autriche a cinq grands partis: le SPO (Parti travailliste), le RPV (conservateurs), les Verts (écologistes) et FPÖ (nationalistes). L'Autriche est devenue membre de l'Union européenne en 1995, et a conservé sa neutralité constitutionnelle.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Österreich wurde zum ersten Mal die von verschiedenen keltischen Stämmen. Noricum, eines keltischen Königreiches, wurde behauptet durch das römische Reich und machte eine Provinz. Nach dem Fall des römischen Reiches, Österreich wurde erobert von Bayern, Slawen und Awaren. Wenn Charlemagne erobert das Land in 788, er ermutigt Kolonisation und Christentum. Österreich, jetzt Teil der östlichen Francia, wurde unter der Kontrolle des Hauses der Babenberger. In 976, in den Bereich bekannt als Marchia Orientalis wurde auf der Babenberger Leopold in der 976. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Die erste Erwähnung des Landes, bekannt als Österreich ist in 966, wenn sie auf dem Gebiet der Babenberger März. Die folgenden Jahrhunderte sind gekennzeichnet durch den frühen Siedlungen des Landes. In 1156, das Privilegium Minus erhöhten Österreich auf das Herzogtum Statuen. Die Babenberger gewann auch das Herzogtum Steiermark 1192. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Mit dem Tod Friedrichs II. in 1246, die Barenberg Zeile endete. Otakar II. von Böhmen wirksam kontrolliert die Herzogtümer Österreich. Nach seiner Niederlage und Durnkrut von Rudolf I. von Deutschland in 1278, seiner Herrschaft zu Ende. Die folgenden Jahrhunderte würde eine Zeit der österreichischen Wohlstand, unter den herrschenden Dynastie der Habsburger. In der vierzehnten und fünfzehnten Jahrhundert, die Habsburger kumulierten Provinzen in der Gegend des Herzogtums Österreich. In 1438, Herzog Albrecht V. von Österreich wurde als Nachfolger von seinem Schwiegervater, Kaiser Sigismund. Obwohl Albert entschieden, für die nur ein Jahr, von diesem Zeitpunkt an, alle Kaiser des Heiligen Römischen Reiches war ein Habsburger, mit einer Ausnahme. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Die Habsburger begann zu akkumulieren landet im Laufe der Jahre, und in 1477 die Erzherzog Maximilian erworben meisten der Niederen Länder nach der Heirat der Erbin von Burgund. Sein Sohn Philipp der Schöne heiratete die Erbin von Kastilien und Aragon, und der Übernahme von Spanien und seine italienische, afrikanische, und New World Hilfsmittel für die Habsburger. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Nach der Schlacht bei Mohacs, der österreichischen Herrscher ihre Territorien. Allerdings ist die Expansion des Osmanischen Reiches in Ungarn führte zu häufigen Konflikten zwischen den beiden Mächten. Die lange Herrschaft von Leopold I. endete der österreichischen Konflikt mit den Türken. Im Anschluss an die Verteidigung von Wien 1628, eine Reihe von Kampagnen in die Rückkehr der Ungarn in die österreichische Control im 1699. Aber, während der zweiten Hälfte der Regierungszeit von Kaiser Karl VI, Österreich verzichtet einige dieser Gewinne. Nach Ablauf dieser Zeit, im Alter von der österreichischen preußischen Dualismus begann in Ungarn. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Verschiedene Niederlagen gegen Napoleon schreibt das Ende des alten Heiligen Römischen Reiches 1806, und in 1804 der österreichischen Reiches gegründet. In 1867 wurde es in der doppelten - Monarchie Österreich - Ungarn. Im Anschluss an die Napoleonischen Kriege, Österreich als einer von Europa's beherrschenden Kräfte zusammen mit Preußen und Russland. In 1815, der deutsche Bund wurde unter dem Vorsitz von Österreich. Österreich und Preußen waren einer der beiden führenden Mächte. Nach Deutschland wollte sich ein einheitliches Land, in Österreich nicht bereit war, zum Teil von ihm und wuchs aus Deutschland, während sie in Preußen wuchs. Nach der Niederlage der Preußen in der Schlacht bei Koniggratz in Böhmen, Österreich verlassen mussten die Deutschen Bundes und wurde in der Folge nicht mehr gestattet, die Teilnahme an der deutschen Politik. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Die Österreichisch-Ungarische Ausgleich "von 1867, die eine doppelte Souveränität unter Franz Joseph I., regierte bis zu seinem Tod. Die Vielfalt des Reiches machte es schwer, in einem Zeitalter der neuen nationalistischen Bewegungen. Die Ermordung von Erzherzog Franz Ferdinand im 1914 war die wahrscheinliche Ursache des Ersten Weltkriegs, die den Untergang der österreichisch-ungarischen Reiches. [PARAGRAPH: 2] In 1918 und 1919, Österreich war bekannt als die der deutschen Republik Österreich. Die Monarchie war jedoch aufgelöst in 1919 und eine parlamentarische Demokratie, wurde im 1920. In 1922, Österreich wurde ein Darlehen zur Verbesserung der allgemeinen wirtschaftlichen Zustand. Mit der Gewährung des Darlehens, die aus Österreich ein unabhängiger Staat auf die Kontrolle durch die Liga der Nationen. Zu der Zeit, die wirkliche Herrscher von Österreich wurde die Liga, durch seine Kommissare in Wien. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Die Erste österreichische Republik dauerte bis 1933. Die beiden großen Parteien bekämpften sich innerhalb des Parlaments. Nach dem österreichischen Bürgerkrieg 1934, mehrere Mitglieder der Schutzbund Partei hingerichtet wurden und die Sozialdemokratische Partei wurde verboten. In 1936, die deutschen Truppen besetzten das Land und Hitler, der in Österreich selbst, verloren Staatsbürgerschaft in 1925. Kurz vor dem Zusammenbruch des Dritten Reiches, Karl Renner, eine provisorische Regierung in Wien. Ähnlich wie in Deutschland, Österreich, zu, wurde in eine britische, französische, sowjetische und eine amerikanische Zone und durch die Alliierten Kommission für Österreich. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Im Mai 1955, Österreich seine Unabhängigkeit und erklärte sich ständig neutrale, die sie noch heute. Das politische System der Zweiten Republik kam zu zeichnen sich durch das System der Proporz, was bedeutet, dass die meisten Beiträge einiger politischer Bedeutung waren geteilter gleichmäßig zwischen den Mitgliedern der Sozialdemokraten und der Volkspartei. Heute hat Österreich fünf großen Parteien: die SPO (Labour Party), die OVP (Konservativen), die Grünen (Umweltschützer), und FPO (Nationalisten). Österreich als Mitglied der Europäischen Union in 1995, und hat sich ihrem verfassungsmäßigen Neutralität.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB]L'Austria è stata risolta da varie tribù celtiche. Noricum, un regno celtica, è stato rivendicato da Romano e di fatto una provincia. Dopo la caduta del Romano Impero, l'Austria è stata invasa da bavaresi, slavi, e Avari. Quando Carlo Magno conquista della terra in 788, ha incoraggiato la colonizzazione e il cristianesimo. Austria, ora parte della Francia orientale, è stata sotto il controllo della casa di Babenberg. Nel 976, la zona nota come Marchia Orientalis è stato dato a Leopoldo di Babenberg nel 976. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Il primo record del terreno essendo noto come l'Austria è nel 966, quando fa riferimento al territorio della Babenberg marzo. Secoli successivi sono caratterizzati dai primi insediamenti del paese. Nel 1156, il Privilegium meno elevati per l'Austria il ducato statue. Il Babenbergs anche ottenuto il Ducato di Stiria nel 1192. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Con la morte di Federico II nel 1246, si è conclusa la Barenberg linea. Otakar II di Boemia efficacemente controllato la ducati d'Austria. Dopo la sua sconfitta e Durnkrut da Rudolf I della Germania nel 1278, il suo regno è venuto a scadenza. Secoli successivi sarebbe un tempo di prosperità austriaco, sotto la dinastia, gli Asburgo. Nel XIV e XV secolo, gli Asburgo province accumulato nella zona del Ducato d'Austria. Nel 1438, Albert V duca d'Austria è stato scelto come successore di suo suocero, l'imperatore Sigismondo. Sebbene Albert pronunciata solo per un anno, da quel momento in poi, ogni imperatore del Sacro Romano Impero era un Asburgo, con una sola eccezione. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Il Asburgo ha iniziato ad accumulare terre nel corso degli anni, e nel 1477 l'arciduca Massimiliano acquisito la maggior parte dei Paesi Bassi dopo aver sposato l'erede di Borgogna. Suo figlio Filippo il Bello sposò l'erede di Castiglia e di Aragona, e la Spagna e il suo acquisito italiana, africana, e del Nuovo Mondo adjuncts per gli Asburgo. [PARAGRAPH: 2] In seguito alla battaglia di Mohacs, austriaco governanti ampliato la loro territori. Tuttavia, l'espansione ottomana in Ungheria ha portato a frequenti conflitti tra le due potenze. Il lungo regno di Leopoldo I si è conclusa con l'Austria in conflitto con i Turchi. In seguito alla difesa di Vienna nel 1628, una serie di campagne hanno portato al ritorno di Ungheria per il controllo austriaco nel 1699. Tuttavia, durante l'ultima parte del regno di Carlo VI, l'Austria rinuncia alcuni di questi vantaggi. Trascorso tale termine, l'età del dualismo prussiano austriaca - ha iniziato in Ungheria. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Diversi sconfitte contro Napoleone, la fine del vecchio Sacro Romano Impero nel 1806, e nel 1804 l'impero austriaco è stata fondata. Nel 1867, è stato trasformato in duplice monarchia d'Austria - Ungheria. In seguito le guerre napoleoniche, l'Austria è emersa come una delle potenze dominanti insieme con la Prussia e la Russia. Nel 1815, la Confederazione tedesca è stata fondata, sotto la Presidenza austriaca. Austria e Prussia sono stati uno dei due principali poteri. Dopo la Germania ha voluto diventare un unico paese, l'Austria era disposta a far parte di essa e cresciuto fuori della Germania, mentre è cresciuta in Prussia. In seguito alla sconfitta della Prussia alla battaglia di Koniggratz in Boemia, l'Austria ha dovuto lasciare la Confederazione tedesca ed è stata successivamente non sono più autorizzati a prendere parte politica tedesca. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Il compromesso austro-ungarico del 1867 ha fornito una doppia sovranità sotto Francesco Giuseppe I, che regnò fino alla sua morte. La diversità degli impero reso difficile il controllo in un'epoca di movimenti nazionalisti emergenti. L'assassinio di arciduca Francesco Ferdinando nel 1914 è stata la probabile causa della prima guerra mondiale, che ha portato alle dimissioni della austro-ungarico. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Nel 1918 e 1919, l'Austria era conosciuta come la Repubblica di tedesco in Austria. La monarchia è stata, tuttavia, sciolto nel 1919 e di una democrazia parlamentare è stata istituita nel 1920. Nel 1922, in Austria è stato dato un prestito di migliorare la condizione economica generale. Con la concessione del prestito, l'Austria è passata da uno stato indipendente per il controllo esercitato dalla Lega delle Nazioni. Al momento, il vero sovrano d'Austria è diventata la Lega, attraverso il suo commissario a Vienna. [PARAGRAPH: 2] La Prima Repubblica austriaca è durato fino al 1933. I due principali partiti combattuto reciprocamente, entro il parlamento. Dopo la guerra civile austriaco nel 1934, diversi membri della Schutzbund partito sono stati eseguiti e il Partito socialdemocratico è stato bandito. Nel 1936, le truppe tedesche occupato il paese e di Hitler, un nativo d'Austria se stesso, ha perso la cittadinanza nel 1925. Poco prima del crollo del Terzo Reich, Karl Renner creazione di un governo provvisorio a Vienna. Tanto come la Germania, l'Austria, troppo, è stato diviso in inglese, francese, uno sovietico e uno americano Zona e disciplinato dalla Commissione alleata per l'Austria. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Nel maggio 1955, l'Austria riacquistato l'indipendenza e si è dichiarato neutrale permanente, che rimane oggi. Il sistema politico della seconda Repubblica è venuto a essere caratterizzata dal sistema di Proporz, il che significa che la maggior parte dei posti di qualche importanza politica sono stati divisi equamente tra i membri dei socialdemocratici e il Partito popolare. Oggi, l'Austria ha cinque grandi parti: la SPO (Partito laburista), il OVP (conservatori), i Verdi (ambientalisti), e FPO (nazionalisti). L'Austria è diventata membro dell'Unione europea nel 1995, e ha mantenuto la sua neutralità costituzionale.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB]Austria fue reiterada por varias tribus celtas. Noricum, un reino celta, que reivindicó el imperio romano e hizo una provincia. Después de la caída del Imperio Romano, Austria fue invadida por los bávaros, eslavos y avaros. Cuando Carlomagno conquistó la tierra en 788, alentó a la colonización y el cristianismo. Austria, que ahora forma parte del este de Francia, estaba bajo el control de la casa de Babenberg. En 976, la zona conocida como Marchia Orientalis fue dado a Leopoldo de Babenberg en 976. [PARAGRAPH: 2] El primer registro de la tierra que es conocido como Austria está en el 966 cuando se refiere al territorio de los Babenberg de marzo. Los siglos siguientes se caracterizan por los primeros asentamientos del país. En 1156, el Privilegium menos elevada de los ducados de Austria a las estatuas. El Babenbergs también obtuvo el Ducado de Estiria en 1192. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Con la muerte de Federico II en 1246, la Barenberg línea terminado. Otakar II de Bohemia efectivamente controlada la duchies de Austria. Después de su derrota y Durnkrut por Rudolf I de Alemania en 1278, su reinado llegó a su fin. Los siguientes siglos se marca una época de prosperidad de Austria, en virtud de la dinastía gobernante, los Habsburgo. En los siglos XIV y XV, los Habsburgo acumulado provincias en la zona del Ducado de Austria. En 1438, el duque Alberto V de Austria fue elegido como sucesor de su suegro, el emperador Segismundo. Aunque Albert gobernó durante sólo un año, a partir de ese momento, todos los emperadores del Sacro Imperio Romano era una Habsburg, con una excepción. [PARAGRAPH: 2] La Habsburgo empezó a acumular tierras a través de los años, y en 1477 el Archiduque Maximiliano adquirido la mayor parte de los Países Bajos después de su matrimonio con la heredera de Borgoña. Su hijo Felipe el Hermoso se casó con la heredera de Castilla y Aragón, y adquirió España y sus italiano, de África, del Nuevo Mundo y complementarios para los Habsburgo. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Después de la Batalla de Mohacs, gobernantes de Austria amplió sus territorios. Sin embargo, la expansión otomana en Hungría dado lugar a frecuentes conflictos entre los dos poderes. El largo reinado de Leopoldo I de Austria en la que terminó el conflicto con los turcos. A raíz de la defensa de Viena en 1628, una serie de campañas se tradujo en el regreso de Hungría para el Control de Austria en 1699. Sin embargo, durante la última parte del reinado del emperador Carlos VI, Austria entregado algunos de esos logros. Después de este tiempo, la edad de dualismo entre Austria y Prusia comenzaron en Hungría. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Diversas derrotas contra Napoleón significó el final del viejo Sacro Imperio Romano en 1806, y en 1804 el Imperio de Austria se fundó. En 1867, se convirtió en la doble monarquía de Austria - Hungría. Después de las guerras Napoleónicas, Austria surgido como una de las potencias dominantes junto con Prusia y Rusia. En 1815, la Confederación Alemana fue fundada bajo la presidencia de Austria. Austria y Prusia fueron una de las dos principales potencias. Después de Alemania desean pasar a ser un país unificado, Austria no estaba dispuesto a convertirse en parte de ella y creció fuera de Alemania, mientras que creció en Prusia. Después de la derrota de Prusia en la batalla de Koniggratz en Bohemia, Austria, tuvo que dejar la Confederación Alemana y posteriormente ya no pueden tomar parte en la política alemana. [PARAGRAPH: 2] La austrohúngara de transacción de 1867 proporcionó una doble soberanía en virtud de Francisco José I, que gobernó hasta su muerte. La diversidad del imperio hizo difícil de controlar en una era de los nuevos movimientos nacionalistas. El asesinato del Archiduque Francisco Fernando en 1914 fue la causa probable de la Primera Guerra Mundial, que llevó a la caída del Imperio Austrohúngaro. [PARAGRAPH: 2] En 1918 y 1919, Austria era conocido como la República de Austria alemana. La monarquía fue, sin embargo, disuelto en 1919 y de una democracia parlamentaria se estableció en 1920. En 1922, Austria se le dio un préstamo para mejorar la condición económica general. Con la concesión del préstamo, Austria pasó de un estado independiente para el control ejercido por la Sociedad de las Naciones. En el momento, el verdadero gobernante de Austria se convirtió en la Liga, a través de su comisionado en Viena. [PARAGRAPH: 2] La Primera República de Austria se prolongó hasta 1933. Los dos partidos principales se enfrentaron en otros en el Parlamento. Después de la Guerra Civil de Austria en 1934, varios miembros de la Schutzbund Partido fueron ejecutados y el Partido Social Demócrata fue prohibido. En 1936, las tropas alemanas ocuparon el país y Hitler, natural de Austria a sí mismo, pierde la ciudadanía en 1925. Justo antes de la caída del Tercer Reich, Karl Renner establecer un Gobierno Provisional en Viena. Mucho como Alemania, Austria, también se divide en un británico, el francés, el soviético y un American Zone y se rige por la Comisión Aliada para Austria. [PARAGRAPH: 2] En mayo de 1955, Austria recuperó su independencia y se declaró neutral permanente, que sigue siendo hoy. El sistema político de la Segunda República llegó a ser caracterizado por el sistema de Proporz, lo que significa que la mayoría de los puestos de algunos importancia política se dividieron por igual entre los miembros de los socialdemócratas y el Partido Popular. Hoy, Austria ha cinco grandes partes: el SPO (Partido Laborista), el OVP (Conservadores), los Verdes (ecologistas), y FPO (nacionalistas). Austria pasó a ser miembro de la Unión Europea en 1995, y ha mantenido su neutralidad constitucional.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>	