<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by lcollins (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- Copyright Firaxis Games 2005 -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text - New -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_HOCKEY_RINK</Tag>
		<English>Hockey Rink</English>
		<French>Patinoire de hockey</French>
		<German>Hockeyeisbahnen</German>
		<Italian>Rinks del hockey</Italian>
		<Spanish>Pista del hockey</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
        <TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_HOCKEY_RINK_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Ice hockey began in Canada, and today it attracts more players and spectators than any other sport.  Leagues are organized throughout the country.  Professional hockey draws thousands of spectators to large arenas and millions to watch their televisions.  Enthusiasm is high at the end of the season, when the two best teams of the National Hockey League, more commonly known as the NHL, emerge from a series of playoffs to compete for the Stanley Cup.  There are currently six Canadian teams in the NHL.  Ice hockey playing-areas are known as hockey rinks.</English>
		<French>[TAB]L'hockey de glace a commencé au Canada, et aujourd'hui il attire plus de joueurs et de spectateurs que n'importe quel autre sport.  Des ligues sont organisées dans tout le pays.  L'hockey professionnel dessine des milliers de spectateurs à de grandes arènes et à millions pour regarder leurs télévisions.  L'enthousiasme est haut à la fin de la saison, quand les deux meilleures équipes de la ligue nationale d'hockey, généralement connues sous le nom de NHL, émergent d'une série de finales pour concurrencer pour la tasse de Stanley.  Il y a actuellement six équipes canadiennes dans le NHL.  Des jouer-secteurs d'hockey de glace sont connus comme patinoires d'hockey.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Eis-Hockey fing in Kanada an, und heute zieht es mehr Spieler und Zuschauer als jeder möglicher andere Sport an.  Ligen werden in dem Land organisiert.  Professionelles Hockey zeichnet Tausenden Zuschauer zu den großen Arenas und zu den Millionen, um ihre fernzusehen.  Begeisterung ist am Ende der Jahreszeit hoch, wenn die zwei besten Mannschaften der nationalen Hockey-Liga, häufiger bekannt als das NHL, von einer Reihe Endspielen auftauchen, um für die Stanley Schale zu konkurrieren.  Es gibt z.Z. sechs kanadische Mannschaften im NHL.  Eis-Hockey Spielenbereiche bekannt als Hockeyeisbahnen.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB]Il hockey di ghiaccio ha cominciato nel Canada ed oggi attrae più giocatori e spectators che qualunque altro sport.  Le leghe sono organizzate durante il paese.  Il hockey professionale disegna i migliaia degli spectators alle grandi arene ed a milioni per guardare le loro televisioni.  L'entusiasmo è alto alla conclusione della stagione, quando le due squadre migliori della lega nazionale del Hockey, conosciute più conunemente come il NHL, emergono da una serie di spareggi per competere per la tazza dello Stanley.  Ci sono attualmente sei squadre canadesi nel NHL.  Le gioc-zone del hockey di ghiaccio sono conosciute come rinks del hockey.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB]El hockey sobre hielo comenzó en Canadá, y atrae hoy a más jugadores y espectadores que cualquier otro deporte.  Organizan a las ligas a través del país.  El hockey profesional dibuja a millares de espectadores a las arenas grandes y a millones para mirar sus televisiones.  El entusiasmo es alto en el final de la estación, cuando los dos mejores equipos de la liga nacional del hockey, conocidos más comunmente como el NHL, emergen de una serie de segundas fases para competir para la taza de Stanley.  Hay actualmente seis equipos canadienses en el NHL.  Las jugar-áreas del hockey sobre hielo se conocen como pistas del hockey.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
        <TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_HOCKEY_RINK_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Hockey Rink[COLOR_REVERT], the Canadian replacement for the [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Opera House[COLOR_REVERT], offers a free Celebrity in exchange for slight Maintenace and no Artist specialists.</English>
		<French>La [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]patinoire de hockey[COLOR_REVERT], le remplacement canadien de l'[COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]opéra[COLOR_REVERT], offre une célébrité gratuite en échange d'un coût d'entretien et à la place d'un spécialiste artiste.</French>
		<German>Die [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Hockeyeisbahnen[COLOR_REVERT], die Kanadisch Ersatz für die [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Opera House[COLOR_REVERT], offers a free Celebrity in exchange for slight Maintenace and no Artist specialists.</German>
		<Italian>L'[COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Rinks del hockey[COLOR_REVERT], la sostituzione Canadese per il [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Opera House[COLOR_REVERT], offers a free Celebrity in exchange for slight Maintenace and no Artist specialists.</Italian>
		<Spanish>El [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Pista del hockey[COLOR_REVERT], la sustitución de Canadiense para el [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Opera House[COLOR_REVERT], offers a free Celebrity in exchange for slight Maintenace and no Artist specialists.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>