<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by lcollins (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- Copyright Firaxis Games 2005 -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text - New -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_ATHLETICS_COMPLEX</Tag>
		<English>Athletics Complex</English>
		<French>Complexe athlétique</French>
		<German>Leichtathletik-Komplex</German>
		<Italian>Atletica Complex</Italian>
		<Spanish>Complejo de Atletismo</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
        <TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_ATHLETICS_COMPLEX_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Australians are enthusiastic about sports, both as the audience and players.  Australian Rules football, soccer, and rugby are the most popular spectator sports.  Cricket is a favorite summer pastime.  Tennis, lawn bowling, gold, and horse racings all have enthusiastic fans.  With the high amount of Australians living on the coast, swimming, sailing, and other water sports are highly popular.  The country has produced numerous world-class athletes, particularly in tennis, swimming, and track.</English>
		<French>[TAB]Les Australiens sont enthousiastes au sujet des sports, en tant que les assistances et joueurs.  L'Australien règne le football, le football, et le rugby sont les sports spectaculaires les plus populaires.  Le cricket est un passe-temps préféré d'été.  Le tennis, le bowling de pelouse, l'or, et les racings tous de cheval ont les ventilateurs enthousiastes.  Avec le montant élevé d'Australiens vivant sur la côte, les sports de l'eau de natation, de navigation, et autre sont fortement populaires.  Le pays a produit de nombreux athlètes de monde-classe, en particulier dans le tennis, la natation, et la voie.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Australier sind über Sport, als die Publikum und die Spieler enthusiastisch.  Australier ordnet Fußball, Fußball an, und Rugby ist der populärste Zuschauersport.  Kricket ist ein Lieblingssommerzeitvertreib.  Tennis, Rasenbowlingspiel, Gold und Pferd alle racings haben enthusiastische Ventilatoren.  Mit der hohen Menge der Australier, die auf der Küste leben, ist Schwimmen-, Segeln und andereswassersport in hohem Grade populär.  Das Land hat zahlreiche Weltkategorie Athleten, besonders im Tennis, in der Schwimmen und in der Schiene produziert.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB]Gli australiani sono entusiasti degli sport, sia come i pubblici che i giocatori.  L'australiano regola il gioco del calcio, calcio ed il rugby è gli sport spectator più popolari.  Il grillo è un pastime favorito di estate.  Il tennis, il bowling del prato, l'oro e i racings tutti del cavallo hanno ventilatori entusiastici.  Con la quantità elevata degli australiani che vivono sul litorale, sport dell'acqua di swimming, di navigazione ed altro sono altamente popolari.  Il paese ha prodotto gli atleti numerosi del mondo-codice categoria, specialmente nel tennis, nello swimming ed in pista.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB]Los australianos son entusiásticos sobre deportes, como las audiencias y los jugadores.  El australiano gobierna el balompié, fútbol, y el rugbi es los deportes espectadores más populares.  El grillo es un pasatiempo preferido del verano.  El tenis, el bowling del césped, el oro, y los racings todos del caballo tienen ventiladores entusiásticos.  Entre la alta cantidad de australianos que viven en la costa, los deportes del agua de la natación, de la navegación, y otro son altamente populares.  El país ha producido a atletas numerosos de la mundo-clase, particularmente en tenis, la natación, y la pista.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
        <TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_ATHLETICS_COMPLEX_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Athletics Complex[COLOR_REVERT], the Australian replacement for the [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Colosseum[COLOR_REVERT], never obsoletes.</English>
		<French>Le [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]complexe athlétique[COLOR_REVERT] remplace le [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]colisée[COLOR_REVERT] pour l'Australie. Il ne devient jamais obsolète.</French>
		<German>Die [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Leichtathletik-Komplex[COLOR_REVERT], die Australisch Ersatz für die [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Kolosseum[COLOR_REVERT], never obsoletes.</German>
		<Italian>L'[COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Atletica Complex[COLOR_REVERT], la sostituzione Australiano per il [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Colosseo[COLOR_REVERT], never obsoletes.</Italian>
		<Spanish>El [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Complejo de Atletismo[COLOR_REVERT], la sustitución de Australiano para el [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Coliseo[COLOR_REVERT], never obsoletes.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>