<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by lcollins (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- Copyright Firaxis Games 2005 -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text - New -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_RINGFORT</Tag>
		<English>Ringfort</English>
		<French>Ringfort</French>
		<German>Ringfort</German>
		<Italian>Ringfort</Italian>
		<Spanish>Ringfort</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
        <TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_RINGFORT_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Ringforts are fortified settlements that are generally agreed to be from the Early Medieval period in Northern Europe, especially Ireland.  A r&#225;th was made of earth and caiseal or cathair were made of stone.  A dun is a more prestigious site, the seat of a ruler.  Historical or archaeological record of the Early Medieval Period in Ireland doesn't come close to the ringfort.  Over 45,000 sites have been identified as ringforts throughout Ireland, but over 60,000 sites can be identified. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Ringforts are traditionally understood as being a dispersed farmstead, the home of a free man and his family.  This veiw has been altered, saying that not all ringforts are not farmsteads, but that they fill a variety of functions.  Other ringfort sites have provided evidence that ringforts played a significant role in the economy of Ireland.  Excavations have lead to the finding of pottery at ringfort sites suggesting that they may have been used as trading posts or other settlement functions.  Yet another theory is that the ringforts were used for defense both because of its name and archaeological evidence.  Ringforts may have been built to give protection to cattle-farming communities and guard their livestock.  The circular shape of the ringfort also shows its defensive advantages.  Explanations from the Early christian period support another idea: ringforts were built to signify nobility, kingship, and authority.  The more elaborate the ringfort, the higher the status of the occupant.  The promotion of one's status was the main purpose of construction of these ringforts.</English>
		<French>[TAB] Ringforts sont fortifiés qui sont généralement accepté d'être le début de la période médiévale dans le nord de l'Europe, en particulier en Irlande. Un ráth a été faite de terre et caiseal ou cathair sont en pierre. A plus dun est un site prestigieux, le siège d'un dirigeant. Historique ou archéologique analytique de la Petite Période Médiévale en Irlande est loin de la ringfort. Plus de 45000 sites ont été identifiés comme ringforts dans toute l'Irlande, mais plus de 60000 sites peuvent être identifiés. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Ringforts sont traditionnellement comprise comme étant un ferme dispersés, le honme d'un homme libre et sa famille. Cette veiw a été modifié, en disant que ce n'est pas tout ringforts ne sont pas fermes, mais qu'ils remplissent une série de fonctions. Autres ringfort sites ont apporté la preuve que ringforts joué un rôle important dans l'économie de l'Irlande. Les fouilles ont conduit à la découverte de la poterie à ringfort des sites suggérant qu'ils auraient été utilisés comme postes de règlement ou d'autres fonctions. Une autre théorie est que l'ringforts ont été utilisés pour la défense tant en raison de son nom et de témoins archéologiques. Ringforts peut avoir été construite pour protéger le bétail, les communautés agricoles et protège son bétail. La forme circulaire de la ringfort montre aussi ses avantages défensifs. Explications de la petite période de l'ère chrétienne soutien une autre idée: ringforts ont été construits pour signifier la noblesse, la royauté, et de l'autorité. Les plus élaborés la ringfort est élevé, plus le statut de l'occupant. La promotion de l'un de ces droits était l'objectif principal de la construction de ces ringforts.</French>
		<German>[TAB] Ringforts sind befestigte Siedlungen, die im Allgemeinen vereinbart, werden aus dem frühen Mittelalter Zeitraum, in Nordeuropa, vor allem in Irland. Ein ráth wurde aus der Erde und caiseal oder cathair waren aus Stein. Ein mahnen ist eine angesehene, der Sitz eines Herrschers. Historischen oder archäologischen Eintrag der Frühen Mittelalter in Irland nicht in die Nähe der ringfort. Mehr als 45000 Websites wurden als ringforts in ganz Irland, aber über 60000 Seiten ermittelt werden können. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Ringforts sind traditionell verstanden als eine verstreute Gehöft, die honme ein freier Mann und seiner Familie. Diese veiw verändert wurde, und sagte, dass nicht alle ringforts sind nicht Bauernhöfe, aber sie füllen eine Vielzahl von Funktionen. Andere ringfort Websites haben den Nachweis erbracht ringforts spielte eine wichtige Rolle in der Wirtschaft der Republik Irland. Ausgrabungen haben zu dem Ergebnis, der Töpferei auf ringfort Websites dass sie wurden als Handelspartner Stellen oder andere Siedlung. Doch eine andere Theorie ist, dass die ringforts wurden für die Verteidigung wegen seines Namens und archäologische Beweise. Ringforts Mai wurden gebaut, um den Schutz der Rinder - Landwirtschaft Gemeinden und bewachen ihr Vieh. Die runde Form des ringfort zeigt auch seine defensiven Vorteile. Erklärungen aus der frühen christlichen Zeit Unterstützung eine andere Idee: ringforts wurden gebaut, um zu verstehen, Adel, Königtum, und Autorität. Die weitere Ausarbeitung des ringfort, desto höher der Status der Insassen. Die Förderung von einem Status war das Hauptziel der Bau dieser ringforts.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB] Ringforts sono fortificati insediamenti, che sono generalmente accettato di essere anticipato dal periodo medievale nel Nord Europa, soprattutto in Irlanda. Un ráth è stato fatto della terra e del caiseal o cathair sono stati fatti di pietra. A dun tratta di un sito più prestigiosa, la sede di un righello. Storico o archeologico, di registrare i primi medievale Periodo in Irlanda non avvicinarsi alla ringfort. Oltre 45000 siti sono stati identificati come ringforts in tutta l'Irlanda, ma oltre 60000 siti possono essere identificati. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Ringforts sono tradizionalmente inteso come un disperso maso, il honme di un uomo libero e la sua famiglia. Questo veiw è stato modificato, dicendo che non tutti ringforts non sono masi, ma che possono riempire una varietà di funzioni. Altri ringfort siti hanno fornito prove del fatto che ringforts svolto un ruolo significativo per l'economia irlandese. Gli scavi hanno portato alla constatazione di ceramica a ringfort siti suggerendo che essi potrebbero essere stati utilizzati come posti di scambio o di altre funzioni di regolamento. Ma un'altra teoria è che il ringforts sono stati utilizzati per la difesa, sia a causa del suo nome e archeologico prove. Ringforts potrebbe essere stata costruita per dare protezione alle comunità agricole - bovini e custodire il loro bestiame. La forma circolare del ringfort mostra anche i suoi vantaggi difensiva. Spiegazioni dal Primo periodo cristiano sostegno un'altra idea: ringforts sono stati costruiti a significare nobiltà, regalità, e di autorità. Il più elaborato il ringfort, maggiore è lo stato dei occupante. La promozione di uno status è stato l'obiettivo principale di costruzione di questi ringforts.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB] Ringforts son asentamientos fortificados que se acordó en general que se de la Early Medieval período en el norte de Europa, especialmente Irlanda. A ráth se hizo de la tierra y caiseal o cathair estaban hechos de piedra. A dun de más es un lugar de prestigio, la sede de un gobernante. Histórico o arqueológico acta de la Early Medieval Período en Irlanda no se acerca a la ringfort. Más de 45000 sitios han sido identificados como ringforts en toda Irlanda, pero más de 60000 sitios pueden ser identificados. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Ringforts tradicionalmente entendida como la dispersión de una granja, la honme de un hombre libre y su familia. Este veiw ha sido alterado, diciendo que no todos los ringforts no son granjas, sino que cubrir una variedad de funciones. Otros ringfort sitios han proporcionado pruebas de que ringforts desempeñado un papel importante en la economía de Irlanda. Las excavaciones han llevado a la conclusión de la cerámica en ringfort sitios lo que hace pensar que pueden haber sido utilizados como puestos de comercio o de otras funciones de arreglo. Otra teoría es que la ringforts se utilizaron para la defensa tanto por su nombre y la evidencia arqueológica. Ringforts puede haber sido construido para dar protección a la cría de las comunidades agrícolas y la guardia de su ganado. La forma circular de la ringfort también muestra sus ventajas defensivas. Explicaciones de los primeros cristianos período de apoyo otra idea: ringforts fueron construidas para significar la nobleza, la monarquía, y de la autoridad. El más complicado en el ringfort, mayor es la situación de los ocupantes. La promoción de la condición es el objetivo principal de la construcción de estos ringforts.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
        <TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_RINGFORT_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Ringfort[COLOR_REVERT], the Irish replacement for the [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Castle[COLOR_REVERT], offers bonus defense.</English>
		<French>Le [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Ringfort[COLOR_REVERT], le remplacement de l'irlandais [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Chateaux[COLOR_REVERT], les offres de bonus defense.</French>
		<German>Die [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Ringfort[COLOR_REVERT], die Irische Ersatz für die [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Schloss[COLOR_REVERT], bietet bonus verteidigung.</German>
		<Italian>L'[COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Ringfort[COLOR_REVERT], la sostituzione irlandas per il [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Castello[COLOR_REVERT], offre bonus di difesa.</Italian>
		<Spanish> El [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Ringfort[COLOR_REVERT], la sustitución de irlandas para el [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Castillo[COLOR_REVERT], ofrece bono de la defensa. </Spanish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>