<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by lcollins (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- Copyright Firaxis Games 2005 -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text - New -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_SVIATOSLAV_I</Tag>
		<English>Sviatoslav I</English>
		<French>Sviatoslav Ier</French>
		<German>Swjatoslaw I.</German>
		<Italian>Sviatoslav I</Italian>
		<Spanish>Sviatoslav I</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_SVIATOSLAV_I_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Sviatoslav I[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Prince of Kiev[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived:[\BOLD] 942 - 972 AD [NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Little is known about the childhood of Sviatoslav, which he spent reigning in Novgorod.  His father, Igor, was killed by the Drevlians around 942 and his mother, Olga, ruled as regent in Kiev until Sviatoslav was able.  His mother converted to Christianity at the court of Byzantine Emperor Constantine Porphyrogenitus in 945, but Sviatoslav continued to worship the gods and goddesses of the Slavic pantheon.  He remained a stubborn pagan all of his life for he believed his warriors would ridicule him if he became a Christian.  The allegiance of his warriors was crucial in his later conquests. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Shortly after his accession to the throne, Sviatoslav began campaigning to expand the Kievan Rus's territory to the Pontic steppe region.  His greatest success was the conquest of Khazaria, which for centuries had been one of the strongest states of Eastern Europe.  Historians can infer that a dispute involving trade led to the initial rivalry between the two countries.  Sviatoslav then proceeded to gain the support of many of Khazaria's vassals.  Those not willing to help were forced to pay tribute.  Sviatoslav then continued to invade Volga Bulgaria and demand tribute from the population.  He employed mercenaries from both Khazaria and Bulgaria because of their superior cavalry.  He also sacked several of the Khazar cities, including the capital, Atil.  Sviatoslav's conquests of these areas now opened up new trade routes previously dominated by the Khazars. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Sviatoslav was later paid by the Byzantines to help them in their war against Bulgaria.  Sviatoslav defeated the Bulgarian ruler Boris II and proceeded to occupy the whole northern Bulgaria.  Sviatoslav moved the capital to a more strategic location, and invaded Bulgaria again in 969.  He devastated Thrace and massacred the city of Philippopolis's inhabitants.  A new Byzantine emperor, John Tzimiskes, later attempted to persuade Sviatoslav into leaving Bulgaria, but failed.  Sviatoslav responded by laying siege to Adrianople, causing panic in Constantinople.  Sviatoslav was met by the Byzantine army at the Battle of Arcadiopolis and lost.  The Byzantine emperor then proceeded to liberate the Balkans from Sviatoslav, causing Sviatoslav to retreat to Dorostol.  The Byzantine armies continued to besiege Dorostol, causing Sviatoslav to come to terms with John and abandon the Balkans.  Fearing that the peace with Sviatoslav would not last, the Byzantine emperor persuaded the Pecheneg Khan Kurya to kill Sviatoslav before he reached Kiev.  </English>
		<French>[H1]Sviatoslav I[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Prince de Ky&#239;v[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Dates :[\BOLD] 942 - 972 ap. J.C.[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Biographie :[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]On sait peu de choses sur l'enfance de Sviatoslav, qui a passé règne dans Novgorod. Son père, Igor, a été tué par les Drevlians autour de 942 et de sa mère, Olga, régna en tant que régente de Kiev jusqu'à ce que Sviatoslav a pu. Sa mère convertie au christianisme à la cour de l'empereur byzantin Constantin Porphyrogenitus en 945, mais Sviatoslav continue d'adorer les dieux et déesses du panthéon slave. Il restait un têtu païen toute sa vie pour qu'il croyait ses guerriers lui serait ridicule si il est devenu chrétien. L'allégeance de ses guerriers était cruciale dans ses dernières conquêtes. [PARAGRAPH 1] Peu de temps après son accession au trône, Sviatoslav campagne a commencé d'étendre le Kievan Rus du territoire à la région des steppes pontiques. Son plus grand succès fut la conquête de Khazaria, qui avait été pendant des siècles l'une des plus fortes d'Europe de l'Est. Les historiens peuvent déduire qu'un litige portant sur le commerce a abouti à la première rivalité entre les deux pays. Sviatoslav procède ensuite à gagner l'appui de nombre de ses vassaux Khazaria. Ceux qui ne sont pas disposés à les aider ont été contraints de rendre hommage. Sviatoslav ensuite continué à envahir Volga Bulgarie et de la demande hommage de la population. Il a employé des mercenaires à la fois Khazaria et de la Bulgarie en raison de leur supériorité cavalerie. Il a également limogé plusieurs des Khazar villes, dont la capitale, Atil. Sviatoslav's conquêtes de ces domaines désormais ouvert de nouvelles routes commerciales auparavant dominé par les Khazars. [PARAGRAPH 1] Sviatoslav a par la suite été payés par les Byzantins pour les aider dans leur guerre contre la Bulgarie. Sviatoslav vaincu le dirigeant bulgare Boris II, et a procédé à occuper l'ensemble du nord de la Bulgarie. Sviatoslav transfert de la capitale à une approche plus stratégique de l'emplacement, et envahi de nouveau en Bulgarie 969. Il a dévasté la Thrace et massacrés, la ville de Philippopolis habitants. Un nouvel empereur byzantin, John Tzimiskes, par la suite tenté de persuader Sviatoslav en quittant la Bulgarie, mais a échoué. Sviatoslav a relevé le défi en assiégeant Andrinople, provoquant la panique dans Constantinople. Sviatoslav a été satisfaite par l'armée byzantine à la bataille de Arcadiopolis et perdues. L'empereur byzantin a ensuite procédé à libérer les Balkans de Sviatoslav, causant Sviatoslav se replier en Dorostol. Les armées byzantines continue à assiéger Dorostol, causant Sviatoslav pour venir à bout de John et d'abandonner les Balkans. Craignant que la paix avec Sviatoslav ne durerait pas, l'empereur byzantin persuadé les Pecheneg Khan Sviatoslav Kurya à tuer avant d'avoir atteint Kiev.</French>
		<German>[H1]Swjatoslaw I.[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Prinz von Kiew[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lebte:[\BOLD] 942 - 972 n. Chr. [NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Hintergrund:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Wenig ist bekannt über die Kindheit von Swjatoslaw, der amtierende verbrachte er in Nowgorod. Sein Vater, Igor, wurde getötet, von der Drevlians rund 942 und seine Mutter, Olga, entschieden als Regentin in Kiew, bis Swjatoslaw konnte. Seine Mutter zum Christentum konvertierte am Hof des byzantinischen Kaisers Konstantin Porphyrogennetos und 945, aber Swjatoslaw weiterhin die Anbetung der Götter und Göttinnen der slawischen Pantheon. Er blieb stur alle heidnischen seines Lebens, denn er glaubte, seine Kämpfer würden Spott ihn, ob er ein Christ. Die Treue seiner Krieger war entscheidend in seinen späteren Eroberungen. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Kurz nach seinem Beitritt auf den Thron, Sviatoslav begann Kampagnen zur Erweiterung der Kiewer Rus im Hoheitsgebiet der pontischen Steppe Region. Sein größter Erfolg war die Eroberung der Khazaria, die seit Jahrhunderten galt als einer der stärksten Staaten in Mittel-und Osteuropa. Historiker können folgern, dass eine Auseinandersetzung mit Handel führte zu der ursprünglichen Rivalität zwischen den beiden Ländern. Swjatoslaw dann weiter auf die Unterstützung von vielen Khazaria's Vasallen. Wer nicht bereit zu helfen, wurden gezwungen, Tribut zollen. Swjatoslaw dann weiter erobern Wolga Bulgarien und Nachfrage Tribut aus der Bevölkerung. Er beschäftigte Söldner aus beiden Khazaria und Bulgarien wegen ihrer überlegenen Kavallerie. Er entließ auch mehrere der Khazar Städte, einschließlich der Hauptstadt Atil. Swjatoslaw's Eroberungen diesen Bereichen jetzt eröffnet neue Handelswege bisher dominiert von den Chasaren. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Swjatoslaw wurde später von den Byzantinern, um ihnen zu helfen in ihrem Krieg gegen Bulgarien. Swjatoslaw besiegte der bulgarischen Herrschers Boris II und verlief für die Sperrung der gesamten nördlichen Bulgarien. Swjatoslaw zog der Hauptstadt zu einer strategischen Lage, Bulgarien erobert und wieder in 969. Er verwüstete Thrakien und massakrierten die Stadt Philippopolis der Einwohner. Eine neue byzantinischen Kaisers Johannes Tzimiskes, später versucht, um Swjatoslaw in Bulgarien verlassen, aber scheiterte. Swjatoslaw reagierten mit Belagerung von Adrianopel, verursacht Panik in Konstantinopel. Swjatoslaw wurde von der byzantinischen Armee in der Schlacht von Arcadiopolis und verloren. Der byzantinische Kaiser dann weiter zur Befreiung des Balkans von Swjatoslaw, was Swjatoslaw zum Rückzug zu Dorostol. Die byzantinischen Armeen weiterhin belagern Dorostol, was Swjatoslaw zu kommen, um mit John aufzugeben und auf dem Balkan. Aus Angst vor, dass der Frieden mit Sviatoslav würde nicht zuletzt, die byzantinische Kaiser überredete die Pecheneg Khan Kurya Swjatoslaw zu töten, bevor er erreicht Kiew.</German>
		<Italian>[H1]Sviatoslav I[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Principe di Kiev[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Vita:[\BOLD] 942 - 972 d.C. [NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Informazioni:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Poco si sa circa l'infanzia di Sviatoslav, che ha trascorso regna in Novgorod. Suo padre, Igor, è stato ucciso dalla Drevlians circa 942 e sua madre, Olga, ha stabilito come reggente fino a Kiev Sviatoslav è stato in grado. Sua madre convertito al cristianesimo presso il tribunale di imperatore bizantino Costantino Porfirogenito e 945, ma Sviatoslav continuato ad adorare gli dei e le dee del pantheon slavo. Egli rimase un testardo pagana tutta la sua vita per i suoi guerrieri credeva lui sarebbe ridicolo se egli divenne un cristiano. La fedeltà dei suoi guerrieri è stata fondamentale nella sua successiva conquiste. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Poco dopo la sua ascesa al trono, Sviatoslav ha iniziato una campagna per espandere la Rus di Kiev territorio per la regione del Ponto steppa. Il suo più grande successo è stata la conquista della Khazaria, che per secoli era stato uno dei più forti stati dell'Europa orientale. Storici può dedurre che una controversia oggetto di scambi commerciali ha portato alla iniziale rivalità tra i due paesi. Sviatoslav quindi proceduto per ottenere il sostegno di molti dei vassalli della Khazaria. Coloro non disposti ad aiutare sono stati costretti a rendere omaggio. Sviatoslav poi continuato a invadere Volga Bulgaria e la domanda di omaggio da parte della popolazione. Ha impiegato da entrambi i mercenari Khazaria e la Bulgaria a causa della loro superiore cavalleria. Egli ha anche licenziato molti dei Khazar città, compresa la capitale, Atil. Sviatoslav's conquiste di questi settori adesso aperto nuove rotte commerciali precedentemente dominato da i Khazari. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Sviatoslav è stato poi pagato dai Bizantini per aiutarli nella loro guerra contro la Bulgaria. Sviatoslav sconfitto il principe bulgaro Boris II e ha proceduto ad occupare tutto il nord della Bulgaria. Sviatoslav trasferì la capitale a una posizione più strategica, e di nuovo invaso la Bulgaria e 969. Tracia e ha devastato la città di massacrati Philippopolis's abitanti. Un nuovo imperatore bizantino, Giovanni Tzimiskes, poi ha tentato di persuadere Sviatoslav lasciando in Bulgaria, ma non è riuscito. Sviatoslav risposto posa assedio di Adrianopoli, provocando il panico e Costantinopoli. Sviatoslav fu conosciuto dai esercito bizantino nella battaglia di Arcadiopolis e perso. L'imperatore bizantino quindi proceduto a liberare i Balcani da Sviatoslav, causando Sviatoslav a ritirarsi a Dorostol. L'esercito bizantino ha continuato a assediare Dorostol, causando Sviatoslav a venire a patti con John e abbandonare i Balcani. Temendo che la pace con Sviatoslav non ultimo, l'imperatore bizantino persuaso il Pecheneg Khan Kurya di uccidere prima di Sviatoslav di Kiev ha raggiunto.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[H1]Sviatoslav I[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Principe de K&#237;ev[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Vivi&#243;:[\BOLD] 942 - 972 d. C. [NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Historia:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Poco se sabe acerca de la infancia de Sviatoslav, que pasó reinante en Novgorod. Su padre, Igor, fue asesinado por la Drevlians alrededor de 942 y su madre, Olga, gobernó como regente hasta Sviatoslav de Kiev pudo. Su madre se convirtió al cristianismo en la corte del emperador bizantino Constantino Porphyrogenitus en 945, pero siguió Sviatoslav culto a los dioses y diosas del panteón eslavas. Él sigue siendo un terco pagano toda su vida para que sus guerreros se cree burla de él si se convirtió en un cristiano. La lealtad de sus guerreros fue fundamental en su posterior conquista. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Poco después de su acceso al trono, Sviatoslav comenzó una campaña para ampliar la Rus de Kiev el territorio de la estepa Pontic región. Su mayor éxito fue la conquista de Khazaria, que durante siglos ha sido uno de los estados más fuertes de Europa oriental. Los historiadores puede deducir que una controversia relacionada con el comercio llevado a la inicial de la rivalidad entre los dos países. Sviatoslav procedió luego a obtener el apoyo de muchos de Khazaria de vasallos. Los que no se vieron obligados a ayudar a pagar tributo. Sviatoslav luego siguió invadir Volga Bulgaria homenaje y la demanda de la población. Él mercenarios empleados de ambas Khazaria y Bulgaria, debido a su superior caballería. También saquearon varios de los Khazar ciudades, incluida la capital, Atil. Sviatoslav la conquista de estas zonas ahora abierto nuevas rutas comerciales anteriormente dominada por el Khazars. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Sviatoslav más tarde fue pagado por los bizantinos para ayudarlos en su guerra contra Bulgaria. Sviatoslav derrotó al búlgaro Boris gobernante II y procedió a ocupar todo el norte de Bulgaria. Sviatoslav trasladó la capital a un lugar más estratégico, y Bulgaria invadido de nuevo en 969. Él devastó Tracia y masacraron a la ciudad de Philippopolis habitantes. Un nuevo emperador bizantino, Juan Tzimiskes, más tarde trató de persuadir para que abandonen Sviatoslav Bulgaria, pero no. Sviatoslav respondió asediando Adrianople, causando pánico en Constantinopla. Sviatoslav fue recibida por el ejército bizantino en la batalla de Arcadiopolis y perdió. El emperador bizantino procedió entonces a liberar a los Balcanes de Sviatoslav, causando Sviatoslav a retirarse a Dorostol. Los ejércitos bizantinos continuó asediando Dorostol, causando Sviatoslav para llegar a un acuerdo con John y abandonar los Balcanes. Temiendo que la paz con Sviatoslav no duraría, la persuadió al emperador bizantino Pecheneg Khan Kurya para matar Sviatoslav antes de que él llegó a Kiev.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_SVIATOSLAV_I_1</Tag>
		<English>Greetings, [CT_NAME].  May you be warned: do not mess with me, for he who licks knives will soon cut his tongue.</English>
		<French>Greetings, [CT_NAME]. Puissiez-vous être mis en garde: ne plaisante pas avec moi, car celui qui se lèche les couteaux vont bientôt couper sa langue.</French>
		<German>Greetings, [CT_NAME]. Mögen Sie gewarnt: nicht mit mir, denn er leckt, die Messer geschnitten wird in Kürze seine Zunge.</German>
		<Italian>Greetings, [CT_NAME]. Possa tu stai in guardia: non pasticciare con me, per lui che lecca coltelli presto tagliata la lingua.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Greetings, [CT_NAME]. Que tenga mucho cuidado: ¡no juegues con mi, para el que se lame cuchillos pronto cortar su lengua.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>