<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by lcollins (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- Copyright Firaxis Games 2005 -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text - New -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_ZIEBEL</Tag>
		<English>Ziebel</English>
		<French>Ziebel</French>
		<German>Ziebel</German>
		<Italian>Ziebel</Italian>
		<Spanish>Ziebel</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_ZIEBEL_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Ziebel[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Khagan Bek of Khazaria[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Ruled:[\BOLD] 618 - 639 AD[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]In the seventh century, the world was ruled by three empires, the Byzantines, the Persians, and the Western Turks.  The Persians and Byzantines had been raging war for years, in a neverending cycle of the Byzantines ending with the look of defeat on their faces.  But Persia was soon to reach its doom, Khazaria.  The Roman emporor Heraclius made an alliance with the Khazars, of which several others follow, in order to finally defeat the Persians, as the Khazars had a powerful army.  The Khazars provided Heraclius with 40,000 men under the Khagan Bek Ziebel. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Ziebel participated in the advance to Persia, but then returned to lay siege on Tiflis, because he was presumably annoyed with Greek strategy.  But, this siege was unsuccessful, and he once again allied himself with Heraclius.  The Khazars under Ziebel broke throught the Caspian Gates and into Persia, and returned rich with plunder.  According to the description of Theophanes, Ziebel returned with "plate and ornaments, the gold, the gems, and the silk, which had been used at the Imperial table, and, with his own hand, distributed rich jewels and earrings to his new allies."  The Khagan of Khazaria then arrived, and Ziebel and his troops all bowed down to the Khagan, and all advanced through Persia.  But as any empire rises to glory, it falls.  After Ziebel, the Khazar Empire fell, and was never in as much glory as it had been under Khagan Bek Ziebel.  </English>
		<French>[H1]Ziebel[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Khagan Bek de Khazaria[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Régné[\BOLD] 618  - 639[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Fond:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Au septième siècle, le monde a été régné par trois empires, le Byzantines, les Persans, et les Turcs occidentaux. Les Persans et le Byzantines avaient été guerre faisante rage pendant des années, dans un cycle interminable de la fin de Byzantines avec le regard de la défaite sur leurs visages. Mais Perse était bientôt d'atteindre son sort malheureux, Khazaria. L'emporor romain Heraclius a fait une alliance avec le Khazars, dont plusieurs d'autres suivent, afin de défaire finalement les Persans, car le Khazars a eu une armée puissante. Le Khazars a fourni à Heraclius 40.000 hommes sous le Khagan Bek Ziebel. Ziebel a participé à l'avance à Perse, mais est puis revenu au siège étendu sur Tiflis, parce qu'il a été vraisemblablement gêné avec la stratégie grecque. Mais, ce siège était non réussi, et il s'est allié de nouveau avec Heraclius. Le Khazars sous Ziebel a cassé le throught les portes caspiennes et en Perse, et est retourné des riches avec le pillage. Selon la description de Theophanes, Ziebel est retourné avec le « plat et les ornements, l'or, les gemmes, et la soie, qui avait été utilisée à la table impériale, et, avec sa propre main, les bijoux et les boucles d'oreille riches distribués à ses nouveaux alliés, ». Le Khagan de Khazaria est alors arrivé, et Ziebel et sien s'assemble tout prosterné devant le Khagan, et tous avancés par Perse. Mais pendant que n'importe quel empire se lève à la gloire, elle tombe. Après Ziebel, l'empire de Khazar est tombé, et n'était jamais dans autant gloire qu'il avait été sous Khagan Bek Ziebel.</French>
		<German>[H1]Ziebel[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Khagan Bek von Khazaria[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Angeordnet:[\BOLD] 618  - 639[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Hintergrund:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]In the seventh century, the world was ruled by three empires, the Byzantines, the Persians, and the Western Turks.  The Persians and Byzantines had been raging war for years, in a neverending cycle of the Byzantines ending with the look of defeat on their faces.  But Persia was soon to reach its doom, Khazaria.  The Roman emporor Heraclius made an alliance with the Khazars, of which several others follow, in order to finally defeat the Persians, as the Khazars had a powerful army.  The Khazars provided Heraclius with 40,000 men under the Khagan Bek Ziebel.  Ziebel participated in the advance to Persia, but then returned to lay siege on Tiflis, because he was presumably annoyed with Greek strategy.  But, this siege was unsuccessful, and he once again allied himself with Heraclius.  The Khazars under Ziebel broke throught the Caspian Gates and into Persia, and returned rich with plunder.  According to the description of Theophanes, Ziebel returned with "plate and ornaments, the gold, the gems, and the silk, which had been used at the Imperial table, and, with his own hand, distributed rich jewels and earrings to his new allies."  The Khagan of Khazaria then arrived, and Ziebel and his troops all bowed down to the Khagan, and all advanced through Persia.  But as any empire rises to glory, it falls.  After Ziebel, the Khazar Empire fell, and was never in as much glory as it had been under Khagan Bek Ziebel.</German>
		<Italian>[H1]Ziebel[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Khagan Bek di Khazaria[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]regolato:[\BOLD] 618  - 639[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Priorità bassa:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Nel settimo secolo, il mondo è stato regolato da tre imperi, dal Byzantines, dai persiani e dai Turchi occidentali. I persiani e il Byzantines erano stati guerra infuriantesi per gli anni, in un ciclo senza fine della conclusione di Byzantines con lo sguardo della sconfitta con loro facce. Ma la Persia era presto di raggiungere la relativa sorte avversa, Khazaria. Il emporor romano Heraclius ha fatto un'alleanza con il Khazars, di cui vari altri seguono, per infine sconfiggere i persiani, poichè il Khazars ha avuto un esercito potente. Il Khazars ha fornito Heraclius 40.000 uomini sotto il Khagan Bek Ziebel. Ziebel ha partecipato all'avanzamento alla Persia, ma allora ha rinviato al siege posto su Tiflis, perché presumibilmente è stato infastidito con strategia greca. Ma, questo siege era infruttuoso ed ancora una volta si è alleato con Heraclius. Il Khazars sotto Ziebel ha rotto il throught i cancelli caspici e nella Persia ed ha restituito i rich con plunder. Secondo la descrizione di Theophanes, Ziebel ha rinviato con “la piastra ed ornamenti, l'oro, le gemme e la seta, che era stata utilizzata alla tabella imperiale e, con la sua propria mano, gioielli ed earrings ricchi distribuiti ai suoi nuovi alleati,„. Il Khagan di Khazaria allora è arrivato e Ziebel e suo si aduna interamente piegato giù al Khagan ed a tutto avanzato attraverso la Persia. Ma mentre tutto l'impero aumenta a glory, cade. Dopo Ziebel, l'impero di Khazar è caduto e non era mai in tan glory come era stato sotto Khagan Bek Ziebel.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[H1]Ziebel[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Khagan Bek de Khazaria[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Gobernado:[\BOLD] 618  - 639[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Trasfondo:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]In the seventh century, the world was ruled by three empires, the Byzantines, the Persians, and the Western Turks.  The Persians and Byzantines had been raging war for years, in a neverending cycle of the Byzantines ending with the look of defeat on their faces.  But Persia was soon to reach its doom, Khazaria.  The Roman emporor Heraclius made an alliance with the Khazars, of which several others follow, in order to finally defeat the Persians, as the Khazars had a powerful army.  The Khazars provided Heraclius with 40,000 men under the Khagan Bek Ziebel. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Ziebel participated in the advance to Persia, but then returned to lay siege on Tiflis, because he was presumably annoyed with Greek strategy.  But, this siege was unsuccessful, and he once again allied himself with Heraclius.  The Khazars under Ziebel broke throught the Caspian Gates and into Persia, and returned rich with plunder.  According to the description of Theophanes, Ziebel returned with "plate and ornaments, the gold, the gems, and the silk, which had been used at the Imperial table, and, with his own hand, distributed rich jewels and earrings to his new allies."  The Khagan of Khazaria then arrived, and Ziebel and his troops all bowed down to the Khagan, and all advanced through Persia.  But as any empire rises to glory, it falls.  After Ziebel, the Khazar Empire fell, and was never in as much glory as it had been under Khagan Bek Ziebel.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_ZIEBEL_1</Tag>
		<English>Greetings, [CT_NAME]. Intelligent people know of what they speak; fools speak of what they know.</English>
		<French>Salutations, [CT_NAME]. Les gens intelligents savent de quoi ils parlent; les imbéciles parlent de ce qu'ils savent.</French>
		<German>Greetings, [CT_NAME]. Intelligente Menschen wissen, was sie sprechen; Narren sprechen von dem, was sie wissen.</German>
		<Italian>Saluti, [CT_NAME]. Persone intelligenti sanno di cosa parlano; stolti parlare di quello che già sanno.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Saludos, [CT_NAME]. La gente inteligente sabe de lo que habla; tontos hablan de lo que saben.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>