<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by lcollins (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- Copyright Firaxis Games 2005 -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text - New -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_KURGAN</Tag>
		<English>Kurgan</English>
		<French>Kourgane</French>
		<German>Kurgan</German>
		<Italian>Kurgan</Italian>
		<Spanish>Kurgan</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
        <TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_KURGAN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]A Kurgan is the Turkish word for burial mound or tumulus.  The word Kurgan is used to describe a burial mound used in the Bronze-Middle ages in Russia, in some parts of Europe.  Kurgans were used mostly throughout central Asia and Russia, around where the Khazar Empire thrived.</English>
		<French>[TAB]Un Kurgan est le mot turc pour le monticule ou le tumulus d'enterrement. Le mot Kurgan est employé pour décrire un monticule d'enterrement utilisé dans les âges Bronze-Moyens en Russie, dans quelques parties de l'Europe. Kurgans ont été employés la plupart du temps dans l'ensemble de l'Asie centrale et de la Russie, autour d'où l'empire de Khazar a prospéré.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Ein Kurgan ist das türkische Wort für Grabhügel oder tumulus. Das Wort Kurgan wird verwendet, um einen Grabhügel zu beschreiben, der im Bronze-Mittleren Alter in Rußland, in einigen Teilen von Europa benutzt wird. Kurgans wurden meistens in zentralem Asien und Rußland, verwendet um, dem das Khazar Reich vorwärtskam.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB]Un Kurgan è la parola turca per il monticello di sepoltura o il tumulus. La parola Kurgan è usata per descrivere un monticello di sepoltura usato nelle età Bronzo-Centrali in Russia, in alcune parti di Europa. Kurgans è stato usato principalmente durante l'Asia centrale e la Russia, intorno a dove l'impero di Khazar ha prosperato.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB]Un Kurgan es la palabra turca para el montón de entierro o el tumulus. La palabra Kurgan se utiliza para describir un montón de entierro usado en las edades Bronce-Medias en Rusia, en algunas partes de Europa. Kurgans fue utilizado sobre todo a través de Asia central y de Rusia, alrededor de donde prosperó el imperio de Khazar.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
        <TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_KURGAN_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Kurgan[COLOR_REVERT], the Khazar replacement for the [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Monument[COLOR_REVERT], offers reduced War Weariness.</English>
		<French>Les [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]monuments[COLOR_REVERT] fournissent une petite quantit&#233; de culture, et sont utiles pour agrandir vos fronti&#232;res culturelles au d&#233;but du jeu.</French>
		<German>[COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Monumente[COLOR_REVERT] erh&#246;hen den kulturellen Wert einer Stadt und erm&#246;glichen die fr&#252;hzeitige Ausdehnung der Stadtgrenzen. </German>
		<Italian>I [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]monumenti[COLOR_REVERT] forniscono una piccola quantit&#224; di cultura e servono a espandere velocemente i confini della citt&#224; nelle fasi iniziali della partita. </Italian>
		<Spanish>Los [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Monumentos[COLOR_REVERT] proporcionan una peque&#241;a cantidad de cultura y son una buena manera de ampliar las fronteras de una ciudad en los primeros tiempos. </Spanish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>