<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by lcollins (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- Copyright Firaxis Games 2005 -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text - New -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
        <TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_FIANNA</Tag>
		<English>Fianna</English>
		<French>Fianna</French>
		<German>Fianna</German>
		<Italian>Fianna</Italian>
		<Spanish>Fianna</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_FIANNA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB] In early Ireland, fianna were small, semi-independent warrior bands who lived in the forests as mercenaries, bandits, and hunters.  They lived seperate from the rest of society and could be called by kings in times of war.  They appear in Irish mythology, most notably in the stories of the Fenian Cycle.  In these stories, the fianna are lead by Fionn mac Cumhail.  The name Fianna &#201;ireann has been used in a number of Irish Republican scouting organizations.  The historical institution of the fian is known from references in early medieval Irish law tracts.  A fian was made up of landless young men, often aristocrats, who hadn't yet come into inheritance of their land.  In the winter, fianna were quartered and fed by the nobility, during which they would keep order on their behalf.  During the summer, they had to live by hunting or selling pelts. [PARAGRAPH: 1]In the stories of the Fenian Cycle, the fianna are depicted as a single standing army in the service of the high sing.  It contained two rival factions, the Clan Ba&#237;scne of Leinster and the Clan Morna of Conacht.  Membership to the fianna was subject to rigorous texts.  For example, the applicant would stand waste deep in a hole armed with a shield while nine warriors threw spears at him.  If wounded, the applicant would fail.  In another text, his hair would be braided and he would be pursued through the forest and would fail if caught.  He would also fail if a branch cracked under his feet, or if the braids in his hair were disturbed.  He would have to be able to leap over a branch the height of his forehead, pass under one as low as his knee, and pull a thorn from his foot without slowing down. He also needed to be a skilled poet.</English>
		<French>[TAB] Au début de l'Irlande, fianna étaient petites, semi indépendant guerrier bandes qui vivent dans les forêts comme des mercenaires, des bandits, et de faim. Ils vivaient séparés du reste de la société et pourraient être appelés par les rois en temps de guerre. Elles apparaissent dans la mythologie irlandaise, et plus particulièrement dans les récits du Cycle Fenian. Dans ces histoires, la fianna sont dirigés par Finn Mac Cumaill. Fianna Éireann le nom a été utilisé dans un certain nombre d'organisations de scoutisme républicaine irlandaise. L'institution historique de la fian est connu au début de références médiévales droit irlandais des tracts. Un fian était composée de jeunes hommes sans terre, souvent aristocrates, qui n'avaient pas encore entré en héritage de leurs terres. En hiver, fianna étaient cantonnés et nourris par e enobility, au cours de laquelle ils maintien de l'ordre en leur nom. Pendant l'été, ils ont dû vivre de la chasse ou de la vente de peaux. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Dans les récits de la Fenian Cycle, le fianna sont dépeints comme une seule armée permanente au service de la haute chanter. Il contenait deux factions rivales, le Clan Baíscne de Leinster et le Clan Morna de Conacht. L'adhésion à la fianna était soumis à la rigueur des textes. Par exemple, la requérante se tiendrait déchets profondeur, dans un trou armé d'un bouclier tandis que neuf guerriers jeté lances à lui. Si blessés, le demandeur serait vouée à l'échec. Dans un autre texte, ses cheveux seraient tressés et il sera poursuivi à travers la forêt et serait vouée à l'échec si capturés. Il souhaiterait également échouer si une branche craqué sous ses pieds, ou si les tresses dans ses cheveux ont été perturbés. Il devrait être en mesure de sauter sur une branche de la hauteur de son front, passe sous un aussi faible que son genou, et tirer une épine de son pied sans ralentir. Il a également besoin d'être un habile poète.</French>
		<German>[TAB] In den frühen Irland, fianna noch klein waren, teilweise unabhängigen Krieger Bands lebte in den Wäldern als Söldner, Banditen und Hunger. Sie lebten getrennt von der übrigen Gesellschaft und könnte durch Könige in Zeiten des Krieges. Sie erscheinen in der irischen Mythologie, vor allem in den Geschichten der Fenian Cycle. In diesen Geschichten, die fianna werden von Fionn Mac Cumhail. Der Name Fianna Éireann wurde in einer Reihe von Irish Republican Pfadfinderbewegung Organisationen. Die historische Einrichtung der fian ist bekannt aus Referenzen in der frühen mittelalterlichen irischen Rechts Schriften. Ein fian wurde von landlosen junge Männer, die oft Aristokraten, die noch nicht in Berührung kommen, Vererbung von ihrem Land. Im Winter, fianna wurden Vierteilung und gefüttert von Th enobility, in denen sie sich zu halten, um auf ihren Namen. Während des Sommers, hatten sie von der Jagd zu leben oder zu verkaufen Pelze. [PARAGRAPH: 1] In den Geschichten der Fenian Cycle, die fianna dargestellt als eine einzige stehende Heer in den Dienst der hohen singen. Es enthielt zwei rivalisierenden Gruppen, die Clan Baíscne Leinster und der Clan Morna von Conacht. Mitgliedschaft in der fianna war Gegenstand einer rigorosen Texte. Zum Beispiel, die Klägerin würde Abfälle tief in ein Loch bewaffnet mit einem Schild, während neun Krieger warf Speere auf ihn. Wenn Verwundete, die Klägerin würde scheitern. In einem anderen Text, sein Haar wäre geflochten und er würde verfolgt werden durch den Wald und würde scheitern, wenn gefangen. Er würde auch nicht, wenn ein Zweig geknackt unter seinen Füßen, oder wenn die Zöpfe in seinem Haar wurden gestört. Er würde in der Lage sein müssen Sprung über eine Zweigstelle der Höhe seiner Stirn, Pass unter einem so niedrig wie seine Knie, und ziehen Sie ein Dorn aus seinem Fuß und ohne Abbremsen. Er wird auch benötigt, um eine qualifizierte Dichter.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB] All'inizio di Irlanda, fianna erano piccole, semi indipendente guerriero bande che vivevano nelle foreste come mercenari, briganti, e di fame. Essi vivevano separati dal resto della società e potrebbe essere chiamato dal re in tempi di guerra. Esse appaiono nella mitologia irlandese, in particolare nelle storie dei Fenian Cycle. In queste storie, il fianna sono guidati da Fionn Mac Cumhail. Fianna Éireann il nome è stato usato in un certo numero di organizzazioni di scout repubblicano irlandese. La storica istituzione del fian è conosciuto da riferimenti agli inizi di diritto irlandese tratti medievali. Un fian era composta da giovani uomini senza terra, spesso nobili, che non era ancora entrato in eredità della loro terra. In inverno, fianna erano squartato e alimentato da ° enobility, durante il quale essi avrebbero mantenere l'ordine a loro nome. Durante l'estate, che il vivere di caccia o di vendita di pellicce. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Nelle storie dei Fenian Cycle, il fianna sono descritti come un unico esercito permanente nel servizio di alta cantare. Essa conteneva due fazioni rivali, il Clan Baíscne di Leinster e Clan Morna di Conacht. Adesione alla fianna è stato oggetto di rigorosa testi. Per esempio, la ricorrente avrebbe rifiuti profondo in un foro armato di uno scudo, mentre nove guerrieri gettato lance a lui. Se feriti, il ricorrente sarebbe ininfluente. In un altro testo, il suo sarebbe treccia di capelli e sarebbe perseguito attraverso la foresta e che se non catturati. Egli avrebbe anche se non una succursale incrinate sotto i suoi piedi, o se il trecce nei suoi capelli sono stati disturbati. Egli avrebbe dovuto essere in grado di saltare più di un ramo l'altezza del suo fronte, passare sotto uno basse come il suo ginocchio, e tirare una spina dal suo piede senza rallentamento. Egli ha anche bisogno di essere un bravo poeta.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB] A principios de Irlanda, fianna eran pequeños, semiáridas bandas independientes guerrero que vivió en los bosques como mercenarios, bandidos, y tiene hambre. Vivían separadas del resto de la sociedad y puede ser llamado por los reyes en tiempos de guerra. Ellos aparecen en la mitología irlandesa, especialmente en las historias de la Fenian Cycle. En estas historias, la fianna se conducen por Fionn Mac Cumhail. El nombre Fianna Éireann ha sido utilizado en una serie de organizaciones de escultismo Republicano Irlandés. La histórica institución de la fian es conocido a partir de las referencias medievales a principios de la legislación irlandesa extensiones. A fian está formada por campesinos sin tierra de los hombres jóvenes, a menudo aristócratas, que todavía no ha entrado en la herencia de sus tierras. En el invierno, fianna fueron acuartelados y alimentado por ª enobility, durante la cual se debería mantener el orden en su nombre. Durante el verano, habían tenido que vivir de la caza o la venta de pieles. [PARAGRAPH: 1] En las historias de la Fenian Cycle, la fianna son presentados como un solo ejército permanente al servicio de la alta cantar. Contiene dos facciones rivales, el Clan Baíscne de Leinster y el Clan Morna de Conacht. Membresía a la fianna se sancionará con la pena de textos. Por ejemplo, el solicitante de pie de residuos en un profundo agujero armado con un escudo mientras que nueve guerreros arrojaron lanzas en él. Si heridos, la demandante no funcionaría. En otro texto, el pelo trenzado y sería él se llevaría a cabo a través del bosque y si no se captura. Asimismo, si no una sucursal agrietada debajo de sus pies, o si las trenzas en el pelo se inquieta. Él tendría que ser capaz de saltar sobre una rama la altura de su frente, en virtud de un pase tan bajo como su rodilla, y tire de una espina de su pie sin reducir la velocidad de. También tiene que ser un experto poeta.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_FIANNA_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>This powerful melee unit (the Irish replacement for the [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Light Swordsman[COLOR_REVERT]) is excellent defending forests and jungles, being able to quickly strike his enemy, then disappear into the woods so fast as they came.</English>
		<French>This powerful melee unit (the Irish replacement for the [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Light Swordsman[COLOR_REVERT]) is excellent defending forests and jungles, being able to quickly strike his enemy, then disappear into the woods so fast as they came.</French>
		<German>This powerful melee unit (the Irish replacement for the [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Light Swordsman[COLOR_REVERT]) is excellent defending forests and jungles, being able to quickly strike his enemy, then disappear into the woods so fast as they came.</German>
		<Italian>This powerful melee unit (the Irish replacement for the [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Light Swordsman[COLOR_REVERT]) is excellent defending forests and jungles, being able to quickly strike his enemy, then disappear into the woods so fast as they came.</Italian>
		<Spanish>This powerful melee unit (the Irish replacement for the [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Light Swordsman[COLOR_REVERT]) is excellent defending forests and jungles, being able to quickly strike his enemy, then disappear into the woods so fast as they came.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_A1</Tag>
		<English>AA</English>
		<French>
			<Text>AA</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>AA</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>AA</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>AA</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_A2</Tag>
		<English>BB</English>
		<French>
			<Text>BB</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>BB</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>BB</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>BB</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_A3</Tag>
		<English>CC</English>
		<French>
			<Text>CC</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>CC</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>CC</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>CC</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_A4</Tag>
		<English>DD</English>
		<French>
			<Text>DD</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>DD</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>DD</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>DD</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_A5</Tag>
		<English>EE</English>
		<French>
			<Text>EE</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>EE</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>EE</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>EE</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_A6</Tag>
		<English>FF</English>
		<French>
			<Text>FF</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>FF</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>FF</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>FF</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_A7</Tag>
		<English>GG</English>
		<French>
			<Text>GG</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>GG</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>GG</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>GG</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_A8</Tag>
		<English>HH</English>
		<French>
			<Text>HH</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>HH</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>HH</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>HH</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_A9</Tag>
		<English>II</English>
		<French>
			<Text>II</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>II</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>II</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>II</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_A0</Tag>
		<English>JJ</English>
		<French>
			<Text>JJ</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>JJ</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>JJ</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>JJ</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_B1</Tag>
		<English>KK</English>
		<French>
			<Text>KK</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>KK</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>KK</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>KK</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_B2</Tag>
		<English>LL</English>
		<French>
			<Text>LL</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>LL</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>LL</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>LL</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_B3</Tag>
		<English>MM</English>
		<French>
			<Text>MM</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>MM</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>MM</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>MM</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_B4</Tag>
		<English>NN</English>
		<French>
			<Text>NN</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>NN</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>NN</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>NN</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_B5</Tag>
		<English>OO</English>
		<French>
			<Text>OO</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>OO</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>OO</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>OO</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_B6</Tag>
		<English>PP</English>
		<French>
			<Text>PP</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>PP</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>PP</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>PP</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_B7</Tag>
		<English>QQ</English>
		<French>
			<Text>QQ</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>QQ</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>QQ</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>QQ</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_B8</Tag>
		<English>RR</English>
		<French>
			<Text>RR</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>RR</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>RR</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>RR</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_B9</Tag>
		<English>SS</English>
		<French>
			<Text>SS</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>SS</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>SS</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>SS</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_B0</Tag>
		<English>TT</English>
		<French>
			<Text>TT</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>TT</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>TT</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>TT</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_C1</Tag>
		<English>UU</English>
		<French>
			<Text>UU</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>UU</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>UU</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>UU</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_C2</Tag>
		<English>VV</English>
		<French>
			<Text>VV</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>VV</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>VV</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>VV</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_C3</Tag>
		<English>WW</English>
		<French>
			<Text>WW</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>WW</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>WW</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>WW</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_C4</Tag>
		<English>XX</English>
		<French>
			<Text>XX</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>XX</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>XX</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>XX</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_C5</Tag>
		<English>YY</English>
		<French>
			<Text>YY</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>YY</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>YY</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>YY</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_C6</Tag>
		<English>ZZ</English>
		<French>
			<Text>ZZ</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>ZZ</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>ZZ</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>ZZ</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_C7</Tag>
		<English>AAA</English>
		<French>
			<Text>AAA</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>AAA</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>AAA</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>AAA</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_C8</Tag>
		<English>BBB</English>
		<French>
			<Text>BBB</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>BBB</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>BBB</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>BBB</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_C9</Tag>
		<English>CCC</English>
		<French>
			<Text>CCC</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>CCC</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>CCC</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>CCC</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIQUE_NAME_C0</Tag>
		<English>DDD</English>
		<French>
			<Text>DDD</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</French>
		<German>
			<Text>DDD</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</German>
		<Italian>
			<Text>DDD</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Italian>
		<Spanish>
			<Text>DDD</Text>
			<Gender>Male</Gender>
			<Plural>0</Plural>
		</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>