<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<resources>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_STRONGER_CHARLES_V_1">Peace is the biggest struggle, time to pay up, [CT_NAME].</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_ABLAY_1">Hello, [CT_NAME]! Your wanderings have brought you to the [OUR_CIV_ADJ] steppe. I advise you to be friendly with the [OUR_CIV_ADJ] people, for these are our lands!</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_AGAMEMNON_1">Greetings.  I am [OUR_NAME], Prince of [OUR_EMPIRE], and defeater of all enemies.  Tell me, are you a friend, or enemy?</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_AHMADINEJAD_1">Greetings, [CT_NAME]. The Islamic Republic has never threatened and will never threaten any country.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_AJATASHATRU_1">Our mantras, our sacred hymns, will purify and cleanse your soul from the evil heathenry that you, [CT_NAME] have been exposed to.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_ALAKSANDU_1">I am [OUR_NAME] of [OUR_CIV_SHORT]. You may want to protect your feet if you seek war,[CT_NAME].</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_ALARIC_1">Greetings! I am [OUR_NAME] of the [OUR_EMPIRE]. When it comes to doing battle, I often say \"The thicker the hay, the easier to mow.\"</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_ALBOIN_1">May the heavens rain down blessings upon you, [CT_NAME]! I am [OUR_NAME], wise and benevolent ruler of [OUR_EMPIRE]! Feel free to begin showering me with tribute at your convenience!</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_ALFRED_1">I, [OUR_NAME], am but a common king, [CT_NAME]. Care for a drink?</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_ALOOMA_1">The mighty [OUR_EMPIRE] greets you. We value our safety so that a lone woman clad in gold might walk with none to fear but God.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_AMANISHABHETO_1">Greetings, [CT_NAME] of the [CT_EMPIRE]. Welcome to the land of riches and prosperity! We are please to serve you...to the degree that serves us.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_AMINA_1">Blessings, [CT_NAME] of the [CT_EMPIRE]. Rest assured we will strive to be benevolent neighbours. A man does not wander far from where his corn is roasting.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_ANDRANIK_1">Greetings! I am [OUR_NAME] of the [OUR_EMPIRE]. I hope that our two great peoples can live together in peace, but if we cannot, I will fight you even if you have a vastly superior army!</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_ANDREA_GRITTI_1">I am honored to meet you, [CT_NAME]. I hope that our two nations will be able to live in peace and friendship.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_ARPAD_1">Welcome to my lands, [CT_NAME]. The [OUR_EMPIRE] advises that you only stretch as far as your blanket reaches.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_ARSACES_1">Welcome [CT_NAME] I am [OUR_NAME] the leader of the noble [OUR_EMPIRE], greet you.  Shall I send my Cataphracts against yours? or shall we ride together to crush our enemies beneath our heals?</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_ATHEAS_1">I am [OUR_NAME] of the [OUR_EMPIRE]. If you must needs come to blows with us speedily, look about you, and behold our fathers' tombs. Attempt to meddle with them and you shall see whether or not we will fight with you.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_ATTILA_1">Greetings! The [OUR_CIV_SHORT] are pleased to leave you in peace. But keep in mind, [CT_NAME], that a hungry bear does not dance.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_AYAPEC_1">I am the fierce and unforgiving [OUR_NAME] of the [OUR_EMPIRE]. Delight us in tribute or face the axes of my warriors!</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_AYUB_KHAN_1">Hello to you, [CT_NAME]. There is nothing wrong with intellectual differences, as long as such differences remain confined to intellectual debates.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_BADUR_1">Ah, [CT_NAME]! Welcome to the [OUR_EMPIRE]! If there is a paradise on earth, it is this, it is this, it is this.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_BAIBARS_1">Our faithful have triumphed against unstoppable scourges.  What chance do you think you have?</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_BAYANCHUR_1">Greetings! I am [OUR_NAME] of the [OUR_EMPIRE], born with glory on Moon Heaven.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_BEN_GURION_1">Shalom, [CT_NAME]. Let us hope you bring with you peaceful relations, for I can overcome most obstacles in my way.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_BOLIVAR_1">I am [OUR_NAME], El Libertador of South America. I live to free people from harsh colonial rule. Will you be a useful ally or a hated enemy?</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_BORU_1">Greetings, [CT_NAME]! I hope we will be allies, for in our togetherness, castles are built.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_BOTHA_1">Greetings, [CT_NAME]. I am [OUR_NAME] of [OUR_CIV_SHORT]. The idea of an Afrikaner people as a cultural entity and religious group with a special language will be retained in South Africa as long as civilisation stands.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_BRIDEI_1">I am [OUR_NAME] of the [OUR_EMPIRE]. Why are you here?</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_BRINNO_1">I am [OUR_NAME], a man of distinguished birth and a brave soldier.  Disrespect me, and I will have your head.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_BULAN">If the rich could hire the poor to die for them, the poor would make a very nice living. Anyhow, what riches may your so-called [CT_EMPIRE] possess?</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_BUREBISTA_1">I am [OUR_NAME], and I will make an equally valuable ally or dangerous opponent.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_CAKSTE_1">I am [OUR_NAME] of the [OUR_EMPIRE]. Each of us strives to move to tomorrow, forging our own destiny!</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_CALGACUS_1">We, the choice flower of Britain, were treasured in her most secret places. Out of sight of subject shores, we kept even our eyes free from the defilement of tyranny. We, the last men on earth, the last of the free, have been shielded till today by the very remoteness and the seclusion for which we are famed. I am [OUR_NAME] of the [OUR_EMPIRE].</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_CANUTE_1">Warm greetings to the [CT_EMPIRE]. I, [OUR_NAME], seek a peace above all earthly dignities, and a still and quiet conscience. </string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_CARDENAS_1">Hola. I am [OUR_NAME] of the [OUR_EMPIRE]. I am convinced that the good intentions of a ruler are simply not enough and that the collective factor represented by the workers is indispensable. Don't you agree [CT_NAME]?</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_CASIMIR_1">Best wishes to you, [CT_NAME] of the [CT_EMPIRE]. Fate throws fortune, but not everyone catches.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_CASTRO_1">I am a revolutionary, [CT_NAME]. And the [OUR_EMPIRE] is a dictatorship of the exploited against the exploiters. </string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_CHANGAMIRE_1">Beware [CT_NAME]!  We drove out our enemies before and we can do it again!</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_CHARLES_XII_1">I am [OUR_NAME].  The best place to find a helping hand is at the end of your own arm.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_CHAVEZ_1">Welcome [CT_NAME].  I have found yet another friend here. And with such a friend we will together form a team, like a soccer team. This will be a fighting team.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_CHE_BONG_NGA_1">Greetings to you, [CT_NAME].  I am [OUR_NAME] and remind you that opportunity knocks but once.  What favors do you bring with you?</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_CHRISTIAN_IV_1">Warm greetings to the [CT_EMPIRE]. I, [OUR_NAME], seek a peace above all earthly dignities, and a still and quiet conscience. </string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_CIVILIS_1">Welcome [CT_NAME] I am [OUR_NAME] the leader of the powerful [OUR_EMPIRE].  The Romans embarrassed my family and insulted me.  They shall pay for this trechary, will you stand with me in my glorious war? Or will I have to destroy you too?</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_CLARK_1">Welcome to [OUR_CIV_SHORT], [CT_NAME]. We prefer our champions to be humble and modest.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_COCHISE_1">Greetings! I am [OUR_NAME] of the [OUR_EMPIRE]. I warn you, do not settle on our land or I will fight you!</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_COLLINS_1">Greetings, [CT_NAME]! I am [OUR_NAME] of the [OUR_CIV_ADJ]. We will not become sitting targets, but become flying columns if you threaten us.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_COLOCOLO_1">Woe upon you [CT_NAME]. I am [OUR_NAME], lord of your destruction!</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_CUNHAMBEBE_1">Greetings, [CT_NAME]! I am [OUR_NAME] of the [OUR_CIV_ADJ] people. Help us safe our precious rainforest and you'll have our eternal gratitude!</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_CUNNE_SHOTE_1">I am [OUR_NAME], chief of the [OUR_CIV_ADJ] people. Let us trade and strengthen our friendship.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_CURTIN_1">Greetings, [CT_NAME].  The game is not lost - or won - until the last bell goes.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_CUZA_1">Felicitari! Eu sunt [OUR_NAME],dominatorul mandriei [OUR_EMPIRE]! Shall our two peoples live in peace or will the proud descendants of the Getae crush you like a worm!</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_DAAR_1">It might come as a surprise to you, [CT_NAME], but I, [OUR_NAME], of the [OUR_CIV_ADJ] people, am still alive!</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_DAVID_1">Greetings.  I am [OUR_NAME], and I welcome you, with a hand on the heart, to the the land of [OUR_CIV_SHORT].</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_DECEBALUS_1">Welcome [CT_NAME] I the great and powerful [OUR_NAME] greet you.  Shall we live in peace or shall the warlike peoples of the [OUR_CIV_SHORT] pillage the [CT_EMPIRE]</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_DEMETRIUS_1">Hello [CT_NAME].  They say that there is a first time for everything, but I have yet to lose a battle.  Keep that in mind when challenging \"the Invincible.\"</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_DIODOTUS_1">Welcome [CT_NAME] I the great and powerful [OUR_NAME] greet you.  Shall we live in peace or shall the warlike peoples of the [OUR_CIV_SHORT] pillage the [CT_EMPIRE]!</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_DONNACONA_1">The great [OUR_CIV_ADJ] people welcome you, [CT_NAME]. Let us tell you tales of a golden kingdom...</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_DUFOUR_1">I am [OUR_NAME], builder of bridges, both diplomatic and physical.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_DUSAN_1">Greetings, [CT_NAME].  Remember, he who digs a trap for others ends up in it himself.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_DUVALIER_1">Greetings from [OUR_EMPIRE], [CT_NAME]. Any decision you make against me, you will make against us all. I know the will of the people for I AM the people!</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_ENHEDUANNA_1">Ah, welcome [CT_NAME].  I have just finished the most perfect poem, care to hear it?</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_ENRICO_DANDOLO_1">I am [OUR_NAME].  Just because I am blind does not mean I cannot see what you are up to, [CT_NAME].</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_EUCRATIDES_1">I am [OUR_NAME] of [OUR_CIV_SHORT].  I have taken my throne by force, and I shall take your's by force as well if you cross me.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_EWUARE_1">I am [OUR_NAME] of the great [OUR_EMPIRE]. We will wary of you like a rotting tooth, and chewing slowly in the meantime.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_FAISAL_1">You cannot destroy the will of the [OUR_CIV_ADJ] people.  If you dare conquor us, we will rise up against you; assist us, and you will prosper.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_FRANZ_1">Greetings to you, [CT_NAME]. Let us work side by side. It is said that success has more than one father.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_GAJAH_MADA_1">Selamat [CT_NAME], I am [OUR_NAME] of the [OUR_EMPIRE]. I have vowed not to taste any spice. As long as I can not unify Nusantara, I will not taste any spice. Before I conquer Gurun, Seram, Tanjungpura, Haru, Pahang, Dompo, Bali, Sunda, Palembang, Tumasik, I will never taste any spice.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_GARIBALDI_1">I offer neither pay, nor quarters, nor food, [CT_NAME]; I offer only hunger, thirst, forced marches, battles and death. </string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_GERONIMO_1">Be sure to stay off my people's land; my people have good aim and are ready to die for their freedom.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_GJERGJ_KASTRIOTI_1">May God bless you and your whole tribe, [CT_NAME]!  Accept my hospitality as celebrate the peace between our peoples!</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_GODWINSON_1">Hello [CT_NAME].  I inherited my throne fair and square, I swear.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_GUSTAV_1">I am [OUR_NAME], here to speak with [CT_NAME] on behalf of the people of the [OUR_EMPIRE]. I seek peace and mutual respect, but am prepare if neither should be met.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_HAAKON_1">I represent all people of [OUR_CIV_SHORT], and I will not support those who do not fufill that duty to their people.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_HAAKONSON_1">I am [OUR_NAME].  I will make sure that your people are taken care of if someone happens to conquer you.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_HASINA_1">Greetings, [CT_NAME]! I am [OUR_NAME] of the [OUR_EMPIRE]. Let us join forces to lead our countries to the cherished goals!</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_HASSAN_1">I, [OUR_NAME], come to you with honest words and an even temper. One who is not moved by words, [CT_NAME], is not moved by the stick.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_HECTOR_1">I am [OUR_NAME] of [OUR_CIV_SHORT]. I have abided by three laws in my life. Honor the gods, love your woman, and defend your country.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_HIDALGO_1">May the blessings of Heaven be upon you, [CT_NAME]. I am [OUR_NAME] of the [OUR_CIV_SHORT]. Mexicanos, Viva Mexico!</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_HIRAM_1">Greetings. I am [OUR_NAME] of the [OUR_EMPIRE]. I am trained to work in gold, silver, bronze, iron, stone, and wood, and in purple, blue, and crimson fabrics and fine linen, and to do all sorts of engraving and execute any design that may be assigned to me.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_HO_CHI_MINH_1">I caution you against aggression, [CT_NAME] of the [CT_EMPIRE]. You will kill 10 of our men, and we will kill 1 of yours, and in the end it will be you who tire of it.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_HUS_1">Greetings, [CT_NAME]. I am [OUR_NAME], if you strike me down, I will become more powerful than you can imagine.  However, if you join my reformation, we can rid the world of corruption.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_HUSSEIN_1">We will remain ever steadfast [CT_NAME].The [OUR_EMPIRE] is not intimidated by the size of the army or the type of hardware the enemy brings.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_IDRIS_1">Greetings, [CT_NAME]. I am [OUR_NAME] of the [OUR_EMPIRE]. Love truth even if it harms you, and hate lies even if they serve you. These are words of wisdom to live by.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_ITHOBAAL_1">The [OUR_EMPIRE] has colonies all over the known world, bringing in unimaginable riches.  Send your envoys, and we shall trade; send your armies, and be annihilated.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_JANYBEK_1">Hello, [CT_NAME]! You may have heard rumors about the terror of the horde, those rumors have been exaggerated.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_JEZEBEL_1">Praise be to Baal. I am [OUR_NAME].</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_JINNAH_1">I have no doubt in my mind that a large body of us visualize [OUR_CIV_SHORT] as people's government.  Either you seize it by force or get it by agreement.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_JOGAILA_1">Hello [CT_NAME].  I hope we can help each other, for the person who gives is the person who has.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_KAMEHAMEHA_1">Hello! Ask me what is the greatest thing in the world, I will reply: It is people, it is people, it is people!</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_KANEMI_1">You can discuss the almighty and the prophet with me or you can simply convert now.  What do you say [CT_NAME]?</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_KEKKONEN_1">Welcome, [CT_NAME] of the [CT_EMPIRE]. An argument rips, but peace builds. Let us build it together.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_KHOMEINI_1">There is no room for play in Islam, [CT_NAME]. It is deadly serious about everything. </string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_KITRA_1">Greetings, [CT_NAME].  The gods have secured my house and bloodline, have they done the same for you?</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_KOSSUTH_1">Revolutions sweeps over the continent!  It is time now time for action; join our ranks or be consumed by our hordes!</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_KRUGER_1">Welcome to the free land of the people of the [OUR_EMPIRE]! We do hope you enjoy your brief visit, [CT_NAME].</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_LANGE_1">God does not help me; I can't remember the last time I saw him in the caucuses.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_LAPU_1">The people of the [OUR_EMPIRE] believe that those who want, find many ways to get. Those who do not, make excuses. I, [CT_NAME], am not one to make excuses.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_LARS_PORSENA_1">By the Nine Gods, I swear that the great house of Tarquin shall suffer wrong no more! Greetings, [CT_NAME], I am [OUR_NAME] of the [OUR_EMPIRE].</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_LARS_TOLUMNIUS_1">Hopefully the fate of the [OUR_EMPIRE] will not be decided by a dice roll.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_LEOPOLD_II_1">I am [OUR_NAME] of the [OUR_EMPIRE]. I come seeking only to promote exploration and advance knowledge.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_LLYWELYN_1">Good day, I am [OUR_NAME] of the [OUR_EMPIRE].  I offer you my hostility!</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_LORENZO_1">\"Whoever wants to be happy, let him be so: about tomorrow there's no knowing.\" I am [OUR_NAME] of the [OUR_EMPIRE].</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_MACDONALD_1">Greetings! I am [OUR_NAME] of the [OUR_EMPIRE]. We offer you the friendship of the glorious nation of [OUR_CIV_SHORT]!</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_MACKENZIEKING_1">I am [OUR_NAME] and I offer you the friendship of the [OUR_EMPIRE]. After all, [CT_NAME], it is what we prevent, rather than what we do that counts most in Government.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_MAGNUS_1">Loyalty is as fickle as a king's favor, [CT_NAME].</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_MAKEDA_1">Riches and happiness to you, [CT_NAME] of the [CT_EMPIRE]. Enjoy our hospitality but bear in mind that a foreigner should always be well behaved.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_MALIK_1">The Great [OUR_EMPIRE] welcomes you [CT_NAME].  Raise even a dinner knife against us, and we weill ransom you back to your own empire.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_MANDELA_1">Greetings, [CT_NAME]. I am [OUR_NAME] of [OUR_CIV_SHORT]. In my country we go to prison first and then become President.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_MANNERHEIM_1">Welcome, [CT_NAME] of the [CT_EMPIRE]. I will reclaim what our great nation has lost.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_MARCOS_1">The  [OUR_EMPIRE] can be great. It is my articles of faith, and Divine Providence has willed that you and I can now translate this faith into deeds.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_MARGRETE_1">Greetings, [CT_NAME] of the [CT_EMPIRE]. I am [OUR_NAME] of [OUR_CIV_SHORT], although you may call me \"Margrete, by the grace of God, Valdemar Daneking's daughter, and Denmark's rightful heir\". What is it you wish to speak of?</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_MARIA_THERESA_1">It is a pleasure to meet you, [CT_NAME]. History is constantly teaching, but it does not find many pupils, so look closely at the world around you.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_MARTI_1">What a surprise...I'm [OUR_NAME] of the powerful nation of [OUR_EMPIRE], bend to my wishes or suffer the consequences.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_MARY_STUART_1">I am [OUR_NAME] of the [OUR_EMPIRE]. To be kind to all, to like many and love a few, to be needed and wanted by those we love, is certainly the nearest we can come to happiness, [CT_NAME]. </string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_MASARYK_1">Greetings, [CT_NAME]. I am [OUR_NAME], do not fear and do not steal.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_MATTHIAS_1">Welcome to this beautiful land, [CT_NAME].  I hope that you bring peace with you, for he who greets with a stick, will be answered with a club.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_MEHAI_1">Felicitari! Eu sunt [OUR_NAME],dominatorul mandriei [OUR_EMPIRE]! Shall our two peoples live in peace or will the proud descendants of the Getae crush you like a worm!</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_MENZIES_1">Welcome, [CT_NAME] of the [CT_EMPIRE], in warmth and best wishes. The greatest enemy to joy and high hopes is the cultivation of bitterness.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_MIKHEIL_1">We will work together, [CT_NAME], but I remain forever faithful to the people of [OUR_EMPIRE].</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_MINDAUGAS_1">I, [OUR_NAME], offer the [CT_EMPIRE] friendship. A person who gives is a person who has. Will you receive this gift, [CT_NAME]?</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_MITHRIDATES_1">Those I conquer, I consider friends.  Are you my friend [CT_NAME]?</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_MOBUTU_1">I am a warrior, [CT_NAME]. I understand the value of peace and cooperation. But if provoked, I will lead the  [OUR_EMPIRE] from conquest to conquest, leaving fire in my wake.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_MODU_1">Greetings, [CT_NAME]! Demand my saddle - I'll give it to you, demand my horse - I'll give it to you, demand my tent - I'll give it to you. But do not demand a single piece of my homeland.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_MUHAMMAD_REZA_1">Greetings, [CT_NAME]. My people will modernize, and restore [OUR_CIV_SHORT] to its former glory.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_MUJIB_1">As we have already given blood, we will give more blood. We will free the people of this country!</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_MURADBEY_1">I am [OUR_NAME]; ride by my side or be cut down.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_MUSSOLINI_1">Pleased to meet you, [CT_NAME]. Forgive me if I do not offer my hand. It's good to trust others but, not to do so is much better.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_MUTOTA_1">Greetings! I am [OUR_NAME] of [OUR_CIV_SHORT]. Let us build walls of stone to preserve the sacredness of our borders!</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_NAMPOINA_1">Let us compromise over matters, [CT_NAME]. One does not like hot, the other does not like cold; make it tepid to make an agreement.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_NARBONA_1">Ya'at'eeh shiyaazh, [CT_NAME]. Walk on a rainbow trail; walk on a trail of song, and all about you will be beauty. There is a way out of every dark mist, over a rainbow trail. Why do you walk the trail that leads to our land?</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_NASSER_1">I am [OUR_NAME].  I suspect that you another imperialist seeking to exploit the [OUR_EMPIRE], am I wrong?</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_NAUNG_1">Greetings, [CT_NAME]. Join the [OUR_EMPIRE] on its journey! If you are facing in the right direction, all you must do is keep walking.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_NESTOR_1">Take my advice [CT_NAME], you should praise the gods and enjoy the wine.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_NIALL_1">[CT_NAME] of the [CT_EMPIRE]. I, [OUR_NAME], welcome youfrom a distance, of course. If one lies down with dogs, one will rise with fleas.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_NIMI_1">Greetings, stranger. Our tranquil [OUR_CIV_ADJ] waterways lead into the heart of an immense darkness.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_NUWAS_1">Blessings, [CT_NAME] of the [CT_EMPIRE], and join me in dialogue. From a pound of talk, comes an ounce of understanding.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_OBASANJO_1">I've brought my country of Nigeria out of the dumps and onto the world stage - and as easy as I've done that, I can take yours off the world stage. Is that a bet you're willing to take?</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_OHIGGINS_1">Greetings, [CT_NAME]. I am [OUR_NAME], in battle I'm brave to the point of insanity.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_OSEI_1">I am [OUR_NAME], King of the [OUR_EMPIRE]. We look forward to welcoming you into the fold...someday.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_OSTENACO_1">Greetings. I am [OUR_NAME], chief of the [OUR_EMPIRE]. A good chief does not take, he gives. Are you a good chief, [CT_NAME]?</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_OWAIN_GLYNDWR_1">Good day, I am [OUR_NAME].  You shall neither take my, nor my country's land.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_PAEZ_1">I am [OUR_NAME], a soldier through and through.  I will gladly fight for the independence of [OUR_CIV_SHORT].</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_PASTRANA_1">I am [OUR_NAME], of [OUR_CIV_SHORT].  I have vowed to expose corruption at all levels, I hope your house is clean [CT_NAME].</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_PATTERSON_1">Greetings, [CT_NAME]. I am [OUR_NAME], I was young, gifted, and black and became the most honourable.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_PEARSON_1">It has too often been too easy for rulers and governments to incite man to war, [CT_NAME]. Let us direct the [CT_CIV_ADJ] and [OUR_CIV_ADJ]  people toward a life of peace together.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_PEDRO_II_1">I am [OUR_NAME] of the [OUR_EMPIRE]. Shall we discuss our future together? If one does not look ahead, one remains behind.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_PERON_1">Greetings to you, [CT_NAME]. A word of advice - if you have a tail of straw, then keep it away from the fire.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_PINOCHET_1">Not a leaf moves in [OUR_EMPIRE] if I don't know about it. Take care to mind your steps, [CT_NAME], lest I take whatever measures necessary to protect the beloved fatherland.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_PIYE_1">Greetings o' traveler, [OUR_NAME] is my name, welcome to the [OUR_EMPIRE].  Please, make yourself at home!</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_PO_NGBE_1">Welcome, [CT_NAME]! I am [OUR_NAME] of the [OUR_CIV_ADJ] people. My spiritual tranquility is boundless, my patience is not.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_RADAMA_1">Let us drink to a good future, [CT_NAME].</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_RADEN_WIJAYA_1">I am [OUR_NAME] of the [OUR_EMPIRE]. Do not extort gold from us, our climate will deal with any invaders.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_RAJENDRA_1">I caution you against aggression, [CT_NAME] of the [CT_EMPIRE]. You will kill 10 of our men, and we will kill 1 of yours, and in the end it will be you who tire of it.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_RISHI_1">Greetings! I am [OUR_NAME] of the [OUR_EMPIRE]. Beware, I flow, move near by flowing, I push, thrust and kill!</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_ROBERT_I_1">Greetings! I am [OUR_NAME].  Remember to be slow in choosing a friend, but slower in changing him.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_RUGA_1">I am [OUR_NAME] of the [OUR_CIV_SHORT].  Disrespect the [OUR_CIV_SHORT], and you shall pay, both in gold and in blood.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_SAAD_1">I, [OUR_NAME], vow that my sultanate will remain independent, lest I am its last ruler.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_SALAMASINA_1">Hello, [CT_NAME] of the [CT_CIV_SHORT]. Let us enjoy today, for our lives are decreed to be taken by the gods!</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_SAN_MARTIN_1">My best friend, [CT_NAME] of the [CT_EMPIRE], is he who rights my wrongs or reproaches my mistakes.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_SANTA_ANNA_1">Hello, [CT_NAME]. I am General Santa Ana, Savior of Mexico!  What have you come to offer me in tribute?</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_SARGON_1">Greetings! I am [OUR_NAME], the true king of Akkad. No, really, I mean it. Did somebody tell you something else? True king, seriously.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_SATUR_1">Greetings [CT_NAME]. I am [OUR_NAME], King of the [OUR_EMPIRE]. Won't you stay for a while and enjoy our Bull Leaping contest?</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_SELEUCUS_1">Welcome [CT_NAME] I the god like [OUR_NAME] greet you.  Shall we live in peace or shall the warlike peoples of the [OUR_CIV_SHORT] pillage the [CT_EMPIRE]</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_SEPE_TIARAJU_1">Greetings, [CT_NAME]! This land has people, remember that, and peace can exist.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_SHAMBARA_1">I hope we can bring each other aid, [CT_NAME], for dark nights will return after these few moonlit nights.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_SHAUSHTATAR_1">Greetings, [CT_NAME].  I hope we will be there are many who throw stones at a red apple.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_SHINSAWBU_1">Greetings, [CT_NAME]. Without proper guidance and meditation, a ruler will lead their empire to ruin and chaos.  Are you such a ruler [CT_NAME]?</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_SHISHUNAGA_1">Humble yourself, [CT_NAME].  A sacred land demands piety.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_SIMEON_I_1">Greetings, [CT_NAME].  Tell me who your friends are, so I can tell who you are.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_SKILURUS_1">One stick is easy to break, while a bundle is unbreakable.  You shall not draw out the tribes of the [OUR_EMPIRE], and break them, for our unity makes us strong.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_SOBIESKI_1">Greetings! I am [OUR_NAME] of the [OUR_EMPIRE].  Before you come to me, always remember: no labour, no oilcakes.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_SONGTSEN_1">Welcome, [CT_NAME].  I hope we can maintain peaceful relations, for excellent people are honored wherever they go.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_STAMBOLOV_1">Dobro utro [CT_NAME]! I am [OUR_NAME] of the [OUR_EMPIRE]. The first sign of true political wisdom has always been the ability to give up the unachievable.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_STEPHEN_1">Greetings, [CT_NAME] of  the [CT_EMPIRE]. Let us be strong  lest prosperity lift us up too much or adversity cast us down.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_SUHARTO_1">We, the [OUR_CIV_ADJ] people, come in peace. But never think that still waters are without crocodiles, [CT_NAME] of the [CT_EMPIRE].</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_SUKARNO_1">I, [OUR_NAME], will take all measures necessary to ensure the survival of the [OUR_EMPIRE].</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_SUNNI_ALI_1">Welcome, [CT_NAME]. \"Baani fondo a si ku  The sure path is never too long\". What path do you choose today?</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_SVIATOSLAV_I_1">Greetings, [CT_NAME].  May you be warned: do not mess with me, for he who licks knives will soon cut his tongue.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_TAHARQA_1">Greetings, [CT_NAME] of the feeble [CT_EMPIRE]. We tolerate your presence in these lands. A termite can do nothing to a stone but lick it.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_TAMERLANE_1">It is true that people of  the [OUR_EMPIRE] may suffer. But suffering is what will get them to the next land. Perhaps yours, [CT_NAME].</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_TECUMSEH_1">Greetings, [CT_NAME]. I am [OUR_NAME]. No tribe has the right to sell land, even to each other, much less to strangers.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_TENGRI_BOGU_1">Greetings [CT_NAME].  If you always watch your back, you will be stabbed in the front.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_TENZIN_1">Peace is essential, [CT_NAME], both for humanity and Enlightenment.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_TEUTA_1">Hello, [CT_NAME]. I am [OUR_NAME] of the [OUR_EMPIRE]. I welcome you, but please know that we build with sweat, and defend with blood.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_THEODORIC_1">I am [OUR_NAME], a toast to your health [CT_NAME].</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_TITO_1">Stop sending people to kill me [CT_NaME].  If you do not stop, I will send one to your palace, and I certainly won't have to send another.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_TOGHRUL_1">The [OUR_CIV_SHORT] are pleased to leave you in peace. I, [OUR_NAME], have still much to do in the name of our common ancestor.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_TOMISLAV_1">Greetings. I am [OUR_NAME] of the mighty [OUR_EMPIRE]. Let us help one another, [CT_NAME]. If strokes are good to give, they are good to receive.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_TOPILTZIN_1">Behold, [CT_NAME]! I am [OUR_NAME] of the [OUR_EMPIRE] - here by the will of the Great Father, and by his will I am chief!</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_TOQUI_LAUTARO_1">Behold, [CT_NAME]! I am [OUR_NAME] of the [OUR_EMPIRE] - here by the will of the Great Father, and by his will I am chief!</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_TOUSSAINT_1">I was born a slave, [CT_NAME], but nature gave me the soul of a free man. The [OUR_EMPIRE] will always be free and will always protect that freedom.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_TRUDEAU_1">Good day and bonjour, to you [CT_NAME]. The [OUR_CIV_ADJ] people wish for peace, but insist that masters in our own house we must be.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_TRUNG_1">[CT_NAME]... I am [OUR_NAME] of the [OUR_EMPIRE]. Remember, don't trouble until trouble troubles you.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_TUDJMAN_1">[OUR_CIV_SHORT] has suffered under the heel of others for too long.  Now that we have our own nation, we shall not suffer others.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_TYMOSHENKO_1">A true leader has no fear when they are sure of their actions, [CT_NAME]. I am always sure of my actions.  Are you?</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_U_KIX_CHAN_1">Welcome, [CT_NAME]! I am [OUR_NAME] of the [OUR_CIV_ADJ] people. May our friendship last longer than the stones.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_UCUPE_1">Welcome to the [OUR_EMPIRE], [CT_NAME].  Try to steal our gold and jade, and you will be found thousands of years later, garroted in my tomb.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_VARGAS_1">Greetings, [CT_NAME]. My name is [OUR_NAME], and I am the president of [OUR_CIV_SHORT].</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_VIJAYALAYA_1">Fire lasts only as long as it heats. The earth lasts only as long as it revolves. Man lasts only as long as he tries. You, [CT_NAME], like I, [OUR_NAME], are but a man.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_VITTORIO_EMANUELE_II_1">Saluti! I am [OUR_NAME] of the [OUR_EMPIRE]. \"Chi la fa l'aspetti.\" He who wrongs someone has to expect something in retaliation. Please Keep that in mind.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_VLAD_1">Greetings, [CT_NAME] of  the [CT_EMPIRE]. Either act as you speak or speak as you act in our time together.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_WALESA_1">Welcome, [CT_NAME]! Liberty is not only a right, but also our common responsibility and duty.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_WENCESLAUS_1">Zounds!  More barbarian hordes!</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_WETTSTEIN_1">Pardon me, [CT_NAME], in case I was not invited.  I am [OUR_NAME], and I believe we need to talk.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_WILLIAMS_1">Beware: Rash councils now, with each malignant plan, each faction, in that evil hour began, at your approach are in confusion fled, nor while you rule, shall raise their dastard head! With pleasure, I offer my services, [CT_NAME].</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_WINNEMUCCA_1">Greetings! I am [OUR_NAME] of the [OUR_EMPIRE]. Tresspass on our land, and see what happens.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_WOVOKA_1">Greetings! I am [OUR_NAME] of the [OUR_EMPIRE]. The wind helps those without an axe to cut wood.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_YAGAN_1">Greetings. I am [OUR_NAME] of the [OUR_EMPIRE]. We are all visitors to this time, this place. Our purpose here is to observe and grow, and then we return home.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_YUNUPINGU_1">Welcome, [CT_NAME]. Know that the [OUR_CIV_SHORT] endeavour to live in peace with this land.</string>
 <string name="AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_ZIEBEL_1">Greetings, [CT_NAME]. Intelligent people know of what they speak; fools speak of what they know.</string>
</resources>
