<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<resources>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_ABORIGINES_NULLA_NULLA_PEDIA">[TAB]A nulla nulla, also known as as waddy or hunting stick, is an Australian Aboriginal war club.  The nulla nulla is a heavy club made of timber used in hand to hand combat.  Known to have the ability to split a shield, this powerful weapon was used for killing or stunning food.  It could also be used as a projectile or be used to make fire and ochre.  They could also be used as a punishment to those who broke Aboriginal law.  The nulla nulla was made by both men and women and could be painted or left unpainted.  Their construction varied from tribe to ribe, but were generall about one meter in length and sometimes had a stone head attached with bees wax and string.  They were made from where a branch met the tree, or from a young tree pulled up with its roots in the ground. </string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_AGEMA_PEDIA">[TAB]The Baktrian Kingdom had its own elite guard, shown so beautifully in golden statuary throughout their prominent enclaves.  These men are armed with spear and blade, and armored in a tough cuirass and boeotian helmet of a design unique to their corps.  They are the elite infantry of Baktria, and form the bulwark of Baktrias opposition to its rabid enemies.  They are a versatile phalanx, adept at their prescribed task but equally proficient when charging as melee fighters.[NEWLINE][TAB]Historically, the Baktrians had a lack of professional guards, which they tried to rectify by training recent arrivals from independent and semi autonomous Greek settlements outside of their kingdom, seeking a secure region for protection after their succession from the Seleucid kingdom.  These Greeks eventually formed the nucleus of this powerful and feared group of soldiers, which was later supplemented by local Greeks.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_AKKADIAN_COMPOSITE_BOWMAN_PEDIA">[H1]The Composite Bow[\H1][PARAGRAPH:2]The Akkadians probably invented the composite bow during the reign of Naram-Sin (2254-2218). A stele from this period shows Naram-Sin holding a composite bow, which is its first appearance in history, suggesting an Akkadian origin.[PARAGRAPH:2]The structure of the composite bow allows a smaller sized bow to pack greater power. The curve of the bow creates a higher draw-weight, releasing more total energy when the arrow is fired. The higher power allowed arrows to pierce leather armor, and possibly even bronze armor, from a great distance. The smaller size makes the composite bow more suitable for use on horseback or chariots. The disadvantage is that a composite bow takes much more time and effort to make than a regular bow, and because it necessitates gluing materials together, it is susceptible to water and humidity.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_ALAE_PEDIA">[TAB]Tacitus described the Batavians as the bravest of the tribes in the area, hardened in the German wars, with cohorts under their own commanders transferred to Britannia.  They retained the honor of the ancient association with the Romans, not required to pay tribute or taxes and used by the Romans only for war: \"They furinished the Empire nothing but men and arms\", Tacitus remarked,  Well-regarded for their skills in horsemanship and swimming - for men and horses could cross the Rhine without losing formation, according to Tacitus.[NEWLINE][TAB]The Alae Miliaria was the cavalry arm of the Batavian Cohorts supplied to the Romans.  The Miliaria would be used to flank and enemy and pepper them with pila (Roman javelins) before closing in a full charge.  These men were superb horsemen and could cross rivers and streams in full battle armor without loosing formation.  An excellent example of this skill is best described by Dio Cassius as he refers to the Battle of the River Medway.\"The barbarians thought that Romans would not be able to cross it without a bridge, and consequently bivouacked in rather careless fashion on the opposite bank; but he sent across a detachment of Germans, who were accustomed to swim easily in full armor across the most turbulent streams.  Thence the Britons retired to the river Thames at a point near where it empties into the ocean and at flood-tide forms a lake. This they easily crossed because they knew where the firm ground and the easy passages in this region were to be found; but the Romans in attempting to follow them were not so successful. However, the Germans swam across again and some others got over by a bridge a little way up-stream, after which they assailed the barbarians from several sides at once and cut down many of them.\" (Cassius Dio, Roman History, Book 60:20)[NEWLINE][TAB]Batavians also supplied large numbers of horsemen for the Emperor's Imperial Horse Guard.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_ALBANIAN_LIGHT_GUERILLA_CAVALRY_PEDIA">[TAB]The Albanians under Gjergj Kastrioti's time developed and employed Guerilla Cavalry Tactics as a means of defense against the invading Ottoman armies.  The Kalorse, a type of \"Light Guerilla Cavalry,\" was able to outrun any unit the Ottomans had to offer.  They made a habit of raiding enemy military encampments when they were least expected, wreaking havoc and causing confusion amongst enemy ranks before they withdrew from battle.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_ANGLO_SAXON_HUSCARL_PEDIA">In Anglo-Saxon England there may have been as many as 3,000 royal housecarls, and a special tax was levied to provide pay in coin. They were housed and fed at the king's expense. They formed a standing army of professional soldiers and also had some administrative duties in peacetime as the King's representatives. The term was often used in contrast to the non-professional fyrd. These Housecarls used a tactic called the shieldwall. In this tactic the Housecarls formed a line with their shields locked blocking the invaders or enemies from penetrating their lines. The Saxons were an aggressive force, and did not like defending. Thus, this battle tactic was not used for a long time. Huscarls were often the only professional soldiers in the kingdom, the rest of the army being made up of militia called the fyrd, peasant levy, and occasionally mercenaries. They were usually armed with the long Danish axe and had shields and mail armour.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_ANIYONEGA_AYASTIGI_PEDIA">[TAB]Ayastigi is the Cherokee word for Fighting Man or Warrior. The Cherokee warpath was made up of many trails that had been carved into the mountains from thousands of years of use by the warriors going to war. They would travel for thousands of miles to make war with their cousins of the Iroquois Nation, and other northern tribes.  Give the ayastigi a direction and a leader and they would follow it. When the war chief struck the atadedawasdodi (war pole), all ayastigi who wished to follow the chief gathered their war gear and struck out on one of their favorite \"sports.\" The Cherokee were not a brutal tribe of war people.  They were just made up of warriors who would go to war over the smallest wrong done to them or one of their own. They were respected and feared by all. The war cry of the Cherokee brought fear through out the mountains when they came calling.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_APACHE_REDSLEEVES_PEDIA">[TAB]In 1837, Mangas Coloradas or Dasoda-hae (Red Sleeves) became principal chief and war leader and began a series of retaliatory raids against the Mexicans. When the United States went to war against Mexico, many Apache bands promised U.S. soldiers safe passage through their lands. When the U.S. claimed former territories of Mexico in 1846, Mangas Coloradas signed a peace treaty, respecting them as conquerors of the Mexican's land. An uneasy peace (a centuries old tradition) between the Apache and the now citizens of the United States held until the 1850s, when an influx of gold miners into the Santa Rita Mountains led to conflict. This period is sometimes called the Apache Wars.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_ARGENTINA_CABALLO_PEDIA">[TAB]Jose de San Martin was a well respected and highly decorated general. He was the sole founder of the \"Regimiento de Granaderos a Caballo\" (Mounted Grenadier Regiment of the Argentine Army). It served as a school which produced some of the best cavalry officers in the history of South American warfare. All of the members of this school were well disciplined, well mannered, and were superior in training to any force before it. The significance of these soldiers would soon be realized when it came time for San Martín to begin assembling the force that would lead the march towards Peru.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_ARMENIA_FEDAYEE_PEDIA">[TAB]Armenian militia better known as Fedayee, is a term referring to Armenian guerrillas who voluntarily leave their families in order to fight for Armenians. The term fedayee was also used by Armenian guerrillas in the Ottoman Empire before and during the First World War, who defended Armenians from persecution. The term was widely used and is still used to describe the volunteers, and can be found in literature and songs.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_ARSIYAH_PEDIA">[TAB]According to Muslim sources, the Arsiyah formed the core of the Khazar army and were extremely influential in Khazar politics, but these assertions may be designed to exaggerate the importance of the Muslim community in Khazaria. The Arsiyah did often act independently of their government. Part of the treaty binding them to Khazar service guaranteed that they would not be used to fight other Muslims. In 913, the Arsiyah ambushed a Viking fleet that had been granted passage to the Caspian Sea by the Khazar government, wiping out thousands of Rus warriors.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_ASHANTI_TWAFO_PEDIA">[TAB]The Ashanti national army was elaborately organized into 6 parts, each with various sub-divisions, and muskets gradually replaced bows and arrows as the main weapons. On the move the army used this general breakdown- advance guard, main body, rearguard, and right and left wings. This detailed organization had several advantages, enabling the Ashanti generals to maneuver their forces with flexibility.  The Twafo was the advance guard within the system.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_ATLANTES_WARRIOR_PEDIA">The Atlantes Warriors were the elite of the elite of the Toltec armies, generals, soldiers of prestige and honor among the masses. So named after the legendary statues outside the old toltec capital city, these warriors were almost without peer during their day.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_BANGLADESH_BAHINI_PEDIA">[TAB]The Sena Bahini has specialized its peacekeeping operations capabilities around the world through participation in peacekeeping and nation building. It has created BIPSOT (Bangladesh Institute of Peace Support Operation Training) which is dedicated to training of peacekeepers for employment in all types of UNPSO (UN Peace Support Operations). </string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_BELGIUM_PIRON_PEDIA">[TAB]Belgian 1st Infantry Brigade, also known by the name of its commander as the \"Brigade Piron\", began as miscellaneous small elements in the United Kingdom, expanded to a \"fusilier\" battalion by the end of 1940, mustered a pair of such battalions in 1941, and in January 1943 assumed the official brigade designation. Various schemes were considered during this time for utilizing the brigade overseas, but it was decided to reserve it for the actual liberation of Belgium.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_BOLIVARIAN_LIBERATADOR_PEDIA">[TAB]Known as \"El Liberatador\", Simon Bolivar waged a war against the Spanish in several regions of South America. After his defeat in the Venezuelan War of Independence in 1811-1812. rebel leader Simon Bolivar fled to New Granada. He later returned with a new army, while the war had entered a tremendously violent phase. After much of the local aristocracy had abandoned the cause of independence, blacks and mulattos carried on the struggle. Elites reacted with open distrust and opposition to the efforts of these common people. Bolivar's forces invaded Venezuela from New Granada in 1813, waging a campaign with a ferocity captured perfectly by their motto, \"guerra a muerte\" (\"war to the death\"). Bolivar's forces defeated Juan Monteverde's Spanish army in a series of battles, taking Caracas in August 6, 1813 and besieging Monteverde at Puerto Cabello in September 1813.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_BRAZIL_PRACINHA_PEDIA">[TAB]It is the main unit that fought against the Brazilian Federation in the Revolution of 32, when the state of Sao Paulo has separated of the rest of the nation and lately was the main Brazilian unit in the World War II. This revolution occurred in 1932, when the Paulistas has not accepted the new rules for the states of the dictator Getúlio Vargas and for 3 months São Paulo was an independent nation. The Revolution was over after bombards of aircrafts and cannons and when the state didn't receive necessary help of allied states.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_BURMA_MON_PEDIA">[TAB]Humans lived in the region that is now Myanmar as early as 11,000 years ago, but the first identifiable civilisation is that of the Mon. The Mon probably began migrating into the area southward from western China in the period from 3000 BC to 1500 BC and settled in the Chao Phraya River basin of southern Thailand around the 6th century AD. </string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_CAROLEAN_PEDIA">[TAB]The Caroleans were soldiers of the Swedish kings Charles XI and Charles XII.  They were part of the yearly Swedish allotment system.  The Caroleans' tactics were to attack fiercely and remain unafraid.  The soldiers also sustained stern discipline, which over the extensive course of a twenty-year-long war would prove vital.  The Swedish army tactics of the time did not teach retreat, so the soldiers were known to never withdraw from battle.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_CHILE_CARABINIERS_PEDIA">[TAB]Carabineros de Chile are the uniformed Chilean national police force and gendarmery, created on April 27, 1927. Their mission is to maintain the order and create public respect for the laws of the country. They depend on the Ministerio de Defensa Nacional (Ministry of National Defense) through the Undersecretary of Carabiniers and the Ministerio del Interior (Ministry of the Interior). Chile also has an investigative police force, the Policia de Investigaciones.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_CHOLA_KALLARANI_PEDIA">[TAB]Technically, the Kallarani weren't employed by either the sovereign or the state. Rather, they were pirates who received tng military unit that could easily go from place to place in a relatively short amount of time. Their elusiveness (when needed) and their knowledge of the terrain made them extremely difficult fighters. The Viet Cong were also highly motivatived and would endure terrible conditions to keep up the fight against the enemy no matter how long it lasted.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_COLOMBIA_AUC_PEDIA">[TAB]The United Self-Defense Forces of Colombia (Autodefensas Unidas de Colombia, or AUC, in Spanish) was created as an umbrella organization of regional far-right paramilitary groups in Colombia, each intending to protect different local economic, social and political interests by fighting insurgents in their areas. It is estimated that it has more than 20,000 militants. The AUC has been considered to be a terrorist organization by many countries and organizations, including the United States and the European Union. The organization was formed in April 1997.  The AUC claimed its primary objective was to protect its sponsors and its supporters from insurgents and their activities, because the Colombian state had historically failed to do so. The AUC asserted itself as a regional and national counter-insurgency force. Former AUC leader Carlos Castaño Gil in 2000 claimed 70 percent of the AUC's operational costs were financed with cocaine-related earnings, the rest coming from \"donations\" from its sponsors. The group's sponsors have included landowners, cattle ranchers, mining or petroleum companies and politicians.  The AUC has also been linked to elements within the Colombian Army with whom they maintained cooperation, including their participation in joint operatives. The Colombian military has been accused of delegating to AUC paramilitaries the task of murdering peasants and labor union leaders, among others, targeted by the group under the suspicion of being guerrilla infiltrators.  The bulk of the AUC's blocks demobilized by early 2006 and its former top leadership was extradited to the U.S. in 2008. However, local successors such as the Black Eagles continue to exist and death threats have been made using its name. On May 8, 2008, employees of a community radio station (Sarare FM Stereo) received a message stating: \"For the wellbeing of you and your loved ones, do not meddle in subjects that do not concern the radio station. AUC, Arauca\". A few days later the letters AUC were daubed on the front of their office. This threat was made due to their participation in a public meeting attended by members of a Congressional Human Rights Commission on the 27 September 2007. Here, members of the public denounced human rights abuses committed in Arauca Department by different parties to the armed conflict, including the AUC.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_CONGO_FIDALGO_PEDIA">[TAB]The Congo kingdom's army consisted of a mass levy of archers, drawn from the general male population, and a smaller corps of heavy infantry, who fought with swords and carried shields for protection. Portuguese documents typically referred to heavy infantry, considered nobles, as fidalgos in documents.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_COPPER_AXEMAN_PEDIA">[TAB] Although not much evidence of warfare in the Indus Valley Civilization has been found, many specimens of weapons have been discovered in the ruins of Harappa and Mohenjo-Daro.  Remains of axes made from copper or bronze have been found and could have been used by hunters in the area.  Some axes that are found contain inscriptions about deities or gods written in Indus Script.  Some of the axes found can be dated to as far back as 1500 BC,</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_CREE_TRACKER_PEDIA">[TAB]The European's earliest knowledge of the Cree placed them in the woodlands around James Bay in Quebec, where they lived in small family groups. From there the Cree gradually spread westward and eventually the lands they occupied stretched from Quebec across the Great Plains to the mountain ranges near the Pacific Ocean. With the arrival of first the French, and later the British, the Cree became engaged in the fur trade. They traded guns to the Blackfeet for the horses they needed to prosper on the plains.  the nineteenth century the Cree had been drastically reduced by disease, especially smallpox, and recurrent wars with other tribes retreating north to escape white settlers pushing up the Missouri River. With the fur trade dropping off and the buffalo disappearing, Cree leaders began working toward creating a safe homeland. They wanted a large native reserve where they could adapt to the European farming lifestyle, yet live according to their own culture, but the government denied their plan. When other tribes tried to fight, the Cree were swept up in the military action and most were settled on small reserves.  Many Cree in the far north escaped forced settlement and maintained their independent life style well into the twentieth century.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_CROATIA_GUARD_PEDIA">[TAB]The Armed Forces of the Republic of Croatia have grown into a respectable and well-organised armed force during the Homeland War of independence. Many military analysts consider that the defense of the Croatian territory was successful, resulting in final military victory. Military tactics and strategy were carried out directly in practice and that is unique in the world. Croatian Armed Forces carried out many successful military operations such as Oluja (Storm) and Bljesak (Flash) in 1995 and Maslenica in 1994.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_CZECH_HUSSITE_PEDIA">[TAB]The Hussite wars also marked the earliest successful use of pistols on the battlefield. The Czechs called the handgun a pítala, and anti-infantry field guns houfnice, from which the English words \"pistol\" and \"howitzer\" have been derived. The Germans had just started corning gunpowder, making it suitable for use in smaller, tactical weapons. A gunman on an open field armed with only a single-shot weapon was no match for a charging knight on a horseback; however, from behind a castle wall, or from within the enclosure of the wagenburg, massed and disciplined gunmen could use the handgun to its greatest potential. From his experiences at the Battle of Grunwald, ika knew exactly how his enemies would attack, and he found new ways to defeat forces numerically superior to his own.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_DENMARK_GUARD_PEDIA">[TAB]Although the Guard Hussars (Gardehusarregimentet) themselves date from 1762, the Danish Army takes the date of the founding of a regiment from its oldest part, in this case the Zealand Life Regiment, which was founded in 1614. This makes the Guard Hussars the oldest regiment of hussars in the world still operational. In addition to its operational role, the Guard Hussar Regiment is one of two regiments in the Danish Army (along with the Den Kongelige Livgarde) to be classed as 'Guards'; in this case, the Guard Hussars perform the same role as the Household Cavalry do in the British Army. The ceremonial uniform of the Guard Hussar Regiment dates from 1860.[PARAGRAPH:1]The motto of the regiment is not in Danish but in Latin: In actis esto volucris, which translates to Be swift in action.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_DINNEHIH_CODETALKER_PEDIA">[TAB]The Navajo Code Talkers, whose ranks exceed 400 during the course of World War II in the Pacific Theater.  Have been credited with saving countless lives and hastening the end of the war. The Code Talker's served in all six Marine divisions from 1942 to 1945. The Code Talker's primary job was to talk and transmit information on tactics, troop movements, orders and other vital battlefield information via telegraphs and radios in their native dialect.  A major advantage of the code talker system was its speed. The method of using Morse code often took hours where as, the Navajos handled a message in minutes.   It has been said that if was not for the Navajo Code Talker's, the Marines would have never taken Iwo Jima. The Navajo's unwritten language was understood by fewer than 30 non-Navajo's at the time of WWII.  The size and complexity of the language made the code extremely difficult to comprehend, much less decipher.  It was not until 1968 that the code became declassified by the US Government.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_ETRURIA_ETRUSCANCHARIOT_PEDIA">[TAB]The only Etruscan chariot found intact dates to ca. 530 BC and is now kept at the Metropolitan Museum in New York City.[PARAGRAPH:1]The chariot was part of a chariot burial, containing the remains of two human corpses, along with two drinking cups. It is decorated with bronze plates, depicting mythological scenes in relief, and ivory, measuring 131 cm in height. The chariot's wheels have nine spokes (rather than the classical Greek four, the Egyptian six, or the Assyrian and Persian eight; excavated chariots from Celtic burials have up to twelve spokes).[PARAGRAPH:1]It was found in 1902 in Monteleone di Spoleto near Spoleto in the province of Perugia of Umbria, by a farmer,called Isidoro Vannozzi, when he was digging a wine cellar. Vannozzi hid it in his barn, concerned that the authorities might confiscate it, and later sold it to two Frenchmen in exchange for, according to family lore, two cows (or according to the local mayor, for 30 terracotta tiles). It was sold to the Metropolitan museum from Florence in 1903, and was illegally exported from Italy. The comune of Monteleone as of January, 2005 is attempting to recuperate the chariot from the Metropolitan museum, but museum representatives have \"respectfully declined\" to return it.[PARAGRAPH:1]There are also persistent rumors in Monteleone, if unverified, that other related finds were made at the same time, that were sold separately on the black market. A full-size copy was made in the mid-20th century, which is on display in Monteleone.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_FALXMAN_PEDIA">[TAB]The Drapanai contingents are made up of resolute warriors, well aware of their role on the battlefield as shock troops. While the average Getic soldier tells himself he is immortal, the Drapanai, more than any others, join battle without fear of death. They fight bare-chested and with only baggy trousers, not for protection but to keep some warmth. Their trademark though is the falx, a vicious blade capable of severing limbs and causing horrible wounds with a single, crushing blow. These warriors are best used as shock troops against enemy infantry. If used properly, they can cut their way through and open a gap in the enemy battle line, allowing other Getic warriors to exploit the opening. Their lack of armor might be a drawback against concentrated enemy missile fire and they should thus not be exposed to enemy ranged infantry needlessly.[NEWLINE][TAB]Historically, a Drapanai soldier is the archetype of the Getic warrior, bare-chested and armed with the falx. The falx weapon was developed from the Thracian rhomphaia and it became a traditional weapon among the Getai. The ones wielding it and who often made up the Drapanai were young vigorous warriors, striving to achieve recognition among their kin and fellow men. The religious aspects should not be overlooked either, as these men formed the frontline and served as shock troops which meant they were more exposed to the enemy, where the Getic religious zeal was of immense importance as these warriors did not fear death, because death was the gateway to their prophet-god Zalmoxis. Their valor is best shown during the Second Dacian War, when the Roman soldiers were issued new types of armor, greaves, modified helmets and especially stronger armguards to protect themselves against the falx, and Roman troops stationed in Dacia, as the Romans called Getia, in the later first century AD were still issued these armguards and armor pieces so not to lose their limbs!</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_FIANNA_PEDIA">[TAB] In early Ireland, fianna were small, semi-independent warrior bands who lived in the forests as mercenaries, bandits, and hunters.  They lived seperate from the rest of society and could be called by kings in times of war.  They appear in Irish mythology, most notably in the stories of the Fenian Cycle.  In these stories, the fianna are lead by Fionn mac Cumhail.  The name Fianna Éireann has been used in a number of Irish Republican scouting organizations.  The historical institution of the fian is known from references in early medieval Irish law tracts.  A fian was made up of landless young men, often aristocrats, who hadn't yet come into inheritance of their land.  In the winter, fianna were quartered and fed by the nobility, during which they would keep order on their behalf.  During the summer, they had to live by hunting or selling pelts. [PARAGRAPH: 1]In the stories of the Fenian Cycle, the fianna are depicted as a single standing army in the service of the high sing.  It contained two rival factions, the Clan Baíscne of Leinster and the Clan Morna of Conacht.  Membership to the fianna was subject to rigorous texts.  For example, the applicant would stand waste deep in a hole armed with a shield while nine warriors threw spears at him.  If wounded, the applicant would fail.  In another text, his hair would be braided and he would be pursued through the forest and would fail if caught.  He would also fail if a branch cracked under his feet, or if the braids in his hair were disturbed.  He would have to be able to leap over a branch the height of his forehead, pass under one as low as his knee, and pull a thorn from his foot without slowing down. He also needed to be a skilled poet.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_FINNISH_JAEGER_PEDIA">[TAB]Modern infantry is given the challenging task of taking and holding terrain, which often involves dangerous,close range fighting. Organized into small squads, their strength lies in their training and equipment (rifle, grenades, helmet, and other critical gear). Often individuals in the squad are trained to be specialists, allowing them access to anti-tank weapons or light machine guns. Experienced in concealment and patrolling close to the enemy, these hard-fighting men play an important and versatile role in modern military conflict.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_GALLEAS_PEDIA">[TAB]The galleass or \"galliass\" developed from large merchant galleys. Converted for military use they were higher and larger than regular (\"light\") galleys. They had up to 32 oars, each worked by up to 5 men. They usually had three masts and a forecastle and aftcastle. Much effort was made in Venice to make these galleasses as fast as possible to compete with regular galleys. The gun-deck usually ran over the rowers' heads, but there are also pictures showing the opposite arrangement.[PARAGRAPH:1]	Galleasses usually carried more sails than true galleys, and were far deadlier; a galley caught broadside lay all but helpless, but coming broadside to a galleass, as with a ship of the line, exposed an attacker to her gunfire. The galleass exemplified an intermediate type between the galley and the true man-of-war. Relatively few galleasses were built ? one disadvantage was that, being more reliant on sails, their position at the front of the galley line at the start of a battle could not be guaranteed ? but they were used at the Battle of Lepanto (7 October 1571), their firepower helping to win victory for the Christian fleet, and some sufficiently seaworthy galleasses accompanied the Spanish Armada in 1588 (e.g. La Girona).[PARAGRAPH:1]	In the Mediterranean, with its shallower waters, less dangerous weather and fickle winds, both galleasses and galleys continued in use, particularly in Venice and Turkey, long after they became obsolete elsewhere. Later, \"round ships\" and galleasses were replaced by galleons and ships of the line which originated in northern Europe. The first Venetian ship of the line was built in 1660.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_GASINDII_PEDIA">Before the invasion of Charlemagne, the Lombards had been building up a force of retainers known as gasindii.  These were some of the best trained troops in Europe, consisting of men in Avar style armor.  They were particularly well trained.  They formed not only the backbone of Carolingian armies in Italy, but of other countries that invaded.  Gasindii could be found in Avar armies as well.  After the Carolingians conquered Lombardy, efforts were made to form private gasindii armies.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_GEORGIA_HORSEMAN_PEDIA">[TAB]The history of Georgia has been marked by a series of invasions and subjugation by several empires (such as Rome, Persia, Arabian Caliphate, Mongol Empire, the Ottoman Empire and the Russian Empire). Like in many cultures of the region, horsemen have traditionally played a role in the defence of the small nation.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_GOTHIC_CAVALRY_PEDIA">[TAB]The goths fought primarly on foot, but unlike other germanic tribes they also employed a large amount of heavy cavalry. The effectiveness of the Gothic heavy-cavalry was substantially heightened by their (innovative in Europe) use of stirrups. Particularly for heavy cavalry, this allows the use of heavier weapons and more cumbersome, but effective armour. Cavalry now had the ability to make head-on attacks on massed infantry, ie the \"shock-troops\" function of cavalry. They are also less likely to be dismounted at the first charge. The advantages of those improvements were one of the most important reasons for gothic victory at Adrianople (August 9, 378), the worst roman defeat since Battle of Cannae (216 BC). It showed weakness of roman army and led to sack of Rome by Visigoths in 410, first since Gallic invasion in 390 BC. Eventually it led to the fall of Western Empire and influenced change of Eastern Empire into Byzantium, with a switch from haevy infantry to heavy cavalry as the main part of the army.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_GRENZER_PEDIA">[TAB]In various Austrian Empires, Grenzers were troops who came from the Croatian and Transylvanian Military Frontier.  The troops were originally founded to defend Austria from the Ottomans, however when no danger lurked, the Grenzers were employed by the Habsburgs in other frontiers of war.  Still, at least one battalion of each regiment would remain guarding the border from invasion threats. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Grenzers were successors of the irregular army of Pandurs, which were also raised by the Habsburgs to defend the border and serve as skirmishers in the Seven Years' War.  By the time of the Napoleonic Wars, the troops formed more regular line infantry regiments.  They were given training in marksmanship, linear tactics, and skirmishing.  At the start of the war, 18 Grenzer regiments formed about a quarter of the Austrian Army. [PARAGRAPH: 1] However, because the Grenzers were not as good in the role of line infantry as the regular regiments, the Austrian military command never gave them much credit, and following a mutiny in 1800, their numbers were reduced.  Despite these setbacks, Grenzers preformed exceptionally well at Marengo and Austerlitz, earning them respect from the French.  Napoleon even considered them the only warlike troops in the entire Austrian Army.  Grenzer troops served for Napoleon until his defeat after the Austrians ceded territories in the War of the Fifth Coalition. [PARAGRAPH: 1] During the 19th century, the Ottoman thread diminished and thus there was less need for troops defending the Frontier.  Additionally, with rise of Slav nationalism and self-determination, the Austrian high command grew suspicious of the Grenzers and a possible revolt.  With these factors, the number of Grenzers was steadily reduced, although they remained in service in the Austrian and later Austro-Hungarian army until the World War II.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_GRIVPANVAR_PEDIA">[TAB]The Grivpanvar are nobles from the highest level of cataphracts that the Pahlava have to draw on. The elite of the clan host form this armoured fist that represents one of the most powerful armoured cavalry the world has ever seen. They deploy in the heaviest armour available and use the kontos as their primary shock weapon. Armoured in iron lamellar corselets, covered by a leather tabard, laminated leg and arm guards and with iron shining from the scale horse barding, these are truly men of iron, in bright armour for horse and man. The horse bearing such loads must be both large and strong, and both the Parthians and Achaemenid Persians bred just such horses, the Nisaean breed of Persia.[NEWLINE][TAB]Historical evidence suggests that the Parthian, heavily-armoured Grivpanvar were, at least partially, a product of military influence from the Central Asian steppes which had inherited the armoured cavalry traditions of the Massagetae and the late Achaemenid Persians. Their name derives from the Pahlavi griwban \"neck-guard\", a helmet armour guard, from whence \"Grivpan\" warrior. In the 3rd century AD, the Romans would begin to deploy such cavalry calling them clibanarii, the name thought to derive from griwbanwar or griva-pana-bara.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_HAJDUK_PEDIA">[TAB]Hajduk is a term that refers to outlaws, highwaymen, and freedom fighters in the Balkans.  In Balkan folkloric custom, hajduci are heroes who lead soldiers into battle against the Ottoman oppressors.  They are comparable to the English legend of Robin Hood and his merry men, who stole from the rich and gave to the poor.  In reality, the hajduci of the 17th, 18th, and 19th centuries were bandits who preyed on Ottoman representatives and local merchants and travelers.  Traditionally, hajduci follow a moral code that prohibited stealing from the poor and unprovoked murder.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_HEAVY_HUSSAR_PEDIA">[TAB]The first hussar units in the Kingdom of Poland were formed by the Sejm, the Polish Parliament, in 1503 which hired three banners of Hungarian mercenaries.  Soon, recruitment also began among Polish and Lithuanian citizens.  The Hussars proved vital to Poland because they were more maneuverable than the previously used lancers.  But the reign of King Stefan Batory, the hussars formed the bulk of the Polish and Lithuanian cavalry.  Over many years, hussars in Hungary became heavier.  When Stefan Batory was elected king of Poland, he reorganized the Polish-Lithuanian hussars of his Royal Guard making them a heavy formation, and equipping lancers as their main weapon. These Polish 'heavy' hussars were known in their homeland as \"husaria\" [PARAGRAPH: 1] With the Battle of Lubiszew in 1577, the \"Golden Age\" of the hussar began.  Until the Battle of Vienna, Polish-Lithuanian hussars rarely lost in battle.  Throughout many battles the Polish-Lithuanian hussars would prove to be an important factor against overwhelming odds. [PARAGRAPH: 1] The primary battle tactic of the Polish-Lithuanian hussars was the charge.  They also tended to repeat the charge until the enemy formation broke.  The hussars fought with a long lance, a szabla, one or two pistols, and a carbine or arquebus, known in Polish as a \"bandolet\".  Polish hussars were also famous for the wings they wore on their backs.  According to some theories, they were designed to foil attacks by Tatar lassos, another theory being that the vibrating of feathers made a strange sound that frightened enemy horses.  However, experiments carried out by re-enactors and movie-makers since the 1970s and more recently by Polish historians in 2001 contradict such ideas. Possibly the wings were worn only during parades and not during combat, but this explanation is also disputed.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_HIGHLANDER_PEDIA">[TAB]Highlanders were the troops that consisted of the common men of the Scottish Highlands. The were usually formed from local clans and acted to preserve order within their communities. Highlanders were particular prominent once the King James VI of Scotland inherited the throne of the Kingdom of England, and became also \"James I\" of England. After the Glorious Revolution and the overthrow of the Roman Catholic James VII by William and Mary, Scotland briefly threatened to select a different Protestant monarch from England. In 1707, however, the Parliament of Scotland and the Parliament of England enacted the twin Acts of Union, which created the Kingdom of Great Britain.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_HUNS_TARKAN_PEDIA">[TAB]These light hussars were ideal for reconnaissance and raiding sources of fodder and provisions in advance of the army. In battle, they were used in such light cavalry roles as harassing enemy skirmishers, overrunning cannon positions, and pursuing fleeing troops. Tarkans also had a reputation for being the dashing, if unruly, adventurers of the army. The traditional image of the tarkan is of a reckless, hard-drinking, hard-swearing, womanising, moustachioed swashbuckler. Less romantically, tarkans were also known (and feared) for their poor treatment of local civilians. In addition to commandeering local food-stocks for the army, hussars were known to also use the opportunity for personal looting and pillaging.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_HUSZAR_CAVALRY_PEDIA">[TAB]The original hussars were from Hungary, known to the Hungarians as huszars.  Originally, the huszars fought in small bands, but were reorganized, well-trained, and motivated formation during the reign of Matthias Corvinus.  The huszars under Matthias fought the Turks and proved successful.  They also showed signs of success against the Bohemians and Poles.  After the king's death, many huszars fled to other European countries, usually as mercenaries for war.  Frederick the Great, for instance, used hussar units widely throughout the War of the Austrian Succession.  Great Britain also hired hussar units to fight in the American War of Independence.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_INDONESIA_KOPASSUS_PEDIA">[TAB]Kopassus has played a pivotal role in Indonesia's modern history since its inception in 1952. Kopassus' main role in shaping history came in 1965 when it became the backbone of the Army, then politically fractured between pro and anticommunist camps, to crush the abortive coup blamed on the Indonesian Communist Party (PKI). The force's contributions were not limited to the military operations they were involved in. Probably much more significant was its success in producing some of the finest and most disciplined Army men, who went on to become statesmen long after they retired from Kopassus and the military. A quick glance at the list of Kopassus men who appear in the book reads like a who's who of the Indonesian Military.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_IRAN_REVOLUTIONARY_GUARD_PEDIA">[TAB]The Army of the Guardians of the Islamic Revolution, is a branch of Iran's military, founded after the Iranian revolution.  Sepah has 125,000 military personnel including ground, air and naval forces. It also controls the paramilitary Basij militia which has 90,000 active personnel, and in recent years has developed into a \"multibillion-dollar business empire.\" The Chief Commander of the Guardians is Mohammad Ali Jafari, who was preceded by Yahya Rahim Safavi.Like many young Iranians during the 1980-88 IranIraq War, Iran's president Mahmoud Ahmadinejad was a member of the Army of Guardians, in the Basij militia. In recent years the Iranian Revolutionary Guard Corps has become a vast military-based conglomerate. It is active in oil and gas, telecom, and farming, to name a few sections, and has considerable economic and political influence. The Guard's expanding economic role is mirrored by an even greater role in politics and security since the presidential election in June 2009.Since its origin as an ideologically driven militia, the Army of the Guardians of the Islamic Revolution has taken an ever more assertive role in virtually every aspect of Iranian society. Its expanded social, political, military, and economic role under president Ahmadinejad's administration  especially during the 2009 presidential election and post-election suppression of protest  has led many analysts to argue that its political power has surpassed even that of the Shiite clerical system.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_IRAQ_REPUBLICAN_GUARD_PEDIA">[TAB]The Republican Guard was charged with protecting the president, Saddam Hussein, and responding to any threat to his power, such as a rebellion or coup, and protecting Baghdad. In 2002 there were reportedly 12,000 members of the Special Republican Guard, drawn primarily from clans loyal to Saddam Hussein and his regime.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_ITALY_ALPINO_PEDIA">[TAB]During the Italian Risorgimento, the volunteers who followed Giuseppe Garibaldi in southern Italy were called Redshirts (Camicie rosse) because of the colour of their shirts (complete uniforms were beyond the finances of the Italian patriots). They were also called i Mille (\"the thousand\"), because that was the number that first set off with Garibaldi from Genoa.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_KANEMBORNU_IRONHELM_PEDIA">[TAB]Alooma's innovations for the Kanem-Bornu army included the employment of fixed military camps (with walls); permanent sieges and \"scorched earth\" tactics, where soldiers burned everything in their path; armored horses and riders; and the use of Berber camelry, Kotoko boatmen, and iron-helmeted musketeers trained by Turkish military advisers.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_KAZAKH_BATYR_PEDIA">[TAB]Baghatur is an old Altaic term for a warrior, a military commander, or an epic hero. The word was introduced in the Middle Ages to many non-Altaic languages by conquering Turkic- and Mongol-speaking nomads, and now exists in different forms such as the Russian Bogatyr', Polish Bohater (meaning hero), Persian and North Indian Bahadur, and Georgian Bagatur. It is also preserved in the modern Turkic and Mongol languages as Turkish Batur, Tatar and Kazakh Batyr, Uzbek Batyr and Mongolian Baatar (as in Ulaanbaatar).</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_KHAMPA_HORSEMAN_PEDIA">[TAB]Most people think of Tibetans as a kind, peaceful, and religious culture.  For the Kham region of Tibet, this statement is untrue.  Kham Tibetans have long been known as a violent group of bandits terrorizing the Tibetan Plateau on horseback.  They were employed by Tibetan Kings in fields of war to fight for them.  In Heinrich Harrer's book \"Seven Years in Tibet\", the Kham Tibetans are described as forcing their way into nomad tents stealing anything of value.  He also reported that they would sometimes kill pilgrims, monks and nuns.  Even today, it is rare to find a Kham man without a large knife on his side.  It was these same people that gave the Chinese communist government the most resistance.  Long after the Tibetans of Lhasa gave up, the Tibetans of Kham continued to fight.  The Chinese who live in the Kham region are often fearful of Kham Tibetans.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_KOA_PEDIA">[TAB]Warfare among tribal chieftains in Hawaii was common, with fierce battles raging frequently.  By the 1780s, warfare was institutionalized, with formal rules and rituals.  The chiefs built temples to pray, sacrifice, and perform ceremonies before launching campaigns.  Warriors were known as koa, and gave their name to the koa tree, whose hard wood provided for many of their weapons.  Hawaiian chieftains were practice of lua, a type of martial arts, and participated in annual festivals to test their abilities.  The warrior code was brutal, and punishment was harsh and violent.  An enemy captured in battle might have his entrails removed and every bone methodically broken while still alive. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Warriors usually wore a loincloth and shaved and oiled their skin to prevent enemies from gripping them in combat.  Nobles also wore a cape, as well as helmets made of wicker or gourds for protection.  These warriors used a variety of weapons such as the ihe (short spear), pololu (long spear), pahoa (wooden dagger), and other weapons.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_KONNIK_PEDIA">[TAB]The Bulgars were highly skilled in the equestrian arts.  Their army mainly consisted of horseman because of their high skill.  Every Bulgar horseman had high discipline and had several horses.  However, only a single horse could be used for wartime matters, and it was forbidden to do anything else with it.  It is believed that the Bulgars were the first who brought the stirrups to Europe.  This gave them advantages above the other European armies of this time.  The Bulgars could use bows still mounted on horses.  Swords and spears were also used in war.  The stirrups also increased the stability and speed of the rider.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_LAWAGETAS_PEDIA">[TAB]In Mycenaean society, the lawagetas were the \"leader of the people\".  The word \"people\" refers to the army, and the lawagetas were commanders of that army.  The lawagetas were powerful men who lead the armies, and received land from the king.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_LIGHT_HORSE_PEDIA">[TAB]The Australian Light Horse were mounted troops that combined the characteristics of both cavalry and mounted infantry.  They served during the Second Boer War and World War I.  Their purpose as both cavalry and mounted infantry was a result of the debate in military groups in Australia concerning the future of mounted troops.  On one hand, the battlefield had become dominated by machine guns and artillery and was too dangerous for mounted troops.  On the other hand, the distances in Australia were too great, and the small amount and poor condition of roads were unable to support mechanized warfare.  Light Horse were like mounted infantry in that they usually fought dismounted, using their horses as transport to the battlefield and as means of quick disengagement when withdrawing or retiring from a battle.  Over time, most Light Horse regiments were converted to motorized infantry, armored car or armored regiments during World War II.  However, a few light horse units still exist today as Royal Australian Armored Corps Cavalry units.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_MACCABEE_PEDIA">The Maccabees were a Jewish national liberation movement that fought for independence from Antiochus IV Epiphanes.  The Maccabees founded the Hasmonean Dynasty of Israel.  In 167 BC, after Antiochus forbade Jewish practice, a priest from Modiin, Mattathias the Hasmonean, sparked a revolt by refusing to worship Greek gods.  After Mattathiass death, his son Judah Maccabee led an army of Jews against the Seleucid Dynasty.  The term Maccabees is used to describe the army of Judah Maccabee. [PARAGRAPH:1] The revolt included many individual battles.  In many, the Maccabeean forces won victory for their use of guerrilla tactics.  After the revolt, the Maccabees cleansed the temple, and declared Judah Maccabee a priest.  A Syrian army was sent to destroy the revolt, but returned after the death of Antiochus. [PARAGRAPH:1] After the revolt, the Maccabees were unsure whether to continue fighting, seeing their military success in the revolt.  Those who continued to fight were led by Judah Maccabee.  Judah Maccabee died in 160 BC in battle.  Judah was succeeded by his younger brother Jonathan, who was already a high priest.  Jonathan made treaties with foreign nations, causing more disputes between those who wanted religious freedom over political power.  In 142 BC, Jonathan died.  He was succeeded by the last son of Mattathias, Simon.  That same year, Demetrius, king of Syria, granted the Jews independence from Syria and Simon went on to found the Hasmonean dynasty. [PARAGRAPH:1] Every year, Jews celebrate Hannukah to celebrate and recognize Judah Maccabees victory over the Seleucids and related miracles.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_MAGHREB_CAVALRY_PEDIA">[TAB]In 711, the Moors invaded Visigoth, Christian Hispania. Under their leader, an African Berber general named Tariq ibn-Ziyad, they brought most of the Iberian Peninsula under Islamic rule in an eight-year campaign. They attempted to move northeast across the Pyrenees Mountains but were defeated by the Frank, Charles Martel, at the Battle of Tours in 732. The Moors ruled in the Iberian peninsula, except for areas in the northwest and the largely Basque regions in the Pyrenees, and in North Africa for several decades. Though the number of \"Moors\" remained small, they gained large numbers of converts. According to Ronald Segal, author of \"Islam's Black Slaves\", some 5.6 million of Iberia's 7 million inhabitants were Muslim by 1200, virtually all of them native inhabitants.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_MAJAPAHIT_SILAT_PEDIA">[TAB]Pencak Silat is a Malay word meaning \"Self-defense\" or \"Fighting\" and its roots go very far back into the islands of Indonesia in the far east. The exact origins of Pencak Silat are not known but what is known is that it is a Martial tradition that extends to many different regions of the world and that it is an effective form of combative movement.[PARAGRAPH:1]The Hindu Empire of Majapahit created the foundation and systemization of the indigenous fighting techniques of Indonesia. The Majapahit warriors were a steeled group of men and were able to drive back the attacks of ruthless generals like Kau Sing and Kublai Khan with the methods they employed for close combat. It was in this empire that we see the famous Kris sword being truly perfected and becoming part and parcel with Silat.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_MALAGASY_MENALAMBA_PEDIA">[TAB]The rising of the menalamba, the Red Shawls, was a revolt against French colonial rule in Madagascar in the 1890s. In the century before the French conquest, rising tensions between modernising kings, self-seeking Christian oligarchs and reactionary guardians of the ancient talismans had weakened the capacity of the kingdom to resist. But just two months after the French occupation of the capital the menalamba revivalist movement sought to restore the customs of the ancestors and expel the French from the island. The civil war of 1895 fully described here for the first time, has cast a shadow on Malagasy politics ever since.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_MAMBISE_PEDIA">[TAB]The word \"mambises\" originated in Santo Domingo, after a brave Negro Spanish officer (Juan Ethninius Mamby) joined the Dominicans in the fight for independence in 1846. The Spanish soldiers referred to the insurgents as \"the men of Mamby,\" and \"mambies.\" When Cuba's first war of independence (known as the Ten Year War) broke out in 1868, some of the same soldiers were assigned to the island, importing what had, by then, become a derogatory Spanish slur. The Cuban rebels adopted the name with pride. The rebels had no choice but to become effective guerrilla-style warriors using the environment, the element of surprise, a fast horse and a machete.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_MANDE_SONGHAICAVALRY_PEDIA">[TAB]The kingdom of Songhai provides another prominent body of documented achievements in the use of light cavalry for the purposes of territorial gain and empire building. Malian and Songhai battle formations, or mandekalu, entailed the use of light cavalry forces bearing padded armor, spears or javelins, and imported swords. Such forces were highly effective in combat with enemy soldiers within the range of the savanna; however, these same cavalry forces were far less effective in the forested areas to the south of the Niger River or within tsetse-fly-ridden regions where horses were vulnerable. Following on the heels of the cavalry were the infantrymen, who typically bore full armor, iron-tipped spears, and poisoned arrows.[PARAGRAPH:1]Ultimately, the development of sophisticated military organizations, advanced strategies and tactics, effective diplomacy, and weaponry of the kingdoms of Mali, Songhai, and successor states of West Africa, was such that these kingdoms largely dictated the conditions of European and Arabic commerce in West Africa well into the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_MAPUCHE_PICUNCHE_PEDIA">[TAB]The Picunche (a mapudungun word meaning \"North People\"), also referred to as picones by the Spanish, were a mapudungun speaking Chilean people living to the north of the Mapuches or Araucanians (a name given to those Mapuche living between the Itata and Toltén Rivers) and south of the Choapa River and the Diaguitas. Until the Conquest of Chile the Itata was the natural limit between the Mapuche, located to the south, and Picunche, to the north. During the Inca attempt to conquer Chile the southern Picunche peoples that successfully resisted them were later known as the Promaucaes.  The Picunche living north of the Promaucaes were called Quillotanes (those living in the Aconcagua River valley north to the Choapa) and Mapochoes (those living in the Maipo River basin) by the Spanish, and were part of the Inca Empire at the time when the first Spaniards arrived in Chile.  Among the peoples the Spanish called the Promaucaes, the people of the Rapel River valley were particularly called by this name by the Spanish. Those of the Mataquito River valley were called the Cures.  The people in the Maule River valley and to the south were distinguished as Maules and those to the south of the Maules and north of the Itata were known as Cauqui by the Inca and Cauquenes by the Spanish and that gave their name to Cauquenes River.  They did not survive into the present day, having died out during the colonial period.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_MARYANNU_PEDIA">[TAB] The most influential Hurrian state, Mitanni, gained much of its power through military might.  The elite warriors of their army were charioteers, called maryannu.  The maryannu were nobles who could afford chariots, and each had a handful of attendants, including an archer that would fight with them from the chariot and servants that would take care of the horses.  The Mitanni chariots themselves served as a model for the chariots of neighboring empires.  It could even be said that the system of having elite nobles who formed the chariot army was started by the Mitanni.  Mitanni chariots were sleek, with two wheels and a team of two horses.  Both the horses and the maryannu were well armored, being covered in scale armor made of bronze or iron.  The tactic of surrounding an enemy with chariots to constantly attack them with missile fire was developed by the Mitanni.  The Mitanni even created the tactic of using chariots as an impact weapon.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_MEDJAY_PEDIA">[TAB]The Medjay were Nubian nomads who became part of the Egyptian police force during the Eighteenth Dynasty.  Perhaps because the Medjay had previously established a history of serving in the Egyptian army that they blended well into Egyptian society.  They had the responsibility of protecting towns in western Thebes and being responsible to its mayor.[PARAGRAPH: 2]  The Medjay also served as tomb guardians during the contruction of the royal necropolis at Deir el-Medina.  The Medjay had the responsibility of ensuring the tomb's safety, inspecting the tomb, protecting the workers, ensuring that the workers were behaving well, and sometimes helping the workers.  Some of their other obligations included acting as messengers, interrogating thieves, being witnesses for administrative functions, and inflicting punishments.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_MEGYPT_MAMLUK_PEDIA">[TAB]The mamluks were slaves trained as warriors by various Arab leaders, partially because early believers in Islam would not fight each other.  Slave warriors got around this ban.  The mamluks were well trained and highly motivated.  A mamluk army from Egypt won a rare victory against the Mongols in Syria, turning these barbarian horsemen back from the Nile and North Africa.  In time the mamluks rose up against their Arab rulers and took control themselves.  When Napoleon invaded Egypt in the eighteenth century, he defeated a mamluk army at the Battle of the Pyramids.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_MEXICO_RURALES_PEDIA">[TAB]Rurales was the name commonly used to designate the Mexican Guardia Rural (Rural Guard): a force of mounted police or gendarmerie that existed between 1861 and 1914. In modern Mexico the name is applied to members of a part-time rural defence corps.[PARAGRAPH:1]The image of the Rurales as a ruthless and efficient organisation, which seldom took prisoners under the notorious ley fuga and inevitably got its man, was deliberately fostered under the Porfirian regime. However, research during the 1970s involving detailed examination of the records of the corps indicated that the Rurales were neither as effective nor as brutal as regime publicists had suggested. Never numbering more than about 4,000 men located in small detachments, the Rurales were too thinly spread to ever completely eliminate unrest in the Mexican countryside. They did however impose a superficial order, especially in the central regions around Mexico City, which encouraged the foreign investment sought by Díaz and his científico advisers . To a certain extent the regime saw the Rurales as a counterweight to the much larger Federal army and in the later years of the regime they were increasingly used to control industrial unrest, in addition to their traditional task of patrolling country areas.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_MINOA_XIFOS_PEDIA">[TAB]The archeological evidence shows presence of huge watchtowers and warlike longboats from the Minoan era. However, there is no evidence of real war or any type of standing army in the Minoan Civilzation. It is possible that these were all elements to show status among the Minoan City States. Still the Minoans housed remerkable smith skills and Minoan smiths were renowned in the classical world and many of them worked abroud in Mainland Greece.[PARAGRAPH:1](Wikipedia: Minoan Civilization)</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_MOCHE_JEQUE_PEDIA">[TAB] Moche settlements in the Jequetepeque Valley were characterized by fortifications and defensive works. While there is no evidence of a foreign invasion, as many scholars have suggested in the past (i.e. a Huari invasion), there is some evidence of social unrest, possibly the result of climatic changes as factions fought for control over scarce resources. </string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_MOUNTIE_PEDIA">[TAB]The Royal Canadian Mounted Police was organized as the Northwest Mounted Police to bring law and order to the Canadian West.  In 1920, the name was changed to its present title.  The corps gained a romantic reputation for daring missions and persistence in trailing criminals.  The force originally numbered to 300 men and came to be known as Red Coats, Riders of the Plains, and, most commonly, Mounties.  The force later absorbed the provincial police forces of the all the territories and provinces except Quebec and Ontario.  It enforces all federal and provincial laws and takes part in selected international peacekeeping activities.  The force currently numbers to about 16,000.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_MUTAPA_ROZVI_PEDIA">[TAB]In 1693 the Portuguese were defeated by the Rozwi. The Rozwi were formed from several Shona states that dominated the plateau of present-day Zimbabwe at the time. The Portuguese were driven off the central plateau and only retained a nominal presence at one of the fairs in the eastern highlands. The whole of present-day Zimbabwe was brought under the control of Changamire and became known as the Rozwi Empire. This fierce tribe of warriors was to be known as the Rozvi people and after driving the Portuguese out of the area, went on to establish the Rozvi Empire.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_NEWZEALAND_DIGGER_PEDIA">[TAB]Digger is New Zealand and Australian military slang term for soldiers from New Zealand and Australia. It originated during World War I. There are numerous theories about the origin of the term. Before the war, the term \"digger\" had been widely used in Australasia to mean a miner, or a Kauri gum-digger in New Zealand. On 25 April 1915, General Sir Ian Hamilton sent a message to the commander of the Australian and New Zealand Army Corps (ANZAC), General William Birdwood, following the landing at Gallipoli. It contained the postscript: \"P.S.-You have got through the difficult business, now you have only to dig, dig, dig, until you are safe.\"</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_NIGERIA_NAARTILLERY_PEDIA">[TAB]The NA Divisions are supported by Combat Support Arms namely; artillery, engineers and signals. The type of support they provide and the sizes of the supported formation determine the size and composition of each support arm. The NA Artillery is divided into field and air defence artillery based on the roles they perform. The artillery acquires targets, coordinates all fire power resources available and delivers such firepower in the battlefield so that the enemy can neither interfere with our operations from air and ground nor develop its own resources effectively.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_NORWAY_HERSIR_PEDIA">[TAB]A hersir was a local military commander of a hundred and owed allegiance to a jarl or king. They were also aspiring landowners, and, like the middle class in many feudal societies, supported the kings in their centralization of power. The hersir was often equipped with a conical helmet and a short mail coat. Most would wield an iron sword, mostly augmented with a wooden shield. They were also known to wield one- or even two-handed axes. The hersir would always fight on foot, usually as part of a shield wall formation. Another formation was also used, the Svinfylking, which was a variation to the shield wall but with several wedge like formations pointing towards the enemy creating a zig zag pattern. Although excellent against other foot troops the Vikings were frequently defeated by mounted troops.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_OLMEC_BLACKAXE_PEDIA">[TAB]Obsidian was used by American Indians and many other primitive peoples for weapons, implements, tools, and ornaments and by the ancient Aztecs, Olmecs and Greeks for mirrors. Because of its conchoidal fracture (smooth curved surfaces and sharp edges), the sharpest stone artifacts were fashioned from obsidian; some of these, mostly arrowheads, have been dated by means of the hydration rinds that form on. Meso-American cultures often employed jade, flint and obsidian in the crafting of items of warfare, ritual and ceremony. The Omlecs used obsidian to create black axes, often polished with flint handles.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_PAKISTAN_SSG_PEDIA">[TAB]Special Services Group (SSG) is an independent commando brigade of the Pakistan Army. It is an elite special operations force similar to the ,Special Air Service and United States Army Special Forces(Green Berets). Official numbers are put at 2,100 men, in 3 Battalions; however the actual strength is classified. It is estimated to have been increased to 4 Battalions, with the eventual formation of 2 Brigades of Special Forces (6 Battalions).</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_PHILIPPINES_KATIPUNEROS_PEDIA">[TAB]The Katipunan (also known as the Katipuneros) was a Philippine revolutionary organization founded by Filipino rebels in Manila, in 1892, which aimed to gain independence from Spain. The word \"Katipunan\" comes from the root word \"tipon\", an indigenous Tagalog word, meaning: \"society\" or \"gather\". Its official revolutionary meanings are translated as Kataas-taasang, Kagalang-galangang Katipunan ng mga Anak ng Bayan (Supreme and Venerable Society of the Children of the Nation). The word were used by Filipino revolutionary rebel leaders. The word were used by Filipino revolutionary rebel leaders. Katipunan is also known by its acronym, KKK (not to be mistaken with the \"Ku Klux Klan\").[PARAGRAPH:1]The KKK had 3 kinds of members. The Katipon (member), the Kawal (soldier), and the Bayani (hero). Each kind of member has different passwords that are secretly used for passage during meetings or entering hideouts.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_PHOENICIA_BIREME_PEDIA">[TAB]The bireme was introduced by the Phoenicians around 800 BC and became the leading warship of the Mediterranean world in the centuries to follow.[PARAGRAPH:1]The Phoenicians were astute naval architects. They lowered the platforms where the oarsmen were seated (crinolines) to increase vessel stability. The battering ram was covered in bronze. The decorative poop was bent and resembled the tail of a scorpion. The balustrade of the battle platform was covered with the shields of warriors, the bireme was thus partially covered in a primitive 'armor'. These war biremes were typically 30 meters in length and 5 meters wide. Phoenicians were the finest seamen of their time, and were often employed as mercenaries.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_PICTS_CRUITHNI_PEDIA">[TAB]The Romans called this pre-Celtic people Pictii, or \"Painted,\" although Claudius' words are proof that (as claimed by many historians), the ancient Picts actually tattooed their bodies with designs. To the non-Roman Celtic world of Scots and Irish and the many tribes of Belgic England and Wales they were known as \"Cruithni\" and for many centuries they represented the unbridled fury of a people who refused to be brought under the yoke of Rome or any foreign invader.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_PILIWNI_GHOSTDANCER_PEDIA">[TAB]The Ghost Dance is a millennialist spiritual movement among Native Americans in the United States that began toward the end of 1888 and reached its peak just before the Wounded Knee Massacre of 1890. Although the religion is still practiced, it enjoyed only a short period of popularity. Believers in the Ghost Dance spirituality are convinced that performing the Ghost Dance will eventually reunite them with their ancestors coming by railway from the spirit world. The ancestor spirits are called upon to heal the sick and to help protect Mother Earth. Meanwhile, the world will return to a primordial state of natural beauty, opening up to swallow up all other those who do not have a strong spirituality based upon the earth.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_SCYTHIA_SCYTHIAN_RIDER_PEDIA">[TAB]These nomadic tribes live for war. War, and horses. A Scythian rider will drink the blood of their first kill as a right of passage. They scalp their victims and wear their skin like handkerchiefs as a sign of status in their tribe. They're even known to flay an entire enemy and use their hide as a cloak, or as a cover for their quivers. In fact, if a Scythian tribesman doesn't make a kill during a given year, they're left out of their main annual ceremony, where warriors drink wine from the gilded skulls of their enemies.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_SELJUK_GHULAM_WARRIOR_PEDIA">[TAB]The Ghulam warriors were slave-soldiers in service of kings and generals throughout the Turkish and Persian Empires of the Medieval and Early Modern eras. Since the break-up of the Abbasid Caliphate, the Ghulam were grouped into whole armies. They were usually Turkic in origin and fought as cavalrymen. The Ghulam seem to have lived celibate lives. The absence of family life and offspring was one of the reasons why Ghulam, even when attaining power, generally failed to start dynasties or proclaim their independence. The only exception to this was the Ghaznavid dynasty of Afghanistan, which originated amongst the Ghulam of the Samanid dynasty.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_SOMALIA_GUULWADAYAAL_PEDIA">[TAB]In August 1972, the government established the People's Militia, known as the Victory Pioneers (Guulwadayaal). Although a wing of the army, the militia worked under the supervision of the Political Bureau of the presidency. After the SRSP's formation in 1976, the militia became part of the party apparatus. Largely because of the need for military reserves, militia membership increased from 2,500 in 1977 to about 10,000 in 1979, and to approximately 20,000 by 1990. After the collapse of Siad Barre's regime, the People's Militia, like other military elements, disintegrated. </string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_SOUTHAFRICA_BOERCOMMANDO_PEDIA">[TAB]Guerrilla tactics were used extensively by the forces of the Afrikaner republics in the Second Boer War in South Africa 1899-1902. After the British defeated the Boer armies in conventional warfare and occupied their capitals of Pretoria and Bloemfontein, Boer commandos reverted to mobile warfare. Units led by leaders such as Christian de Wet harassed slow-moving British columns and attacked railway lines and encampments. The Boers were almost all mounted and possessed long range magazine loaded rifles. This gave them the ability to attack quickly and cause many casualties before retreating rapidly when British reinforcements arrived. In the early period of the guerrilla war, Boer commandoes could be very large, containing several thousand men and even field artillery. However, as their supplies of food and ammunition gave out, the Boers increasingly broke up into smaller units and relied on captured British arms and ammunition.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_SPEAR_ELEPHANT_PEDIA">[TAB]The Champa warriors used elephants as their main battle force.  The Champa placed a single warrior atop a platform on the elephant's back.  The warrior would weild a spear or shoot arrows at his enemies.  The Cham armies are regarded as being warlike and cruel.  A Chinese writer described a troop of Cham imperial guards who fought with bows made of bamboo, crossbows, javelins, and spears who rode elephants into battle.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_SWISS_HELLEBARDIER_PEDIA">[TAB]During the Late Middle Ages, mercenary forces grew in importance in Europe, as veterans from the Hundred Years War and other conflicts came to see soldiering as a profession rather than a temporary activity, and commanders sought long-term professionals rather than temporary feudal levies to fight their wars. Swiss mercenaries (Reisläufer) were valued throughout Late Medieval Europe for the power of their determined mass attack in deep columns with the pike and halberd. Hiring them was made even more attractive because entire ready-made Swiss mercenary contingents could be obtained by simply contracting with their local governments, the various Swiss cantonsthe cantons had a form of militia system in which the soldiers were bound to serve and were trained and equipped to do so. It should be noted, however, that the Swiss also hired themselves out individually or in small bands.[PARAGRAPH:1]The warriors of the Swiss cantons had gradually developed a reputation throughout Europe as skilled soldiers, due to their successful defense of their liberties against their Austrian Habsburg overlords, starting as early as the late thirteenth century, including such remarkable upset victories over heavily-armoured knights as Morgarten and Laupen. This was furthered by later successful campaigns of regional expansion (mainly into Italy). By the fifteenth century they were greatly valued as mercenary soldiers, particularly following their series of notable victories in the Burgundian Wars in the latter part of the century. As a result, bands of men, sometime acting independently, other times under the banners of their cantons, marched off to foreign lands to fight in the causes of others, for pay. The native term Reisläufer literally means \"one who goes to war\" and is derived from Middle High German Reise, meaning \"military campaign.\"[PARAGRAPH:1]The Swiss, with their head-down attack in huge columns with the long pike, refusal to take prisoners, and consistent record of victory, were greatly feared and admiredfor instance, Machiavelli addresses their system of combat at length in The Prince. The Valois Kings of France, in fact, considered it a virtual impossibility to take the field of battle without Swiss pikemen as the infantry core of their armies. (Although often referred to as \"pikemen,\" the Swiss mercenary units also contained halberdiers  as well until several decades into the sixteenth century, as well as a small number of skirmishers armed with crossbows or crude firearms to precede the rapid advance of the attack column.)[PARAGRAPH:1]The young men who went off to fight, and sometimes die, in foreign service had several incentiveslimited economic options in the still largely-rural cantons; adventure; pride in the reputation of the Swiss as soldiers; and finally what military historian Sir Charles Oman describes as a pure love of combat and warfighting in and of itself, forged by two centuries of conflict.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_THORAKITAI_PEDIA">[TAB]The Seleukidoi took to the thureophoroi and went one better, armoring their improved unit to the teeth and giving him a longer spear with a wider blade. These men are exceedingly well trained and often can make the difference in any battle simply by making their fearsome appearance known. They carry theuros shields with silver medusa heads emblazoned on the front and wear helmets that are strengthened with mail 'veils', making their appearance even more fearsome. As if this was not enough, they carry heavy javelins to break enemy lines and long spears to drive the charge home when they are finished with their javelin throwing. They fight in an organized formation, but not in a phalanx, and are thus more mobile than the Phalanx. They are the best and fittest men within the Hypastistai and are often able to break an enemy line. They have no real weakness in battle, but are extremely expensive to maintain, so their numbers are always few and far between. They should be used as an elite shock infantry, because this is the role for which they were made. They should be well supported, because if these hardy and grizzled veterans rout, it could induce the rest of the army to do so as well![NEWLINE][TAB]Historically, the Seleukidos Thorakitai Argyraspidai were a small elite unit of the Hypastistai that were the leaders of an infantry charge. Their heavy armor was elaborate and expensive, making their numbers never more than one thousand (among six thousand Hypastistai). They were used during many battles, but were notoriously absent from Raphia due to their being refitted after a battle with rebels supported by the Parthai. They slowly dwindled in number as the kingdom's finances did the same. They were no longer a factor when the Seleukidod king fought the Romaioi in Makedonia, a battle at which they would have been very much appreciated. If a capable ruler were to take the Seleukidos throne and carefully manage the kingdom's finances, perhaps he could utilize these fine soldiers far longer than happened historically.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_TIMURID_BARLAS_PEDIA">[TAB]The Barlas were a Turko-Mongol nomadic confederation of Central Asia and the chief tribe of the Timurid emperors who ruled much of Central Asia, Iran, and South Asia in the Middle Ages. The Barlas were descendants of the Mongol warlord Bodonchir who was also considered the direct ancestor of Genghis Khan. The Turko-Mongol conqueror Timur was from a noble family of the Barlas clan.[PARAGRAPH:1]The Mughal Empire of South Asia was founded by Zahir ud-din Muhammad Babur, a descendent of the Timurids. The Barlas family name is used by the descendents of Mughals in Pakistan.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_TROY_GUARD_PEDIA">[TAB]The Apollonian Guard was a unit of the Trojan Army, named after the largest and most important gate of Troy, the Apallonian Gate, and were noted as some of the greatest and most experienced soldiers of the Trojans. These soldiers were usually put into the front-line of battles, and were noted to be a unit of perfection in javelin-throwing and horse-riding. They were led solely by Poludamas, an important general and military advisor of King Priam, and a lueitenant and friend of Hector. Much of the unit was destroyed in the first battle of the Trojan War, when Hector and Poludamas led the Apallonian Guard against Achilles and his elite soldiers when they raided the Grand Temple of Apollo, the patron god of Troy. The rest were wiped out in a final stand at the Citadel of Troy, the area were the palace, temples and the Towers of Ilium laid. There Poludamas died, seven days after Hector's death at the hands of Achilles, and directly before Paris, also known as Alexandros, killed Achilles in the Gardens of Troy, and then was killed in combat, then afterwards Helen did a whorish act, and took of her top to seduce King Meneleus of Sparta, her ex-husband, to spare her.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_TUPI_TOMOIO_PEDIA">[TAB]The Tomoios are one of many tribes that make up the Tupi family. Like other natives from the region, they were assimilated, enslaved or simply exterminated by Portuguese and Spanish settlers, nearly leading to their complete annihilation, with the exception of a few isolated communities. The remnants of these tribes are today confined to indigenous reservations or acculturated to some degree into the dominant society. The Tomoios were a formidable presence within the Amazon rain forests when the Poruguese first arrived in Brazil.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_UYGHUR_ALTAICRIDER_PEDIA">[TAB]Uyghur history is the story of an obscure nomadic tribe from the Altai Mountains rising to challenge the Chinese Empire and ultimately becoming the diplomatic arm of the Mongol invasion. The ancestors of the Uyghur include the nomadic Gaoche people and possibly the Tocharian peoples of the Tarim Basin. The Uyghur participated in a coalition of Tiele under the leadership of the Syr-Tardush tribe, who allied with the Chinese Sui Empire in 603 to defeat Tardu Khan and win their independence. In 744 the Uyghur, together with other related subject tribes (the Basmil and Qarluq), defeated the Gokturk Khanate and founded the Uyghur Empire at Mount Ötüken, which lasted for about 100 years.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_VANATORI_PEDIA">[TAB]The Mountain Hunters are one of the oldest types of units in the Romanian military. This is an \"infantry with special abilities\" branch and it is dedicated to mountain warfare.[NEWLINE][TAB] The Mountain Hunters do not consider themselves \"special forces\". \"We like others to call us that way\", said Lt-Col Cristinel Cernea, commander of the 21st battalion, 2nd Brigade, the most elite Mountain Hunters battalion in the country. The Mountain Hunters are locally called Vanatori de Munte, or VM's for short.[NEWLINE][TAB]On the 3rd of November, 1916, the 1st Mountain Corps was established, opening a very important chapter in the history of this elite branch.  This event was remembered on the 3rd of November 2001, when the Mountain Hunters celebrated 85 years of existence.  The elite branch of the infantry existed in the past as well, however it was in 1916 when they started to be called \"Vanatori de Munte\" (Mountain Hunters) and when their main purpose was set to be fighting in mountainous regions.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_VEDIC_RATHIN_PEDIA">[TAB]The main duty of the king in Vedic civilizations was to protect the tribe. He was aided by two functionaries, the \"purohita\" (chaplain) and the \"senani\" (army chief; \"sena\": army). The former not only gave advice to the ruler but also practiced spells and charms for success in war. Soldiers on foot (\"patti\") and on chariots (\"rathin\"), armed with bow and arrow were common. The king employed \"spasa\" (spies) and \"duta\"s (messengers). He often got a ceremonial gift, \"bali\", from the people. </string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_VIETNAM_VIETCONG_PEDIA">[TAB]The Viet Cong is a special unit for the Vietnamese civilization. Viet Cong were used by the Vietnamese army as a fast-moving military unit that could easily go from place to place in a relatively short amount of time. Their elusiveness (when needed) and their knowledge of the terrain made them extremely difficult fighters. The Viet Cong were also highly motivatived and would endure terrible conditions to keep up the fight against the enemy no matter how long it lasted.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_VYTIS_PEDIA">[TAB] The Vytis, or the Chaser, represents the knight on the Coat of Arms of Lithuania.  Various interpretations about what it represents exist; one being that Vytis represents the Lithuanian god of thunder.  The Vytis may also represent a Lithuanian war god.  The Lithuanian Coat of Arms is one of the oldest coats of arms in Europe, and rather than containing symbols adopted from the coat of arms of dynasties, the symbols are adopted from duke portrait seals.  This greatly differs from the traditional coat of arms of other European countries.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_WELSH_LONGBOWMAN_PEDIA">During the Anglo-Norman invasion of Wales, the Welsh Longbow was put into use.  The English soon learned how powerful this weapon could be, and began to recruit Welsh Longbowmen into their own army.  The Welsh Longbow is most famous for its role in the Battle of Agincourt, and the Hundred Years' War.  The Longbowmen, using the Welsh Longbow, would fire a rain of arrows and the enemy.  The Welsh Longbow was used unil the development of gunpowder.  Overall, the weapon was a powerful type of medieval longbow.  The Welsh Longbow was difficult to master because of its draw weight.  Because of the difficulty, many users of the Welsh Longbow were eventually deformed in their arms and wrists.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_WESTINDIES_JDFENGINEER_PEDIA">[TAB]1 Engineer Regiment (JDF) is a unit of the Jamaica Defence Force primarily responsible for providing military and civil engineering. The regiment was formed in 1992 after a requirement was identified for increased military and civil engineering capability for the JDF than could be provided by the then existing structure. At the time, all JDF engineering capacity was provided by the Construction Squadron and the Engineering Unit of the Support and Services Battalion. The regiment today consists of a total of four distinct sub-units.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_XIONGNU_ELITE_PEDIA">[TAB]In the winter of 200 BC, following a siege of Taiyuan, Emperor Gao of China personally led a military campaign against Modu. At the battle of Baideng, he was ambushed reputedly by 300,000 elite Xiongnu cavalry. The emperor was cut off from supplies and reinforcements for seven days, only narrowly escaping capture.[PARAGRAPH:1]After the defeat at Pingcheng, the Han emperor abandoned a military solution to the Xiongnu threat. Instead, in 198 BC, the courtier Liu Jing was despatched for negotiations. The peace settlement eventually reached between the parties included a Han princess given in marriage to the shanyu (called heqin or \"harmonious kinship\"); periodic gifts of silk, liquor and rice to the Xiongnu; equal status between the states; and the Great Wall as mutual border.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_YEMEN_MAQILWARRIOR_PEDIA">[TAB]The people of the Western Sahara are descended from two known tribes that were the original inhabitants of the territory: the Zenata and the Sanhaja. Beginning in the seventh century, they resisted the invasion of Muslim Arab peoples from the east, but they accepted Islam. Under the influence of Islam, the first unified movement of the population was created, resulting in the establishment of the Almoravid dynasty. At the end of the 13th century, Arab Yeminite people, known as Maqil, invaded the Western Sahara and created a new political and social culture. The Mauritanian Thirty-Year War (1644-74) was the unsuccessful final effort to repel the Yemeni Maqil Arab invaders led by the Beni Hassan tribe. The descendants of the Yemeni Beni Hassan warriors became the upper stratum of Moorish society.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_YORUBA_PEDIA">The Yoruba had their own Art of War. As part of rituals, which the male Yoruba needed to become men, they were trained from their early childhood on to be specialists in disciplines like horseback riding, swimming and hunting.</string>
 <string name="TXT_KEY_UNIT_ZAPOROZHIAN_COSSACK_PEDIA">[TAB]The Zaporozhian Cossacks were Cossacks who lived in Zaporizhya, a region in Central Ukraine.  The Zaporozhian Host grew rapidly in the 15th century by serfs escaping the Polish Lithuanian Commonwealth.  The base and fortress of the Cossacks was the Zaporozhian Sich, which was originally built in the area known as Zaporizhia.  During the course of the 16th, 17th and well into the 18th century, the Zaporozhian Cossacks became a strong political and military forced that challenged the authority of the Poland-Lithuania, the Ottoman Empire and its vassal, the Crimean Khanate, and the Tsardom of Russia.  The Host underwent a sequence of conflicts and alliances involving the three powers before being destroyed in the late 18th century by the Russian Empire.</string>
</resources>
