<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by lcollins (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- Copyright Firaxis Games 2005 -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text - New -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_TIBET_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Tibetan Empire</English>
		<French>Tibet</French>
		<German>Tibetische Reich</German>
		<Italian>Tibetana Impero</Italian>
		<Spanish>Tibetano Imperio</Spanish>
	</TEXT>	
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_TIBET_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Tibet</English>
		<French>Tibétains</French>
		<German>Tibet</German>
		<Italian>Tibet</Italian>
		<Spanish>T&#237;bet</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_TIBET_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Tibetan</English>
    <French>
	    <Text>tibétain:tibétaine:tibétains:tibétaines</Text>
	    <Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
	    <Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
    </French>
		<German>Tibetische</German>
		<Italian>Tibetana</Italian>
		<Spanish>Tibetano</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_TIBET_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]Tibet became a unified kingdom in the seventh century AD under King Songtsen Gampo, a lively ruler whose lineage is traced from the Yarlung Valley.  Songtsen Gampo was not a practicing Buddhist, but his queens, from Nepal and China, built the first Buddhist temple in Lhasa and furnished it with images.  However, Buddhism did not become firmly rooted until the following century, when King Trisong Detsen invited the Indian teacher Shantarakshita to establish Tibet's first Buddhist monastery, which he accomplished with the aid of the compelling Padmasambhava. [PARAGRAPH: 1] The Yarlung Empire fell apart in the ninth century.  Interest in Buddhism remained limited until the tenth century, when Tibetans traveled to India to study and translate sacred texts.  Indian masters also came to Tibet to spread the religion, the most celebrated being Atisha whose arrival in 1042 AD traditionally marks the "Second Propagation" of Buddhism into the country.  Atisha's followers founded the Kadam-pa religious order.  The order stressed the importance of applying the ideals of a bodhisattva in the practitioner's daily life. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Other orders born at this time included the Sakya-pa, which won powerful allies in the Mongol Empire, notably Kublai Khan.  The declining of Mongol influence in the middle of the fourteenth century weakened the Sakya-pa.  A new dynasty, the Pamotrupa, sought to revive the glory of the Yarlung kings, while the discovery of texts "hidden" by Padmasambhava gave fresh momentum to the Nyingma-pa order he had founded. [PARAGRAPH: 1] The most influential scholar and reformer of the time was Tsong Khapa.  His avocation of monastic discipline motivated his disciples to found the Gelug-pa religious order.  The Gelug-pa at first avoided direct involvement in secular matters, but their piety attracted Mongol attention.  In 1578 the Mongol leader Altan Khan gave a prominent Gelug-pa lama the title of Dalai Lama.  Half a century later, with Mongolian assistance, the Dalai Lama became Tibet's sacred and secular leader.  This theocratic system of government survived until 1959, when the communist Chinese drove the fourteenth Dalai Lama into exile.</English>
		<French>[TAB] Tibet est devenu un royaume unifié au septième siècle de notre ère, sous King Songtsen Gampo, un dirigeant dont la lignée animé est tracé de la vallée de Yarlung. Songtsen Gampo n'était pas un pratiquant bouddhiste, mais ses reines, du Népal et de la Chine, a construit le premier temple bouddhiste à Lhassa et meublées avec des images. Toutefois, les bouddhistes ne devienne pas solidement ancrée jusqu'au siècle suivant, lorsque le roi Trisong Detsen invité le professeur indien Shantarakshita Tibet pour établir le premier monastère bouddhiste, qu'il a accompli avec l'aide de la impérieux Padmasambhava. [PARAGRAPH 1] L'empire Yarlung bascule dans le neuvième siècle. L'intérêt pour le bouddhisme est resté limité jusqu'à la dixième siècle, alors que les Tibétains sont rendus en Inde pour étudier et traduire des textes sacrés. Maîtres indiens également venus au Tibet pour répandre la religion, le plus célèbre étant Atisha dont l'arrivée en 1042 AD marque traditionnellement le «deuxième propagation" du bouddhisme dans le pays. Atisha's disciples fonda le Kadam-pa ordre religieux. L'ordonnance a souligné l'importance d'appliquer les idéaux d'un bodhisattva dans le quotidien du praticien. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Autres commandes né à cette époque comprenait la Sakya-pa qui a gagné de puissants alliés dans l'Empire mongol, notamment Kublai Khan. Le déclin de l'influence des Mongols au milieu du XIVe siècle, l'affaiblissement de Sakya-pa. Une nouvelle dynastie, la Pamotrupa, a tenté de raviver la gloire des rois Yarlung, alors que la découverte de textes «cachés» par Padmasambhava a donné un nouvel élan à la Nyingma-pa ordre qu'il avait fondé. [PARAGRAPH 1] Le plus influent érudit et réformateur de l'époque était Tsong Khapa. Son favori de la discipline monastique motivé ses disciples à trouvé le Gelug-pa ordre religieux. Le Gelug-pa évité en première implication directe dans les questions laïques, mais leur piété Mongol attiré l'attention. En 1578 le dirigeant mongol Altan Khan a fait un éminent lama Gelug-pa le titre de Dalaï-Lama. Un demi-siècle plus tard, avec l'aide mongol, le Dalaï Lama du Tibet est devenu sacré et séculier leader. Ce système de gouvernement théocratique survécu jusqu'en 1959, date à laquelle le régime communiste chinois a conduit le quatorzième Dalaï-Lama en exil.</French>
		<German>TAB] Tibet wurde zu einem einheitlichen Königreich im siebten Jahrhundert n. Chr. unter King Songtsen Gampo, eine lebendige Herrscher, dessen Abstammung ist, vom Yarlung-Tal. Songtsen Gampo war kein praktizierender Buddhist, aber seine Königinnen, aus Nepal und China baute das erste buddhistische Tempel in Lhasa eingerichtet und sie mit Bildern. Allerdings, Buddhist nicht zu fest verwurzelt, bis das folgende Jahrhundert, als König Trisong Detsen lud der indischen Lehrer Shantarakshita nach Tibet gründen die erste buddhistische Kloster, das er erreicht mit Hilfe der zwingenden Padmasambhava. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Der Yarlung Reich zerfiel in der neunten Jahrhundert. Interesse am Buddhismus blieb begrenzt bis zum zehnten Jahrhundert, als Tibeter reiste nach Indien zu studieren und heilige Texte zu übersetzen. Indische Meister auch nach Tibet kam, um die Religion, die meisten gefeiert wird Atisha, deren Ankunft in 1042 AD markiert traditionell die "Zweite Verbreitung" des Buddhismus in das Land. Atisha's Kadam Anhänger gründeten die Ordensgemeinschaft-pa. Der Auftrag unterstreicht die Bedeutung der Anwendung der Ideale eines Bodhisattva in den Praktiker-Alltag. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Weitere Aufträge geboren in dieser Zeit auch die Sakya-pa gewonnen, die mächtige Verbündete in der mongolischen Reiches, insbesondere Kublai Khan. Die sinkenden Einfluss der Mongolen in der Mitte des vierzehnten Jahrhunderts schwächte die Sakya-pa. Eine neue Dynastie, die Pamotrupa, wollte wieder den Ruhm des Yarlung-Könige, während die Entdeckung von Texten "versteckt" von Padmasambhava hat frischen Schwung in der Nyingma-pa Damit er gegründet hatte. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Die einflussreichsten Gelehrten und Reformator der Zeit wurde Tsong Khapa. Sein Hobby der klösterlichen Disziplin motiviert seine Jünger zu gründen die Gelug-pa Orden. Die Gelug-pa in der ersten vermieden eine direkte Beteiligung in weltlichen Angelegenheiten, aber ihre Frömmigkeit zog mongolischen Aufmerksamkeit. In 1578 die mongolischen Führer Altan Khan hat eine herausragende Gelug-pa Lama den Titel des Dalai Lama. Ein halbes Jahrhundert später, mit mongolischen Hilfe, der Dalai Lama wurde Tibet's heilige und weltliche Führer. Dieses System der theokratischen Regierung überlebte, bis 1959, als das kommunistische China fuhr der vierzehnten Dalai Lama ins Exil.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB] Tibet divenne un regno unificato nel settimo secolo dC sotto King Songtsen Gampo, un vivace righello lignaggio cui è tracciata dalla Valle di Yarlung. Songtsen Gampo non era un praticante buddista, ma il suo regine, dal Nepal e Cina, costruì il primo tempio buddista a Lhasa e arredato con immagini. Tuttavia, non è diventato buddista saldamente radicato fino al secolo successivo, quando il re Trisong Detsen invitato il maestro indiano Shantarakshita Tibet, per stabilire il primo monastero buddista, che ha compiuto con l'aiuto della Comporre Padmasambhava. [PARAGRAPH: 1] La Yarlung impero è crollato nel nono secolo. Interesse per il buddismo è rimasto limitato fino al decimo secolo, quando i tibetani viaggiato in India per studiare e tradurre i testi sacri. Maestri indiani sono venuti anche in Tibet per diffondere la religione, il più celebrato è Atisha il cui arrivo in 1042 AD tradizionalmente segna la "Seconda Propagazione" del buddismo nel paese. Atisha seguaci fondò la Kadam-pa ordine religioso. L'ordine ha sottolineato l'importanza di applicare gli ideali di un bodhisattva nel praticante della vita quotidiana. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Altri ordini nato in questo momento incluso il Sakya-pa, che ha vinto potenti alleati nella Impero mongolo, in particolare, Kublai Khan. Il declino di influenza mongolo e la metà del XIV secolo indebolito la Sakya-pa. Una nuova dinastia, il Pamotrupa, ha cercato di ravvivare la gloria del Yarlung re, mentre la scoperta di testi "nascosti" da Padmasambhava ha dato nuovo impulso al Nyingma-pa ordine che aveva fondato. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Il più influente studioso e riformatore del tempo è stato Tsong Khapa. La sua vocazione monastica di disciplina motivati i suoi discepoli a trovare il Ghelug-pa ordine religioso. Il Ghelug-ma in primo evitare il coinvolgimento diretto nelle questioni secolari, ma la loro pietà attirato l'attenzione mongolo. Nel 1578 il leader mongolo Altan Khan ha dato un Ghelug-lama, il titolo del Dalai Lama. Mezzo secolo più tardi, con l'assistenza mongolo, il Dalai Lama del Tibet divenne sacra e secolare leader. Questo sistema di governo teocratico sopravvissuto fino al 1959, quando i comunisti cinesi ha spinto il XIV Dalai Lama, in esilio.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB] Tíbet se convirtió en un reino unificado en el siglo VII dC bajo King Songtsen Gampo, un animado gobernante cuyo linaje se remontan desde el valle de Yarlung. Songtsen Gampo no era un practicante budista, pero sus reinas, de Nepal y de China, construyó el primer templo budista en Lhasa y decoradas con imágenes. Sin embargo, no llegó a ser budista firmemente arraigado hasta el siglo siguiente, cuando el Rey Trisong Detsen invitó a la India para establecer profesor Shantarakshita Tíbet el primer monasterio budista, que se realiza con la ayuda de la imperiosa Padmasambhava. [PARAGRAPH: 1] El Yarlung Imperio se vino abajo en el siglo IX. El interés en el budismo sigue siendo limitado hasta el siglo X, cuando los tibetanos viajó a la India para estudiar y traducir los textos sagrados. India maestros también llegó al Tíbet para difundir la religión, la más célebre que se Atisha cuya llegada en 1042 AD tradicionalmente marca el "Segundo de propagación" del budismo en el país. Atisha seguidores fundaron la pa-Kadam orden religiosa. La orden destaca la importancia de la aplicación de los ideales de un bodhisattva en el profesional de la vida cotidiana. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Otras órdenes nacido en este tiempo incluyen la Sakya-pa que ganó poderosos aliados en el Imperio Mongol, en particular Kublai Khan. El declive de la influencia mongol en la mitad del siglo XIV debilitado la Sakya-pa. Una nueva dinastía, la Pamotrupa, trató de revivir la gloria de los reyes Yarlung, mientras que el descubrimiento de los textos "escondidos" por Padmasambhava dio un nuevo impulso a la Nyingma-pa orden que había fundado. [PARAGRAPH: 1] El más influyente erudito y reformador de la época fue Tsong Khapa. Su vocación de la disciplina monástica motivados a sus discípulos para fundar la Gelug-pa orden religiosa. El Gelug-pa evitarse en la primera participación directa en los asuntos seculares, pero su piedad Mongol atraído la atención. En 1578 el líder mongol Altan Khan hizo una prominente Gelug-pa lama el título de Dalai Lama. Medio siglo más tarde, con la asistencia de Mongolia, el Dalai Lama del Tibet se convirtió en sagrado y laico líder. Este sistema de gobierno teocrático sobrevivió hasta 1959, cuando los comunistas chinos llevó el decimocuarto Dalai Lama en el exilio.t</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>	