<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 Beyond the Sword -->
<!-- Modified by the Civ Gold Team -->
<!-- -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_MEGYPT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Mamluk Empire</English>
		<French>Mamluk Empire</French>
		<German>Mamluk Empire</German>
		<Italian>Mamluk Empire</Italian>
		<Spanish>Mamluk Empire</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_MEGYPT_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Mamluks</English>
		<French>Mamluks</French>
		<German>Mamluks</German>
		<Italian>Mamluks</Italian>
		<Spanish>Mamluks</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_MEGYPT_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Mamluk Empire and Modern Egypt[\H1][NEWLINE][NEWLINE][TAB]The Byzantines were able to regain control of the country after a brief Persian invasion early in the 7th century, until in AD 639, Egypt was absorbed into the Islamic Empire by the Muslim Arabs. When they defeated the Byzantine Armies in Egypt, with the help of some revolutionary Egyptians, the Arabs brought Sunni Islam  to the country. Early in this period, Egyptians began to blend their new faith with indigenous beliefs and practices that had survived through Coptic Christianity that was expanded in Egypt by the Byzantines, leading to various Sufi orders that have flourished to this day.  Muslim rulers nominated by the Islamic Caliphate remained in control of Egypt for the next six centuries, with Cairo as the seat of the Caliphate under the Fatimids. With the end of the Kurdish Ayyubid dynasty, the Mamluks, a Turco-Circassian military caste, took control about AD 1250. By late 13th century, Egypt linked the Red Sea, India, Malaya, and East Indies.  The strategic positioning "assured importance in productive economy."  They continued to govern the country until the conquest of Egypt by the Ottoman Turks in 1517, after which it became a province of the Ottoman Empire. The mid-14th-Century Black Death killed about 40% of the country's population.  After the 15th century, the threat of military European Crusaders and Central Asian Mongols set the Egyptian system into decline.  The defensive militarization challenged the civil society and economic institutions. The weakening of the economic system combined with the effects of Black Death left Egypt vulnerable to foreign invasion which can be seen with the Portuguese taking over their trade.  Egypt suffered six famines between 1687 and 1731.  The famine that afflicted Egypt in 1784 cost it roughly one-sixth of its population.

The brief French invasion of Egypt led by Napoleon Bonaparte  began in 1798. The expulsion of the French in 1801 by Ottoman, Mamluk, and British forces was followed by four years of anarchy in which Ottomans, Mamluks, and Albanians who were nominally in the service of the Ottomans, wrestled for power. Out of this chaos, the commander of the Albanian regiment, Muhammad Ali (Kavalali Mehmed Ali Pasha) emerged as a dominant figure and in 1805 was acknowledged by the Sultan in Istanbul as his viceroy  in Egypt; the title implied subordination to the Sultan but this was in fact a polite fiction: Ottoman power in Egypt was finished and Muhammad Ali, an ambitious and able leader, established a dynasty that was to rule Egypt (at first really and later as British puppets) until the revolution of 1952.  His primary focus was military: he annexed Northern Sudan (1820–1824), Syria (1833), and parts of Arabia and Anatolia; but in 1841 the European powers, fearful lest he topple the Ottoman Empire itself, checked him: he had to return most of his conquests to the Ottomans, but he kept the Sudan and his title to Egypt was made hereditary. A more lasting result of his military ambition is that it made him the moderniser of Egypt. Eager to learn the military (and therefore industrial) techniques of the great powers he sent students to the West and invited training missions to Egypt. He built industries, a system of canals for irrigation and transport, and reformed the civil service.  For better or worse, the introduction in 1820 of long-staple cotton, the Egyptian variety of which became famous, transformed Egyptian agriculture into a cash-crop monoculture before the end of the century. The social effects of this were enormous: it led to the concentration of agriculture in the hands of large landowners, and, with the additional trigger of high cotton prices caused by the United States' civil war production drop, to a large influx of foreigners who began in earnest the exploitation of Egypt for international commodity production.  Muhammad Ali was succeeded briefly by his son Ibrahim (in September 1848), then by a grandson Abbas I (in November 1848), then by Said (in 1854), and Isma'il (in 1863). Abbas I was cautious. Said and Ismail were ambitious developers; unfortunately they spent beyond their means. The Suez Canal, built in partnership with the French, was completed in 1869. The cost of this and other projects had two effects: it led to enormous debt to European banks, and caused popular discontent because of the onerous taxation it required. In 1875 Ismail was forced to sell Egypt's share in the canal to the British Government. Within three years this led to the imposition of British and French controllers who sat in the Egyptian cabinet, and, "with the financial power of the bondholders behind them, were the real power in the Government."  Local dissatisfaction with Ismail and with European intrusion led to the formation of the first nationalist groupings in 1879, with Ahmad Urabi a prominent figure. In 1882 he became head of a nationalist-dominated ministry committed to democratic reforms including parliamentary control of the budget. Fearing a diminishment of their control, Britain and France intervened militarily, bombarding Alexandria and crushing the Egyptian army at the battle of Tel el-Kebir.  They reinstalled Ismail's son Tewfik as figurehead of a de facto British protectorate.

In 1914 the Protectorate was made official, and the title of the head of state, which had changed from pasha to khedive in 1867, was changed to sultan, to repudiate the vestigial suzerainty of the Ottoman sultan, who was backing the Central powers in World War I. Abbas II was deposed as khedive and replaced by his uncle, Hussein Kamel, as sultan.  In 1906, the Dinshaway Incident prompted many neutral Egyptians to join the nationalist movement. After the First World War, Saad Zaghlul and the Wafd Party led the Egyptian nationalist movement, gaining a majority at the local Legislative Assembly. When the British exiled Zaghlul and his associates to Malta on 8 March 1919, the country arose in its first modern revolution. Constant revolting by the Egyptian people throughout the country led Great Britain to issue a unilateral declaration of Egypt's independence on 22 February 1922.  The new Egyptian Government drafted and implemented a new constitution in 1923 based on a parliamentary representative system. Saad Zaghlul was popularly elected as Prime Minister of Egypt in 1924. In 1936 the Anglo-Egyptian Treaty  was concluded. Continued instability in the Government due to remaining British control and increasing political involvement by the king led to the ousting of the monarchy and the dissolution of the parliament in a military coup d'état known as the 1952 Revolution. The officers, known as the Free Officers Movement, forced King Farouk to abdicate in support of his son Fuad.  On 18 June 1953, the Egyptian Republic was declared, with General Muhammad Naguib as the first President of the Republic. Naguib was forced to resign in 1954 by Gamal Abdel Nasser – the real architect of the 1952 movement – and was later put under house arrest. Nasser assumed power as President in June 1956. British forces completed their withdrawal from the occupied Suez Canal Zone on 13 June 1956. His nationalization of the Suez Canal on 26 July 1956 prompted the 1956 Suez Crisis.  Three years after the 1967 Six Day War, during which Israel had invaded and occupied Sinai, Nasser died and was succeeded by Anwar Sadat. Sadat switched Egypt's Cold War allegiance from the Soviet Union to the United States, expelling Soviet advisors in 1972. He launched the Infitah economic reform policy, while violently clamping down on religious and secular opposition alike.  In 1973, Egypt, along with Syria, launched the October War, a surprise attack against the Israeli forces occupying the Sinai Peninsula and the Golan Heights. It was an attempt to regain part of the Sinai territory Israel had captured 6 years earlier. Sadat hoped to seize some territory through military force, and then regain the rest of the peninsula by diplomacy. The conflict sparked an international crisis between the two world superpowers: the US and the USSR, both of whom intervened. Two UN-mandated ceasefires were needed to bring military operations to a halt. While the war ended with a military Israeli victory, it presented Sadat with a political victory that later allowed him to regain the Sinai in return for peace with Israel.  Sadat made a historic visit to Israel in 1977, which led to the 1979 peace treaty in exchange for the complete Israeli withdrawal from Sinai. Sadat's initiative sparked enormous controversy in the Arab world and led to Egypt's expulsion from the Arab League, but it was supported by most Egyptians.  A fundamentalist military soldier assassinated Sadat in Cairo in 1981. He was succeeded by the incumbent Hosni Mubarak. In 2003, the Egyptian Movement for Change, popularly known as "Kefaya," was launched to seek a return to democracy and greater civil liberties.
</English>
		<French>[H1]Mamluk Empire and Modern Egypt[\H1][NEWLINE][NEWLINE][TAB]The Byzantines were able to regain control of the country after a brief Persian invasion early in the 7th century, until in AD 639, Egypt was absorbed into the Islamic Empire by the Muslim Arabs. When they defeated the Byzantine Armies in Egypt, with the help of some revolutionary Egyptians, the Arabs brought Sunni Islam  to the country. Early in this period, Egyptians began to blend their new faith with indigenous beliefs and practices that had survived through Coptic Christianity that was expanded in Egypt by the Byzantines, leading to various Sufi orders that have flourished to this day.  Muslim rulers nominated by the Islamic Caliphate remained in control of Egypt for the next six centuries, with Cairo as the seat of the Caliphate under the Fatimids. With the end of the Kurdish Ayyubid dynasty, the Mamluks, a Turco-Circassian military caste, took control about AD 1250. By late 13th century, Egypt linked the Red Sea, India, Malaya, and East Indies.  The strategic positioning "assured importance in productive economy."  They continued to govern the country until the conquest of Egypt by the Ottoman Turks in 1517, after which it became a province of the Ottoman Empire. The mid-14th-Century Black Death killed about 40% of the country's population.  After the 15th century, the threat of military European Crusaders and Central Asian Mongols set the Egyptian system into decline.  The defensive militarization challenged the civil society and economic institutions. The weakening of the economic system combined with the effects of Black Death left Egypt vulnerable to foreign invasion which can be seen with the Portuguese taking over their trade.  Egypt suffered six famines between 1687 and 1731.  The famine that afflicted Egypt in 1784 cost it roughly one-sixth of its population.

The brief French invasion of Egypt led by Napoleon Bonaparte  began in 1798. The expulsion of the French in 1801 by Ottoman, Mamluk, and British forces was followed by four years of anarchy in which Ottomans, Mamluks, and Albanians who were nominally in the service of the Ottomans, wrestled for power. Out of this chaos, the commander of the Albanian regiment, Muhammad Ali (Kavalali Mehmed Ali Pasha) emerged as a dominant figure and in 1805 was acknowledged by the Sultan in Istanbul as his viceroy  in Egypt; the title implied subordination to the Sultan but this was in fact a polite fiction: Ottoman power in Egypt was finished and Muhammad Ali, an ambitious and able leader, established a dynasty that was to rule Egypt (at first really and later as British puppets) until the revolution of 1952.  His primary focus was military: he annexed Northern Sudan (1820–1824), Syria (1833), and parts of Arabia and Anatolia; but in 1841 the European powers, fearful lest he topple the Ottoman Empire itself, checked him: he had to return most of his conquests to the Ottomans, but he kept the Sudan and his title to Egypt was made hereditary. A more lasting result of his military ambition is that it made him the moderniser of Egypt. Eager to learn the military (and therefore industrial) techniques of the great powers he sent students to the West and invited training missions to Egypt. He built industries, a system of canals for irrigation and transport, and reformed the civil service.  For better or worse, the introduction in 1820 of long-staple cotton, the Egyptian variety of which became famous, transformed Egyptian agriculture into a cash-crop monoculture before the end of the century. The social effects of this were enormous: it led to the concentration of agriculture in the hands of large landowners, and, with the additional trigger of high cotton prices caused by the United States' civil war production drop, to a large influx of foreigners who began in earnest the exploitation of Egypt for international commodity production.  Muhammad Ali was succeeded briefly by his son Ibrahim (in September 1848), then by a grandson Abbas I (in November 1848), then by Said (in 1854), and Isma'il (in 1863). Abbas I was cautious. Said and Ismail were ambitious developers; unfortunately they spent beyond their means. The Suez Canal, built in partnership with the French, was completed in 1869. The cost of this and other projects had two effects: it led to enormous debt to European banks, and caused popular discontent because of the onerous taxation it required. In 1875 Ismail was forced to sell Egypt's share in the canal to the British Government. Within three years this led to the imposition of British and French controllers who sat in the Egyptian cabinet, and, "with the financial power of the bondholders behind them, were the real power in the Government."  Local dissatisfaction with Ismail and with European intrusion led to the formation of the first nationalist groupings in 1879, with Ahmad Urabi a prominent figure. In 1882 he became head of a nationalist-dominated ministry committed to democratic reforms including parliamentary control of the budget. Fearing a diminishment of their control, Britain and France intervened militarily, bombarding Alexandria and crushing the Egyptian army at the battle of Tel el-Kebir.  They reinstalled Ismail's son Tewfik as figurehead of a de facto British protectorate.

In 1914 the Protectorate was made official, and the title of the head of state, which had changed from pasha to khedive in 1867, was changed to sultan, to repudiate the vestigial suzerainty of the Ottoman sultan, who was backing the Central powers in World War I. Abbas II was deposed as khedive and replaced by his uncle, Hussein Kamel, as sultan.  In 1906, the Dinshaway Incident prompted many neutral Egyptians to join the nationalist movement. After the First World War, Saad Zaghlul and the Wafd Party led the Egyptian nationalist movement, gaining a majority at the local Legislative Assembly. When the British exiled Zaghlul and his associates to Malta on 8 March 1919, the country arose in its first modern revolution. Constant revolting by the Egyptian people throughout the country led Great Britain to issue a unilateral declaration of Egypt's independence on 22 February 1922.  The new Egyptian Government drafted and implemented a new constitution in 1923 based on a parliamentary representative system. Saad Zaghlul was popularly elected as Prime Minister of Egypt in 1924. In 1936 the Anglo-Egyptian Treaty  was concluded. Continued instability in the Government due to remaining British control and increasing political involvement by the king led to the ousting of the monarchy and the dissolution of the parliament in a military coup d'état known as the 1952 Revolution. The officers, known as the Free Officers Movement, forced King Farouk to abdicate in support of his son Fuad.  On 18 June 1953, the Egyptian Republic was declared, with General Muhammad Naguib as the first President of the Republic. Naguib was forced to resign in 1954 by Gamal Abdel Nasser – the real architect of the 1952 movement – and was later put under house arrest. Nasser assumed power as President in June 1956. British forces completed their withdrawal from the occupied Suez Canal Zone on 13 June 1956. His nationalization of the Suez Canal on 26 July 1956 prompted the 1956 Suez Crisis.  Three years after the 1967 Six Day War, during which Israel had invaded and occupied Sinai, Nasser died and was succeeded by Anwar Sadat. Sadat switched Egypt's Cold War allegiance from the Soviet Union to the United States, expelling Soviet advisors in 1972. He launched the Infitah economic reform policy, while violently clamping down on religious and secular opposition alike.  In 1973, Egypt, along with Syria, launched the October War, a surprise attack against the Israeli forces occupying the Sinai Peninsula and the Golan Heights. It was an attempt to regain part of the Sinai territory Israel had captured 6 years earlier. Sadat hoped to seize some territory through military force, and then regain the rest of the peninsula by diplomacy. The conflict sparked an international crisis between the two world superpowers: the US and the USSR, both of whom intervened. Two UN-mandated ceasefires were needed to bring military operations to a halt. While the war ended with a military Israeli victory, it presented Sadat with a political victory that later allowed him to regain the Sinai in return for peace with Israel.  Sadat made a historic visit to Israel in 1977, which led to the 1979 peace treaty in exchange for the complete Israeli withdrawal from Sinai. Sadat's initiative sparked enormous controversy in the Arab world and led to Egypt's expulsion from the Arab League, but it was supported by most Egyptians.  A fundamentalist military soldier assassinated Sadat in Cairo in 1981. He was succeeded by the incumbent Hosni Mubarak. In 2003, the Egyptian Movement for Change, popularly known as "Kefaya," was launched to seek a return to democracy and greater civil liberties.
</French>
		<German>[H1]Mamluk Empire and Modern Egypt[\H1][NEWLINE][NEWLINE][TAB]The Byzantines were able to regain control of the country after a brief Persian invasion early in the 7th century, until in AD 639, Egypt was absorbed into the Islamic Empire by the Muslim Arabs. When they defeated the Byzantine Armies in Egypt, with the help of some revolutionary Egyptians, the Arabs brought Sunni Islam  to the country. Early in this period, Egyptians began to blend their new faith with indigenous beliefs and practices that had survived through Coptic Christianity that was expanded in Egypt by the Byzantines, leading to various Sufi orders that have flourished to this day.  Muslim rulers nominated by the Islamic Caliphate remained in control of Egypt for the next six centuries, with Cairo as the seat of the Caliphate under the Fatimids. With the end of the Kurdish Ayyubid dynasty, the Mamluks, a Turco-Circassian military caste, took control about AD 1250. By late 13th century, Egypt linked the Red Sea, India, Malaya, and East Indies.  The strategic positioning "assured importance in productive economy."  They continued to govern the country until the conquest of Egypt by the Ottoman Turks in 1517, after which it became a province of the Ottoman Empire. The mid-14th-Century Black Death killed about 40% of the country's population.  After the 15th century, the threat of military European Crusaders and Central Asian Mongols set the Egyptian system into decline.  The defensive militarization challenged the civil society and economic institutions. The weakening of the economic system combined with the effects of Black Death left Egypt vulnerable to foreign invasion which can be seen with the Portuguese taking over their trade.  Egypt suffered six famines between 1687 and 1731.  The famine that afflicted Egypt in 1784 cost it roughly one-sixth of its population.

The brief French invasion of Egypt led by Napoleon Bonaparte  began in 1798. The expulsion of the French in 1801 by Ottoman, Mamluk, and British forces was followed by four years of anarchy in which Ottomans, Mamluks, and Albanians who were nominally in the service of the Ottomans, wrestled for power. Out of this chaos, the commander of the Albanian regiment, Muhammad Ali (Kavalali Mehmed Ali Pasha) emerged as a dominant figure and in 1805 was acknowledged by the Sultan in Istanbul as his viceroy  in Egypt; the title implied subordination to the Sultan but this was in fact a polite fiction: Ottoman power in Egypt was finished and Muhammad Ali, an ambitious and able leader, established a dynasty that was to rule Egypt (at first really and later as British puppets) until the revolution of 1952.  His primary focus was military: he annexed Northern Sudan (1820–1824), Syria (1833), and parts of Arabia and Anatolia; but in 1841 the European powers, fearful lest he topple the Ottoman Empire itself, checked him: he had to return most of his conquests to the Ottomans, but he kept the Sudan and his title to Egypt was made hereditary. A more lasting result of his military ambition is that it made him the moderniser of Egypt. Eager to learn the military (and therefore industrial) techniques of the great powers he sent students to the West and invited training missions to Egypt. He built industries, a system of canals for irrigation and transport, and reformed the civil service.  For better or worse, the introduction in 1820 of long-staple cotton, the Egyptian variety of which became famous, transformed Egyptian agriculture into a cash-crop monoculture before the end of the century. The social effects of this were enormous: it led to the concentration of agriculture in the hands of large landowners, and, with the additional trigger of high cotton prices caused by the United States' civil war production drop, to a large influx of foreigners who began in earnest the exploitation of Egypt for international commodity production.  Muhammad Ali was succeeded briefly by his son Ibrahim (in September 1848), then by a grandson Abbas I (in November 1848), then by Said (in 1854), and Isma'il (in 1863). Abbas I was cautious. Said and Ismail were ambitious developers; unfortunately they spent beyond their means. The Suez Canal, built in partnership with the French, was completed in 1869. The cost of this and other projects had two effects: it led to enormous debt to European banks, and caused popular discontent because of the onerous taxation it required. In 1875 Ismail was forced to sell Egypt's share in the canal to the British Government. Within three years this led to the imposition of British and French controllers who sat in the Egyptian cabinet, and, "with the financial power of the bondholders behind them, were the real power in the Government."  Local dissatisfaction with Ismail and with European intrusion led to the formation of the first nationalist groupings in 1879, with Ahmad Urabi a prominent figure. In 1882 he became head of a nationalist-dominated ministry committed to democratic reforms including parliamentary control of the budget. Fearing a diminishment of their control, Britain and France intervened militarily, bombarding Alexandria and crushing the Egyptian army at the battle of Tel el-Kebir.  They reinstalled Ismail's son Tewfik as figurehead of a de facto British protectorate.

In 1914 the Protectorate was made official, and the title of the head of state, which had changed from pasha to khedive in 1867, was changed to sultan, to repudiate the vestigial suzerainty of the Ottoman sultan, who was backing the Central powers in World War I. Abbas II was deposed as khedive and replaced by his uncle, Hussein Kamel, as sultan.  In 1906, the Dinshaway Incident prompted many neutral Egyptians to join the nationalist movement. After the First World War, Saad Zaghlul and the Wafd Party led the Egyptian nationalist movement, gaining a majority at the local Legislative Assembly. When the British exiled Zaghlul and his associates to Malta on 8 March 1919, the country arose in its first modern revolution. Constant revolting by the Egyptian people throughout the country led Great Britain to issue a unilateral declaration of Egypt's independence on 22 February 1922.  The new Egyptian Government drafted and implemented a new constitution in 1923 based on a parliamentary representative system. Saad Zaghlul was popularly elected as Prime Minister of Egypt in 1924. In 1936 the Anglo-Egyptian Treaty  was concluded. Continued instability in the Government due to remaining British control and increasing political involvement by the king led to the ousting of the monarchy and the dissolution of the parliament in a military coup d'état known as the 1952 Revolution. The officers, known as the Free Officers Movement, forced King Farouk to abdicate in support of his son Fuad.  On 18 June 1953, the Egyptian Republic was declared, with General Muhammad Naguib as the first President of the Republic. Naguib was forced to resign in 1954 by Gamal Abdel Nasser – the real architect of the 1952 movement – and was later put under house arrest. Nasser assumed power as President in June 1956. British forces completed their withdrawal from the occupied Suez Canal Zone on 13 June 1956. His nationalization of the Suez Canal on 26 July 1956 prompted the 1956 Suez Crisis.  Three years after the 1967 Six Day War, during which Israel had invaded and occupied Sinai, Nasser died and was succeeded by Anwar Sadat. Sadat switched Egypt's Cold War allegiance from the Soviet Union to the United States, expelling Soviet advisors in 1972. He launched the Infitah economic reform policy, while violently clamping down on religious and secular opposition alike.  In 1973, Egypt, along with Syria, launched the October War, a surprise attack against the Israeli forces occupying the Sinai Peninsula and the Golan Heights. It was an attempt to regain part of the Sinai territory Israel had captured 6 years earlier. Sadat hoped to seize some territory through military force, and then regain the rest of the peninsula by diplomacy. The conflict sparked an international crisis between the two world superpowers: the US and the USSR, both of whom intervened. Two UN-mandated ceasefires were needed to bring military operations to a halt. While the war ended with a military Israeli victory, it presented Sadat with a political victory that later allowed him to regain the Sinai in return for peace with Israel.  Sadat made a historic visit to Israel in 1977, which led to the 1979 peace treaty in exchange for the complete Israeli withdrawal from Sinai. Sadat's initiative sparked enormous controversy in the Arab world and led to Egypt's expulsion from the Arab League, but it was supported by most Egyptians.  A fundamentalist military soldier assassinated Sadat in Cairo in 1981. He was succeeded by the incumbent Hosni Mubarak. In 2003, the Egyptian Movement for Change, popularly known as "Kefaya," was launched to seek a return to democracy and greater civil liberties.
</German>
		<Italian>[H1]Mamluk Empire and Modern Egypt[\H1][NEWLINE][NEWLINE][TAB]The Byzantines were able to regain control of the country after a brief Persian invasion early in the 7th century, until in AD 639, Egypt was absorbed into the Islamic Empire by the Muslim Arabs. When they defeated the Byzantine Armies in Egypt, with the help of some revolutionary Egyptians, the Arabs brought Sunni Islam  to the country. Early in this period, Egyptians began to blend their new faith with indigenous beliefs and practices that had survived through Coptic Christianity that was expanded in Egypt by the Byzantines, leading to various Sufi orders that have flourished to this day.  Muslim rulers nominated by the Islamic Caliphate remained in control of Egypt for the next six centuries, with Cairo as the seat of the Caliphate under the Fatimids. With the end of the Kurdish Ayyubid dynasty, the Mamluks, a Turco-Circassian military caste, took control about AD 1250. By late 13th century, Egypt linked the Red Sea, India, Malaya, and East Indies.  The strategic positioning "assured importance in productive economy."  They continued to govern the country until the conquest of Egypt by the Ottoman Turks in 1517, after which it became a province of the Ottoman Empire. The mid-14th-Century Black Death killed about 40% of the country's population.  After the 15th century, the threat of military European Crusaders and Central Asian Mongols set the Egyptian system into decline.  The defensive militarization challenged the civil society and economic institutions. The weakening of the economic system combined with the effects of Black Death left Egypt vulnerable to foreign invasion which can be seen with the Portuguese taking over their trade.  Egypt suffered six famines between 1687 and 1731.  The famine that afflicted Egypt in 1784 cost it roughly one-sixth of its population.

The brief French invasion of Egypt led by Napoleon Bonaparte  began in 1798. The expulsion of the French in 1801 by Ottoman, Mamluk, and British forces was followed by four years of anarchy in which Ottomans, Mamluks, and Albanians who were nominally in the service of the Ottomans, wrestled for power. Out of this chaos, the commander of the Albanian regiment, Muhammad Ali (Kavalali Mehmed Ali Pasha) emerged as a dominant figure and in 1805 was acknowledged by the Sultan in Istanbul as his viceroy  in Egypt; the title implied subordination to the Sultan but this was in fact a polite fiction: Ottoman power in Egypt was finished and Muhammad Ali, an ambitious and able leader, established a dynasty that was to rule Egypt (at first really and later as British puppets) until the revolution of 1952.  His primary focus was military: he annexed Northern Sudan (1820–1824), Syria (1833), and parts of Arabia and Anatolia; but in 1841 the European powers, fearful lest he topple the Ottoman Empire itself, checked him: he had to return most of his conquests to the Ottomans, but he kept the Sudan and his title to Egypt was made hereditary. A more lasting result of his military ambition is that it made him the moderniser of Egypt. Eager to learn the military (and therefore industrial) techniques of the great powers he sent students to the West and invited training missions to Egypt. He built industries, a system of canals for irrigation and transport, and reformed the civil service.  For better or worse, the introduction in 1820 of long-staple cotton, the Egyptian variety of which became famous, transformed Egyptian agriculture into a cash-crop monoculture before the end of the century. The social effects of this were enormous: it led to the concentration of agriculture in the hands of large landowners, and, with the additional trigger of high cotton prices caused by the United States' civil war production drop, to a large influx of foreigners who began in earnest the exploitation of Egypt for international commodity production.  Muhammad Ali was succeeded briefly by his son Ibrahim (in September 1848), then by a grandson Abbas I (in November 1848), then by Said (in 1854), and Isma'il (in 1863). Abbas I was cautious. Said and Ismail were ambitious developers; unfortunately they spent beyond their means. The Suez Canal, built in partnership with the French, was completed in 1869. The cost of this and other projects had two effects: it led to enormous debt to European banks, and caused popular discontent because of the onerous taxation it required. In 1875 Ismail was forced to sell Egypt's share in the canal to the British Government. Within three years this led to the imposition of British and French controllers who sat in the Egyptian cabinet, and, "with the financial power of the bondholders behind them, were the real power in the Government."  Local dissatisfaction with Ismail and with European intrusion led to the formation of the first nationalist groupings in 1879, with Ahmad Urabi a prominent figure. In 1882 he became head of a nationalist-dominated ministry committed to democratic reforms including parliamentary control of the budget. Fearing a diminishment of their control, Britain and France intervened militarily, bombarding Alexandria and crushing the Egyptian army at the battle of Tel el-Kebir.  They reinstalled Ismail's son Tewfik as figurehead of a de facto British protectorate.

In 1914 the Protectorate was made official, and the title of the head of state, which had changed from pasha to khedive in 1867, was changed to sultan, to repudiate the vestigial suzerainty of the Ottoman sultan, who was backing the Central powers in World War I. Abbas II was deposed as khedive and replaced by his uncle, Hussein Kamel, as sultan.  In 1906, the Dinshaway Incident prompted many neutral Egyptians to join the nationalist movement. After the First World War, Saad Zaghlul and the Wafd Party led the Egyptian nationalist movement, gaining a majority at the local Legislative Assembly. When the British exiled Zaghlul and his associates to Malta on 8 March 1919, the country arose in its first modern revolution. Constant revolting by the Egyptian people throughout the country led Great Britain to issue a unilateral declaration of Egypt's independence on 22 February 1922.  The new Egyptian Government drafted and implemented a new constitution in 1923 based on a parliamentary representative system. Saad Zaghlul was popularly elected as Prime Minister of Egypt in 1924. In 1936 the Anglo-Egyptian Treaty  was concluded. Continued instability in the Government due to remaining British control and increasing political involvement by the king led to the ousting of the monarchy and the dissolution of the parliament in a military coup d'état known as the 1952 Revolution. The officers, known as the Free Officers Movement, forced King Farouk to abdicate in support of his son Fuad.  On 18 June 1953, the Egyptian Republic was declared, with General Muhammad Naguib as the first President of the Republic. Naguib was forced to resign in 1954 by Gamal Abdel Nasser – the real architect of the 1952 movement – and was later put under house arrest. Nasser assumed power as President in June 1956. British forces completed their withdrawal from the occupied Suez Canal Zone on 13 June 1956. His nationalization of the Suez Canal on 26 July 1956 prompted the 1956 Suez Crisis.  Three years after the 1967 Six Day War, during which Israel had invaded and occupied Sinai, Nasser died and was succeeded by Anwar Sadat. Sadat switched Egypt's Cold War allegiance from the Soviet Union to the United States, expelling Soviet advisors in 1972. He launched the Infitah economic reform policy, while violently clamping down on religious and secular opposition alike.  In 1973, Egypt, along with Syria, launched the October War, a surprise attack against the Israeli forces occupying the Sinai Peninsula and the Golan Heights. It was an attempt to regain part of the Sinai territory Israel had captured 6 years earlier. Sadat hoped to seize some territory through military force, and then regain the rest of the peninsula by diplomacy. The conflict sparked an international crisis between the two world superpowers: the US and the USSR, both of whom intervened. Two UN-mandated ceasefires were needed to bring military operations to a halt. While the war ended with a military Israeli victory, it presented Sadat with a political victory that later allowed him to regain the Sinai in return for peace with Israel.  Sadat made a historic visit to Israel in 1977, which led to the 1979 peace treaty in exchange for the complete Israeli withdrawal from Sinai. Sadat's initiative sparked enormous controversy in the Arab world and led to Egypt's expulsion from the Arab League, but it was supported by most Egyptians.  A fundamentalist military soldier assassinated Sadat in Cairo in 1981. He was succeeded by the incumbent Hosni Mubarak. In 2003, the Egyptian Movement for Change, popularly known as "Kefaya," was launched to seek a return to democracy and greater civil liberties.
</Italian>
		<Spanish>[H1]Mamluk Empire and Modern Egypt[\H1][NEWLINE][NEWLINE][TAB]The Byzantines were able to regain control of the country after a brief Persian invasion early in the 7th century, until in AD 639, Egypt was absorbed into the Islamic Empire by the Muslim Arabs. When they defeated the Byzantine Armies in Egypt, with the help of some revolutionary Egyptians, the Arabs brought Sunni Islam  to the country. Early in this period, Egyptians began to blend their new faith with indigenous beliefs and practices that had survived through Coptic Christianity that was expanded in Egypt by the Byzantines, leading to various Sufi orders that have flourished to this day.  Muslim rulers nominated by the Islamic Caliphate remained in control of Egypt for the next six centuries, with Cairo as the seat of the Caliphate under the Fatimids. With the end of the Kurdish Ayyubid dynasty, the Mamluks, a Turco-Circassian military caste, took control about AD 1250. By late 13th century, Egypt linked the Red Sea, India, Malaya, and East Indies.  The strategic positioning "assured importance in productive economy."  They continued to govern the country until the conquest of Egypt by the Ottoman Turks in 1517, after which it became a province of the Ottoman Empire. The mid-14th-Century Black Death killed about 40% of the country's population.  After the 15th century, the threat of military European Crusaders and Central Asian Mongols set the Egyptian system into decline.  The defensive militarization challenged the civil society and economic institutions. The weakening of the economic system combined with the effects of Black Death left Egypt vulnerable to foreign invasion which can be seen with the Portuguese taking over their trade.  Egypt suffered six famines between 1687 and 1731.  The famine that afflicted Egypt in 1784 cost it roughly one-sixth of its population.

The brief French invasion of Egypt led by Napoleon Bonaparte  began in 1798. The expulsion of the French in 1801 by Ottoman, Mamluk, and British forces was followed by four years of anarchy in which Ottomans, Mamluks, and Albanians who were nominally in the service of the Ottomans, wrestled for power. Out of this chaos, the commander of the Albanian regiment, Muhammad Ali (Kavalali Mehmed Ali Pasha) emerged as a dominant figure and in 1805 was acknowledged by the Sultan in Istanbul as his viceroy  in Egypt; the title implied subordination to the Sultan but this was in fact a polite fiction: Ottoman power in Egypt was finished and Muhammad Ali, an ambitious and able leader, established a dynasty that was to rule Egypt (at first really and later as British puppets) until the revolution of 1952.  His primary focus was military: he annexed Northern Sudan (1820–1824), Syria (1833), and parts of Arabia and Anatolia; but in 1841 the European powers, fearful lest he topple the Ottoman Empire itself, checked him: he had to return most of his conquests to the Ottomans, but he kept the Sudan and his title to Egypt was made hereditary. A more lasting result of his military ambition is that it made him the moderniser of Egypt. Eager to learn the military (and therefore industrial) techniques of the great powers he sent students to the West and invited training missions to Egypt. He built industries, a system of canals for irrigation and transport, and reformed the civil service.  For better or worse, the introduction in 1820 of long-staple cotton, the Egyptian variety of which became famous, transformed Egyptian agriculture into a cash-crop monoculture before the end of the century. The social effects of this were enormous: it led to the concentration of agriculture in the hands of large landowners, and, with the additional trigger of high cotton prices caused by the United States' civil war production drop, to a large influx of foreigners who began in earnest the exploitation of Egypt for international commodity production.  Muhammad Ali was succeeded briefly by his son Ibrahim (in September 1848), then by a grandson Abbas I (in November 1848), then by Said (in 1854), and Isma'il (in 1863). Abbas I was cautious. Said and Ismail were ambitious developers; unfortunately they spent beyond their means. The Suez Canal, built in partnership with the French, was completed in 1869. The cost of this and other projects had two effects: it led to enormous debt to European banks, and caused popular discontent because of the onerous taxation it required. In 1875 Ismail was forced to sell Egypt's share in the canal to the British Government. Within three years this led to the imposition of British and French controllers who sat in the Egyptian cabinet, and, "with the financial power of the bondholders behind them, were the real power in the Government."  Local dissatisfaction with Ismail and with European intrusion led to the formation of the first nationalist groupings in 1879, with Ahmad Urabi a prominent figure. In 1882 he became head of a nationalist-dominated ministry committed to democratic reforms including parliamentary control of the budget. Fearing a diminishment of their control, Britain and France intervened militarily, bombarding Alexandria and crushing the Egyptian army at the battle of Tel el-Kebir.  They reinstalled Ismail's son Tewfik as figurehead of a de facto British protectorate.

In 1914 the Protectorate was made official, and the title of the head of state, which had changed from pasha to khedive in 1867, was changed to sultan, to repudiate the vestigial suzerainty of the Ottoman sultan, who was backing the Central powers in World War I. Abbas II was deposed as khedive and replaced by his uncle, Hussein Kamel, as sultan.  In 1906, the Dinshaway Incident prompted many neutral Egyptians to join the nationalist movement. After the First World War, Saad Zaghlul and the Wafd Party led the Egyptian nationalist movement, gaining a majority at the local Legislative Assembly. When the British exiled Zaghlul and his associates to Malta on 8 March 1919, the country arose in its first modern revolution. Constant revolting by the Egyptian people throughout the country led Great Britain to issue a unilateral declaration of Egypt's independence on 22 February 1922.  The new Egyptian Government drafted and implemented a new constitution in 1923 based on a parliamentary representative system. Saad Zaghlul was popularly elected as Prime Minister of Egypt in 1924. In 1936 the Anglo-Egyptian Treaty  was concluded. Continued instability in the Government due to remaining British control and increasing political involvement by the king led to the ousting of the monarchy and the dissolution of the parliament in a military coup d'état known as the 1952 Revolution. The officers, known as the Free Officers Movement, forced King Farouk to abdicate in support of his son Fuad.  On 18 June 1953, the Egyptian Republic was declared, with General Muhammad Naguib as the first President of the Republic. Naguib was forced to resign in 1954 by Gamal Abdel Nasser – the real architect of the 1952 movement – and was later put under house arrest. Nasser assumed power as President in June 1956. British forces completed their withdrawal from the occupied Suez Canal Zone on 13 June 1956. His nationalization of the Suez Canal on 26 July 1956 prompted the 1956 Suez Crisis.  Three years after the 1967 Six Day War, during which Israel had invaded and occupied Sinai, Nasser died and was succeeded by Anwar Sadat. Sadat switched Egypt's Cold War allegiance from the Soviet Union to the United States, expelling Soviet advisors in 1972. He launched the Infitah economic reform policy, while violently clamping down on religious and secular opposition alike.  In 1973, Egypt, along with Syria, launched the October War, a surprise attack against the Israeli forces occupying the Sinai Peninsula and the Golan Heights. It was an attempt to regain part of the Sinai territory Israel had captured 6 years earlier. Sadat hoped to seize some territory through military force, and then regain the rest of the peninsula by diplomacy. The conflict sparked an international crisis between the two world superpowers: the US and the USSR, both of whom intervened. Two UN-mandated ceasefires were needed to bring military operations to a halt. While the war ended with a military Israeli victory, it presented Sadat with a political victory that later allowed him to regain the Sinai in return for peace with Israel.  Sadat made a historic visit to Israel in 1977, which led to the 1979 peace treaty in exchange for the complete Israeli withdrawal from Sinai. Sadat's initiative sparked enormous controversy in the Arab world and led to Egypt's expulsion from the Arab League, but it was supported by most Egyptians.  A fundamentalist military soldier assassinated Sadat in Cairo in 1981. He was succeeded by the incumbent Hosni Mubarak. In 2003, the Egyptian Movement for Change, popularly known as "Kefaya," was launched to seek a return to democracy and greater civil liberties.
</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_MEGYPT_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Mamluk</English>
		<French>Mamluk</French>
		<German>Mamluk</German>
		<Italian>Mamluk</Italian>
		<Spanish>Mamluk</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_CAIRO</Tag>
		<English>Cairo</English>
		<French>Cairo</French>
		<German>Cairo</German>
		<Italian>Cairo</Italian>
		<Spanish>Cairo</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_ALEXANDRIA</Tag>
		<English>Alexandria</English>
		<French>Alexandria</French>
		<German>Alexandria</German>
		<Italian>Alexandria</Italian>
		<Spanish>Alexandria</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_ASWAN</Tag>
		<English>Aswan</English>
		<French>Aswan</French>
		<German>Aswan</German>
		<Italian>Aswan</Italian>
		<Spanish>Aswan</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_FUSTAT</Tag>
		<English>Fustat</English>
		<French>Fustat</French>
		<German>Fustat</German>
		<Italian>Fustat</Italian>
		<Spanish>Fustat</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_AL_GIZA</Tag>
		<English>Al Giza</English>
		<French>Al Giza</French>
		<German>Al Giza</German>
		<Italian>Al Giza</Italian>
		<Spanish>Al Giza</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_PORT_SAID</Tag>
		<English>Port Said</English>
		<French>Port Said</French>
		<German>Port Said</German>
		<Italian>Port Said</Italian>
		<Spanish>Port Said</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_SUEZ</Tag>
		<English>Suez</English>
		<French>Suez</French>
		<German>Suez</German>
		<Italian>Suez</Italian>
		<Spanish>Suez</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_ISMAILIA</Tag>
		<English>Ismailia</English>
		<French>Ismailia</French>
		<German>Ismailia</German>
		<Italian>Ismailia</Italian>
		<Spanish>Ismailia</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_AL_JIZAH</Tag>
		<English>Al Jizah</English>
		<French>Al Jizah</French>
		<German>Al Jizah</German>
		<Italian>Al Jizah</Italian>
		<Spanish>Al Jizah</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_AL_FAYYUM</Tag>
		<English>Al Fayyum</English>
		<French>Al Fayyum</French>
		<German>Al Fayyum</German>
		<Italian>Al Fayyum</Italian>
		<Spanish>Al Fayyum</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_BANI_SUWAYF</Tag>
		<English>Bani Suwayf</English>
		<French>Bani Suwayf</French>
		<German>Bani Suwayf</German>
		<Italian>Bani Suwayf</Italian>
		<Spanish>Bani Suwayf</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_AL_MINYA</Tag>
		<English>Al Minya</English>
		<French>Al Minya</French>
		<German>Al Minya</German>
		<Italian>Al Minya</Italian>
		<Spanish>Al Minya</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_ASYUT</Tag>
		<English>Asyut</English>
		<French>Asyut</French>
		<German>Asyut</German>
		<Italian>Asyut</Italian>
		<Spanish>Asyut</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_SAWHAJ</Tag>
		<English>Sawhaj</English>
		<French>Sawhaj</French>
		<German>Sawhaj</German>
		<Italian>Sawhaj</Italian>
		<Spanish>Sawhaj</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_TANTA</Tag>
		<English>Tanta</English>
		<French>Tanta</French>
		<German>Tanta</German>
		<Italian>Tanta</Italian>
		<Spanish>Tanta</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_GAZA</Tag>
		<English>Gaza</English>
		<French>Gaza</French>
		<German>Gaza</German>
		<Italian>Gaza</Italian>
		<Spanish>Gaza</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_DAMANHUR</Tag>
		<English>Damanhur</English>
		<French>Damanhur</French>
		<German>Damanhur</German>
		<Italian>Damanhur</Italian>
		<Spanish>Damanhur</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_AZ_ZAQAZIQ</Tag>
		<English>Az Zaqaziq</English>
		<French>Az Zaqaziq</French>
		<German>Az Zaqaziq</German>
		<Italian>Az Zaqaziq</Italian>
		<Spanish>Az Zaqaziq</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_AL_MANSURA</Tag>
		<English>Al Mansura</English>
		<French>Al Mansura</French>
		<German>Al Mansura</German>
		<Italian>Al Mansura</Italian>
		<Spanish>Al Mansura</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_SHIBIN_AL_KAUM</Tag>
		<English>Shibin al Kaum</English>
		<French>Shibin al Kaum</French>
		<German>Shibin al Kaum</German>
		<Italian>Shibin al Kaum</Italian>
		<Spanish>Shibin al Kaum</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_HELUAN</Tag>
		<English>Heluan</English>
		<French>Heluan</French>
		<German>Heluan</German>
		<Italian>Heluan</Italian>
		<Spanish>Heluan</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_AL_QUSAYR</Tag>
		<English>Al Qusayr</English>
		<French>Al Qusayr</French>
		<German>Al Qusayr</German>
		<Italian>Al Qusayr</Italian>
		<Spanish>Al Qusayr</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_DUMYAT</Tag>
		<English>Dumyat</English>
		<French>Dumyat</French>
		<German>Dumyat</German>
		<Italian>Dumyat</Italian>
		<Spanish>Dumyat</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_SHUBRA_AL_KHAYMAH</Tag>
		<English>Shubra al Khaymah</English>
		<French>Shubra al Khaymah</French>
		<German>Shubra al Khaymah</German>
		<Italian>Shubra al Khaymah</Italian>
		<Spanish>Shubra al Khaymah</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_AL_MAHALLAH_AL_KUBRA</Tag>
		<English>Al Mahallah al Kubra</English>
		<French>Al Mahallah al Kubra</French>
		<German>Al Mahallah al Kubra</German>
		<Italian>Al Mahallah al Kubra</Italian>
		<Spanish>Al Mahallah al Kubra</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_KAFR_AD_DAWWAR</Tag>
		<English>Kafr ad Dawwar</English>
		<French>Kafr ad Dawwar</French>
		<German>Kafr ad Dawwar</German>
		<Italian>Kafr ad Dawwar</Italian>
		<Spanish>Kafr ad Dawwar</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_QINA</Tag>
		<English>Qina</English>
		<French>Qina</French>
		<German>Qina</German>
		<Italian>Qina</Italian>
		<Spanish>Qina</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_AL_UQSUR</Tag>
		<English>Al Uqsur</English>
		<French>Al Uqsur</French>
		<German>Al Uqsur</German>
		<Italian>Al Uqsur</Italian>
		<Spanish>Al Uqsur</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_AL_GHURDAGAH</Tag>
		<English>Al Ghurdagah</English>
		<French>Al Ghurdagah</French>
		<German>Al Ghurdagah</German>
		<Italian>Al Ghurdagah</Italian>
		<Spanish>Al Ghurdagah</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_MATRUH</Tag>
		<English>Matruh</English>
		<French>Matruh</French>
		<German>Matruh</German>
		<Italian>Matruh</Italian>
		<Spanish>Matruh</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_ARMANT</Tag>
		<English>Armant</English>
		<French>Armant</French>
		<German>Armant</German>
		<Italian>Armant</Italian>
		<Spanish>Armant</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_SAUKIN</Tag>
		<English>Saukin</English>
		<French>Saukin</French>
		<German>Saukin</German>
		<Italian>Saukin</Italian>
		<Spanish>Saukin</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>