<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by lcollins (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- Copyright Firaxis Games 2005 -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text - New -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_UKRAINE_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Ukrainian Empire</English>
		<French>Nation d'Ukraine</French>
		<German>Ukrainisch Reich</German>
		<Italian>Ucraino Impero</Italian>
		<Spanish>Ucraniano Imperio</Spanish>
	</TEXT>	
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_UKRAINE_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Ukraine</English>
		<French>Ukrainiens</French>
		<German>Ukraine</German>
		<Italian>Ucraina</Italian>
		<Spanish>Ucrania</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_UKRAINE_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Ukrainian</English>
    <French>
	    <Text>ukrainien:ukrainienne:ukrainiens:ukrainiennes</Text>
	    <Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
	    <Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
    </French>
		<German>Ukrainisch</German>
		<Italian>Ucraino</Italian>
		<Spanish>Ucraniano</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_UKRAINE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB] The first historical state on Ukrainian territory was the Kievan Rus.  The name "Ukraine" actually was a term that once referred to a border region in the 1100s.  In 988 or 989 AD, the conversion of the Kievan state to Christianity was begun under Prince Vladimir.  Domestic conflicts eventually led to the breakup of the Kievan Rus into a number of small principalities, most of which were conquered by the invading Mongols in the 1200s, including Kiev itself.  An independent state of Galicia and Volynia existed until the 1300s before being conquered by Poland and Lithuania.  With the union of Poland and Lithuania in 1569, almost all of the Ukrainian territories were absorbed into the Polish kingdom. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Religious conflict between Roman Catholic Poles and Orthodox Ukrainians and peasant resistance against serfdom brought a nationwide uprising against Polish rule.  It was lead by Bohdan Khmelnytsky, a Cossack hetman, or commander, who established a Ukrainian state along the Dnieper River.  A partly military society, the Cossacks were made up of runaway serfs and others seeking freedom in the border lands.  The Ukrainian state was to be brief.  Brought on by military and political needs, it entered into an alliance with the czar of Muscovy, the state from which the Russian Empire developed.  In 1667, Ukraine was split between Russia and Poland.  An eastern Ukrainian state, governed by a hetman and Rada, or Council, but controlled by Russia, existed until 1764, when its government was abolished.  When Poland itself was partitioned in the late 1700s, most of western Ukraine also fell under Russian rule.  The rest became part of the Austro-Hungarian Empire. [PARAGRAPH: 1] A Ukrainian nationalist movement was active in both empires, but under the Russian tsars, Ukrainian cultural activities were strictly prohibited.  Between 1876 and 1906 no books were allowed to be printed in Ukrainian, and the language was banned from schools.  Under Austrian rule, Ukrainians were able to develop their cultural and political life more fully.  In 1917, during World War I, the Russian Empire was defeated and Ukrainian leaders formed the Central Rada, which withheld rule from the Russian temporary government.  After the Bolsheviks overthrew the provisional government later that year, a struggle began between the Communists and nationalists for control of Ukraine.  On January 22, 1918, the Central Rada announced it was fully independent Ukraine.  With the help of German and Austrian troops, the communists were barred from Ukraine.  The Ukrainians in Austria faced much different problems with the breakup of the Austrian Empire. [PARAGRAPH: 1] In the former Russian Ukraine, civil war ensued as several governments struggled for power.  The Communists eventually reoccupied the region, establishing the Ukrainian Soviet Socialist Republic.  In 1922, jointly with the Russian and other Soviet republics, it formed the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics, or Soviet Union.  During the 1930s, the policy of forced collectivization of agriculture was carried out by order of Soviet dictator Joseph Stalin.  Resistance by Ukrainian farmers was finally broken by elimination of their food, causing the death by starvation of millions of people.  In 1939, on the eve of World War II, as a result of a Soviet pact with Germany, Galicia and Bukovina were reattached to the Ukrainian republic.  During the war, Ukraine underwent extensive damage from both Nazi German and Soviet forces.  The Transcarpathian region was united with Ukraine in 1945 and Crimea in 1954. [PARAGRAPH: 1] The breakdown of the Soviet political and economic system, and the growing feelings of nationalism of its many peoples, eventually led to the defeat of the Soviet Union in 1991.  On August 24, 1991, a declaration of independence was adopted by the Ukrainian parliament.  It was approved by 90 percent of eligible voters in a referendum on December 1, 1991.  Ukraine is now a republic with a president, a legislature, and a prime minister and Council of Ministers. </English>
		<French>[TAB] le premier état historique sur le territoire ukrainien était le Kievan Rus.  La « Ukraine » nommée était réellement une limite qui s'est par le passé rapportée à une région de frontière dans le 1100s.  Dans l'ANNONCE 988 ou 989, la conversion de l'état de Kievan en christianisme a été commencée sous prince Vladimir.  Les conflits de domestique ont par la suite mené à la dissolution du Kievan Rus dans un certain nombre de petites principautés, les la plupart dont ont été conquis par les mongoles envahissants dans le 1200s, y compris Kiev lui-même.  Un état indépendant de la Galicie et de Volynia a existé jusqu'au 1300s avant d'être conquise par la Pologne et la Lithuanie.  Avec l'union de la Pologne et de la Lithuanie en 1569, presque tous les territoires ukrainiens ont été absorbés dans le royaume polonais. [PARAGRAPH : 1] Le conflit religieux entre Polonais catholiques et résistance orthodoxe d'Ukrainiens et rurale contre le serfdom a apporté un soulèvement dans tout le pays contre la règle polonaise.  C'était fil par Bohdan Khmelnytsky, un hetman Cossack, ou le commandant, qui a établi un état ukrainien le long du fleuve de Dnieper.  Une société partiellement militaire, les Cosaques se sont composées des serfs et de d'autres d'emballement liberté cherchante dans les territoires frontaliers.  L'état ukrainien était d'être bref.  Apporté dessus par les besoins militaires et politiques, il est entré dans une alliance avec le tsar de Muscovy, l'état dont l'empire russe s'est développé.  En 1667, l'Ukraine a été dédoublée entre la Russie et la Pologne.  Un état ukrainien oriental, régi par un hetman et un Rada, ou le Conseil, mais commandé par la Russie, existée jusqu'en 1764, quand son gouvernement a été supprimé.  Quand la Pologne elle-même a été divisée vers la fin de 1700s, la majeure partie de l'Ukraine occidentale est également tombée selon la règle russe.  Le repos est devenu une partie de l'empire Austro-Hongrois. [PARAGRAPH : 1] Un mouvement nationaliste ukrainien était en activité dans les deux empires, mais sous les tsars russes, des activités culturelles ukrainiennes ont été strictement interdites.  Entre 1876 et 1906 aucuns livres ont été laissés être imprimés dans l'Ukrainien, et la langue a été interdite des écoles.  Selon la règle autrichienne, les Ukrainiens pouvaient développer leur vie culturelle et politique plus entièrement.  En 1917, pendant la Première Guerre Mondiale, l'empire russe a été défait et les chefs ukrainiens ont formé le Rada central, qui a retenu la règle du gouvernement provisoire russe.  Après que les bolchéviques aient renversé le gouvernement temporaire plus tard qu'année, une lutte a commencé entre les communistes et les nationalistes pour la commande de l'Ukraine.  Le 22 janvier 1918, le Rada central l'a annoncé était l'Ukraine entièrement indépendante.  Avec l'aide des troupes allemandes et autrichiennes, les communistes ont été empêchés de l'Ukraine.  Les Ukrainiens en Autriche ont fait face à des problèmes beaucoup différents avec la dissolution de l'empire autrichien. [PARAGRAPH : 1] En ancienne Ukraine russe, la guerre civile s'est ensuivie pendant que plusieurs gouvernements luttaient pour la puissance.  Les communistes ont par la suite réoccupé la région, établissant la République socialiste soviétique ukrainienne.  En 1922, en commun avec le Russe et d'autres républiques soviétiques, il a formé l'union des Républiques socialistes soviétiques, ou de l'Union Soviétique.  Pendant les années 30, la politique de la collectivisation obligatoire de l'agriculture a été effectuée par ordre de dictateur soviétique Joseph Stalin.  La résistance par des fermiers d'Ukrainian a été finalement cassée par l'élimination de leur nourriture, causant la mort par la famine des millions de personnes.  En 1939, la veille de la deuxième guerre mondiale, en raison d'un pacte soviétique avec l'Allemagne, la Galicie et Bukovina ont été rattachés à la république ukrainienne.  Pendant la guerre, l'Ukraine a subi des dommages étendus des forces allemandes et soviétiques nazies.  La région transcarpathienne a été unie à l'Ukraine en 1945 et à la Crimée en 1954. [PARAGRAPH : 1] La panne du système économique politique et soviétique, et les sentiments croissants du nationalisme de ses nombreux peuples, par la suite mené à la défaite de l'Union Soviétique en 1991.  Le 24 août 1991, une déclaration de l'indépendance a été adoptée par le Parlement ukrainien.  Il a été approuvé par 90 pour cent d'électeurs éligibles dans un référendum le 1er décembre 1991.  L'Ukraine est maintenant une république avec un président, une législature, et un premier ministre et un Conseil de Ministres.</French>
		<German>[TAB] war der erste historische Zustand auf ukrainischer Gegend das Kievan Rus.  Die NamensUkraine war wirklich eine Bezeichnung, die sich einmal auf eine Randregion im 1100s bezog.  In ANZEIGE 988 oder 989 wurde die Umwandlung des Kievan Zustandes zum Christentum unter Prinzen Vladimir angefangen.  Hausangestelltkonflikte führten schließlich zu das Auseinanderbrechen des Kievan Rus in eine Anzahl von kleinen principalities, denen die meisten von den eindringenden Mongolen im 1200s erobert wurden, einschließlich Kiew selbst.  Ein unabhängiger Staat von Galizien und von Volynia bestand bis das 1300s, bevor er durch Polen und Litauen erobert wurde.  Mit dem Anschluß von Polen und von Litauen 1569, wurden fast alle ukrainischen Gegenden in das polnische Königreich aufgesogen. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Frommer Konflikt zwischen römisch-katholischen Polen und orthodoxem Ukrainians- und ländlichem Widerstand gegen serfdom holte einen allgemein Aufstieg gegen polnische Richtlinie.  Es war Leitung durch Bohdan Khmelnytsky, ein Kosakenhetman oder Kommandant, der einen ukrainischen Zustand entlang dem Dnieper Fluß herstellte.  Eine teils militärische Gesellschaft, die Kosaken bestanden Durchgehensklaven und -andere suchende Freiheit in den Grenzgebieten.  Der ukrainische Zustand war, kurz zu sein.  An geholt durch die militärischen und politischen Notwendigkeiten, nahm es an einem Bündnis mit dem Zar von Muscovy teil, von dem der Zustand das russische Reich sich entwickelte.  1667 wurde Ukraine zwischen Rußland und Polen aufgespaltet.  Ein östlicher ukrainischer Zustand, geregelt durch einen Hetman und ein Rada oder Rat, aber durch Rußland gesteuert, bestanden bis 1764, als seine Regierung abgeschafft wurde.  Als Polen selbst Ende 1700s verteilt wurde, fielen die meisten von Westukraine auch unter russische Richtlinie.  Der Rest wurde Teil des Austro-Ungarischen Reiches. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Eine ukrainische nationalistische Bewegung war in beiden Reichen aktiv, aber unter den russischen Zaren, wurden ukrainische kulturelle Tätigkeiten ausschließlich verboten.  Zwischen 1876 und 1906 keinen Büchern wurden gewährt, in ukrainischem gedruckt zu werden, und die Sprache wurde von den Schulen verboten.  Unter österreichischer Richtlinie waren Ukrainians, ihr kulturelles und politisches Leben völlig zu entwickeln.  1917 während des Ersten Weltkrieges, wurde das russische Reich besiegt und ukrainische Führer bildeten das zentrale Rada, das Richtlinie von der russischen temporären Regierung zurückhielt.  Nachdem die Bolschewike die provisorische Regierung später besiegten, die Jahr, ein Kampf zwischen den Kommunisten und den Nationalisten zur Steuerung von Ukraine anfing.  Am 22. Januar 1918 verkündete das zentrale Rada es war völlig unabhängige Ukraine.  Mit Hilfe der deutschen und österreichischen Truppen wurden die Kommunisten von Ukraine abgehalten.  Das Ukrainians in Österreich stellte viel unterschiedliche Probleme mit dem Auseinanderbrechen des österreichischen Reiches gegenüber. [PARAGRAPH: 1] In der ehemaligen russischen Ukraine folgte Bürgerkrieg, während einige Regierungen für Energie kämpften.  Die Kommunisten reoccupied schließlich die Region und stellen die ukrainische sowjetische sozialistische Republik her.  1922 zusammen mit dem Russen und anderen sowjetischen Republiken, bildete es den Anschluß der sowjetischen sozialistischen Republiken oder die Sowjetunion.  Während der dreißiger Jahre wurde die Politik der Zwangskollektivierung der Landwirtschaft auf Befehl von sowjetischem Diktator Joseph Stalin durchgeführt.  Widerstand durch ukrainische Landwirte wurde schließlich durch die Beseitigung ihrer Nahrung gebrochen und verursachte den Tod durch Verhungern von Millionen Leuten.  1939 auf dem Vorabend des Zweiten Weltkrieges, resultierend aus einem sowjetischen Pakt mit Deutschland, wurden Galizien und Bukovina zur ukrainischen Republik wiederbefestigt.  Während des Krieges machte Ukraine umfangreiche Beschädigung von den deutschen und sowjetischen Nazikräften durch.  Die Transcarpathian Region wurde mit Ukraine 1945 und Krim 1954 vereinigt. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Der Zusammenbruch des sowjetischen politischen und Wirtschaftssystems und die wachsenden Gefühle des Nationalismus seiner vielen Völker, schließlich geführt zu die Niederlage der Sowjetunions 1991.  Am 24. August 1991 wurde eine Unabhängigkeitserklärung vom ukrainischen Parlament angenommen.  Es wurde von 90 Prozent geeigneten Wählern in einem Referendum am 1. Dezember 1991 genehmigt.  Ukraine ist jetzt eine Republik mit einem Präsidenten, eine Gesetzgebung und ein Premierminister und ein Ministerrat.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB] il primi storici dichiarano sul territorio ucraino erano il Kievan Rus.  L'Ucraina noma realmente era un termine che si è riferito una volta ad una regione del bordo nel 1100s.  In ANNUNCIO 988 o 989, la conversione del Kievan dichiara a Christianity è stata cominciata sotto il principe Vladimir.  I conflitti del Domestic finalmente hanno condotto al disfacimento del Kievan Rus in un certo numero di piccoli principalities, la maggior parte di cui sono stati conquistati dai Mongols d'invasione nel 1200s, compreso Kiev in se.  Un independent dichiara della Galizia e Volynia ha esistito fino al 1300s prima della conquista dalla Polonia e dalla Lituania.  Con l'unione della Polonia e della Lituania in 1569, quasi tutti i territori ucraini sono stati assorbiti nel regno polacco. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Il conflitto religioso fra Pali cattolici e resistenza agricola ortodossa e di Ukrainians contro il serfdom ha portato una rivolta nazionale contro la regola polacca.  Era cavo da Bohdan Khmelnytsky, un hetman Cossack, o il comandante, che ha stabilito un ucraino dichiara lungo il fiume di Dnieper.  Una società parzialmente militare, i Cossacks si è composta dei servi e di altri di instabilità la libertà di ricerca nelle terre di bordo.  L'ucraini dichiarano erano di essere brevi.  Portato sopra dai bisogni militari e politici, ha preso parte ad un'alleanza con il czar di Muscovy, il dichiarare da cui l'impero russo si è sviluppato.  in 1667, l'Ucraina è stata spaccata fra la Russia e la Polonia.  Un ucraino orientale dichiara, governato da un hetman e da un Rada, o dal Consiglio, ma controllato dalla Russia, esistita fino al 1764, quando il relativo governo si è abolito.  Quando la Polonia in se è stata divisa verso la fine di 1700s, la maggior parte dell'Ucraina occidentale inoltre sono rientrato nella regola russa.  Il resto si è trasformato in in parte dell'impero Austro-Ungherese. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Un movimento nazionalista ucraino era attivo in entrambi gli imperi, ma sotto i tsars russi, le attività culturali ucraine sono state proibite rigorosamente.  Fra 1876 e 1906 nessun libri si sono conceduti essere stampati in ucraino e la lingua si è vietata dalle scuole.  Secondo la regola austriaca, Ukrainians poteva sviluppare la loro vita culturale e politica completamente.  In 1917, durante la guerra mondiale I, l'impero russo è stato sconfitto ed i capi ucraini hanno formato il Rada centrale, che ha ritenuto la regola dal governo provvisorio russo.  Dopo che i Bolsheviks overthrew più successivamente il governo provvisorio che anno, una lotta ha cominciato fra i comunisti ed i nazionalisti per controllo dell'Ucraina.  Il 22 gennaio 1918, il Rada centrale lo ha annunciato era l'Ucraina completamente indipendente.  Con l'aiuto delle truppe tedesche ed austriache, i comunisti sono stati esclusi dall'Ucraina.  Il Ukrainians in Austria ha affrontato i problemi molto differenti con il disfacimento dell'impero austriaco. [PARAGRAPH: 1] In Ucraina russa precedente, la guerra civile ha seguito mentre parecchi governi hanno lottato per alimentazione.  I comunisti finalmente rioccupati la regione, stabilente Repubblica socialista sovietica ucraina.  In 1922, insieme con il Russo ed altre repubbliche sovietiche, ha formato l'unione delle Repubbliche socialiste sovietiche, o l'Unione Sovietica.  Durante i 1930s, la politica della collettivizzazione forzata dell'agricoltura è stata effettuata per ordine del dictator sovietico Joseph Stalin.  La resistenza dai coltivatori ucraini infine è stata rotta dall'eliminazione del loro alimento, causante la morte da inedia di milioni di gente.  In 1939, la vigilia della seconda guerra mondiale, come conseguenza di un patto sovietico con la Germania, la Galizia e Bukovina sono stati riattaccati alla repubblica ucraina.  Durante la guerra, l'Ucraina ha subito vasti danni sia dalle forze tedesche che sovietiche naziste.  La regione Transcarpathian è stata unita all'Ucraina in 1945 ed alla Crimea in 1954. [PARAGRAPH: 1] La ripartizione del sistema politico ed economico sovietico e le sensibilità crescenti di nazionalismo della sua numerosa gente, finalmente condotto alla sconfitta dell'Unione Sovietica in 1991.  Il 24 agosto 1991, una dichiarazione di indipendenza è stata adottata dal Parlamento ucraino.  È stato approvato da 90 per cento degli elettori eleggibili in un referendum il 1° dicembre 1991.  L'Ucraina ora è una repubblica con un presidente, una legislatura e un ministro e un Consiglio dei Ministri principali.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB] el primer estado histórico en territorio ucraniano era el Kievan Rus.  La Ucrania conocida era realmente un término que refirió una vez a una región de la frontera en el 1100s.  En el ANUNCIO 988 o 989, la conversión del estado de Kievan al cristianismo fue comenzada debajo de príncipe Vladimir.  Los conflictos del Domestic condujeron eventual a la desintegración del Kievan Rus en un número de principalities pequeños, la mayor parte de que fueron conquistados por los Mongols invasores en el 1200s, incluyendo Kiev sí mismo.  Un estado independiente de Galicia y de Volynia existió hasta el 1300s antes de ser conquistada por Polonia y Lituania.  Con la unión de Polonia y de Lituania en 1569, casi todos los territorios ucranianos fueron absorbidos en el reino polaco. [TAB: 1] El conflicto religioso entre postes católicos y la resistencia ortodoxa de Ukrainians y campesina contra el serfdom trajo una sublevación a nivel nacional contra regla polaca.  Era plomo de Bohdan Khmelnytsky, hetman Cossack, o el comandante, que estableció un estado ucraniano a lo largo del río de Dnieper.  Compusieron a una sociedad en parte militar, los Cossacks de siervos y de otros del fugitivo libertad que buscaba en las zonas fronterizas.  El estado ucraniano era ser breve.  Traído encendido por necesidades militares y políticas, entró en una alianza con el czar de Muscovy, el estado de el cual el imperio ruso se convirtió.  En 1667, Ucrania estuvo partida entre Rusia y Polonia.  Un estado ucraniano del este, gobernado por un hetman y un Rada, o consejo, pero controlado por Rusia, existida hasta 1764, cuando su gobierno fue suprimido.  Cuando Polonia sí mismo fue repartida en el último 1700s, la mayor parte de Ucrania occidental también cayó bajo regla rusa.  El resto se convirtió en parte del imperio Austro-Húngaro. [TAB: 1] Un movimiento nacionalista ucraniano era activo en ambos imperios, pero debajo de los tsars rusos, las actividades culturales ucranianas fueron prohibidas terminantemente.  Entre 1876 y 1906 ningunos libros fueron permitidos para ser impresos en ucraniano, y la lengua fue prohibida de escuelas.  Bajo regla austríaca, Ukrainians podía desarrollar su vida cultural y política más completamente.  En 1917, durante Primera Guerra Mundial, el imperio ruso fue derrotado y los líderes ucranianos formaron el Rada central, que retuvo regla del gobierno temporal ruso.  Después de que los Bolsheviks derrocaran el gobierno provisional más adelante que año, una lucha comenzó entre los comunistas y los nacionalistas para el control de Ucrania.  El 22 de enero de 1918, el Rada central lo anunció era Ucrania completamente independiente.  Con la ayuda de las tropas alemanas y austríacas, barraron a los comunistas de Ucrania.  El Ukrainians en Austria hizo frente a problemas mucho diversos con la desintegración del imperio austríaco. [TAB: 1] En la Ucrania rusa anterior, la guerra civil sobrevino mientras que varios gobiernos lucharon para la energía.  Los comunistas reocuparon eventual la región, estableciendo la república socialista soviética ucraniana.  En 1922, en común con el ruso y otras repúblicas soviéticas, formó la unión de repúblicas socialistas soviéticas, o Unión Soviética.  Durante los años 30, la política de la colectivización forzada de la agricultura fue realizada por orden de dictador soviético José Stalin.  La resistencia de los granjeros ucranianos finalmente fue rota por la eliminación de su alimento, causando la muerte por el hambre de millones de gente.  En 1939, en la víspera de la Segunda Guerra Mundial, como resultado de un pacto soviético con Alemania, Galicia y Bukovina fueron reatados a la república ucraniana.  Durante la guerra, Ucrania experimentó daño extenso de fuerzas alemanas y soviéticas nazis.  La región Transcarpathian fue unida con Ucrania en 1945 y Crimea en 1954. [TAB: 1] La interrupción del sistema político y económico soviético, y las sensaciones cada vez mayor del nacionalismo de sus numerosos gente, conducido eventual a la derrota de la Unión Soviética en 1991.  El 24 de agosto de 1991, un declaración de la independencia fue adoptado por el parlamento ucraniano.  Fue aprobado por 90 por ciento de votantes elegibles en un referéndum el 1 de diciembre de 1991.  Ucrania ahora es una república con un presidente, una legislatura, y un primer ministro y un Consejo de Ministros.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>	