<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Civ4GameText>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_ABORIGINES_BORARING_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]A bora ring is a cultural site important to Indigenous Australians. Bora rings are circles of foot-hardened earth surrounded by raised embankments. They were generally constructed in pairs (although some sites have three), with a bigger circle about 22 metres in diameter and a smaller one of about 14 metres. The rings are joined by a sacred walkway. The rings were used in ceremonies, particularly for initiation. They are named for the belt worn by initiated tribesmen.</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_AKKADIAN_TEMPLE_ISHTAR_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[H1]Temple of Ishtar[\H1][PARAGRAPH:2]Ishtar is a goddess of fertility, love, war, and sex.  In the Babylonian pantheon, she "was the divine personification of the planet Venus."  Ishtar was above all associated with sexuality: her cult involved sacred prostitution.  Her holy city Uruk was called the "town of the sacred courtesans"; and she herself was the "courtesan of the gods."</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_ALBANIA_ILLOGOR_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]A Llogor was a place where Albanians would hide munitions with which to fight their Turkish, Serbian, and Montenegrin oppressors. Especially in the early 1900s these were important when Albanians from all regions were uniting to reclaim their land from the Ottoman conquerors: one of the movies about the war for the declaration of Albania's independence is about a homemade gunpowder mill in the mountains that was used to produce the ammunition the men waged war against their enemies with.</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_ANGLO_SAXON_MOOT_HILL_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>A Moot hill is a hill or mound historically used as a meeting place. In early mediaeval Britain, such hills were used for moots, meetings of local people to settle local business. Among other things, proclamations might be read; decisions might be taken; court cases might be settled at a moot. Although some moot hills were naturally occurring features or had been created long before as burial mounds, others were purpose-built.</English>
      <German>in German</German>
      <Italian>in Italian</Italian>
      <Spanish>in Spanish</Spanish>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_ANISHNAABEK_MIDEWIWIN_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]The name Midewiwin is derived from a Native American term for the Grand Medicine Society, a super-secret society of which today members would nominally be called by others than the Medewiwin, Shamans. Tribal groups who had such societies include the Ojibwa, Chippewa, Ottawa, and Potawatomi, the last of whom were prominent residents of the Midewiwin National Tallgrass Prairie region from the mid 1700's to the early to mid-1800's. According to the Potawatomi, Mide' or Mida (pronounced mid-day), means mystic' or mystically powerful.' The curing rituals performed by the members of the Midewiwin relied heavily on a tradition that incorporated mystical elements arising from the beliefs about the spirits that protected the "the original people".</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_ANIYONEGA_DIDANAWISGI_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]Didanawisgi is the Cherokee word for medicine man. A common thread woven through all Native American remedies is the idea of "wellness" a term recently picked up by some in the modern medical professions. A state of "wellness" is described as "harmony between the mind, body and spirit." The Cherokee word "tohi" - health - is the same as the word for peace. You're in good health when your body is at peace. The "medicine circle" has no beginning and no end and therefore represents a concept of "harmonious unity."</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_APACHE_BUTCHER_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]The Western Apache hunted deer and pronghorns mostly in the ideal late fall season. After the meat was smoked into jerky around November, a migration from the farm sites along the stream banks in the mountains to winter camps in the Salt, Black, Gila river and even the Colorado River valleys. Plains Apache hunters pursued primarily buffalo and deer. Other hunted animals were badgers, bears, beavers, fowls, geese, opossums, otters, rabbits and turtles.[PARAGRAPH:1]Eating certain animals was taboo. Although different cultures had different taboos, some common examples of taboo animals included bears, peccaries, turkeys, fish, snakes, insects, owls, and coyotes.</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_ARGENTINA_DANCESTUDIO_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]Tango is Argentina's musical symbol. The Milonga dance was a predecessor, slowly evolving into mordern tango. By the 1930s, tango had changed from a dance focused music to one of lyric and poetry. The golden age of tango (1930 to mid-1950s) mirrored that of Jazz and Swing in the United States, featuring large orchestral groups.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Argentine Tango consists of a variety of styles that developed in different regions and eras, and in response to the crowding of the venue and even the fashions in clothing. Even though they all developed in Argentina and Uruguay, they were also exposed to influences reimported from Europe and North America.</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_ARMENIA_KHACHKAR_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]Armenian khachkars are a unique part of the national heritage. Intricately decorated crosses are carved on monolithic rocks. There are over 4,000 khachkars in Armenia, and every one of them has a singular pattern. Over time they evolved into an incredibly ornate form which reached its peak in the 12-13th centuries.[PARAGRAPH:1]Khachkars are most commonly used as tombstones, but were sometimes used as memorials. The biggest khachkar cemetery in Armenia is the Noratus Cemetery, while the biggest in the world is in Jugha, in Nakhichevan.[PARAGRAPH:1]Most khachkars do not depict Christ on the cross, but a few notable exceptions exist.[PARAGRAPH:1]</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_ARMUARIE_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]While not necessarily this is specific to Romania - it is more correct to say this was some kind of "feudal privilege" granted to "free villages" (or to the "free peasant" - razeshi or moshneni - communities). The "serf villages" (satele de iobagi in Romanian) didn't have the right to build mills, forges or to have their own forests. They had to "buy" this services/products from their "master" ( boier in Romanian ) or "supervising" monastery ( if this was the case ) - with money or, more likely, working a number of days the land of their landlords. Opposite to this - the "free villages" had the granted right ( usually from the king - voievod or domn in Romanian ) to posses a "communal mills", or forges, judge some minor delicts by elder, even to trade non-agricultural products and so on. Most of these villages was founded in border-regions and, for their status, need to send soldiers (armed by the village) in case of war.[NEWLINE]This was a successful "social arrangement" for more than 2 centuries (XIVth-XVIth) and provided enough partially-trained soldiers to defend with some good military victories against superior enemy forces (Turkish, Polish, Hungarians and so on). Unfortunately - starting with the beginning of XVIth century the two Romanians principates ruled by Romanian lords (Walachia and Moldavia) - became the stage of internal fighting between landlords in order to impose a "friendly" king. The land and revenues of "free-villages" was a good motivation for the greed of "boier-s and their abuse. In less than a century most of "free peasant" was transformed to serfs and the remaining ones was forced to accept reduction of their "feudal privileges". Despite the fact that those measure reduced the army and capacity of defense - the fear of nobleman for possible peasant uprising lead to drastically reduction of pre-existent "peasant militia". Even so, especially in western part of Walachia, there remains "traces" of old organization until the end of XIXth century (those man formed the main part of Tudor Vladimirescu's revolutionary units in 1821).</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_ARSENAL_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]The Venetian Arsenal (Italian: Arsenale di Venezia) is a shipyard and naval depot that played a leading role in Venetian empire-building. It was one of the most important areas of Venice, lying in the Castello sestiere.[PARAGRAPH:1]The Byzantine-style establishment may have existed as early as the eighth century, though the present structure is usually said to have been begun in 1104 during the reign of Ordelafo Faliero, although there is no evidence for such a precise date. It definitely existed by the early thirteenth century and is mentioned in Dante's Inferno. The name probably comes from Arabic Dar al Sinaa ("Dockyard") and the concept was clearly Islamic as much as Byzantine. [PARAGRAPH:1]Initially the state dockyard worked merely to maintain naval ships built privately, but in 1320 the Arsenal Nuovo was built, much larger than the original. It enabled all the state's navy and the larger merchant ships to be both constructed and maintained in one place. The Arsenal incidentally became an important centre for rope manufacture, while housing for the arsenal workers grew up outside its walls. [PARAGRAPH:1]Venice developed methods of mass-producing warships in the Arsenal, including the frame-first system to replace the Roman hull-first practice. The new system was much faster and required less wood. At the peak of its efficiency in the early sixteenth century, the Arsenal employed some 16,000 people who apparently were able to produce nearly one ship each day, and could fit out, arm, and provision a newly-built galley with standardized parts on a production-line basis not seen again until the Industrial Revolution. [PARAGRAPH:1]The staff of the Arsenal also developed new firearms at an early date, beginning with bombards in the 1370s and numerous small arms against the Genoese a few years later. Improvements in handguns led to their muzzle velocity (and therefore their ability to penetrate armor) exceeding that of the crossbow. The Venetian condottieri leader, Bartolomeo Colleoni, is usually given credit as being the first to mount the Arsenal's new lighter-weight artillery on mobile carriages for field use. [PARAGRAPH:1]The Arsenal's main gate, the Porta Magna, was built in about 1460 and was the first Classical revival structure to be built in Venice. It was perhaps built by Antonio Gambello from a design by Jacopo Bellini. Two lions taken from Greece situated beside it were added in 1687. One of the lions, known as the Piraeus Lion, is notable for having been defaced with lengthy runic inscriptions carved in the eleventh century by Scandinavian mercenary soldiers. [PARAGRAPH:1]The Arsenal Novissimo was begun in 1473. It enabled the creation of a system similar to an assembly line, in which hulls were constructed in the newer areas of the Arsenal before being fitted out in the old Arsenal. In the late sixteenth century, the Arsenal's designers experimented with larger ships as platforms for heavy naval guns. The most impressive was the galleass, already used at Lepanto, and developed from the old merchanting "great galley". It was huge, with sails as well as oars, and was virtually a floating fortress, with guns mounted on wheeled carriages along the sides in the modern fashion. It was slow and unwieldy in battle, however, and few were ever built. The galleon, also developed at the Arsenal, was an armed sailing ship, a slimmer version of the merchant "round ship". It was useful in major naval battles, but not in the small bays and off the frequent lee shores of the Dalmatian coast. [PARAGRAPH:1]Significant parts of the Arsenal were destroyed under Napoleonic rule, and later rebuilt to enable the Arsenal's present use as a naval base. It is also used as a research centre, an exhibition venue during the Venice Biennale and is home to a historic boat preservation centre.</English>
      <French>[TAB]L'Arsenal de Venise (en italien : Arsenale di Venezia) est un dépôt et un chantier naval qui joua un rôle primordial dans la construction de l'empire vénitien. Il fut l'un des quartiers les plus importants de Venise, s'étendant dans le Castello sestiere.[PARAGRAPH:1]Ce bâtiment de style byzantin peut avoir existé depuis le 8ème siècle, bien qu'on date habituellement le début de la construction de la structure actuelle à 1104 pendant le règne d'Ordelafo Faliero, bien qu'il n'y ait aucune preuves d'une date aussi précise. Il existe avec certitude depuis le début de 13ème siècle et est mentionné dans l'Enfer de Dante. Le nom provient probablement de l'arabe Dar al Sinaa ("chantier naval") et le concept est clairement arabe beaucoup plus que byzantin. [PARAGRAPH:1]Originellement, le chantier naval ne travaillait quasiment qu'à entretenir et construire les navires privés, mais en 1320 l'Arsenal Nuovo fut bâti, plus grand que le précédent. Il permit à toute la marine de l'état et aux navires marchants les plus importants d'être tous ensembles construits et entretenus dans un seul endroit. L'Arsenal devint incidemment un centre importent de la manufacture de cordes, tandis que les quartiers en dehors des murs de la ville s'agrandissaient pour accueillir les travailleurs de l'Arsenal. [PARAGRAPH:1]Venise développa des méthodes de production de masse de navires dans l'Arsenal, notamment le système de construction en premier de la charpente venant remplacer l'ancienne méthode de construction de la coque en premier inventée par les Romains. Ce nouveau système permettait de construire plus vite et demandait moins de bois. Au maximum de son efficacité au début du 16ème siècle, l'Arsenal employa jusqu'à 16 000 personnes qui étaient apparemment capable de produire presque un navire par jour et pouvaient équiper, armer et provisionner une galère nouvellement construire grâce à des méthodes standardisées dans une ligne de production qui ne sera pas égalée avant la révolution industrielle. [PARAGRAPH:1]Le personnel de l'Arsenal développa aussi de nouvelles armes à feu dès le début, commençant par des bombardes vers 1370 et de nombreuses petites armes à feu utilisées contre les Génois quelques années plus tard. Les améliorations des armes de poings augmentèrent la vélocité de balles en sortie de canon (et par là, leur capacité à pénétrer des armures) excédant celle des arbalètes. On attribue généralement le crédit au chef des condottieri vénitien, Bartolomeo Colleoni, d'avoir monté les nouvelles pièces d'artillerie légère de l'Arsenal sur des chariots mobiles pour un usage sur le champ de bataille. [PARAGRAPH:1]La principale porte de l'Arsenal, la Porta Magna, fut construite aux environs de 1460 et fut la première structure du renouveau classique à Venise. Elle fut peut-être construite par Antonio Gambello d'après des plans de Jacopo Bellini. Deux statues de lion prises en Grèce situées à coté furent ajoutées en 1687. Un des lions, connu sous le nom de Lion de Pirée, fut dégradé notablement par de longues inscriptions runiques gravées au 11ème siècle par des soldats mercenaires vikings. [PARAGRAPH:1]La construction de l'Arsenal Novissimo commença en 1473. Il permit la création d'un système proche des chaînes d'assemblage, dans lequel les coques étaient construites dans les quartiers du nouvel Arsenal avant d'être aménagées dans l'ancien arsenal. A la fin du 16ème siècle, les ingénieurs de l'Arsenal expérimentèrent de larges navires en tant que plateformes pour des canons navals lourds. La plus impressionnante fut la galéasse, utilisée à Lépante, et développée à partir des grandes galères marchandes. Elle était gigantesque, avec des voiles aussi bien que des rames, et était virtuellement une forteresse flottante, avec des canons montés sur chariots le long des flancs. Cependant, elle était lente et difficile à manier, et peu furent finalement construites. Le galion, lui aussi développé à l'Arsenal, était un navire à voiles armé, une version plus légère des gros navires marchands. Il fut largement utilisé dans les principales batailles navales, mais jamais dans les petites baies et les fréquents bancs de sables de la cote dalmatienne. [PARAGRAPH:1]Des parties signifiantes de l'Arsenal furent détruites sous le régime napoléonien, et rebâties plus tard pour permettre à l'Arsenal actuel son utilisation en tant que base navale. Il est aussi utilisé comme centre de recherche, comme lieu d'exposition pendant la biennale vénitienne et comme centre de préservation des navires historiques.</French>
      <German>[TAB]The Venetian Arsenal (Italian: Arsenale di Venezia) is a shipyard and naval depot that played a leading role in Venetian empire-building. It was one of the most important areas of Venice, lying in the Castello sestiere.[PARAGRAPH:1]The Byzantine-style establishment may have existed as early as the eighth century, though the present structure is usually said to have been begun in 1104 during the reign of Ordelafo Faliero, although there is no evidence for such a precise date. It definitely existed by the early thirteenth century and is mentioned in Dante's Inferno. The name probably comes from Arabic Dar al Sinaa ("Dockyard") and the concept was clearly Islamic as much as Byzantine. [PARAGRAPH:1]Initially the state dockyard worked merely to maintain naval ships built privately, but in 1320 the Arsenal Nuovo was built, much larger than the original. It enabled all the state's navy and the larger merchant ships to be both constructed and maintained in one place. The Arsenal incidentally became an important centre for rope manufacture, while housing for the arsenal workers grew up outside its walls. [PARAGRAPH:1]Venice developed methods of mass-producing warships in the Arsenal, including the frame-first system to replace the Roman hull-first practice. The new system was much faster and required less wood. At the peak of its efficiency in the early sixteenth century, the Arsenal employed some 16,000 people who apparently were able to produce nearly one ship each day, and could fit out, arm, and provision a newly-built galley with standardized parts on a production-line basis not seen again until the Industrial Revolution. [PARAGRAPH:1]The staff of the Arsenal also developed new firearms at an early date, beginning with bombards in the 1370s and numerous small arms against the Genoese a few years later. Improvements in handguns led to their muzzle velocity (and therefore their ability to penetrate armor) exceeding that of the crossbow. The Venetian condottieri leader, Bartolomeo Colleoni, is usually given credit as being the first to mount the Arsenal's new lighter-weight artillery on mobile carriages for field use. The Arsenal's main gate, the Porta Magna, was built in about 1460 and was the first Classical revival structure to be built in Venice. It was perhaps built by Antonio Gambello from a design by Jacopo Bellini. Two lions taken from Greece situated beside it were added in 1687. One of the lions, known as the Piraeus Lion, is notable for having been defaced with lengthy runic inscriptions carved in the eleventh century by Scandinavian mercenary soldiers. [PARAGRAPH:1]The Arsenal Novissimo was begun in 1473. It enabled the creation of a system similar to an assembly line, in which hulls were constructed in the newer areas of the Arsenal before being fitted out in the old Arsenal. In the late sixteenth century, the Arsenal's designers experimented with larger ships as platforms for heavy naval guns. The most impressive was the galleass, already used at Lepanto, and developed from the old merchanting "great galley". It was huge, with sails as well as oars, and was virtually a floating fortress, with guns mounted on wheeled carriages along the sides in the modern fashion. It was slow and unwieldy in battle, however, and few were ever built. The galleon, also developed at the Arsenal, was an armed sailing ship, a slimmer version of the merchant "round ship". It was useful in major naval battles, but not in the small bays and off the frequent lee shores of the Dalmatian coast. [PARAGRAPH:1]Significant parts of the Arsenal were destroyed under Napoleonic rule, and later rebuilt to enable the Arsenal's present use as a naval base. It is also used as a research centre, an exhibition venue during the Venice Biennale and is home to a historic boat preservation centre.</German>
      <Italian>[TAB]The Venetian Arsenal (Italian: Arsenale di Venezia) is a shipyard and naval depot that played a leading role in Venetian empire-building. It was one of the most important areas of Venice, lying in the Castello sestiere.[PARAGRAPH:1]The Byzantine-style establishment may have existed as early as the eighth century, though the present structure is usually said to have been begun in 1104 during the reign of Ordelafo Faliero, although there is no evidence for such a precise date. It definitely existed by the early thirteenth century and is mentioned in Dante's Inferno. The name probably comes from Arabic Dar al Sinaa ("Dockyard") and the concept was clearly Islamic as much as Byzantine. [PARAGRAPH:1]Initially the state dockyard worked merely to maintain naval ships built privately, but in 1320 the Arsenal Nuovo was built, much larger than the original. It enabled all the state's navy and the larger merchant ships to be both constructed and maintained in one place. The Arsenal incidentally became an important centre for rope manufacture, while housing for the arsenal workers grew up outside its walls. [PARAGRAPH:1]Venice developed methods of mass-producing warships in the Arsenal, including the frame-first system to replace the Roman hull-first practice. The new system was much faster and required less wood. At the peak of its efficiency in the early sixteenth century, the Arsenal employed some 16,000 people who apparently were able to produce nearly one ship each day, and could fit out, arm, and provision a newly-built galley with standardized parts on a production-line basis not seen again until the Industrial Revolution. [PARAGRAPH:1]The staff of the Arsenal also developed new firearms at an early date, beginning with bombards in the 1370s and numerous small arms against the Genoese a few years later. Improvements in handguns led to their muzzle velocity (and therefore their ability to penetrate armor) exceeding that of the crossbow. The Venetian condottieri leader, Bartolomeo Colleoni, is usually given credit as being the first to mount the Arsenal's new lighter-weight artillery on mobile carriages for field use. The Arsenal's main gate, the Porta Magna, was built in about 1460 and was the first Classical revival structure to be built in Venice. It was perhaps built by Antonio Gambello from a design by Jacopo Bellini. Two lions taken from Greece situated beside it were added in 1687. One of the lions, known as the Piraeus Lion, is notable for having been defaced with lengthy runic inscriptions carved in the eleventh century by Scandinavian mercenary soldiers. [PARAGRAPH:1]The Arsenal Novissimo was begun in 1473. It enabled the creation of a system similar to an assembly line, in which hulls were constructed in the newer areas of the Arsenal before being fitted out in the old Arsenal. In the late sixteenth century, the Arsenal's designers experimented with larger ships as platforms for heavy naval guns. The most impressive was the galleass, already used at Lepanto, and developed from the old merchanting "great galley". It was huge, with sails as well as oars, and was virtually a floating fortress, with guns mounted on wheeled carriages along the sides in the modern fashion. It was slow and unwieldy in battle, however, and few were ever built. The galleon, also developed at the Arsenal, was an armed sailing ship, a slimmer version of the merchant "round ship". It was useful in major naval battles, but not in the small bays and off the frequent lee shores of the Dalmatian coast. [PARAGRAPH:1]Significant parts of the Arsenal were destroyed under Napoleonic rule, and later rebuilt to enable the Arsenal's present use as a naval base. It is also used as a research centre, an exhibition venue during the Venice Biennale and is home to a historic boat preservation centre.</Italian>
      <Spanish>[TAB]The Venetian Arsenal (Italian: Arsenale di Venezia) is a shipyard and naval depot that played a leading role in Venetian empire-building. It was one of the most important areas of Venice, lying in the Castello sestiere.[PARAGRAPH:1]The Byzantine-style establishment may have existed as early as the eighth century, though the present structure is usually said to have been begun in 1104 during the reign of Ordelafo Faliero, although there is no evidence for such a precise date. It definitely existed by the early thirteenth century and is mentioned in Dante's Inferno. The name probably comes from Arabic Dar al Sinaa ("Dockyard") and the concept was clearly Islamic as much as Byzantine. [PARAGRAPH:1]Initially the state dockyard worked merely to maintain naval ships built privately, but in 1320 the Arsenal Nuovo was built, much larger than the original. It enabled all the state's navy and the larger merchant ships to be both constructed and maintained in one place. The Arsenal incidentally became an important centre for rope manufacture, while housing for the arsenal workers grew up outside its walls. [PARAGRAPH:1]Venice developed methods of mass-producing warships in the Arsenal, including the frame-first system to replace the Roman hull-first practice. The new system was much faster and required less wood. At the peak of its efficiency in the early sixteenth century, the Arsenal employed some 16,000 people who apparently were able to produce nearly one ship each day, and could fit out, arm, and provision a newly-built galley with standardized parts on a production-line basis not seen again until the Industrial Revolution. [PARAGRAPH:1]The staff of the Arsenal also developed new firearms at an early date, beginning with bombards in the 1370s and numerous small arms against the Genoese a few years later. Improvements in handguns led to their muzzle velocity (and therefore their ability to penetrate armor) exceeding that of the crossbow. The Venetian condottieri leader, Bartolomeo Colleoni, is usually given credit as being the first to mount the Arsenal's new lighter-weight artillery on mobile carriages for field use. The Arsenal's main gate, the Porta Magna, was built in about 1460 and was the first Classical revival structure to be built in Venice. It was perhaps built by Antonio Gambello from a design by Jacopo Bellini. Two lions taken from Greece situated beside it were added in 1687. One of the lions, known as the Piraeus Lion, is notable for having been defaced with lengthy runic inscriptions carved in the eleventh century by Scandinavian mercenary soldiers. [PARAGRAPH:1]The Arsenal Novissimo was begun in 1473. It enabled the creation of a system similar to an assembly line, in which hulls were constructed in the newer areas of the Arsenal before being fitted out in the old Arsenal. In the late sixteenth century, the Arsenal's designers experimented with larger ships as platforms for heavy naval guns. The most impressive was the galleass, already used at Lepanto, and developed from the old merchanting "great galley". It was huge, with sails as well as oars, and was virtually a floating fortress, with guns mounted on wheeled carriages along the sides in the modern fashion. It was slow and unwieldy in battle, however, and few were ever built. The galleon, also developed at the Arsenal, was an armed sailing ship, a slimmer version of the merchant "round ship". It was useful in major naval battles, but not in the small bays and off the frequent lee shores of the Dalmatian coast. [PARAGRAPH:1]Significant parts of the Arsenal were destroyed under Napoleonic rule, and later rebuilt to enable the Arsenal's present use as a naval base. It is also used as a research centre, an exhibition venue during the Venice Biennale and is home to a historic boat preservation centre.</Spanish>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_ASHANTI_DRUMMING_STATION_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]The talking drum is a West African drum whose pitch can be regulated to the extent that it is said the drum "talks" and can be used for drum communication. Talking drums are hour-glass shaped with two heads (made from either goat, lizard, or fish skin) tuned by straps that connect the heads with each other. The player puts the drum under one shoulder and beats the instrument with a specialised beater. The pitch is raised or lowered by squeezing or releasing the drum's strings with the upper arm. This can produce highly informative sounds to convey complicated messages.</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_ATHLETICS_COMPLEX_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]Australians are enthusiastic about sports, both as the audience and players.  Australian Rules football, soccer, and rugby are the most popular spectator sports.  Cricket is a favorite summer pastime.  Tennis, lawn bowling, gold, and horse racings all have enthusiastic fans.  With the high amount of Australians living on the coast, swimming, sailing, and other water sports are highly popular.  The country has produced numerous world-class athletes, particularly in tennis, swimming, and track.</English>
      <French>[TAB]Les Australiens sont enthousiastes au sujet des sports, en tant que les assistances et joueurs.  L'Australien règne le football, le football, et le rugby sont les sports spectaculaires les plus populaires.  Le cricket est un passe-temps préféré d'été.  Le tennis, le bowling de pelouse, l'or, et les racings tous de cheval ont les ventilateurs enthousiastes.  Avec le montant élevé d'Australiens vivant sur la côte, les sports de l'eau de natation, de navigation, et autre sont fortement populaires.  Le pays a produit de nombreux athlètes de monde-classe, en particulier dans le tennis, la natation, et la voie.</French>
      <German>[TAB]Australier sind über Sport, als die Publikum und die Spieler enthusiastisch.  Australier ordnet Fußball, Fußball an, und Rugby ist der populärste Zuschauersport.  Kricket ist ein Lieblingssommerzeitvertreib.  Tennis, Rasenbowlingspiel, Gold und Pferd alle racings haben enthusiastische Ventilatoren.  Mit der hohen Menge der Australier, die auf der Küste leben, ist Schwimmen-, Segeln und andereswassersport in hohem Grade populär.  Das Land hat zahlreiche Weltkategorie Athleten, besonders im Tennis, in der Schwimmen und in der Schiene produziert.</German>
      <Italian>[TAB]Gli australiani sono entusiasti degli sport, sia come i pubblici che i giocatori.  L'australiano regola il gioco del calcio, calcio ed il rugby è gli sport spectator più popolari.  Il grillo è un pastime favorito di estate.  Il tennis, il bowling del prato, l'oro e i racings tutti del cavallo hanno ventilatori entusiastici.  Con la quantità elevata degli australiani che vivono sul litorale, sport dell'acqua di swimming, di navigazione ed altro sono altamente popolari.  Il paese ha prodotto gli atleti numerosi del mondo-codice categoria, specialmente nel tennis, nello swimming ed in pista.</Italian>
      <Spanish>[TAB]Los australianos son entusiásticos sobre deportes, como las audiencias y los jugadores.  El australiano gobierna el balompié, fútbol, y el rugbi es los deportes espectadores más populares.  El grillo es un pasatiempo preferido del verano.  El tenis, el bowling del césped, el oro, y los racings todos del caballo tienen ventiladores entusiásticos.  Entre la alta cantidad de australianos que viven en la costa, los deportes del agua de la natación, de la navegación, y otro son altamente populares.  El país ha producido a atletas numerosos de la mundo-clase, particularmente en tenis, la natación, y la pista.</Spanish>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_AUSTRIAN_HOFMUSEEN_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]The construction of the Ringstrasse as a reaction to the events of the 1848 Revolutions resulted in many important cultural building being constructed.  One of these buildings was the Hofmuseen, or court museums.  Currently, the artistic works of the Hofmuseen are located in the Leopold Museum in Vienna.</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_BAKTRIA_MINT_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]Not much today exists to tell us of these strange Greeks from India.  Well positioned on the Silk Road from Anatolia to Far East Asia.  The Baktrians were a wealthy people.  They were also rich in mineral deposits such as gold.  Their mints were famous for their skills in making coins.[NEWLINE][TAB]Their coins were some of the most technologically advanced, sophisticated and aesthetically pleasing to all of those from the ancient world.  Finally the largest gold coin ever minted that has been discovered came from a Baktrian Mint.</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_BANGLADESH_KABADDI_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]Kabaddi is a combative team game, played with absolutely no equipment, in a rectangular court, either out-doors -or indoors with seven players on the ground in each side. Each -side takes alternate chances at offence and defense. The basic idea of the game is to score points by raiding into the opponents court and touching as many defense players as possible without getting caught on a single breath. During play, the players on the defensive side are called "Antis" while the player of the offense is called the "Raider". Kabaddi is perhaps the only combative sport in which attack is an individual attempt while defense is a group effort.</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_BATAVII_STABLE_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]The Batavians were master horsemen.  Their troops furnished great numbers of horsemen to the Roman Empire and graves of Batavian soldiers have been found in Brittan and Romania with their horses.[NEWLINE][TAB]One of the many skills the Batavian horsemen were said to have had is the ability to make their horses swim across rivers with full battle armor on all the while in perfect formation.  To do this their horses must have been trained from the time they were foals to adulthood.</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_BELGIUM_FRITKOT_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]A Belgian legend claims that the term "French" was introduced when British or American soldiers arrived in Belgium during World War I, and consequently tasted Belgian fries. They supposedly called them "French", as it was the official language of the Belgian Army at that time.[PARAGRAPH:1]Whether or not Belgians invented them, "frites" became the national snack and a substantial part of both national dishes, making the Belgians their largest per capita consumers[citation needed] in Europe and their "symbolic" creators. The national dishes are "steak and fries with salad", and "mussels with fries".</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_BOLIVARIAN_CHUAOFIELD_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]Remote and inaccessible, Chuao is a village in modern-day Venezuela. It is renowned for producing some of the finest cocoa beans in the world. These beans, of the criollo variety, have become increasingly rare due to disease and interbreeding with other species of cocoa. The town itself is largely given over to production of the highly-sought after bean; the central square and many public spaces are used for drying and fermenting the cocoa.</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_BOULEVARD_CIRCLE_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]Boulevard Circle and its key element, channel, embrace the Old Riga from three sides, enclosed by the Daugava River from the remaining side. Ensemble of parks, created after 1856, became the first stage of fortification system reconstruction commenced in the 17th century by Swedish military engineers. Extensive parks with few loosely scattered buildings and residential blocks have become a wonderful counterpoint to the Old Riga. Boulevard Circle separates the Old Riga from Art Noveau blocks in the centre.</English>
      <French>Not in French</French>
      <German>Not in German</German>
      <Italian>Not in Italian</Italian>
      <Spanish>Not in Spanish</Spanish>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_BRAZIL_ESTADIO_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]The most popular sport in Brazil is football (soccer), and the country is renowned for the quality of its players. The Brazilian national football team has been victorious in the World Cup tournament a record five times. Soccer is a "way of life" for millions of Brazilians and exerts an immense influence in a social context of Brazil. The history of soccer in Brazil has a direct correlation with the history of the people and perhaps can be the best explanation of the Brazil soccer appreciation and style.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]In theory, various people from different continents of the world helped build a unique Brazilian culture. The Brazilian soccer style clearly signifies culture of its people who dance samba and use creativity and swing to promote various rhythms and choreographies. Soccer then takes the form of art and its player's plays the role of soccer artists. This agility is valued by the Brazilian popular culture through the dance, capoeira, and soccer.</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_BROCH_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]Brochs are Iron Age dry stone hollow-walled structures found only in Scotland.  Brochs are some of the most sophisticated examples of dry stone architecture ever created.  The origin of brochs is still a subject of research.  Originally, archaeologists believed that brochs were built by an influx of immigrants pushed northward first by the Belgic tribes in southeast England and later by the Roman invasion of England.  However, there was never doubt that brochs were a Scottish invention.  The distribution of brochs is centered on northern Scotland, but some can be found on the borders and on the west coast of Scotland.  [PARAGRAPH: 1] The original interpretation of brochs was that they were defensive structures, places of refuge for the community and their livestock.  Another theory is that they are castles where local landowners held sway over a subject population.  A more recent theory is that brochs were the stately homes of their time.  However, there is lack of proof for this theory as well.  The fact that brochs are found in groupings may also suggest that they had a defensive or offensive function.  Some site beside cliffs and were protected by large ramparts.</English>
      <French>[TAB]Brochs âge de fer sont en pierre sèche creux à parois des structures que l'on retrouve uniquement en Ecosse. Brochs sont quelques-uns des exemples les plus sophistiqués de l'architecture en pierre sèche jamais créé. L'origine de brochs est encore un sujet de recherche. Al'origine, les archéologues estime que brochs ont été construits par un afflux d'immigrants poussés vers le nord en premier par le Belgic tribus dans le sud-Angleterre et, plus tard, par l'invasion romaine de l'Angleterre. Cependant, il n'y avait jamais eu de doute que brochs sont une invention écossaise. La répartition des brochs est centré sur le nord de l'Ecosse, mais certains peuvent être trouvés sur les frontières et sur la côte ouest de l'Ecosse. [PARAGRAPH 1] À l'origine, l'interprétation des brochs est qu'ils sont des structures défensives, des lieux de refuge pour la communauté et de leur bétail. Une autre théorie est qu'ils sont des châteaux, où les propriétaires terriens locaux a frappé la population sur un sujet. Plus récemment, la théorie est que brochs sont les demeures de leur temps. Cependant, il ya un manque de preuve pour cette théorie aussi. Le fait que l'on trouve dans brochs groupements peut également penser que ceux-ci avaient une fonction défensive ou offensive. Certains site à côté des falaises et étaient protégées par de grands remparts.</French>
      <German>[TAB]Brochs sind Eisenzeit trocken hohlen Stein-walled Strukturen, die nur in Schottland. Brochs sind einige der modernsten Beispiele für trockene Stein-Architektur jemals erstellt. Der Ursprung der brochs ist noch Gegenstand der Forschung. Ursprünglich, Archäologen glaubten, dass brochs wurden durch einen Zustrom von Immigranten nach Norden gedrängt erste von der belgischen Stämme im Südosten von England und später von der römischen Invasion Englands. Allerdings gab es nie Zweifel daran, dass brochs waren eine schottische Erfindung. Die Verteilung der brochs ist zentriert im Norden Schottlands, aber einige finden sich an den Grenzen und an der Westküste Schottlands. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Die ursprüngliche Auslegung des brochs war, dass sie waren defensive Strukturen, die Orte der Zuflucht für die Gemeinschaft und ihre Tiere. Eine andere Theorie ist, dass sie die Burgen, wo lokale Landbesitzer hielt Herrschaft über ein Thema Bevölkerung. Eine neuere Theorie ist, dass brochs waren die stattlichen Häuser ihrer Zeit. Allerdings gibt es Mangel an Beweisen für diese Theorie als gut. Die Tatsache, dass brochs finden sich in Gruppen können auch darauf hin, dass sie eine defensive oder offensive Funktion. Einige Website neben Klippen und wurden durch große Wälle.</German>
      <Italian>[TAB]Brochs sono Età del ferro cave di pietra a secco pareti strutture trovate solo in Scozia. Brochs sono alcuni dei più sofisticati esempi di architettura in pietra a secco mai creato. L'origine di brochs è ancora un argomento di ricerca. Originariamente, archeologi brochs creduto che sono state costruite da un afflusso di immigranti spinto verso nord dalla prima Belgic tribù in Inghilterra e poi a sud-est dal Romano invasione d'Inghilterra. Tuttavia, non c'è mai stato dubbio che fosse un brochs scozzese invenzione. La distribuzione di brochs è centrata sul nord della Scozia, ma alcuni possono essere trovate sui confini e sulla costa occidentale della Scozia. [PARAGRAPH: 1] L'originale interpretazione del brochs era che fossero le strutture difensive, luoghi di rifugio per la comunità e il loro bestiame. Un'altra teoria è che sono castelli terrieri locali dove terrà regnare su un argomento popolazione. Un più recente teoria è che brochs erano le dimore del loro tempo. Tuttavia, vi è la mancanza di prove per questa teoria pure. Il fatto che si trovano in brochs raggruppamenti possono anche suggerire che avevano una funzione difensiva o offensiva. Alcuni sito accanto e scogliere erano protetti da grandi bastioni.</Italian>
      <Spanish>[TAB]Brochs son la Edad de Hierro de piedra seca de paredes huecas estructuras que se encuentran sólo en Escocia. Brochs son algunos de los más sofisticados ejemplos de la arquitectura de piedra seca que jamás se han creado. El origen de brochs es todavía un tema de la investigación. Originalmente, los arqueólogos cree que brochs fueron construidas por la afluencia de inmigrantes hacia el norte empujado primero por el Belgic tribus en el sudeste de Inglaterra y más tarde por la invasión romana de Inglaterra. Sin embargo, nunca hubo dudas de que brochs fueron una invención de Escocia. La distribución de brochs se centra en el norte de Escocia, pero algunas se pueden encontrar en las fronteras y en la costa oeste de Escocia. [PARAGRAPH: 1] El original interpretación de brochs es que son estructuras defensivas, los lugares de refugio para la comunidad y su ganado. Otra teoría es que son los propietarios de las tierras donde castillos celebrada domina un tema de población. Una teoría más reciente es la que se brochs casas de su tiempo. Sin embargo, no hay falta de la prueba de esta teoría también. El hecho de que se encuentran en brochs agrupaciones también puede sugerir que tenían una función defensiva u ofensiva. Algunos sitio al lado de los acantilados y están protegidas por grandes murallas.</Spanish>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_BURMA_PAYA_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]A paya or stupa is a Buddhist structure made up of five constituent parts. Each component is rich in metaphoric content. For example, "the shape of the stupa represents the Buddha, crowned and sitting in meditation posture on a lion throne. His crown is the top of the spire; his head is the square at the spire's base; his body is the vase shape; his legs are the four steps of the lower terrace; and the base is his throne." The components of the stupa are also identified with the five elements - earth, water, fire, air, and space - held to constitute the fabric of manifest existence.</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_CAER_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]A caer is a royal residence in Wales during the first millenium AD or earlier.  Caer can be loosely translated into castle, palace, or fort, but no English word captures the same characteristics as a caer.  A caer was the home to both the king, his royal family, and entourage which consisted of loyal retainers, monks, scholars, chief advisors, and bards who provided entertainment.  Caers were renowned for their great feasts that lasted as long as a year.  In these feasts, kings and upper classes of multiple kingdoms would meet to show wealth and status in society.  Caers weren't only palaces, they were defenseive fortresses.  They were usually hill forts, like the Cameot hill fort at South Cadbury in Somerset, or the coastal forts like Tintagen in Cornwall and Aberdyfi in Ceredigion.  Small kingdoms only contained one caer, but larger ones contained many.</English>
      <French>[TAB]Un caer est une résidence royale au pays de Galles au cours du premier millénaire après JC ou même plus tôt. Caer peut être librement traduit en château, palais, ni forteresse, mais aucun mot anglais saisit les mêmes caractéristiques comme caer. Un caer la maison était à la fois le roi, sa famille royale, et de l'entourage qui se composait de fidèles vassaux, des moines, des universitaires, des conseillers en chef, et qui lui ont fourni des bardes de divertissement. Caers étaient réputés pour leurs grandes fêtes qui a duré aussi longtemps que d'un an. Dans ces fêtes, les rois et les classes supérieures de plusieurs royaumes se réuniront pour montrer la richesse et le statut dans la société. Caers ne sont pas seulement les palais, ils étaient defenseive forteresses. Ils étaient généralement collines fortifiées, à l'instar de la Cameot colline fort à Cadbury dans le Somerset Sud, les zones côtières ou les forts comme Tintagen à Cornwall et Aberdyfi en Ceredigion. Les petits royaumes ne contenait un caer, mais beaucoup plus gros contenus.</French>
      <German>[TAB]Ein caer ist eine königliche Wohnsitz in Wales während des ersten Jahrtausends n. Chr. oder früher. Caer kann locker ins Schloss, Palast oder Festung, aber kein Wort Englisch erfasst die gleichen Eigenschaften wie ein caer. Ein caer wurde das Haus an den König, seine königliche Familie und Umgebung, bestehend aus treuen Begleiter, Mönche, Gelehrte, Chef Berater, und Sänger, die eine Unterhaltung. Caers waren bekannt für ihre große Feste, dass, so lange dauerte als ein Jahr. In diesen Feste, Könige und der oberen Klassen mehrerer Königreiche würde zu zeigen, Reichtum und Status in der Gesellschaft. Caers waren nicht nur Paläste, wurden sie defenseive Festungen. Sie waren in der Regel Hügel Festungen, wie die Cameot Hügel Kastell von South Cadbury in der Somerset, oder an der Küste Festungen wie Tintagen im Cornwall und Aberdyfi im Ceredigion. Kleine Königreiche, die nur ein caer, sondern größere enthielt viele.</German>
      <Italian>[TAB]Un caer è una residenza reale in Galles durante il primo millennio dC o precedenti. Caer può essere liberamente tradotto in castello, palazzo, o forte, ma nessuna parola inglese cattura le stesse caratteristiche di uno caer. Un caer è stata la patria di entrambi il re, la sua famiglia reale, e che consisteva di seguito retainers, leale, monaci, studiosi, capo consulenti, e bards che ha fornito intrattenimento. Caers erano famosi per le loro grandi feste che finché è durato un anno. In queste feste, re e superiore di più classi regni si riunirà per mostrare la ricchezza e lo statuto della società. Caers sono stati non solo i palazzi, erano defenseive fortezze. Essi sono stati in genere collina forti, come la Cameot collina forte a Sud Cadbury nel Somerset, o costiere forti come Tintagen in Cornovaglia e Aberdyfi nel Ceredigion. Piccoli regni contenuto solo uno caer, ma quelli di maggiori dimensioni contenute molte.</Italian>
      <Spanish>[TAB]A caer es una residencia real en el País de Gales durante el primer milenio dC o antes. Caer puede ser vagamente traducido al castillo, palacio o fortaleza, pero no capta la palabra Inglés mismas características como caer. A caer fue el hogar de ambos el rey, su familia real, y que consistía séquito de leales retenedores, los monjes, estudiosos, jefe de asesores y bardos que siempre entretenimiento. Caers eran famosas por sus grandes fiestas, que duró tanto como un año. En estas fiestas, los reyes y las clases altas de múltiples reinos se reunirá para mostrar la riqueza y la condición en la sociedad. Caers no sólo son palacios, que se defenseive fortalezas. Se les suele colinas fortificadas, como la Cameot colina fuerte en el Sur Cadbury en Somerset, la zona costera o fuertes como Tintagen en Cornwall y Aberdyfi en Ceredigion. Pequeños reinos sólo figura un caer, pero más grandes que figuran muchos.</Spanish>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_CHILE_COPPERWORKS_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]Copper has played a large role in the Chilean economy since at least 1825, when British and Americans were already competingwith other foreign investors to control Chile's copper and silver market.  By 1835, Chile was exporting 12,700 tons of copper a year, much of it to the United States.  Copper accounted for fifty-five per cent of the country's economy by 1860.  Chile became highly dependent upon its copper exports. After the War of the Pacific (1879-83), the quantity of copper that Chile mined continued to skyrocket.  Although the demand for copper put Chile way ahead of other nations in the region, its increasing dependence on copper put it at the mercy of the world market.</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_CHITALISHTE_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]A chitalishte is a Bulgarian organization and edifice which accomplishes numerous functions at once, including a community center, library, and theater.  It is also used as an educational institution, where people of various ages can take a foreign language, dance, music, and other courses.  The chitalishta of the 19th and 20th centuries played a vital role in protecting and developing Bulgarian culture.  The first chitalishta appeared in the 1850s, and later evolved into a building that would serve many purposes.</English>
      <French>[TAB]Un chitalishte est une organisation et un édifice qui accomplit de nombreuses fonctions immédiatement, y compris un centre social, bibliothèque, et un théâtre bulgares.  Il est également employé en tant qu'établissement éducatif, où les gens de divers âges peuvent prendre une langue étrangère, la danse, la musique, et d'autres cours.  Le chitalishta des 19èmes et 20èmes siècles a joué un rôle essentiel en protégeant et en développant la culture bulgare.  Le premier chitalishta est apparu dans le 1850s, et plus tard s'est transformé en un bâtiment qui atteindrait beaucoup d'objectifs.</French>
      <German>[TAB]Ein chitalishte ist eine bulgarische Organisation und ein Gebäude, das zahlreiche Funktionen sofort, einschließlich ein Einkaufszentrum, Bibliothek vollendet, und ein Theater.  Es wird auch als pädagogische Anstalt verwendet, in der Leute des verschiedenen Alters eine Fremdsprache, Tanz, Musik und andere Kurse nehmen können.  Das chitalishta der 19. und 20. Jahrhunderte spielte eine lebenswichtige Rolle in dem Schützen und der bulgarischen Kultur entwickelnd.  Das erste chitalishta erschien im 1850s und entwickelte später in ein Gebäude, das viele Zwecke dienen würde.</German>
      <Italian>[TAB]Un chitalishte è un'organizzazione e una struttura che compie le funzioni numerose immediatamente, compreso un ritrovo comunale, biblioteca e un teatro bulgari.  Inoltre è usato come istituto scolastico, in cui la gente di varie età può prendere una lingua straniera, il ballo, la musica ed altri corsi.  Il chitalishta dei diciannovesimi e ventesimi secoli ha svolto un ruolo vitale nella protezione e nello sviluppare della coltura bulgara.  Il primo chitalishta è comparso nel 1850s e più successivamente si è evoluto in una costruzione che avrebbe molti scopi.</Italian>
      <Spanish>[TAB]Un chitalishte es una organización y un edificio que logra funciones numerosas inmediatamente, incluyendo un centro de comunidad, biblioteca, y un teatro búlgaros.  También se utiliza como institución educativa, en donde la gente de varias edades puede tomar un idioma extranjero, danza, música, y otros cursos.  El chitalishta de los diecinueveavo y vigésimos siglos desempeñó un papel vital en la protección y desarrollar de la cultura búlgara.  El primer chitalishta apareció en el 1850s, y se desarrolló más adelante en un edificio que respondería a muchos propósitos.</Spanish>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_CHOLA_TRADE_GUILD_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]Towards the end of the 9th century, southern India had developed extensive maritime and commercial activity, especially wieconomic reform package called "doi moi" (Renovation). Private ownership was encouraged in industries, commerce and agriculture. In many ways, this followed the Chinese model and achieved similar results. Vietnam achieved significant growth over the next decade-and-a-half, making it the world's second-fastest growing economy of the time.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Upon taking power, Vietnamese communists had created a command economy in the nation. Collectivization of farms, factories and economic capital was implemented, and millions of people put to work in government programs. For many decades, Vietnam's economy was plagued with inefficiency and corruption in state programs. This trend seems to be reversing as a free market begins to take hold within the country.</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_CHORTEN_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]In early India, mounds of earth, brick, and stone were used to house holy Buddhist relics.  These structures became known as stupas.  Their housing of Buddhist relics lead to the stupas as being seen as a symbol of Buddha's final liberation known as nirvana.  As their use spread across Asia with Buddhism, stupas retained their basic function as relic holders.  In Tibet, where they are known as chortens, the form was employed not only for sacred burial monuments, but also for metal reliquaries that are kept on Buddhist temple altars.  Tibetan chortens are overcome by elaborate tiered finials, often decorated with streamers and flags. [PARAGRAPH: 1] As well as ornate reliquaries set with precious stones and grand temples, such as the Pango Chorten in Gyantse, chortens can take the form of simple wayside markers made from little more than piles of rocks on the circuit around Mount Kailas.  They can be seen throughout the Tibetan countryside.  They offer weary pilgrims and other travelers the spiritual reassurance that, wherever they may find themselves, the Buddha is all around.</English>
      <French>[TAB]Au début de l'Inde, des monticules de terre, la brique et la pierre sont utilisés pour abriter les reliques saintes bouddhistes. Ces structures que l'on a appelé stupas. Leur logement de reliques bouddhiques conduire à la stupas comme étant perçue comme un symbole de la libération finale de Bouddha connu sous le nirvana. Comme leur utilisation répandre dans toute l'Asie avec le bouddhisme, stupas conservé leur fonction de base comme relique titulaires. Au Tibet, où ils sont connus comme chortens, le formulaire a été utilisé non seulement pour les monuments funéraires sacrés, mais aussi pour que le métal reliquaires sont gardées sur temple bouddhiste autels. Tibétain chortens sont surmontés par paliers élaborer embouts, souvent décorée de banderoles et drapeaux. [PARAGRAPHE 1] En plus de fixer des reliquaires orné de pierres précieuses, et les grands temples, tels que le Pango Chorten à Gyantse, chortens peuvent prendre la forme de simples marqueurs de voie de faits peu plus que des amas de roches sur le circuit autour du Mont Kailas . Ils peuvent être vus à travers le paysage tibétain. Ils offrent las pèlerins et autres voyageurs spirituels rassurer que, partout où ils se trouvent, le Bouddha est partout.</French>
      <German>[TAB]In frühen Indien, Hügel der Erde, Ziegel und Steine wurden verwendet, um Haus heiligen buddhistischen Reliquien. Diese Strukturen wurde bekannt als Stupas. Ihr Gehäuse von buddhistischen Reliquien führen zu den Stupas als als ein Symbol für die endgültige Befreiung Buddha bekannt als Nirvana. Da ihre Verwendung in ganz Asien mit dem Buddhismus, Stupas behalten ihre grundlegende Funktion als Relikt Inhaber. In Tibet, wo sie sind bekannt als Chörten, die Form war nicht nur für die heiligen Begräbnisstätte Denkmal, sondern auch für die Metall-Reliquien aufbewahrt, die auf buddhistischen Tempel Altäre. Tibetischen Chörten sind durch aufwändige Tiered finials, oft verziert mit Luftschlangen und Fahnen. [ABSATZ: 1] Neben Reliquienschreine verziert mit Edelsteinen und großen Tempel, wie der Pango Chorten in Gyantse, Chörten können in Form von einfachen Strecke Marker aus nicht viel mehr als Haufen von Felsen auf der Rennstrecke um den Berg Kailas . Sie können sich in der gesamten tibetischen Landschaft. Sie bieten müden Pilger und andere Reisende die spirituelle Zusicherung, dass, wo immer sie sich finden, die Buddha ist rund um die Uhr.</German>
      <Italian>[TAB]Ai primi di India, montagne di terra, di mattoni, pietra, e sono stati utilizzati per casa santa reliquie buddiste. Queste strutture divenne noto come stupa. I loro alloggi di reliquie buddiste portare alla stupa ad essere visto come un simbolo di liberazione finale di Buddha conosciuto come il nirvana. Come il loro uso diffuso in tutta l'Asia con il buddismo, stupa conservato la loro funzione di base, come reliquia titolari. In Tibet, dove sono noti come chortens, il modulo è stato impiegato non solo per la sepoltura dei monumenti sacri, ma anche per metallo reliquiari, che sono tenuti al tempio buddista altari. Tibetano chortens sono superate da elaborare livelli finials, spesso decorata con striscioni e bandiere. [PARAGRAFO: 1] Oltre a impostare reliquiari ornato con pietre preziose, e grandi templi, come il Pango Chorten e Gyantse, chortens può assumere la forma di un semplice marcatori strada fatta da poco più di cumuli di pietra sul circuito attorno al monte Kailas . Essi possono essere visti in tutto il paesaggio tibetano. Essi offrono stanchi pellegrini e altri viaggiatori spirituale rassicurazione che, ovunque si trovino, il Buddha è tutto intorno.</Italian>
      <Spanish>[TAB]A principios de la India, montículos de tierra, ladrillo, piedra y fueron utilizados para albergar las reliquias sagradas budistas. Estas estructuras se conoció como stupas. Su vivienda de reliquias budistas llevar a la stupas de ser visto como un símbolo de la liberación definitiva de Buda conocida como nirvana. Como su uso extendido a través de Asia con el budismo, stupas conservado su función básica como reliquia titulares. En el Tíbet, en los que se conoce como chortens, fue la forma empleada no sólo para el entierro monumentos sagrados, pero también de metal relicarios que se mantienen en templo budista altares. Chortens tibetano se superen por elaborar en niveles terminaciones, a menudo decorada con banderas y serpentinas. [APARTADO: 1] Además de relicarios conjunto adornado con piedras preciosas, y grandes templos, como el Pango Chorten en Gyantse, chortens puede adoptar la forma de marcadores camino simple hecho de poco más de pilas de rocas en el circuito de todo el monte Kailas . Que se puede ver todo el paisaje tibetano. Ofrecen cansados peregrinos y otros viajeros de la tranquilidad espiritual de que, dondequiera que se encuentren, el Buda está por todas partes.</Spanish>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_CLOISTER_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>Monastacism grew greatly during the twelfth century, and its reflection in architecture can be found in cloisters.  Before the twelfth century, cloisters were rarely seen.  The earliest visible cloister in Lombardy is the clositer at S. Alberto di Pizzo Como.  Lombard cloisters commonly possessed features like single colonnettes, central doorways, and archivolts of an unmoulded order.  These features were replaced with features native to Provence.  Cloisters with coupled colonnettes had been built in Lombardy as early as 1100.  These clositers show characteristics of those of Provence, Languedoc, and Spain.  The Lombard cloister is perhaps best represented at S. Zeno of Verona, which was built between 1175 and 1200.  The first vaulted cloisters could be found at Vezzolano.  The cloisters here date from 1180 to 1189.  The vault and decorations of these cloisters commonly contained French influence.  This style of cloister was reproduced in the thirteenth century by the Goths at Chiaravelle.</English>
      <French>Monastacism s'est développé considérablement pendant le douzième siècle, et sa réflexion dans l'architecture peut être trouvée dans les cloîtres. Avant le douzième siècle, des cloîtres ont été rarement vus. Le cloître évident le plus tôt en Lombardie est le clositer chez S. Alberto di Pizzo Como. Lombard cloître les dispositifs généralement possédés comme des colonnettes simples, portes centrales, et les archivolts de l'unmoulded l'ordre. Ces dispositifs ont été remplacés avec des dispositifs indigènes en Provence. Des cloîtres avec des colonnettes couplés avaient été construits en Lombardie dès 1100. Ces clositers montrent des caractéristiques de ceux de la Provence, du Languedoc, et de l'Espagne. Le cloître de Lombard peut-être mieux est représenté à S. Zeno de Vérone, qui a été construit entre 1175 et 1200. Les premiers cloîtres sautés ont pu être trouvés chez Vezzolano. Les cloîtres ici datent de 1180 à 1189. La chambre forte et les décorations de ces cloîtres ont généralement contenu l'influence de Français. Ce modèle de cloître a été reproduit au treizième siècle par le Goths chez Chiaravelle.</French>
      <German>Monastacism wuchs groß während des twelfth Jahrhunderts, und seine Reflexion in der Architektur kann in den Klöstern gefunden werden. Vor dem twelfth Jahrhundert wurden Klöster selten gesehen. Das früheste sichtbare Kloster in Lombardei ist das clositer bei S. Alberto di Pizzo Como. Lombard kapselt allgemein besessene Eigenschaften wie einzelne colonnettes, zentrale Eingänge ab, und archivolts von unmoulded Auftrag. Diese Eigenschaften wurden mit den Eigenschaften ersetzt, die nach Provence gebürtig sind. Klöster mit verbundenen colonnettes waren in Lombardei schon in 1100 errichtet worden. Diese clositers zeigen Eigenschaften von denen von Provence, von Languedoc und von Spanien. Das Lombard Kloster wird möglicherweise gut an S. Zeno von Verona dargestellt, das zwischen 1175 und 1200 errichtet wurde. Die ersten vaulted Klöster konnten bei Vezzolano gefunden werden. Die Klöster hier datieren von 1180 bis 1189. Die Wölbung und die Dekorationen dieser Klöster enthielten allgemein Franzoseeinfluß. Diese Art des Klosters wurde im dreizehnten Jahrhundert durch das Goths bei Chiaravelle reproduziert.</German>
      <Italian>Monastacism si è sviluppato notevolmente durante il twelfth secolo e la relativa riflessione nell'architettura può essere trovata in cloisters. Prima del twelfth secolo, i cloisters sono stati visti raramente. Il cloister visibile più in anticipo in Lombardia è il clositer a S. Alberto di Pizzo Como. Lombard cloisters le caratteristiche comunemente possedute come i singoli colonnettes, porte centrali e i archivolts dell'unmoulded l'ordine. Queste caratteristiche sono state sostituite con le caratteristiche natali in Provenza. I Cloisters con i colonnettes coppia erano stati costruiti in Lombardia fin da 1100. Questi clositers mostrano le caratteristiche di quelli della Provenza, di Languedoc e della Spagna. Il cloister del Lombard forse è rappresentato il più bene allo S. Zeno di Verona, che è stata costruita fra 1175 e 1200. I primi cloisters vaulted hanno potuto essere trovati a Vezzolano. I cloisters qui datano da 1180 a 1189. La volta e le decorazioni di questi cloisters hanno contenuto comunemente l'influenza del francese. Questo stile del cloister è stato riprodotto nel tredicesimo secolo dal Goths a Chiaravelle.</Italian>
      <Spanish>Monastacism creció grandemente durante el twelfth siglo, y su reflexión en arquitectura se puede encontrar en cloisters. Antes del twelfth siglo, los cloisters fueron vistos raramente. El cloister visible más temprano de Lombardía es el clositer en S. Alberto di Pizzo Como. Lombard cloisters características comúnmente poseídas como los solos colonnettes, umbrales centrales, y los archivolts del unmoulded orden. Estas características fueron substituidas por las características nativas a Provence. Los Cloisters con colonnettes juntados habían sido construidos en Lombardía desde 1100. Estos clositers demuestran características de los de Provence, de Languedoc, y de España. El cloister de Lombard quizás se representa lo más mejor posible en S. Zeno de Verona, que fue construida entre 1175 y 1200. Los primeros cloisters saltados se podían encontrar en Vezzolano. Los cloisters aquí fechan a partir de 1180 a 1189. La cámara acorazada y las decoraciones de estos cloisters contuvieron comúnmente influencia del francés. Este estilo del cloister fue reproducido en el décimotercer siglo por el Goths en Chiaravelle.</Spanish>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_COLOMBIA_COFFEE_ESTATE_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]Historical data indicates that the Jesuits brought coffee seeds to South America with them circa 1730 CE, but there are different versions of this. Tradition says that the coffee seeds were brought by a traveler from Guyana who passed through Venezuela before reaching Colombia. The oldest written testimony of the presence of coffee in Colombia is attributed to a Jesuit priest, José Gumilla. In his book The Orinoco Illustrated (1730), he registered the presence of coffee in the mission of Saint Teresa of Tabajé, near where the Meta river empties into the Orinoco. Further testimony comes from the archbishop-viceroy Caballero y Gongora (1787) who registered the presence of the crop in the north east of the country near Giron (Santander) and Muzo (Boyaca) in a report that he provided to the Spanish authorities.  The first coffee crops were planted in the eastern part of the country. In 1835 the first commercial production was registered with 2,560 green coffee bags that were exported from the port of Cucuta, near the border with Venezuela. A priest named Francisco Romero is attributed to have been very influential in the propagation of the crop in the northeast region of the country. After hearing the confession of the parishioners of the town of Salazar de la Palmas, he required as penance the cultivation of coffee. Coffee became established in the departments of Santander and North Santander, Cundinamarca, Antioquia, and the historic region of Caldas.  Despite these early developments, the consolidation of coffee as a Colombian export did not come about until the second half of the 19th century. The great expansion that the world economy underwent at that time allowed Colombian landowners to find attractive opportunities in international markets. Little by little, the United States became the most important consumer of coffee in the world, while Germany and France became the most important markets in Europe.  The then large Colombian landowners had already tried to exploit the new opportunities that the expansion of the international markets offered. Between 1850 and 1857 the country experienced a significant increase in tobacco and quinine exports, and thereafter leather and live cattle. These early efforts in the export of agricultural commodities turned out too fragile; they in fact were only reactionary attempts to find the greatest profitability from the high international prices of the time, rather than attempts to create a solid and diversified export platform. The production of these sectors went into period of decline when the respective bonanza of their international prices terminated, hence a true industrial consolidation was prevented.With the fall of international prices, that registered the transition from the 19th to the 20th century, the profitability of the large estates plummeted. As if this was not enough the Thousand Days War, which took place during the first years of the new century, also negatively influenced the important landowners, making it impossible for them to maintain their plantations in good conditions; this circumstance summed to the fact that these producers had incurred in large amounts of foreign debt in order to further develop their plantations, which finally ruined them. The coffee estates of Santander and North Santander entered into crisis and the estates of Cundinamarca and Antioquia stalled.  The crisis that affected the large estates brought with it one of the most significant changes of the Colombian coffee industry. Since 1875 the number of small coffee producers had begun to grow in Santander as well as in some regions of Antioquia and in the region referred to as Viejo or Old Caldas. In the first decades of the 20th century a new model to develop coffee exports based on the rural economy had already been consolidated, supported by internal migration and the colonization of new territories in the center and western regions of the country, principally in the departments of Antioquia, Caldas, Valle, and in the northern part of Tolima. Both the expansion of this new coffee model and the crisis that affected the large estates allowed the western regions of Colombia to take the lead in the development of the coffee industry in the country.  This transformation was very favorable for the owners of the small coffee estates that were entering the coffee market. The cultivation of coffee was a very attractive option for local farmers, as it offered the possibility of making permanent and intensive use of the land. Under this productive model of the traditional agriculture, based on the slash and burn method, the land remained unproductive for long periods of time. In contrast, coffee offered the possibility of having an intense agriculture, without major technical requirements and without sacrificing the cultivation of subsistence crops, thus generating the conditions for the expansion of a new coffee culture, dominated by small farms.  Although this new breed of coffee farmers demonstrated a significant capacity to grow at the margin of current international prices, Colombia did not have a relatively important dynamism in the global market of this product. As can be observed in the following graph, during the period between 1905 and 1935 the coffee industry in Colombia grew dynamically thanks to the vision and long term politics derived from the creation of the National Federation of Coffee Growers of Colombia in 1927.  The union of local farmers and small producers around the Federation has permitted them to confront logistical and commercial difficulties that would not have been possible individually. With time and through the research made at Cenicafé,  founded in 1938, and the Federation's agricultural Extension Service, improved cultivation systems. More efficient spatial patterns were developed that permitted the differentiation of the product and supported its quality. Currently the Land of Coffee in Colombia includes all of the mountain ranges and other mountainous regions of the country, and generates income for over 500,000 coffee farming families.</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_CONGO_NKISI_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]An Nkisi (plural Minkisi, also Nkishi/Minkishi), literally translates as "sacred medicine". The term Nkisi is the general name for a variety of objects used throughout the Congo Basin in Central Africa thought to contain spiritual powers or spirits (called "mpungo"). Minkisi serve many purposes. Some are used in divination practices. Many are used for healing, while others provide success in hunting, trade, or sex. Important minkisi are often credited with powers in multiple domains. Most famously, minkisi may also take the form of anthropomorphic or zoomorphic wooden carvings, and it is these that have principally interested art historians.</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_CORTEGIANE_ONESTE_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]Talented prostitutes might escape the brothel to convert themselves into courtesans, women who controlled sexual commerce and found their clientele among rich and cultivated men.  Venice, where ruling families preserved their wealth by restricting marriage to one or two sons, were renowned for their many "honorable courtesans" (cortegiane oneste).  Numerous courtesans succeeded in entering literary and humanist circles, and a few became celebrated poets.</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_CROATIA_KINGSTOWER_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]The use of fortification and guard towers have been critical throughout Croatia's military history. There geography, bound by sea and mountains, has required a defense facilitated by the types of advantages provided by guard towers.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]The defensive towers of west and south European fortifications in the Middle Ages were often very regularly and uniformly constructed, whereas Central European city walls tend to show a variety of different styles. In these cases, the gate and wall towers often reach up to considerable heights, and gates equipped with two towers on either side are much rarer. Apart from the purely military, defensive purpose, towers also played an important representative and artistic role in the conception of a fortified complex. In many senses, the architecture of the city thus competed with that of the castle of the noble men and city walls were often a manifestation of the pride of a particular city.</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_CZECH_VYSILAC_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]The first attempts at radio broadcasting in Czechoslovakia began after the First World War. The first radio programme, made up of words and music, was broadcast on the first anniversary of the establishment of independent Czechoslovakia on October 28th, 1918, from the telegraph station at Prague's Petrin lookout tower. Regular radio broadcasts began on May 18th 1923, from a military tent in Prague-Kbely, making Czechoslovakia the second European country after the UK to have regular radio broadcasting. The year 1926 saw the introduction of several novelties, such as the time signal and regular news bulletins that were produced by Czechoslovak Press Agency.</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DENMARK_MANOR_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]For centuries, most of Denmark was divided into a relatively small number of large estates, the farms of gentlemen. The seats of such estates were the herregaarde, or manor houses. There are still more than 400 manor houses in Denmark, dating from as far back as 1200 and as recently as 1915. Today, about 80 of these stately houses are open, at least in part, to the public. Time has wrought changes, sometimes peculiar changes, in these sturdy ghosts. But all are windows on a time when luxury, beauty, art and even the splendor of nature were the birthright of the lucky few.[PARAGRAPH:1]</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_DINNEHIH_HOGAN_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]The hogan is considered sacred to those who practice the Navajo religion. The religious song "The Blessingway" describes the first hogan as being built by Coyote with help from beavers to be a house for First Man, First Woman, and Talking God. The Beaver People gave Coyote logs and instructions on how to build the first hogan, now known as a "forked stick" or "male" hogan. This hogan resembles a pyramid with five triangular faces. Earth may fill the spaces between the framework logs, hiding the five faceted shape and creating thick, winter-protective walls. Today, while some older hogans are still used as dwellings and others are maintained for ceremonial purposes, new hogans are rarely intended as family dwellings.</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_ETRURIA_FANUM_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]The Fanum Voltumnae, or shrine of Voltumna, was the chief sanctuary of the Etruscans (fanum means sacred place, a much broader notion than a single temple). Numerous sources refer to a league of the "Twelve Peoples" (lucumonies) of Etruria, formed for religious purposes but evidently having some political functions. The league of 12 city states met annually at the Fanum, located in a place chosen as omphalos (sacred navel), the geographical and spiritual centre of the whole Etruscan nation. Each spring the political and religious leaders from the cities would meet to discuss military campaigns, civic affairs and pray to their common gods. Chief amongst these was Voltumna (or Veltha), god of the underworld. Historians have been looking for the Fanum from at least the 15th century but, until now, the precise location of the shrine is still unknown, though it may have been in an area near modern Orvieto (believed by many to be the ancient Volsinii).[PARAGRAPH:1]Roman historian Titus Livius mentioned the Fanum Voltumnae five times in his works and indicated Volsinii as the place where the shrine was located. He describes the meetings that took place at the Fanum between Etruscan leaders. He refers in particular to a meeting in which two groups applied to assist the city of Veio in a war it was waging. The council's answer was no, because Veio had declared war without first notifying it. Livius also says that Roman merchants who travelled to a huge fair attached to the meeting acted as spies, reporting back on Etruscan affairs to authorities in the city state of Rome. He was alone in mentioning god Voltumna, whereas Marcus Terentius Varro indicated a god prince of Etruria. That the Fanum was somewhere in Central Italy in the area between Orvieto and Viterbo is probable enough, but as Titus Livius has given no clue to its locality, and as no inscriptions have thrown light on the subject, it can be but pure conjecture to assign to it this or that particular site.[PARAGRAPH:1]</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_FINLAND_SAUNA_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]Historical evidence and records indicate that the Finns built the first wooden saunas over 2000 years ago. The early Finnish sauna was dug into a hill or embankment. As tools and techniques advanced, they were later built above ground using wooden logs. Rocks were heated in a stone fireplace with a wood fire. The smoke from the fire filled the room as the air warmed.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Once the temperature reached desired levels, the smoke was allowed to clear and the bathers entered. The wood smoke aroma still lingered and was part of the cleansing ritual. This type of traditional smoke sauna was called a savusauna, which means smoke sauna in Finnish. The smell of smoke and wood is relaxing to most people, especially those who have never been to sauna before. As the home of the sauna, Finnish sauna culture is well established, and plays an ongoing role in the central social structure.</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_FOLWARK_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]Folwarks are giant Polish farms that were operated in the Polish-Lithuanian Commonwealth from the 14th century into the 20th.  They were used to produce a surplus of food.  The first folwarks were created on church and monastery owned grounds, but were later adopted by nobility and rich peasants.  The creation of folwarks was boosted by a growing demand for grain and its high profit. Folwark-based grain export was an important part of the economy of the Polish-Lithuanian commonwealth.  [PARAGRAPH: 1] The fall of agriculture goods prices in the end of the 17th century marked the start of a crisis for the folwark related economy.  The noble's attempt to increase use of folwarks only hurt the economic crisis more.  Until the 18th century, folwarks remained the basis for Polish noble's economic and political power.  After the abolition of serfdom in Poland, folwarks used paid labor.  Folwarks were abolished by the People's Republic of Poland with the PKWN decree of 6 September 1944 about agricultural reform</English>
      <French>[TAB]Folwarks sont géant polonais exploitations qui ont été opérés dans le polonais-lituanien du 14e siècle dans le 20ème. Ils ont servi à produire un excédent de nourriture. La première folwarks ont été créés sur l'église et le monastère appartenant motifs, mais ont par la suite été adopté par la noblesse et les paysans riches. La création de folwarks a été stimulée par une demande croissante de céréales et de sa forte rentabilité. Folwark fondée sur l'exportation de céréales a été une partie importante de l'économie de la polonais-lituanien Commonwealth. [PARAGRAPH: 1] La chute du prix des produits agricoles à la fin du 17e siècle ont marqué le début d'une crise pour la folwark liés économie. La noble tentative d'accroître l'utilisation des folwarks seulement blessé plus de la crise économique. Jusqu'au 18e siècle, folwarks demeure la base d'nobles polonais du pouvoir économique et politique. Après l'abolition du servage en Pologne, folwarks utilisé travail rémunéré. Folwarks ont été abolis par la République populaire de Pologne avec le PKWN décret du 6 septembre 1944 sur la réforme agricole.</French>
      <German>[TAB]Folwarks sind riesigen polnischen Bauernhöfen betrieben, die in der polnisch-litauischen Commonwealth aus dem 14. Jahrhundert in das 20. Jahrhundert. Sie wurden für die Herstellung von einem Überschuss von Lebensmitteln. Die erste folwarks wurden auf Kirche und Kloster im Besitz Gründen, sondern wurden später vom Adel und reichen Bauern. Die Schaffung von folwarks wurde durch eine wachsende Nachfrage nach Getreide und seiner hohen Gewinn. Folwark - auf der Grundlage Getreide exportieren war ein wichtiger Teil der Wirtschaft in der polnisch-litauischen Commonwealth. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Der Rückgang der Landwirtschaft Waren, die Preise in der Ende des 17. Jahrhunderts markiert den Beginn einer Krise für die folwark ähnliche Wirtschaft. Die edle Versuch zur Erhöhung der Nutzung von folwarks nur schaden, die wirtschaftliche Krise. Bis zum 18. Jahrhundert, folwarks blieb die Grundlage für die polnische edlen die wirtschaftliche und politische Macht. Nach der Abschaffung der Leibeigenschaft in Polen, folwarks verwendet Lohnarbeit. Folwarks abgeschafft wurden von der Volksrepublik Polen mit dem PKWN Dekret vom 6. September 1944 über die Agrarreform.</German>
      <Italian>[TAB]Folwarks sono gigante polacco aziende agricole che sono stati operati nel Polacco-Lituano dal 14 ° secolo in 20a. Essi sono stati utilizzati per la produzione di un surplus di cibo. Il primo folwarks sono stati creati sulla chiesa e del convento di proprietà motivi, ma sono stati in seguito adottati dalla nobiltà e ricchi contadini. La creazione di folwarks è stata incentivata da una crescente domanda di cereali e il suo alto profitto. Folwark a base di grano di esportazione è stato una parte importante dell 'economia di Stato polacco - lituano. [PARAGRAPH: 1] La caduta dei prezzi in agricoltura merci alla fine del 17 ° secolo ha segnato l'inizio di una crisi per il folwark connessi economia. Il nobile del tentativo di aumentare l'uso di folwarks solo male la crisi economica più. Fino al 18 ° secolo, folwarks rimasti la base per la nobile polacco potere economico e politico. Dopo l'abolizione della serfdom in Polonia, folwarks utilizzati pagato lavoro. Folwarks sono state abolite dalla Repubblica popolare di Polonia con il PKWN decreto del 6 settembre 1944 sulla riforma agricola.</Italian>
      <Spanish>[TAB]Folwarks son gigantes granjas polacas que fueron operados en la Comunidad de Polonia - Lituania desde el siglo 14 en la 20. Estos recursos se utilizaron para producir un excedente de alimentos. La primera folwarks se crearon en la iglesia y el monasterio de propiedad de motivos, pero luego fueron aprobadas por la nobleza y los campesinos ricos. La creación de folwarks fue impulsada por una creciente demanda de cereales y su alto beneficio. Folwark basado en la exportación de cereales es una parte importante de la economía de la polaca y lituana ELA. [PARAGRAPH: 1] La caída de los precios de los bienes en la agricultura a finales del siglo 17 marcó el inicio de una crisis para la folwark relacionados con la economía. El noble intento de aumentar la utilización de folwarks sólo perjudican la crisis económica más. Hasta el siglo 18, folwarks sigue siendo la base de nobles polacos del poder económico y político. Después de la abolición de la servidumbre de la gleba en Polonia, folwarks utilizados trabajo remunerado. Folwarks fueron abolidas por la República Popular de Polonia con la PKWN decreto de 6 de septiembre de 1944 sobre la reforma agrícola.</Spanish>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_FURDO_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]Since Roman times, bathers have traveled to Budapest to seek out its natural baths.  Today, these hot springs still exist, but other manmade baths have been created.  The hot springs in Hungary contain radium and other minerals that contain unique healing properties.  During the Ottoman occupation of Hungary, numerous baths were built such as Rudas, Gellert, and Kiraly.  Other bath houses can be found in Hungary, such as Csaszar, Lukacs, Rac, Szechenyi, and Dagaly.</English>
      <French>[TAB]Depuis l'époque romaine, les baigneurs se sont rendus à Budapest pour rechercher ses baignoires naturelles. Aujourd'hui, ces sources thermales existent encore, mais d'autres bains de l'homme ont été crés. Les sources thermales en Hongrie contiennent du radium et d'autres minéraux qui comprennent des propriétés curatives. Au cours de l'occupation ottomane de la Hongrie, de nombreux bains ont été construites telles que Rudas, Gellert, et Kiraly. Autres bain maisons peut être trouvée en Hongrie, comme Csaszar, Lukacs, Rac, Szechenyi, et Dagaly.</French>
      <German>[TAB]Seit römischen Zeiten, die Badegäste haben reiste nach Budapest, um ihre natürlichen Bädern. Heute werden diese heißen Quellen noch vorhanden ist, aber auch andere Bäder Menschenhand geschaffen wurden. Die heißen Quellen in Ungarn enthalten Radium und anderen Mineralien, die einzigartige heilende Eigenschaften. Während der osmanischen Besetzung von Ungarn, zahlreiche Bäder gebaut wie Rudas, Gellert, und Kiraly. Andere Bad Häuser befinden sich in Ungarn, wie Csaszar, Lukacs, Rac, Szechenyi, und Dagaly.</German>
      <Italian>[TAB]Fin dai tempi dei romani, i bagnanti sono recato a Budapest per cercare la sua naturale bagni. Oggi, queste sorgenti calde ancora esistono, ma altri manmade bagni sono stati creati. Le sorgenti calde in Ungheria contenere radio e di altri minerali che contengono unica proprietà curative. Durante l'occupazione ottomana di Ungheria, numerosi bagni sono stati costruiti come Rudas, Gellert, e Kiraly. Altri bagno case si possono trovare in Ungheria, come Csaszar, Lukacs, Rac, Szechenyi, e Dagaly.</Italian>
      <Spanish>[TAB]Desde la época de los romanos, los bañistas han viajado a Budapest para buscar sus baños naturales. Hoy en día, estas termas todavía existen, pero otras artificiales baños se han creado. Las fuentes termales contienen Hungría en el radio y otros minerales que contienen propiedades curativas únicas. Durante la ocupación otomana de Hungría, numerosos baños fueron construidos como Rudas, Gellert, y Kiraly. Otras casas de baño se encuentran en Hungría, como Csaszar, Lukacs, Rac, Szechenyi, y Dagaly.</Spanish>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_GEORGIA_SENAKI_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB] Georgia is well known for its rich folklore, unique traditional music, theatre, cinema, and art. Georgians are renowned for their love of music, dance, theatre and cinema. In the 20th century there have been notable Georgian painters, ballet choreographers and poets. Georgian theatre has a long history; its oldest national form was the "Sakhioba" (extant from the 3rd century BC to the 17th century AD). The Georgian National Theatre was founded in 1791 in Tbilisi, by the writer, dramatist and diplomat Giorgi Avalishvili (1769-1850). Its leading actors were Dimitri Aleksi-Meskhishvili, David Machabeli, David Bagrationi, Dimitri Cholokashvili and others.</English>
      <French>[TAB] Georgia is well known for its rich folklore, unique traditional music, theatre, cinema, and art. Georgians are renowned for their love of music, dance, theatre and cinema. In the 20th century there have been notable Georgian painters such as Niko Pirosmani, Lado Gudiashvili, Elene Akhvlediani; ballet choreographers such as George Balanchine, Vakhtang Chabukiani, and Nino Ananiashvili; poets such as Galaktion Tabidze, Lado Asatiani, and Mukhran Machavariani; and theatre and film directors such as Robert Sturua, Tengiz Abuladze, Giorgi Danelia and Otar Ioseliani.</French>
      <German>[TAB] Georgia is well known for its rich folklore, unique traditional music, theatre, cinema, and art. Georgians are renowned for their love of music, dance, theatre and cinema. In the 20th century there have been notable Georgian painters such as Niko Pirosmani, Lado Gudiashvili, Elene Akhvlediani; ballet choreographers such as George Balanchine, Vakhtang Chabukiani, and Nino Ananiashvili; poets such as Galaktion Tabidze, Lado Asatiani, and Mukhran Machavariani; and theatre and film directors such as Robert Sturua, Tengiz Abuladze, Giorgi Danelia and Otar Ioseliani.</German>
      <Italian>[TAB] Georgia is well known for its rich folklore, unique traditional music, theatre, cinema, and art. Georgians are renowned for their love of music, dance, theatre and cinema. In the 20th century there have been notable Georgian painters such as Niko Pirosmani, Lado Gudiashvili, Elene Akhvlediani; ballet choreographers such as George Balanchine, Vakhtang Chabukiani, and Nino Ananiashvili; poets such as Galaktion Tabidze, Lado Asatiani, and Mukhran Machavariani; and theatre and film directors such as Robert Sturua, Tengiz Abuladze, Giorgi Danelia and Otar Ioseliani.</Italian>
      <Spanish>[TAB] Georgia is well known for its rich folklore, unique traditional music, theatre, cinema, and art. Georgians are renowned for their love of music, dance, theatre and cinema. In the 20th century there have been notable Georgian painters such as Niko Pirosmani, Lado Gudiashvili, Elene Akhvlediani; ballet choreographers such as George Balanchine, Vakhtang Chabukiani, and Nino Ananiashvili; poets such as Galaktion Tabidze, Lado Asatiani, and Mukhran Machavariani; and theatre and film directors such as Robert Sturua, Tengiz Abuladze, Giorgi Danelia and Otar Ioseliani.</Spanish>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_GETAI_PORT_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]The more enterprising tribes amongst the Getai used the rivers strewn throughout their lands to establish great networks of trade. They were able to link the variety of settlements that were found on the rivers with one another. Since the Getai had no remarkable tradition of maritime trade, the rivers were a welcome alternative. Rivers were easier to navigate than the open seas, and were found closer to the familiar settings of the mountains and forests. Trade along the rivers provided an extra source of income, and as a result, both great and small cities alike were able achieve wealth by utilizing the circuitous paths of river merchants.</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_GOTHS_PLUNDER_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]After Alaric laid siege to Rome for a third time, the city was taken and Alaric's dream came true. In a grand procession he rode at the head of his army through the streets of the great capital.[PARAGRAPH:1]Then began the work of destruction. The Goths ran in crowds through the city, wrecked private houses and public buildings and seized everything of value they could find. Alaric gave orders that no injury should be done to the Christian churches, but other splendid buildings of the great city were stripped of the beautiful and costly articles that they contained, and all the gold and silver was carried away from the public treasury.[PARAGRAPH:1]In the midst of the pillage Alaric dressed himself in splendid robes and sat upon the throne of the emperor, with a golden crown upon his head.[PARAGRAPH:1]While Alaric was sitting on the throne thousands of Romans were compelled to kneel down on the ground before him and shout out his name as conqueror and emperor. Then the theaters and circuses were opened, and Roman athletes and gladiators had to give performances for the amusement of the conquerors. After six days of pillage and pleasure Alaric and his army marched through the gates, carrying with them the riches of Rome.[PARAGRAPH:1]</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_GREAT_TEMPLE_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]The Toltecs built many temples for many purposes throughout their empire. There is some dispute about the purposes of the temples in the early part of the empire or pre-military rule. But according to all sources they were religious in nature. In one legend about the feathered serpent god Quetzalcoatl, the temples were sources of sacrifices of not humans, but fruit and snakes to the plumed serpent god, until a military coup that exiled the high priest Acatyl Topiltzin and forced him and the other followers of the Plumed Serpent from the city. But most historians believe that the temples were, like most meso-american civilizations, places of human sacrifice, but also symbols of the Toltec majesty as they spread their influence far and wide throughout their empire and surrouding lands. </English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_HAMBAR_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]A hambar is a corn crib or small structure used for storing and drying corn in the Balkans and bordering regions in the Pannonian plain.  Although many hambars are generally obsolete, there are still some hambars found throughout the Balkan region.  The word originates from the Turkish word ambar meaning "storehouse, warehouse, or repository."  The word in its original form, ambar, is also used in Serbia.</English>
      <French>[TAB]Un hambar est une huche de maïs ou une petite structure utilisée pour stocker et sécher le maïs aux Balkans et des régions encadrantes dans la plaine de Pannonian.  Bien que beaucoup de hambars soient généralement désuets, il restent quelques hambars trouvés dans toute la région balkanique.  Le mot provient de la signification ambar de mot turc « entrepôt, entrepôt, ou dépôt. »  Le mot sous sa forme originale, ambar, est également employé en Serbie.</French>
      <German>[TAB]Ein hambar ist eine Maiskrippe oder eine kleine Struktur, die für die Speicherung und das Trocknen von Mais in den Balkan und die einfassenden Regionen in der Pannonian Ebene benutzt werden.  Obgleich viele hambars im Allgemeinen überholt sind, gibt es noch etwas hambars, die während der Balkan Region gefunden werden.  Das Wort entsteht von der ambar Bedeutung des türkischen Wortes Lagerhaus, Lager oder Behälter.  Das Wort in seiner ursprünglichen Form, ambar, wird auch in Serbien verwendet.</German>
      <Italian>[TAB]Un hambar è una greppia del cereale o una piccola struttura usata per immagazzinare e l'essiccamento del cereale nei Balcani e le regioni bordering nella pianura di Pannonian.  Anche se molti hambars sono generalmente obsoleti, ci sono ancora alcuni hambars trovati durante la regione Balkan.  La parola proviene dal significato ambar deposito, magazzino, o deposito di parola turca.  La parola nella relativa forma originale, ambar, inoltre è usata in Serbia.</Italian>
      <Spanish>[TAB]Un hambar es un pesebre del maíz o una estructura pequeña usada para almacenar y secar maíz en los Balcanes y las regiones que confinan en el llano de Pannonian.  Aunque muchos hambars son generalmente obsoletos, todavía hay algunos hambars encontrados a través de la región balcánica.  La palabra origina del significado ambar almacén, almacén, o depósito de la palabra turca.  La palabra en su forma original, ambar, también se utiliza en Serbia.</Spanish>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_HARAPPAN_SEWER_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB] In the Indus Valley, cleanliness was obviously an important part of their society.  The ancient cities of Harappa and Mohenjo-Daro of the Indus Valley Civilization constructed complex networks of brick-lined sewage drains from around 2600 BC.  These cities also had outdoor flush toilets connected to this network.  The urban areas of the Indus Valley also provided public and private baths, sewerage was disposed through underground drains build with precisely laid bricks.  Sophisticated water management systems drained the sewage into reservoirs.  Drains from houses were also connected to wider public drains.</English>
      <French>[TAB] Dans la vallée de l'Indus, la propreté est évidemment une partie importante de leur société. Les anciennes villes d'Harappa et Mohenjo-Daro de la civilisation de l'Indus construit des réseaux complexes de brique doublure draine les eaux usées d'environ 2600 avant JC. Ces villes ont également outdoor toilettes à chasse d'eau connectées à ce réseau. Les agglomérations urbaines de la vallée de l'Indus a également fourni des bains publics et privés, a été éliminé grâce à l'assainissement des drains souterrains construire avec des briques précisément définies. Des systèmes sophistiqués de gestion de l'eau drainée dans les réservoirs d'eaux usées. Des égouts de maisons ont également été connectés à un public plus large drains.</French>
      <German>[TAB] In der Indus-Tal, Sauberkeit war natürlich ein wichtiger Teil ihrer Gesellschaft. Die antiken Städte und Harappa Mohenjo-Spende der Indus Valley Civilization konstruierten komplexen Netzwerken aus Backstein-lined Kanalisation aus der Zeit um 2600 v. Chr.. Diese Städte hatten auch im Freien flush Toiletten an diesem Netzwerk. Die städtischen Gebieten der Indus-Tal auch die öffentlichen und privaten Bäder, Kanalisation entsorgt wurde durch unterirdische Kanalisation bauen, die genau mit Ziegeln. Ausgefeilte Wasser-Management-Systemen in die Kanalisation entwässert Reservoire. Abflüsse von Häusern wurden auch an weiteren öffentlichen Kanalisation.</German>
      <Italian>[TAB] Nel cuore della Valle, per la pulizia è stata, ovviamente, una parte importante della loro società. L'antica città di Harappa e Mohenjo-daro della Civiltà della valle dell'Indo costruito reti complesse di mattoni in fila i canali di scolo delle acque reflue da circa il 2600 aC. Queste città ha avuto anche all'aperto flush toilets collegato a questa rete. Le aree urbane di Indus Valley ha fornito anche i bagni pubblici e privati, la rete fognaria è stato smaltito attraverso i canali di scolo sotterraneo costruito con mattoni di cui appunto. Sofisticati sistemi di gestione delle acque di depurazione in prosciugato le riserve. Case da canali di scolo sono stati inoltre collegata a un pubblico più ampio dei canali di scolo.</Italian>
      <Spanish>[TAB] En el valle de Indus, la limpieza es obviamente una parte importante de su sociedad. Las antiguas ciudades de Harapa y Mohenjo-daro de la civilización del valle Indus construyeron complejas redes de ladrillo-alineadas alrededor de los desagües de aguas residuales 2600 aC. En estos lugares al aire libre había inodoros conectados a esta red. Las zonas urbanas del valle de Indus también baños públicos y privados, de alcantarillado se eliminan a través de los drenajes subterráneos construir con ladrillos precisamente establecidas. Sofisticados sistemas de gestión del agua drenada en los reservorios de aguas residuales. Desagües de las casas también fueron conectados a un público más amplio el sistema de alcantarillado.</Spanish>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_HOCKEY_RINK_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]Ice hockey began in Canada, and today it attracts more players and spectators than any other sport.  Leagues are organized throughout the country.  Professional hockey draws thousands of spectators to large arenas and millions to watch their televisions.  Enthusiasm is high at the end of the season, when the two best teams of the National Hockey League, more commonly known as the NHL, emerge from a series of playoffs to compete for the Stanley Cup.  There are currently six Canadian teams in the NHL.  Ice hockey playing-areas are known as hockey rinks.</English>
      <French>[TAB]L'hockey de glace a commencé au Canada, et aujourd'hui il attire plus de joueurs et de spectateurs que n'importe quel autre sport.  Des ligues sont organisées dans tout le pays.  L'hockey professionnel dessine des milliers de spectateurs à de grandes arènes et à millions pour regarder leurs télévisions.  L'enthousiasme est haut à la fin de la saison, quand les deux meilleures équipes de la ligue nationale d'hockey, généralement connues sous le nom de NHL, émergent d'une série de finales pour concurrencer pour la tasse de Stanley.  Il y a actuellement six équipes canadiennes dans le NHL.  Des jouer-secteurs d'hockey de glace sont connus comme patinoires d'hockey.</French>
      <German>[TAB]Eis-Hockey fing in Kanada an, und heute zieht es mehr Spieler und Zuschauer als jeder möglicher andere Sport an.  Ligen werden in dem Land organisiert.  Professionelles Hockey zeichnet Tausenden Zuschauer zu den großen Arenas und zu den Millionen, um ihre fernzusehen.  Begeisterung ist am Ende der Jahreszeit hoch, wenn die zwei besten Mannschaften der nationalen Hockey-Liga, häufiger bekannt als das NHL, von einer Reihe Endspielen auftauchen, um für die Stanley Schale zu konkurrieren.  Es gibt z.Z. sechs kanadische Mannschaften im NHL.  Eis-Hockey Spielenbereiche bekannt als Hockeyeisbahnen.</German>
      <Italian>[TAB]Il hockey di ghiaccio ha cominciato nel Canada ed oggi attrae più giocatori e spectators che qualunque altro sport.  Le leghe sono organizzate durante il paese.  Il hockey professionale disegna i migliaia degli spectators alle grandi arene ed a milioni per guardare le loro televisioni.  L'entusiasmo è alto alla conclusione della stagione, quando le due squadre migliori della lega nazionale del Hockey, conosciute più conunemente come il NHL, emergono da una serie di spareggi per competere per la tazza dello Stanley.  Ci sono attualmente sei squadre canadesi nel NHL.  Le gioc-zone del hockey di ghiaccio sono conosciute come rinks del hockey.</Italian>
      <Spanish>[TAB]El hockey sobre hielo comenzó en Canadá, y atrae hoy a más jugadores y espectadores que cualquier otro deporte.  Organizan a las ligas a través del país.  El hockey profesional dibuja a millares de espectadores a las arenas grandes y a millones para mirar sus televisiones.  El entusiasmo es alto en el final de la estación, cuando los dos mejores equipos de la liga nacional del hockey, conocidos más comunmente como el NHL, emergen de una serie de segundas fases para competir para la taza de Stanley.  Hay actualmente seis equipos canadienses en el NHL.  Las jugar-áreas del hockey sobre hielo se conocen como pistas del hockey.</Spanish>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_HUNG_VEGVAR_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>After the Turks conquered much of southern Hungary, a new defensive line inside the country was strongly needed. Out of castles, mansions, churches and monasteries a new defensive line was built with the efforts of the bondsmen of the surrounding area within a short time. A new system of castles was created, which began at the Adriatic Sea, ended at the lower Danube River and enclosed the area that was controlled by the Turks. The most important places were Kanizsa, Györ and Komárom, in the north Érsekújvár, Kassa, Szatmár and in the east Várad, Gyula, Lippa and Temesvár, these fortresses observed every Turkish movement. [PARAGRAPH:1]From the 1550s on, the Vienna council sent some military engineers to Hungary, that rebuilt the most important Végvárs to a modern standard. The most important functions of the Végvárs were to defend the borders, secure the roads and the river crossings, the prevention of the enemy troop supplies and the security of the people and their goods in the surrounding area. [PARAGRAPH:1]Towers were built from where the defenders could fire at the attacking enemies that wanted to climb the walls, whereas the defenders where protected from enemy bombardments. After 1556 the military council took control over the Végvárs, thus they were under a uniform and competent command. Furthermore, smart defenders invented new military equipment and in peaceful times the wine supply didn't only delight the castles crew.  [PARAGRAPH:2]</English>
      <German>Nachdem die Türken sich in Ungarn einrichteten, wurde dringend eine neue Verteidigungslinie im Inneren des Landes benötigt. Aus Ritterburgen und Schlössern, Herrenhäusern, Kirchen und Klöstern wurde mit großen Anstrengungen seitens der Leibeigenen aus der Umgebung in kurzer Zeit eine neue Verteidigungslinie erschaffen. Ein komplettes Burgensystem entstand das beginnend an der Adria bis zur unteren Donau verlief und das von Türken besetzte Gebiet einschloss. Die bedeutendsten Orte waren Kanizsa, Gyor und Komárom; im Norden außerdem Érsekújvár, Kassa, Szatmár und im Osten Várad, Gyula, Lippa und Temesvár, welche jede türkische Bewegung überwachten. [PARAGRAPH:1]Ab Mitte der 1550er Jahre sandte der Wiener Rat einige italienische Militäringenieure nach Ungarn, die die wichtigsten Végvár gemäß den damaligen Ansprüchen umbauten. Die wichtigsten Aufgaben der Végvár waren die Verteidigung der Grenzen, die Sicherung der Straßen und der Flussübergänge, die Unterbindung des feindlichen Truppennachschubs und der Schutz der Bevölkerung der jeweiligen Umgebung und deren Eigentum. [PARAGRAPH:1]Aus den Mauerfluchten wurden schmucke fünfseitige Türme gebaut. Von dort aus konnten die Verteidiger die Angreifer die die Mauern erstürmen wollten, unter Feuer nehmen, sie selbst waren vor feindlichem Beschuss geschützt. Ab 1556 gerieten die Végvár unter die Kontrolle des Militärrates und damit eröffnete sich die Möglichkeit das Burgensystem unter ein einheitliches und fähiges Kommando zu stellen. Zudem erfanden einige gewiefte Verteidiger neue Kriegsmaschinerie und der Weinvorrat der Burgen erfreute in friedlicheren Zeiten nicht nur die Burgbesatzung. [PARAGRAPH:2]</German>
      <Italian>Dopo che i turchi conquistarono larga parte dell'Ungheria meridionale si rese fortemente necessaria una nuova linea di difese sul territorio. Grazie agli sforzi dei vassalli delle aree vicine, in poco tempo ne fu costruita una che correva esternamente alle dimore dei cavalieri e dei signori, ai castelli, alle chiese e ai monasteri. La nuova linea difensiva era costituita da una serie di castelli che partiva dal mar Adriatico e terminava sulle rive del basso Danubio, delimitando cosi il territorio controllato dai turchi. Le postazioni piu importanti furono Kanizsa, Györ e Komárom, a nord Érsekújvár, Kassa e Szatmár e ad est Várad, Gyula, Lippa e Temesvár; da queste fortezze era possibile tenere sotto controllo tutti i movimenti delle truppe turche. [PARAGRAPH:1]Dalla meta del XVI secolo, il consiglio di Vienna invio in Ungheria alcuni ingegneri militari che ristrutturarono i piu importanti végvár secondo standard moderni. Le funzioni piu importanti dei vegvár furono di sorvegliare i confini, di garantire un passaggio sicuro sulle strade e sul fiume, di intercettare i rifornimenti delle truppe nemiche e di difendere la popolazione e i loro beni nelle aree circostanti. [PARAGRAPH:1]Furono edificate delle torri da cui i soldati posti a difesa, ben protetti dai bombardamenti nemici, potevano far fuoco sui soldati che cercavano di arrampicarsi lungo le mura. Dopo il 1556 il consiglio militare prese il controllo dei végvár che, di conseguenza, furono amministrati da un comando uniforme e competente. Inoltre, dei soldati brillanti inventarono un nuovo equipaggiamento militare mentre in tempo di pace le abbondanti risorse di vino non deliziarono unicamente gli abitanti dei castelli.</Italian>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_HUNS_CATTLE_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]The Huns were a confederation of nomadic pastoralist people who, appearing from beyond the Volga, invaded Europe c. AD 370 and built up an enormous empire in Eurasia. They kept herds of cattle, horses, goats, and sheep as sources as food, as well as resources for clothing and other materials.</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_INDONESIA_SPICESTOCKS_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]The Indonesian Archipelago, home of the Spice Islands, has been an important trade destination since ancient times, when early Chinese sailors began to find profit in the spice trade. Much of Indonesia's history has been influenced by the many foreign powers that have been drawn to the archipelago and by its wealth of natural resources. Spice Islands most commonly refers to the Maluku Islands (formerly the Moluccas), which lie on the equator, between Sulawesi (Celebes) and the New Guinea islands in what is now Indonesia.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Until the late 18th century, the Moluccas were the only source of economically significant spices, including clove, nutmeg and mace. Archaeological and linguistic evidence places Spice Island traders within a trading circuit reaching as far as mainland India around 200 BC. Pliny, the Roman author, described cloves not long afterwards. Javanese and Chinese merchants were heavily involved in the spice trade, and spices reached Europe only after passing through many foreign hands, with the main western terminus of the trade at Alexandria in Egypt.</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_IRAN_SCIENCE_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]Iranian Mines and Mining Industries Development and Renovation Organization (IMIDRO) is a major holding company active in the mining sector in Iran. IMIDRO has 8 major companies and 55 operational subsidiaries active in steel, aluminum, copper, cement and mineral exploitation fields.Due to diversifying its oil-based economy, and the current sanctions against Iran, Iran has developed its biotechnology, nanotechnology, and pharmaceuticals industries.</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_IRAQ_MESMUSEUM_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]Because of the archaeological riches of Mesopotamia, its collections are amongst the most important in the world; and it has a fine record of scholarship and display. The British connection with the museum (and with Iraq) means that exhibits have always been displayed bilingually (English and Arabic). It contains important artifacts from the over 5,000 year long history of Mesopotamia in 28 galleries and vaults.</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_ITALY_CARNIVAL_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]Hundreds of years ago, the followers of the Catholic religion in Italy started the tradition of holding a wild costume festival right before the first day of Lent. Because Catholics are not supposed to eat meat during Lent, they called their festival, carnevale - which means "to put away the meat". As time passed, carnivals in Italy became quite famous; and in fact the practice spread to France, Spain, and all the Catholic countries in Europe. Then as the French, Spanish, and Portuguese began to take control of the Americas and other parts of the world, they brought with them their tradition of celebrating carnival.[PARAGRAPH:1]</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_KANEMBORNU_OASIS_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]Kanem-Bornu under Aluma was strong and wealthy. Government revenue came from tribute (or booty, if the recalcitrant people had to be conquered), sales of slaves, and duties on and participation in trans-Saharan trade. Unlike West Africa, the Chadian region did not have gold. Still, it was central to one of the most convenient trans-Saharan routes. Between Lake Chad and Fezzan lay a sequence of well-spaced wells and oases, and from Fezzan there were easy connections to North Africa and the Mediterranean Sea. Many products were sent north, including natron (sodium carbonate), cotton, kola nuts, ivory, ostrich feathers, perfume, wax, and hides, but the most important of all were slaves. Imports included salt, horses, silks, glass, muskets, and copper.</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_KAZAKH_HORSE_FARM_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]Because livestock was central to the Kazakhs' traditional lifestyle, most of their nomadic practices and customs relate in some way to livestock. Kazakhs have historically been very affectionate about horse-riding. Traditional curses and blessings invoked disease or fecundity among animals, and good manners required that a person ask first about the health of a man's livestock when greeting him and only afterward inquire about the human aspects of his life. Even today, many Kazakhs express interest in equestrianism and horse-racing. In the national cuisine, livestock meat can be cooked in a variety of ways and is usually served with a wide assortment of traditional bread products. Refreshments often include black tea and traditional milk-derived drinks such as ayran, shubat and kymyz. A traditional Kazakh dinner involves a multitude of appetisers on the table, followed by a soup and one or two main courses such as pilaf and beshbarmak. They also drink their national beverage, which consists of fermented mare's milk.</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_KOTEL_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>The Kotel, or Western Wall, in Jerusalem is the holiest of Jewish sites.  It is so sacred, because it is the remnant of the Herodian wall that enclosed and supported the Second Temple.  It is also called the Wailing Wall because for centuries, Jews have gathered at the wall to mourn the loss of their temple. [PARAGRAPH:1] The Western Wall was built by King Herod in 20 BC during his expansion of the Temple.  The construction took 11 years.  In 70 AD, the Romans destroyed Jerusalem and the Temple.  All that remained of the Temple, was the wall.  During the Ottoman Period, the wall became the Jews chief place of travel, where they came to grieve the destruction of the temple. [PARAGRAPH:1] For centuries, the Western Wall was located in a narrow ally, and could hold only a few hundred worshipers.  But, in 1967, after the Six Day War, Israelis created the Western Wall Plaza, which can accommodate tens of thousands of worshippers.  Another improvement made to the wall, was that the wall was made six and a half feet higher by digging down and exposing two more of the stones from the retaining wall.  This area was covered by debris for centuries.</English>
      <French>Le Kotel, ou le mur occidental, à Jérusalem est le plus saint des emplacements juifs. Il est si sacré, parce que c'est le reste du mur de Herodian qui inclus et soutenu le deuxième temple. Ce s'appelle également le mur pleurant parce que pendant des siècles, les juifs se sont réunis au mur pour pleurer la perte de leur temple. [PARAGRAPH : 1] Le mur occidental a été construit par le Roi Herod dans 20 AVANT JÉSUS CHRIST pendant son expansion du temple. La construction a pris 11 ans. Dans l'ANNONCE 70, le Romans a détruit Jérusalem et le temple. Tout ce qui est resté du temple, était le mur. Pendant la période de tabouret, le mur place en chef est allé bien à juifs' de voyage, où ils sont venus pour s'affliger la destruction du temple. [PARAGRAPH : 1] Pendant des siècles, le mur occidental a été situé dans un allié étroit, et a pu tenir seulement quelques cent worshipers. Mais, en 1967, après la guerre de six jours, les Israéliens ont créé la plaza occidentale de mur, qui peut adapter à des dizaines de milliers d'adorateurs. Une autre amélioration apportée au mur, était que le mur a été fait six des pieds et demi plus de haut en creusant vers le bas et en exposant deux davantage des pierres à partir du mur de soutènement. Ce domaine a été couvert par des débris pendant des siècles.</French>
      <German>Das Kotel oder die westliche Wand, in Jerusalem ist der jüdischen Aufstellungsorte das heiligste. Es ist so heilig, weil es der Rest der Herodian Wand ist, die beiliegend und gestützt dem zweiten Bügel. Es wird auch die Klagemauer genannt, weil für Jahrhunderte, Juden an der Wand erfaßt haben, um den Verlust ihres Bügels zu beklagen. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Die westliche Wand wurde vom König Herod in 20 BC während seiner Expansion des Bügels errichtet. Der Aufbau dauerte 11 Jahre. In ANZEIGE 70 zerstörte das Romans Jerusalem und den Bügel. Alle, die vom Bügel blieb, war die Wand. Während der Ottoman-Periode stand die Wand Hauptort der Juden' des Spielraums, wohin sie kamen, sich die Zerstörung des Bügels Sorgen zu machen. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Für Jahrhunderte war die westliche Wand in einem schmalen Verbündeten und konnte nur einige hundert Anbetern halten. Aber, 1967, nach dem sechstägigen Krieg, stellten Israelis die westliche Wand-Piazza her, die 10 Tausenden worshippers unterbringen kann. Eine andere Verbesserung, die zur Wand gebildet wurde, war, daß die Wand sechs und eine Hälfte die Füße höher gebildet wurde, indem man unten grub und mehr zwei der Steine von der Stützmauer herausstellte. Dieser Bereich wurde durch Rückstand für Jahrhunderte umfaßt.</German>
      <Italian>Il Kotel, o la parete occidentale, a Gerusalemme è il più santo dei luoghi ebrei. È così sacred, perché è il resto della parete di Herodian che incluso e sostenuto il secondo tempiale. Inoltre è denominato la parete lamentantesi perché per i secoli, gli ebrei hanno riunito alla parete per addolorarsi la perdita del loro tempiale. [PARAGRAPH: 1] La parete occidentale è stata costruita BC dal re Herod in 20 durante la sua espansione del tempiale. La costruzione ha occorr 11 anno. In ANNUNCIO 70, il Romans ha distrutto Gerusalemme ed il tempiale. Tutta che rimanesse del tempiale, era la parete. Durante il periodo del Ottoman, la parete ha stato bene posto principale agli ebrei' della corsa, in cui sono venuto addolorarsi la distruzione del tempiale. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Per i secoli, la parete occidentale è stata situata in un alleato stretto ed ha potuto tenere soltanto alcuni cento worshipers. Ma, in 1967, dopo la guerra di sei giorni, gli israeliani hanno generato il Plaza occidentale della parete, che può accomodare i dieci delle migliaia dei worshippers. Un altro miglioramento apportato alla parete, era che la parete è stata fatta sei e piedi di metà più d'altezza scavando giù ed esponendo due più delle pietre dal muro di sostegno. Questo settore è stato trattato tramite residui per i secoli.</Italian>
      <Spanish>El Kotel, o la pared occidental, en Jerusalén es los más santos de sitios judíos. Es tan sagrada, porque es el remanente de la pared de Herodian que incluido y apoyado el segundo templo. También se llama la pared que se lamenta porque por siglos, los judíos han recolectado en la pared para estar de luto la pérdida de su templo. [PARAGRAPH: 1] La pared occidental fue construida por rey Herod en 20 A.C. durante su extensión del templo. La construcción tomó 11 años. En el ANUNCIO 70, el Romans destruyó Jerusalén y el templo. Toda que permanecía del templo, era la pared. Durante el período del otomano, la pared sintió bien principal lugar de los judíos el' del recorrido, adonde vinieron afligirse la destrucción del templo. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Por siglos, la pared occidental fue situada en un aliado estrecho, y podía sostener solamente a algunos cientos worshipers. Pero, en 1967, después de la guerra de seis días, los israelíes crearon la plaza occidental de la pared, que puede acomodar diez de millares de devotos. Otra mejora llevada a cabo a la pared, era que la pared fue hecha seises y los pies de una mitad más altos cavando abajo y exponiendo dos más de las piedras del muro de contención. Esta área fue cubierta por la ruina por siglos.</Spanish>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_KURGAN_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]A Kurgan is the Turkish word for burial mound or tumulus.  The word Kurgan is used to describe a burial mound used in the Bronze-Middle ages in Russia, in some parts of Europe.  Kurgans were used mostly throughout central Asia and Russia, around where the Khazar Empire thrived.</English>
      <French>[TAB]Un Kurgan est le mot turc pour le monticule ou le tumulus d'enterrement. Le mot Kurgan est employé pour décrire un monticule d'enterrement utilisé dans les âges Bronze-Moyens en Russie, dans quelques parties de l'Europe. Kurgans ont été employés la plupart du temps dans l'ensemble de l'Asie centrale et de la Russie, autour d'où l'empire de Khazar a prospéré.</French>
      <German>[TAB]Ein Kurgan ist das türkische Wort für Grabhügel oder tumulus. Das Wort Kurgan wird verwendet, um einen Grabhügel zu beschreiben, der im Bronze-Mittleren Alter in Rußland, in einigen Teilen von Europa benutzt wird. Kurgans wurden meistens in zentralem Asien und Rußland, verwendet um, dem das Khazar Reich vorwärtskam.</German>
      <Italian>[TAB]Un Kurgan è la parola turca per il monticello di sepoltura o il tumulus. La parola Kurgan è usata per descrivere un monticello di sepoltura usato nelle età Bronzo-Centrali in Russia, in alcune parti di Europa. Kurgans è stato usato principalmente durante l'Asia centrale e la Russia, intorno a dove l'impero di Khazar ha prosperato.</Italian>
      <Spanish>[TAB]Un Kurgan es la palabra turca para el montón de entierro o el tumulus. La palabra Kurgan se utiliza para describir un montón de entierro usado en las edades Bronce-Medias en Rusia, en algunas partes de Europa. Kurgans fue utilizado sobre todo a través de Asia central y de Rusia, alrededor de donde prosperó el imperio de Khazar.</Spanish>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_MAGHREB_BERBERPASTURE_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]Although stereotyped in the West as nomads, most Berbers were in fact traditionally farmers, living in the mountains relatively close to the Mediterranean coast, or oasis dwellers; the Tuareg and Zenaga of the southern Sahara, however, were nomadic. Some groups, such as the Chaouis, practiced transhumance. Traditional transhumance is the seasonal movement of livestock, ascending to mountain pastures in summer and descending to relatively warm areas in the valleys or desert fringe in winter. Transhumance is based on the difference of climate between the mountains (where the herds stay during the summer) and the lowlands (where they remain the winter). Its importance to pastoralist societies cannot be overstated. Milk, butter and cheese - the products of transhumance - often form the basis of the local population's diet.</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_MAJAPAHIT_CAITRA_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]The main event of the Majapahit administrative calendar took place on the first day of the month of Caitra (March-April) when representatives from all territories paying tax or tribute to Majapahit came to the capital to pay court. Majapahit's territories were roughly divided into three types: the palace and its vicinity; the areas of east Java and Bali which were directly administrated by officials appointed by the king; and the outer dependencies which enjoyed substantial internal autonomy.</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_MALAGASY_SALEGYHALL_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]Salegy is the best-known and most widely exported dance pop music of Madagascar. It began in northern coastal towns like Majunga, Nosy Be and Diego Suarez (Antsiranana). Salegy is driving, 12/8 music with clear affinities to mainland Afropop styles in places like Zimbabwe and Mozambique. It is characterized by gently rippling guitar work, organ or keyboards and sometimes accordion, and powerful vocal armonies.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]The style originated with Malagasy folk songs, often sung during moonlight feasts. But as in the birth sagas of so many 20th century roots pop styles, pioneering musicians also needed to get an education in foreign music. As international pop styles, and music technology seeped into this remote, local scene, salegy pop emerged, and was being widely recorded by the 1950s and 60s. It evolved to feature rich, harmonized vocals and chiming guitar lines locked, restless, animated 12/8 rhythms. There is also a calmer, more romantic genre of the music, known as malesa.</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_MANDE_PORO_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]The Poro, or Purrah or Purroh, is a secret society of Sierra Leone and Liberia. The Poro has its special ritual and language, tattooing and symbols, but details are scarce, due to an oath of secrecy. It meets usually in the dry season, between the months of October and May. The rendezvous is in the bush, at an enclosure, separated into apartments by mats and roofed only by the overhanging trees, serving as a club-house. There are three grades, the first for chiefs and big men, the second for fetish-priests and the third for the crowd. The ceremonies of the Purrah are presided over by the Poro devil, a man in fetish dress, who addresses the meeting through a long tube of wood.</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_MAPUCHE_MOHEDAN_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]Toqui (Mapudungun for axe or axe-bearer) is a title conferred by the Mapuche  (an indigenous Chilean people) to those who are chosen as their leaders during times of war. The toqui is chosen in an assembly or parliament (coyag), of the chiefs (loncos) of the various clans (Rehues) or confederation of clans (Aillarehues), allied during the war in question. The Toqui could command strict obedience of all the warriors and their loncos during the war, organize them in units and appoint leaders over them. This command would continue until toqui was killed, deposed in another parliament (as in the case of Lincoyan, for poor leadership), or upon completion of the war for which he was chosen.  Some of the more famous Toqui in the Arauco War with the Spanish introduced tactical innovations; for instance, Lautaro introduced infantry tactics to defeat horsemen. Lemucaguin was the first Toqui to use firearms and artillery in battle. Nongoniel was the first Toqui to use cavalry with the Mapuche army. Cadeguala was the first to successfully use Mapuche cavarly to defeat Spanish cavalry in battle. Anganamón was the first to mount his infantry to keep up with his fast moving cavalry. Lientur pioneered the tactic of numerous and rapid malóns into Spanish territory.</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_MARAE_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]A marae is a sacred place which served for both religious and social purposes in pre-Christian Polynesian societies.  In all Polynesian languages, any variant of this word means "cleared, free of weeds, trees, etc."  It generally consists of an area of cleared land roughly rectangular, bordered with stones or wooded posts.  In the Maori of New Zealand, the marae is still a vital part of everyday life.  However, in most other Polynesian societies, most marae were destroyed or abandoned with the arrival of Christianity.  Despite all this, marae were built and still considered as a holy place and nobody would build on it.  [PARAGRAPH: 1] In Maori society, the marae is a place where the culture can be celebrated.  Various intertribal ceremonies were also practiced in the marae.  In Maori usage, marae is technically the enclosed space in front of a meeting house.  However, it is usually used to describe the marae itself and the surrounded complex.  The meeting house is the setting for important meetings, sleepovers, and craft and cultural activities.  The wharakeai, dining hall, is sued primarily for communal meals.  Many of the words associated with marae in tropical Polynesia are kept in the Maori context.</English>
      <French>[TAB] Un marae est un lieu sacré qui servait à la fois pour des raisons sociales et religieuses dans le préprimaire Christian sociétés polynésiennes. Dans toutes les langues polynésiennes, une variante de ce mot signifie "nettoyés, exempts de mauvaises herbes, les arbres, etc" Elle est généralement constituée d'une zone de terres déminées à peu près rectangulaire, bordés de pierres ou d'arbres postes. Dans les Maori de la Nouvelle-Zélande, les marae est toujours une partie essentielle de la vie quotidienne. Toutefois, dans la plupart des autres sociétés polynésiennes, la plupart des marae ont été détruits ou abandonnés avec l'arrivée du christianisme. Malgré tout cela, marae ont été construits et toujours considéré comme un lieu saint et personne ne s'appuierait sur elle. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Dans la société maorie, les marae est un lieu où la culture peut être célébré. Diverses cérémonies intertribaux ont également été pratiquée dans les marae. En Maoris utilisation, marae est techniquement un espace clos devant une réunion de maison. Cependant, il est souvent utilisé pour décrire les marae lui-même et le milieu complexe. La réunion maison est le cadre de réunions importantes, sleepovers, et de l'artisanat et des activités culturelles. Le wharakeai, réfectoire, est poursuivi principalement pour des repas communaux. Beaucoup des mots associés à marae en Polynésie tropicales sont conservées dans le contexte des Maoris.</French>
      <German>[TAB] Ein marae ist ein heiliger Ort, der für beide serviert religiösen und sozialen Zwecken in der vorchristlichen polynesischen Gesellschaften. In allen polynesischen Sprachen, jede Variante dieses Wort bedeutet "geräumt, frei von Unkraut, Bäume, usw." Es besteht aus einem allgemeinen Bereich der geräumten Flächen rund rechteckig, grenzt mit Steinen oder bewaldeten Stellen. In den Maori in Neuseeland, die marae ist nach wie vor ein wesentlicher Bestandteil des täglichen Lebens. Aber auch in den meisten anderen polynesischen Gesellschaften, die meisten marae wurden zerstört oder aufgegeben mit der Ankunft des Christentums. Trotz all dieser marae gebaut wurden und noch immer als ein heiliger Ort, und niemand würde auf sie. [ABSATZ: 1] In Maori Gesellschaft, die marae ist ein Ort, wo die Kultur gefeiert werden kann. Verschiedene intertribal Zeremonien wurden auch geübt in der marae. In Maori Nutzung, marae ist technisch der geschlossenen Raum vor der Sitzung. Allerdings ist es in der Regel zur Beschreibung der marae selbst und der umgeben komplex. Die Sitzung ist die Einstellung für den wichtigen Sitzungen, sleepovers, und handwerklichen und kulturellen Aktivitäten. Die wharakeai, Speiseraum, verklagt ist in erster Linie für gemeinsames Essen. Viele der Wörter im Zusammenhang mit marae in tropischen Polynesien werden in der Maori.</German>
      <Italian>[TAB] Un marae è un luogo sacro, che è servita sia per scopi religiosi e sociali nel pre- cristiano Polinesia società. In tutte le lingue della Polinesia, qualsiasi variante di questa parola significa ", però, la libera di erbacce, alberi, ecc" Essa consiste in genere di una zona di terra eliminato circa rettangolare, confinante con pietre o boschive post. Nel Maori della Nuova Zelanda, il marae è ancora una parte vitale della vita quotidiana. Tuttavia, nella maggior parte delle altre società polinesiana, la maggior parte marae sono state distrutte o abbandonate con l'arrivo del cristianesimo. Nonostante tutto questo, marae sono stati costruiti e ancora considerato come un luogo sacro, e nessuno potrebbe costruire su di essa. [PARAGRAFO: 1] Nel Maori società, il marae è un luogo in cui la cultura può essere celebrato. Diversi intertribal cerimonie sono state praticate anche nel marae. In Maori uso, marae è tecnicamente il spazio chiuso di fronte a una riunione casa. Tuttavia, è di solito usato per descrivere la marae stesso e circondato il complesso. La riunione casa è l'impostazione di riunioni importanti, sleepovers, e artigianali e le attività culturali. Il wharakeai, sala da pranzo, è citato in primo luogo per i pasti in comune. Molte delle parole associate con marae nella Polinesia tropicali sono conservate nel contesto Maori.</Italian>
      <Spanish>[TAB] Una marae es un lugar sagrado, que sirve tanto para fines religiosos y sociales en los polinesios antes de las sociedades cristianas. En todos los idiomas polinesios, cualquier variante de esta palabra significa "limpia, libre de malezas, árboles, etc" Generalmente consta de un área de terreno despejado, aproximadamente rectangulares, bordeado con piedras o arbolado puestos. En los maoríes de Nueva Zelandia, el marae sigue siendo una parte vital de la vida cotidiana. Sin embargo, en la mayoría de las otras sociedades de Polinesia, la mayoría de marae fueron destruidos o abandonados con la llegada del cristianismo. A pesar de todo esto, marae se construyeron y aún considerado como un lugar sagrado y nadie puede construir sobre ella. [APARTADO: 1] En la sociedad maorí, el marae es un lugar donde la cultura puede ser celebrado. Varios intertribales ceremonias también se practica en los marae. En uso de los maoríes, es técnicamente el marae espacio cerrado delante de una casa de reunión. Sin embargo, es generalmente utilizado para describir el mismo y el marae rodeado complejo. En la reunión se casa es el escenario de importantes reuniones, sleepovers, y en la artesanía y las actividades culturales. El wharakeai, comedor, es demandado principalmente para las comidas comunales. Muchas de las palabras asociadas con marae tropicales en la Polinesia se mantienen en el contexto maoríes.</Spanish>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_MEGARON_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]The megaron was the "Great Hall" in Minoan-Mycenaean society.  It was used for many purposes, including poetry, feasts, worshipping gods, sacrifice, and counsels of war.  A famous megaron is the reception hall of the king in the Palace of Tyrins.  The megaron is a rectangular hall with a two-collumned porch.</English>
      <French>[TAB]Le megaron était le « grand Hall » dans la société de Minoan-Mycenaean. Il a été employé pour beaucoup de buts, y compris la poésie, régals, dieux adorants, sacrifice, et avocats-conseils de guerre. Un megaron célèbre est le hall de réception du roi dans le palais de Tyrins. Le megaron est un hall rectangulaire avec a two-collumned le porche. </French>
      <German>[TAB]Das megaron war der große Hall in der Minoan-Mycenaean Gesellschaft. Es wurde für viele Zwecke, einschließlich Poesie, Feste, anbetende Götter, Opfer und Ratschläge des Krieges verwendet. Ein berühmtes megaron ist die Aufnahmehalle des Königs im Palast von Tyrins. Das megaron ist eine rechteckige Halle mit a two-collumned Portal.</German>
      <Italian>[TAB]Il megaron era il Corridoio grande nella società di Minoan-Mycenaean. È stato usato per molti scopi, compreso la poesia, le festività, i dii d'adorazione, il sacrificio ed i consulenti legali della guerra. Un megaron famoso è il corridoio di ricezione del re nel palazzo di Tyrins. Il megaron è un corridoio rettangolare con la a two-collumned il portico.</Italian>
      <Spanish>[TAB]El megaron era el gran Pasillo en la sociedad de Minoan-Mycenaean. Fue utilizado para muchos propósitos, incluyendo poesía, los banquetes, los dioses que se adoraban, el sacrificio, y los consejos de la guerra. Un megaron famoso es el pasillo de la recepción del rey en el palacio de Tyrins. El megaron es un pasillo rectangular con a two-collumned el pórtico. </Spanish>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_MEGYPT_EXHIBITION_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]Jean François Champollion and Ippolito Rosellini were some of the first Egyptologists of wide acclaim. The German Karl Richard Lepsius  was an early participant in the investigations of Egypt; mapping, excavating, and recording several sites. Champollion announced his general decipherment of the system of Egyptian hieroglyphics  for the first time, employing the Rosetta Stone as his primary aid. The Stone's decipherment was a very important development of Egyptology. With subsequently ever-increasing knowledge of Egyptian writing and language, the study of Ancient Egyptian  civilisation was able to proceed with greater academic rigour and with all the added impetus that comprehension of the written sources was able to engender. Egyptology became more professional via work of William Matthew Flinders Petrie, among others. Petrie introduced techniques of field preservation, recording, and excavating. Howard Carter's expedition brought much acclaim to the field of Egyptology.Around 1830, Rifa'a el-Tahtawi was one of the first main scholars of Egyptian Egyptology. He was inspired by the work of Muslim Egyptologists in medieval Egypt, though modern Egyptian Egyptology developed slowly compared to its Western scholars, primarily because of Islamic identity. Islamic and modern Egyptian civilization has been influenced by the pre-Islamic Egyptian culture with which Egyptology is concerned.In the Modern era, the Supreme Council for Antiquities control excavation permits for Egyptologists to conduct their work. The field can now use geophysical methods and other applications of modern sensing techniques to further Egyptology. The Egyptian languages (such as Hieratics and Coptic) and the Egyptian writing systems are still of importance in Egyptology.</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_MENARA_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]The Cham Empire was a religious empire, and built many temples.  A common feature of these temples is that there are towers, or menaras, in these temples.  The most famous temples of the Cham are the temples at My Son.  Other temples with towers are Po Klaung, Po Nagar, and Pho Hai.  In the village of Khuong My in the Vietnamese province of Quang Nam stands a group of three Cham towers dating from the 10th century. [PARAGRAPH: 1] The Po Nagar towers once stood at the entrance to a river. The Po Nagar towers complex was built between the 7th and 12th century. The most beautiful towers were built in the year 813 and 817. Most were destroyed and only four towers are still standing. Each tower is a shrine to a different deity.  There are eight towers at Binh Dinh which are commonly used to study Champa.</English>
      <French>[TAB]L'empire de Cham était un empire religieux, et a construit beaucoup de temples. Un dispositif commun de ces temples est qu'il y a des tours dans des ces temples. Les temples les plus célèbres du Cham sont les temples à mon fils. D'autres temples avec des tours sont PO Klaung, PO Nagar, et Pho Hai. Dans le village de Khuong mon dedans la province vietnamienne de Quang Nam tient un groupe de trois tours de Cham datant du 10ème siècle. [PARAGRAPH : 1] Le PO Nagar domine une fois tenu à l'entrée à un fleuve. Le complexe de tours de PO Nagar a été établi entre le 7ème et 12ème siècle. Les tours les plus belles ont été construites en l'année 813 et 817. Les la plupart ont été détruites et seulement quatre tours se tiennent toujours. Chaque tour est un tombeau à une déité différente. Il y a huit tours chez Binh Dinh qui sont utilisées généralement pour étudier Champa.</French>
      <German>[TAB]Das cham-Reich war ein frommes Reich und errichtete viele Bügel. Eine allgemeine Eigenschaft dieser Bügel ist, daß es Aufsätze in diesen Bügeln gibt. Die berühmtesten Bügel des Cham sind die Bügel an meinem Sohn. Andere Bügel mit Aufsätzen sind PO Klaung, PO Nagar und Pho Hai. Im Dorf von Khuong meinem innen steht die vietnamesische Provinz von Quang Nam eine Gruppe von drei Chamaufsätzen, die vom 10. Jahrhundert datieren. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Das PO Nagar towers einmal gestanden am Eingang zu einem Fluß. Der PO Nagar Aufsatzkomplex wurde zwischen dem 7. und 12. Jahrhundert errichtet. Die schönsten Aufsätze wurden im Jahr 813 und 817 errichtet. Die meisten wurden zerstört und nur vier Aufsätze stehen noch. Jeder Aufsatz ist ein Schrein zu einer anderen Gottheit. Es gibt acht Aufsätze bei Binh Dinh, die allgemein verwendet sind, Champa zu studieren.</German>
      <Italian>[TAB]L'impero del Cham era un impero religioso ed ha costruito molte tempie. Una caratteristica comune di queste tempie è che ci sono torrette in queste tempie. Le tempie più famose del Cham sono le tempie al mio figlio. Altre tempie con le torrette sono Po Klaung, Po Nagar e Pho Hai. Nel villaggio di Khuong mio dentro la provincia vietnamita di Quang Nam si leva in piedi un gruppo di tre torrette del Cham che datano dal decimo secolo. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Il Po Nagar torreggia su levato in piedi una volta all'entrata ad un fiume. Il complesso delle torrette di Po Nagar è stato sviluppato fra il settimo e dodicesimo secolo. Le torrette più belle sono state costruite durante gli anni 813 e 817. La maggior parte sono stati distrutti e soltanto quattro torrette ancora stanno levando in piedi. Ogni torretta è uno shrine ad un deity differente. Ci sono otto torrette a Binh Dinh che sono comunemente usate studiare Champa.</Italian>
      <Spanish>[TAB]El imperio del Cham era un imperio religioso, y construyó muchos templos. Una característica común de estos templos es que hay torres en estos templos. Los templos más famosos del Cham son los templos en mi hijo. Otros templos con las torres son Po Klaung, Po Nagar, y Pho Hai. En la aldea de Khuong mi adentro la provincia vietnamita de Quang Nam está parado un grupo de tres torres del Cham que fechan a partir del 10mo siglo. [PARAGRAPH: 1] El Po Nagar se eleva estado parado una vez en la entrada a un río. El complejo de las torres del Po Nagar fue construido entre el 7mo y 12mo siglo. Las torres más hermosas fueron construidas en el año 813 y 817. La mayoría fueron destruidas y solamente cuatro torres todavía están estando paradas. Cada torre es una capilla a un diverso deity. Hay ocho torres en Binh Dinh que son de uso general estudiar Champa.</Spanish>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_MEXICO_CHARREADA_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]A charreada is a Mexican-style rodeo that is different from other rodeos. The Mexican cowboy or cowgirl is known as a charro or charra. In an American rodeo the competitors race against the clock, so the emphasis is on speed in any given event. On the other hand, in a Mexican charreada the excellent style and skills of the rider or roper are emphasized, and only one event is timed.[PARAGRAPH:1]Charrería (a word encompassing all aspects of the art) came to Mexico from Salamanca, Spain, in the 16th century. Interesting is the fact that when the Spaniards first settled in Mexico they were under the orders of the ruler to raise horses, but not to allow the Mexicans to ride them. By 1528 the Spaniards had very large cattle-raising estates. They soon found it necessary to employ the Mexicans as vaqueros or herdsman, and the natives soon became excellent horsemen. Small landholders, known as rancheros or ranchers, were the first genuine charros and invented charreadas.[PARAGRAPH:1]</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_MINOA_ANAKTORA_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]The Minoans are perhaps most known for their huge palaces (Anaktoras). While it was believed that all of these palaces were built in the Middle Minoan period around 2000 BC, it have later been proved that this is not the case and that the palace at Malia were built as early as the third millennium BC in the Early Minoan period. The three main old palaces were the ones at Malia, Knossos and Phaistos. These palaces had a number of functions, such as centers of government, administrative offices, shrines, workshops, and storage spaces. This have created a discussion if it really is right to call these buildings palaces, and the term court building have been suggested instead. However, the original term is probably too well entrenched to be replaced.[PARAGRAPH:1]Often the conventions of better-known, younger palaces have been used to reconstruct older ones, but this practice may be obscuring fundamental functional differences. Most older palaces had only one story and no representative facades. They were U-shaped, with a big central court, and generally were smaller than later palaces. Late palaces are characterised by multi-story buildings. The west facades had sandstone ashlar masonry. Knossos is the best-known example. See Knossos. Further building conventions could include storage magazines, a north-south orientation, a pillar room, a Minoan Hall system, a western court, and pier-and-door entrance ways. Palatial architecture in the First Palace Period is identified by its 'square within a square' style, whilst later, Second Palace Period constructions incorporated more internal divisions and corridors.[PARAGRAPH:1]It is a common architectural standard among the Middle Minoan 'palaces' that they are aligned with their surrounding topography. The MM palatial structure of Phaistos appears to align with Mount Ida, whilst Knossos is aligned with Juktas. These are oriented along a north-south axis. One suggested reason for this is the ritual significance of the mountain, where a number of Peak Sanctuaries have been excavated like Petsophas. The material record for these sites show clusters of clay figurines and evidence of animal sacrifice.[PARAGRAPH:1](Wikipedia: Minoan Civilization)</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_MOCHE_HUACA_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]In Quechua, a Native American language of South America, a huaca or wak'a is an object that represents something revered, typically a monument of some kind. The term huaca can refer to natural locations, such as immense rocks. Some huacas have been associated with veneration and ritual. Andean cultures believed every object has a physical presence and two camaquen (spirits), one to create it and another to animate it. They would invoke its spirits for the object to function.[PARAGRAPH:1] The term 'huaca' is often associated with pyramids and temples in Moche culture. Impressive ziggurats can be found in a number of Moche sites. </English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_MUTAPA_ZIMBA_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]The word "Zimbabwe" could be a short form for "ziimba remabwe" or "ziimba rebwe", a Shona term, which means "the great or big house built of stone boulders". In the Karanga dialect of the Shona language, "imba" means "a house" or "a building" and "ziimba", or "zimba", mean "a huge/big building or house". A second theory is that Zimbabwe is a contracted form of "dzimba woye" which means "venerated houses" in the Zezuru dialect of the Shona language. This term is usually reserved for chiefs' houses or graves.</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_NEWZEALAND_WOOLSHED_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]Shearing sheds (or wool sheds) are large sheds located on sheep stations to accommodate large scale sheep shearing activities. In countries where large numbers of sheep are kept for wool, sometimes many thousands in a flock, shearing sheds are vital to house the necessary shearing equipment, and to ensure that the shearers and /or crutchers have a ready supply of dry, empty sheep. The shed also provides space where the wool is classed and pressed into approved wool packs and stored to await transport to market.</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_NIGERIA_JUJUHALL_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]The music of Nigeria includes many kinds of folk and popular music, some of which are known worldwide. Styles of folk music are related to the multitudes of ethnic groups in the country, each with their own techniques, instruments, and songs. JuJu is a style of Nigerian popular music, derived from traditional Yoruba percussion. This music, unlike apala, sakara, and fuji, was not created by Muslim Yoruba, and is therefore secular. JuJu music is performed primarily by artists from the southwestern region of Nigeria, where the Yoruba are the most numerous ethnic group. In performance, audience members commonly shower JuJu musicians with paper money; this tradition is known as "spraying."</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_NORWAY_FISHMARKET_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]Beside oil, gas, and income from the merchant fleet, stockfish is Norway's longest sustained export commodity, and the socioeconomically most profitable export over the centuries.  Stockfish is unsalted fish, especially cod, dried by sun and wind on wooden racks on the foreshore called flakes, or in special drying houses. The drying of food  is the world's oldest known preservation method, and dried fish has a storage life of several years. The method is cheap and effective in suitable climates, the work can be done by the fisherman and family, and the resulting product is easily transported to market.  Cod is the most common fish used in stockfish production, while other whitefish, such as pollock, haddock, ling and tusk, are used to a lesser degree.  Over the centuries, several variants of stockfish have evolved, notably salt cod. Salting was not economically feasible before the 17th century, when cheap salt from southern Europe became available to the maritime nations of northern Europe.</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_OLMEC_STONEHEAD_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]The best-recognized aspect of the Olmec civilzation are the enormous helmeted heads. As no known pre-Columbian text explains these, these impressive monuments have been the subject of much speculation. Once theorized to be ballplayers, it is now generally accepted that these heads are portraits of rulers. According to archaeologist David Grove, the unique elements in the headgear can also be recognized in headdresses of human figures on other Gulf Coast monuments, suggesting that these are personal or group symbols. The heads range in size from the Rancho La Cobata head, at 3.4 m high, to the pair at Tres Zapotes, at 1.47 m. It has been calculated that the largest heads weigh more than 20 tons.</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_PAKISTAN_ISI_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]The Directorate for Inter-Services Intelligence (more commonly known as Inter-Services Intelligence or simply by its initials ISI) is Pakistan's premier intelligence agency. It is the largest of the three intelligence agencies of Pakistan, the other being the Intelligence Bureau (IB) and Military Intelligence (MI).  ISI was established as an independent intelligence agency in 1948 in order to strengthen the sharing of military intelligence between the three branches of Pakistan's armed forces in the aftermath of the Indo-Pakistani War of 1947, which had exposed weaknesses in intelligence gathering, sharing and coordination between the Pakistan Army, Air Force and Navy.  ISI's headquarters are situated in Islamabad. It is currently headed by Lieutenant General Ahmad Shuja Pasha, who took over as ISI's Director in September 2008.After independence in 1947, two new intelligence agencies were created in Pakistan: the Intelligence Bureau (IB) and the Military Intelligence (MI). However, the weak performance of the MI in sharing intelligence between the Army, Navy and Air Force during the Indo-Pakistani War of 1947 led to the creation of the Directorate for Inter-Services Intelligence (ISI) in 1948.  The ISI was structured to be manned by officers from the three main military services, and to specialize in the collection, analysis and assessment of external intelligence, either military or non-military.  The ISI was the brainchild of Australian-born British Army officer, Major General R. Cawthome, then Deputy Chief of Staff in the Pakistan Army.  Initially, the ISI had no role in the collection of internal intelligence, with the exception of the North-West Frontier Province and Azad Kashmir.  In the late 1950s, when Ayub Khan became the President of Pakistan, he expanded the role of ISI in monitoring opposition politicians, and sustaining military rule in Pakistan.  The ISI was reorganised in 1966 after intelligence failures in the Indo-Pakistani War of 1965, and expanded in 1969. Khan entrusted the ISI with the responsibility for the collection of internal political intelligence in East Pakistan. Later on, during the Baloch nationalist revolt in Balochistan in the mid-1970s, the ISI was tasked with performing a similar intelligence gathering operation.  The ISI lost its importance during the regime of Zulfiqar Ali Bhutto, who was very critical of its role during the 1970 general elections, which triggered off the events leading to the partition of Pakistan and emergence of Bangladesh.  After General Zia ul-Haq seized power in July 1977, the ISI was expanded by making it responsible for the collection of intelligence about the Sindh-based Pakistan Communist Party and various political parties such as the Pakistan Peoples Party (PPP).  The Soviet-Afghan war of the 1980s saw the enhancement of the covert action capabilities of the ISI by the US Central Intelligence Agency (CIA). A special Afghan Section was created under the command of colonel Mohammed Yousaf to oversee the coordination of the war. A number of officers from the ISI's Covert Action Division received training in the US and many covert action experts of the CIA were attached to the ISI to guide it in its operations against the Soviet troops by using the Afghan Mujahideen.</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_PARTHIA_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]The required education for a child of a noble family included writing, religious instruction, physical education, and training in the courtly arts.  A noble child would begin attending school between the ages of five and seven years of age.  The hammozgar, or teacher would instract him in writing and memorization of the Zoroastrian holy scriptures, as well as to recite the yasts and hold the Barsom, or sacred bundle, at a very early age.  As well he would be versed in astrology, literature, writing and the law.  He would also be trained in the etiquette of the court, ceremonies, how to treat women, gardening, and singing.  He would play games such as chess and Backgammon.  He would further be trained in horsemanship, hunting, archery, wrestling, polo, and the military arts, with his training and studies completed by the age of fifteen.</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_PHILIPPINES_NIPA_HUT_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]The Nipa hut also known as Bahay Kubo, is an indigenous house used in the Philippine Islands. The native house is constructed out of bamboo tied together, with a thatched roof using dried grass.[PARAGRAPH:1]Nipa huts were once the native houses of the indigenous people of the Philippines before the Spaniards arrived, and is still used today, especially in rural areas. Different architectural designs are present among the different ethno-linguistic groups in the country, although all of them conform to being stilt houses, similar to those found in neighboring countries such as Indonesia, Malaysia, Palau, and the Pacific Islands.[PARAGRAPH:1]</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_PHOENICIA_DYE_FACILITY_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]Tyrian purple, also known as royal purple or imperial purple, is a purple-red dye which was first produced by the ancient Phoenicians in the city of Tyre.[PARAGRAPH:1]Tyrian purple was expensive: the fourth-century BC historian Theopompus reported, "Purple for dyes fetched its weight in silver at Colophon" in Asia Minor.[PARAGRAPH:1]The dye substance occurs naturally, but must be harvested by humans. It consists of a fresh mucus secretion from the hypobranchial gland of a medium-sized predatory sea snail, commonly called the spiny dye-murex, a species in the family Muricidae, the murex or rock shells.[PARAGRAPH:1]In nature the snails use the secretion as part of their predatory behaviour, but the snail also secretes this substance when it is poked or physically attacked by humans. Therefore the dye can be collected either by "milking" the snails, which is more labor intensive but is a renewable resource, or by collecting and then crushing the snails completely, which is destructive.[PARAGRAPH:1]As well as Tyrian purple, the Phoenicians also made a purple-blue indigo dye, referred to as royal blue or hyacinth purple, which was made from a closely-related species of marine snail.[PARAGRAPH:1]The fast, non-fading dye was an item of luxury trade, prized by Romans, who used it to colour ceremonial robes. It is believed that the intensity of the purple hue improved, rather than faded, as the dyed cloth aged. Pliny the Elder described the dyeing process of two purples in his Natural History: ... the Tyrian hue ... is considered of the best quality when it has exactly the colour of clotted blood, and is of a blackish hue to the sight, but of a shining appearance when held up to the light; hence it is that we find Homer speaking of "purple blood".[PARAGRAPH:1]Archaeological data from Tyre indicate that the snails were collected in large vats and left to decompose. This produced a hideous stench that was actually mentioned by ancient authors. Not much is known about the subsequent steps, and the actual ancient method for mass-producing the two murex dyes has not yet been successfully reconstructed.[PARAGRAPH:1]</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_PICTS_CRANNOG_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]A crannog is the name given in Scotland and Ireland to an artificial island or natural island, used for a settlement. The name can also be used to refer to wooden platforms erected on shallow loch floors, although understandably few remains of this sort have been found.[PARAGRAPH:1]The choice of an island as a home is thought to have been for defence as well as the availability of food in the form of fish nearby. The crannog could be reached from the nearest shore by means of a causeway built up with stones, or else a wooden gangway built atop raised piles.[PARAGRAPH:1]The islet of Eilean Domhnuill, Loch Olabhat on North Uist may be the earliest crannóg, dated to 3200-2800 BC in the Neolithic period. Most crannógs were in use from the Iron Age through to the early Medieval period, at about the same time as the brochs, the wags, duns and the larger roundhouses.[PARAGRAPH:1]</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_PILIAKALNIS_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB] Piliakalniai are hill forts in ancient and medieval Lithuania.  The first piliakalniai are dated to the 1st millennium BC.  Most forts were refortified in later centuries against the constant invasions of the Teutonic Knights.  Most of the forts were located on the banks of a river, or where two rivers met.  The hill was often sculpted for defense, with flattened tops and steeper slopes.  The fortifications also were typically wooden, though some had stone or brick walls.  During the early years of the Grand Duchy of Lithuania, piliakalniai played a major role in battles against the Livonian Order and Teutonic Knights.  During that time, their construction decreased but they became stronger.  Their effectiveness decreased as firearms and cannons developed, and their numbers began to decline.</English>
      <French>[TAB] Piliakalniai sont collines fortifiées dans l'Antiquité et au Moyen Lituanie. La première piliakalniai sont à la date du 1er millénaire avant notre ère. Les plus forts sont refortified siècles plus tard, en constante contre les invasions des chevaliers teutoniques. La plupart des ouvrages sont situés sur les rives d'un fleuve, ou lorsque deux rivières remplies. La colline était souvent sculpté de la défense, avec des sommets aplatis et pentes plus raides. Les fortifications sont aussi généralement en bois, même si certains ont des murs de pierre ou de brique. Au cours des premières années du Grand-Duché de Lituanie, piliakalniai joué un rôle majeur dans les batailles contre l'Ordre livonien et les chevaliers teutoniques. Pendant ce temps, leur construction a augmenté, mais elles sont devenues plus fortes. Leur efficacité diminue à mesure que les armes à feu et de canons développés, et leur nombre a commencé à diminuer.</French>
      <German>[TAB] Piliakalniai Hügel sind Festungen in der Antike und Mittelalter Litauen. Die erste piliakalniai sind datiert auf das 1. Jahrtausend v. Chr.. Die meisten refortified Festungen wurden in späteren Jahrhunderten gegen die ständigen Invasionen der Deutschen Ritterorden. Die meisten Forts befanden sich am Ufer eines Flusses, wo zwei Flüsse oder erfüllt werden. Der Hügel wurde oft Skulpturen für Verteidigung, mit abgeflachtem Tops und steiler Hänge. Die Festung wurde in der Regel auch aus Holz, aber einige hatten Stein oder Ziegelwände. Während der frühen Jahre des Großfürstentums Litauen, piliakalniai spielte eine wichtige Rolle in der Schlacht gegen den Livländischen Ordens und Deutschen Ritterorden. Während dieser Zeit, deren Bau aber sie erhöht wurde stärker. Ihre Wirksamkeit zurückgegangen als Schusswaffen und Kanonen entwickelt, und ihre Zahl begann zu sinken.</German>
      <Italian>[TAB] Piliakalniai sono collina e antiche fortificazioni medievali e Lituania. Il primo piliakalniai sono datati al 1 ° millennio aC. La maggior parte delle fortezze erano refortified nei secoli successivi la costante contro le invasioni dei Cavalieri Teutonico. La maggior parte delle fortezze erano situato sulle rive di un fiume, o dove ha incontrato due fiumi. La collina è stata spesso scolpito per la difesa, con cime appiattite e pendenze. Anche le fortificazioni sono stati in genere di legno, anche se ha avuto alcuni muri in pietra o in mattoni. Durante i primi anni del Granducato di Lituania, piliakalniai svolto un ruolo importante nella battaglia contro la Livonian Ordine Teutonico e Cavalieri. Durante quel tempo, la loro costruzione è aumentato, ma è diventata più forte. La loro efficacia è diminuita, come armi da fuoco e cannoni sviluppato, e il loro numero ha iniziato a declinare.</Italian>
      <Spanish>[TAB] Piliakalniai son fuertes en la colina de la antigua y medieval de Lituania. La primera fecha se piliakalniai a la 1 ª milenio antes de Cristo. Los más fuertes fueron refortified siglos más tarde en contra de las invasiones constantes Teutónica de los Caballeros. La mayoría de las fortalezas se encuentra en la orilla de un río, o en los que se reunió dos ríos. La colina era a menudo esculpida para la defensa, con cimas aplanadas y escarpadas laderas. Las fortificaciones fueron también típicamente de madera, aunque había algunos muros de piedra o ladrillo. Durante los primeros años de la Gran Ducado de Lituania, piliakalniai desempeñado un papel importante en las batallas contra el Livonian Orden Teutónica y Caballeros. Durante ese tiempo, el aumento de su construcción, sino que se convirtió en más fuerte. Su efectividad se redujo como las armas de fuego y cañones desarrollados, y su número empezó a disminuir.</Spanish>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_PILIWNI_PEYOTE_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]Sweat Lodges have long been used by the earliest north Americans for healing and ritualistic purposes. From earliest recorded time, peyote has been used by indigenous peoples, such as the Huichol of northern Mexico and by various Native American Tribal Groups. There is documented evidence of the religious, ceremonial, and healing uses of peyote dating back over 20,000 years. The tradition began to spread northward as part of a revival of native spirituality under the auspices of what came to be known as the Native American Church, whose members refer to peyote as "the sacred medicine", and use it to combat alcoholism and spiritual, physical, and other social ills.</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_RING_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>Kurash is a form of upright jacket wrestling native to Uzbekistan, practiced since ancient times. This Central Asian sport developed thousands of years ago as a form of training for fighting, for both self-defence and war. This is reflected in the rules, where clothing is required which mimics armour or battle-garb, and where grips on the trousers and ground fighting are banned, since bending over low or going to the ground make a fighter vulnerable to weapon thrusts. The emphasis on standing fighting develops strong balance and quick footwork, which help greatly when fighting with weapons.</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_RINGFORT_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]Ringforts are fortified settlements that are generally agreed to be from the Early Medieval period in Northern Europe, especially Ireland.  A ráth was made of earth and caiseal or cathair were made of stone.  A dun is a more prestigious site, the seat of a ruler.  Historical or archaeological record of the Early Medieval Period in Ireland doesn't come close to the ringfort.  Over 45,000 sites have been identified as ringforts throughout Ireland, but over 60,000 sites can be identified. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Ringforts are traditionally understood as being a dispersed farmstead, the home of a free man and his family.  This veiw has been altered, saying that not all ringforts are not farmsteads, but that they fill a variety of functions.  Other ringfort sites have provided evidence that ringforts played a significant role in the economy of Ireland.  Excavations have lead to the finding of pottery at ringfort sites suggesting that they may have been used as trading posts or other settlement functions.  Yet another theory is that the ringforts were used for defense both because of its name and archaeological evidence.  Ringforts may have been built to give protection to cattle-farming communities and guard their livestock.  The circular shape of the ringfort also shows its defensive advantages.  Explanations from the Early christian period support another idea: ringforts were built to signify nobility, kingship, and authority.  The more elaborate the ringfort, the higher the status of the occupant.  The promotion of one's status was the main purpose of construction of these ringforts.</English>
      <French>[TAB] Ringforts sont fortifiés qui sont généralement accepté d'être le début de la période médiévale dans le nord de l'Europe, en particulier en Irlande. Un ráth a été faite de terre et caiseal ou cathair sont en pierre. A plus dun est un site prestigieux, le siège d'un dirigeant. Historique ou archéologique analytique de la Petite Période Médiévale en Irlande est loin de la ringfort. Plus de 45000 sites ont été identifiés comme ringforts dans toute l'Irlande, mais plus de 60000 sites peuvent être identifiés. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Ringforts sont traditionnellement comprise comme étant un ferme dispersés, le honme d'un homme libre et sa famille. Cette veiw a été modifié, en disant que ce n'est pas tout ringforts ne sont pas fermes, mais qu'ils remplissent une série de fonctions. Autres ringfort sites ont apporté la preuve que ringforts joué un rôle important dans l'économie de l'Irlande. Les fouilles ont conduit à la découverte de la poterie à ringfort des sites suggérant qu'ils auraient été utilisés comme postes de règlement ou d'autres fonctions. Une autre théorie est que l'ringforts ont été utilisés pour la défense tant en raison de son nom et de témoins archéologiques. Ringforts peut avoir été construite pour protéger le bétail, les communautés agricoles et protège son bétail. La forme circulaire de la ringfort montre aussi ses avantages défensifs. Explications de la petite période de l'ère chrétienne soutien une autre idée: ringforts ont été construits pour signifier la noblesse, la royauté, et de l'autorité. Les plus élaborés la ringfort est élevé, plus le statut de l'occupant. La promotion de l'un de ces droits était l'objectif principal de la construction de ces ringforts.</French>
      <German>[TAB] Ringforts sind befestigte Siedlungen, die im Allgemeinen vereinbart, werden aus dem frühen Mittelalter Zeitraum, in Nordeuropa, vor allem in Irland. Ein ráth wurde aus der Erde und caiseal oder cathair waren aus Stein. Ein mahnen ist eine angesehene, der Sitz eines Herrschers. Historischen oder archäologischen Eintrag der Frühen Mittelalter in Irland nicht in die Nähe der ringfort. Mehr als 45000 Websites wurden als ringforts in ganz Irland, aber über 60000 Seiten ermittelt werden können. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Ringforts sind traditionell verstanden als eine verstreute Gehöft, die honme ein freier Mann und seiner Familie. Diese veiw verändert wurde, und sagte, dass nicht alle ringforts sind nicht Bauernhöfe, aber sie füllen eine Vielzahl von Funktionen. Andere ringfort Websites haben den Nachweis erbracht ringforts spielte eine wichtige Rolle in der Wirtschaft der Republik Irland. Ausgrabungen haben zu dem Ergebnis, der Töpferei auf ringfort Websites dass sie wurden als Handelspartner Stellen oder andere Siedlung. Doch eine andere Theorie ist, dass die ringforts wurden für die Verteidigung wegen seines Namens und archäologische Beweise. Ringforts Mai wurden gebaut, um den Schutz der Rinder - Landwirtschaft Gemeinden und bewachen ihr Vieh. Die runde Form des ringfort zeigt auch seine defensiven Vorteile. Erklärungen aus der frühen christlichen Zeit Unterstützung eine andere Idee: ringforts wurden gebaut, um zu verstehen, Adel, Königtum, und Autorität. Die weitere Ausarbeitung des ringfort, desto höher der Status der Insassen. Die Förderung von einem Status war das Hauptziel der Bau dieser ringforts.</German>
      <Italian>[TAB] Ringforts sono fortificati insediamenti, che sono generalmente accettato di essere anticipato dal periodo medievale nel Nord Europa, soprattutto in Irlanda. Un ráth è stato fatto della terra e del caiseal o cathair sono stati fatti di pietra. A dun tratta di un sito più prestigiosa, la sede di un righello. Storico o archeologico, di registrare i primi medievale Periodo in Irlanda non avvicinarsi alla ringfort. Oltre 45000 siti sono stati identificati come ringforts in tutta l'Irlanda, ma oltre 60000 siti possono essere identificati. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Ringforts sono tradizionalmente inteso come un disperso maso, il honme di un uomo libero e la sua famiglia. Questo veiw è stato modificato, dicendo che non tutti ringforts non sono masi, ma che possono riempire una varietà di funzioni. Altri ringfort siti hanno fornito prove del fatto che ringforts svolto un ruolo significativo per l'economia irlandese. Gli scavi hanno portato alla constatazione di ceramica a ringfort siti suggerendo che essi potrebbero essere stati utilizzati come posti di scambio o di altre funzioni di regolamento. Ma un'altra teoria è che il ringforts sono stati utilizzati per la difesa, sia a causa del suo nome e archeologico prove. Ringforts potrebbe essere stata costruita per dare protezione alle comunità agricole - bovini e custodire il loro bestiame. La forma circolare del ringfort mostra anche i suoi vantaggi difensiva. Spiegazioni dal Primo periodo cristiano sostegno un'altra idea: ringforts sono stati costruiti a significare nobiltà, regalità, e di autorità. Il più elaborato il ringfort, maggiore è lo stato dei occupante. La promozione di uno status è stato l'obiettivo principale di costruzione di questi ringforts.</Italian>
      <Spanish>[TAB] Ringforts son asentamientos fortificados que se acordó en general que se de la Early Medieval período en el norte de Europa, especialmente Irlanda. A ráth se hizo de la tierra y caiseal o cathair estaban hechos de piedra. A dun de más es un lugar de prestigio, la sede de un gobernante. Histórico o arqueológico acta de la Early Medieval Período en Irlanda no se acerca a la ringfort. Más de 45000 sitios han sido identificados como ringforts en toda Irlanda, pero más de 60000 sitios pueden ser identificados. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Ringforts tradicionalmente entendida como la dispersión de una granja, la honme de un hombre libre y su familia. Este veiw ha sido alterado, diciendo que no todos los ringforts no son granjas, sino que cubrir una variedad de funciones. Otros ringfort sitios han proporcionado pruebas de que ringforts desempeñado un papel importante en la economía de Irlanda. Las excavaciones han llevado a la conclusión de la cerámica en ringfort sitios lo que hace pensar que pueden haber sido utilizados como puestos de comercio o de otras funciones de arreglo. Otra teoría es que la ringforts se utilizaron para la defensa tanto por su nombre y la evidencia arqueológica. Ringforts puede haber sido construido para dar protección a la cría de las comunidades agrícolas y la guardia de su ganado. La forma circular de la ringfort también muestra sus ventajas defensivas. Explicaciones de los primeros cristianos período de apoyo otra idea: ringforts fueron construidas para significar la nobleza, la monarquía, y de la autoridad. El más complicado en el ringfort, mayor es la situación de los ocupantes. La promoción de la condición es el objetivo principal de la construcción de estos ringforts.</Spanish>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_SCYTHIA_SCYTHIANSTABLES_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]If the Scythians were not the first to domesticate the horse they were among the earliest, if not the first of the Central Asian people to learn to ride it. Mounted soldiers was the Scythians' success in war; so when they penetrated into Asia, the technique of riding was rapidly adopted and mastered throughout the entire Middle Eastern area.[PARAGRAPH:1]Though the Scythian had elaborate bitted bridles, the stirrup was not known to them and they rode on saddleclothes, relying on grip and balance. Even so, they were formidable horsemen in battle.</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_SELEUKEION_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]When Alexander the Great died he left behind a power vacuum only to be filled by his generals, the Diadochi, who carved up his empire for themselves.  One of these generals, Seleucus I, was proclaimed chiliach, or General of the Army, under Perdiccas.[NEWLINE][TAB]When Perdiccas was murdered in 321bc, which Seleucus had a hand in; he moved quickly to seize Babylon and the entirety of the Old Persian Empire.  At the time of Seleucus own murder he was in control of the largest of the Successor kingdoms, with an empire that stretched from Asia Minor to India.[NEWLINE][TAB]To help control the towns and cities local magistrates worked from a building called the Seleukeion.  These buildings managed everything from day to day running of the city.  To trade along the vital trade routes east.  Principles among those were the Persian Royal Road and the Silk Road.</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_SELJUK_NIZAM_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]A Nizamiyya is one of the medieval institutions of higher education established by Khwaja Nizam al-Mulk in the eleventh century in present-day Iran. The name nizamiyyah derives from his name. Founded at the beginning of the Seljuk empire, they are considered to be the model of madrassas, or Islamic religious schools. Nizamiyyah institutes were the first well organized universities in the Muslim world. The quality of education was the highest in the Islamic world, and they were even renowned in Europe. They were supported financially, politically, and spiritually by the royal establishment and the elite class. The most famous and celebrated of all the nizamiyyah schools was Al-Nizamiyya of Baghdad (established 1065), where Khwaja Nizam al-Mulk appointed the distinguished philosopher and theologian, al-Ghazali, as a professor. Persian poet Sa'di was a student of the Baghdad Nizamiyyah. Other nizamiyyah schools were located in Nishapur, Balkh, Herat and Isfahan.</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_SOMALIA_MOGADISHU_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]The sultanates and republics of Merca, Mogadishu, Barawa, Hobyo and their respective ports became profitable trade outlets for commodities originating from the interior of the State. The farming communities of the hinterland brought their products to the coastal cities, where they were sold to local merchants who maintained a lucrative foreign commerce with ships sailing to and coming from Arabia, India, Venetia, Persia, Egypt, Portugal, and as far away as China. Vasco Da Gama, who passed by Mogadishu in the 15th century, noted that it was a large city with houses of four or five storeys high and big palaces in its centre and many mosques with cylindrical minarets.  In the 16th century, Duarte Barbosa noted that many ships from the Kingdom of Cambaya sailed to Mogadishu with cloths and spices for which they in return received gold, wax and ivory. Barbaso also highlighted the abundance of meat, wheat, barley, horses, and fruit on the coastal markets, which generated enormous wealth for the merchants.  Mogadishu, the center of a thriving weaving industry known as toob benadir (specialized for the markets in Egypt and Syria), together with Merca and Barawa also served as transit stops for Swahili merchants from Mombasa and Malindi and for the gold trade from Kilwa.  Jewish merchants from the Hormuz also brought their Indian textile and fruit to the Somali coast in exchange for grain and wood.</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_SOUTHAFRICA_BRAAI_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]The word braaivleis (pronounced "bry-flays") is Afrikaans for "roasted meat". The word braai (pronounced "bry", rhyming with the word "cry") is Afrikaans for "barbecue" or "roast" and is a social custom in South Africa and Zimbabwe. It originated with the Afrikaner people, but has since been adopted by South Africans of many ethnic backgrounds. The word vleis is Afrikaans for "meat", so in this word, the "s" is not a plural.</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_SWISS_ZOLL_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[PARAGRAPH:1][TAB]The Old Swiss Confederacy was an alliance among the valley communities of the central Alps. The Confederacy facilitated management of common interests (free trade) and ensured peace on the important mountain trade routes.</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_THING_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]A ting is a governing assembly in Scandinavian societies, made up of the free people of the area and supervised by judges.  Medieval Scandinavia was dominated by warring clans and tribes, and a body of law was required to settle disputes.  In Sweden, ting is not only used when referring medieval assemblies, but also for sub-national county councils, which are called Landsting.  The name was also used in medieval times for tings that government the historical Landskap provinces.  The name was also found in the names of the first level instances of the Swedish court system.</English>
      <French>[TAB]Ting est un ensemble régissant dans les sociétés scandinaves, composées des personnes libres du secteur et dirigées par des juges.  La Scandinavie médiévale a été dominée par les clans et les tribus faisants la guerre, et un corps de loi a été exigé pour régler des conflits.  En Suède, ting est non seulement employé en se référant les assemblées médiévales, mais également pour les County Councils sous-nationaux, qui s'appellent Landsting.  Le nom a été également employé dans des périodes médiévales pour des tings ce gouvernement les provinces historiques de Landskap.  Le nom a été également trouvé dans les noms des premiers exemples de niveau du système de cour suédois.</French>
      <German>[TAB]Ein Ting ist eine regelnversammlung in den skandinavischen Gesellschaften, gebildet von den freien Leuten des Bereichs und von den Richtern überwacht.  Mittelalterliches Skandinavien wurde durch warring Clane und Stämme beherrscht, und ein Körper des Gesetzes wurde angefordert, Debatten zu vereinbaren.  In Schweden wird das Ting nicht nur verwendet, wenn man mittelalterliche Versammlungen, aber auch für sub-national Grafschaftsräte verweist, die Landsting angerufen werden.  Der Name wurde auch in den mittelalterlichen Zeiten für tings diese Regierung die historischen Landskap Provinzen verwendet.  Der Name wurde auch in den Namen der ersten Niveauinstanzen der schwedischen Gerichtsverfassung gefunden.</German>
      <Italian>[TAB]Ting è un complessivo governante nelle società scandinave, composte della gente libera della zona e sorvegliate dai giudici.  La Scandinavia medioevale è stata dominata dai clan e dalle tribù facenti la guerra e un corpo di legge è stato richiesto depositare le dispute.  In Svezia, ting non solo è usato quando fa riferimento i complessivi medioevali, ma anche per i County Council sub-nazionali, che sono denominati Landsting.  Il nome inoltre è stato usato nei periodi medioevali per i tings quel governo le province storiche di Landskap.  Il nome inoltre è stato trovato nei nomi dei primi casi del livello del sistema di corte svedese.</Italian>
      <Spanish>[TAB]Ein Ting ist eine regelnversammlung in den skandinavischen Gesellschaften, gebildet von den freien Leuten des Bereichs und von den Richtern überwacht.  Mittelalterliches Skandinavien wurde durch warring Clane und Stämme beherrscht, und ein Körper des Gesetzes wurde angefordert, Debatten zu vereinbaren.  In Schweden wird das Ting nicht nur verwendet, wenn man mittelalterliche Versammlungen, aber auch für sub-national Grafschaftsräte verweist, die Landsting angerufen werden.  Der Name wurde auch in den mittelalterlichen Zeiten für tings diese Regierung die historischen Landskap Provinzen verwendet.  Der Name wurde auch in den Namen der ersten Niveauinstanzen der schwedischen Gerichtsverfassung gefunden.</Spanish>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_TROPICANA_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]The Club Tropicana is a world known cabaret and club in Havana, Cuba. It was launched in 1939 on a six-acre suburban estate in Havana. Heralded as a "Paradise Under the Stars," the Tropicana became known for its showgirls, conga sounds, domino tournaments and flashy, spectacular productions. When the indoor cabaret at the air-conditioned Arcos de Cristal opened on March 15, 1952, it had a combined total seating capacity of 1,700 for the interior and outside areas.[PARAGRAPH:2]The Tropicana had an impact in spreading Cuban culture internationally. The Tropicana was hardly a sleazy Mob hangout but rather a world-class entertainment venue that discriminating gangsters happened to enjoy frequenting. An excellent resource on Cuban popular culture, lavish entertainment, and everyday life.[NEWLINE]Party all night and free Salsa lessons with a two drink minimum!</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_TROY_AGORA_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]Central to every Greek city and town was the agora, a marketplace and meeting place. It was a large, usually rectangular space surrounded by buildings. Platforms, altars and statues of gods, sportsmen and political figures could also be found there. The stoa, which formed an edge of the agora, was a long building with columns. Shops were located in the stoa. More expensive items could be bought here.[PARAGRAPH:1]In some cities, local councils met in nearby buildings; other buildings were used to store public records and important political documents. Public spectators could watch criminals being placed on trial in the agora.[PARAGRAPH:1]Men and slaves usually did the shopping, with slaves and donkeys carrying the purchases; wealthier women may have visited to buy perfumes, jewellery and expensive cloth.[PARAGRAPH:1]Farmers came with their produce. In the large empty space of the agora, stallholders set up their sun shaded tables and sold such items as meat, fish, fruits and vegetables, cheeses, eggs, honey, wine, olive oil and animals (e.g. donkeys, horses, hens). Fresh meat and fish were displayed on marble slabs that kept the food cool. "Fast food" was also sold to hungry and thirsty shoppers. Slaves were placed on display and bought and sold.[PARAGRAPH:1]Merchants also bought and sold exotic foreign items in the agora. Ivory and gems came from Egypt, elephants from India, silk from China, wool from countries surrounding Greece, purple dye from the eastern countries, grain from areas around the Black Sea.[PARAGRAPH:1]Craftsmen had stalls, shops or workshops in or near the agora. Here they sold their goods or took orders. Sandles could be measured and made, barbers would trim hair and beards. Money changers and bankers would also conduct their business here.[PARAGRAPH:1]Men seeking employment would mix with employers looking for labourers. Some of those seeking work could be professionals or tradesmen, or they could have no skills.[PARAGRAPH:1]In the shady parts of the agora, family and friends could meet for a chat, while business people could make deals. Citizens could join in, or listen to, discussions about community and political issues. They may have watched musical and theatrical entertainments.[PARAGRAPH:1]Women and slaves could use a public fountain in the agora to collect their daily supply of water in pots.[PARAGRAPH:1]Busy and bustling, the agora was a vital area for a community.[PARAGRAPH:1]</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_TUPI_MALOCA_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]A maloca is an ancestral long house used by the natives of the Amazon, notably in Colombia and Brazil. Each community has a maloca with its own unique characteristics. For many years, these long houses were missionaries' objects of attack. Several families with patrilineal relations live together in a maloca, distributed around the long house in different compartments. In general, the chief of the local descent group lives in the compartment nearest to the back wall of the long house. As well, each family has its own furnace. During festivals and in formal ceremonies, which involve dances for males, the long house space is rearranged; the centre of the long house is the most important area where the dance takes place.</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_URHOKPOTA_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>The Urhokpota building worked as a courthouse in the Empire of Benin. It is said that the charm which was buried at the gate of the Palace brought prosperity to the Kingdom. The Oba lodged Okpota in a house near the Palace in the area of the present day Exhibition Centre. The verandah to his house soon became a meeting place for the elders, even for the Oba, and Urhokpota has ever since remained a Centre for meeting and useful deliberations.</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_UYGHUR_GRAPEARBOR_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]The Uyghur people are hugely welcoming to guests. The grape arbor provides blissful shelter from the relentless sun, and to sit here in such a comfortable courtyard and enjoy a moment of cool breeze under the grapevine is a real treat in itself. Even if you were a stranger, they would welcome you with whole-hearted hospitality, offering all they have - from tea to fresh fruits to dry fruits to home made yogurt to refresh you.</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_VAULTED_GRANARY_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]The Nubians had their own way of constructing vaults, called the Nubian Vault.  It was used to construct various buildings, such as granaries.  One of the key advantages of the Nubian vault is that it can be built without any support or shuttering.  The bricks were laid leaning at a small slope against the gabble walls in a length-wise vault.  The ancient Nubian technique was later revived by the Egyptian architect Hassan Fathy in the 1940's.</English>
      <French>[TAB]Le Nubians a eu leur propre manière de construire des chambres fortes, appelée la chambre forte de Nubian. Il a été employé pour construire de divers bâtiments, tels que des greniers. Un des avantages principaux de la chambre forte de Nubian est qu'il peut être construit sans n'importe quel appui ou shuttering. Les briques étaient penchement étendu à une petite pente contre les murs gabble dans une chambre forte en long. La technique antique de Nubian plus tard a été rétablie par l'architecte égyptien Hassan Fathy dans les années 40.</French>
      <German>[TAB]Das Nubians hatte ihre eigene Weise des Konstruierens der Wölbungen, genannt die Nubian Wölbung. Es wurde verwendet, um verschiedene Gebäude, wie Getreidespeicher zu konstruieren. Einer der Schlüsselvorteile der Nubian Wölbung ist, daß er ohne irgendeine Unterstützung oder Verschalung errichtet werden kann. Die Ziegelsteine waren gelegtes Lehnen an einer kleinen Steigung gegen die gabble Wände in einer Längswölbung. Die alte Nubian Technik wurde später vom ägyptischen Architekten Hassan Fathy in den vierziger Jahren wieder belebt.</German>
      <Italian>[TAB]Il Nubians ha avuto loro proprio senso di costruzione delle volte, denominato la volta di Nubian. È stato usato per costruire le varie costruzioni, quali i granai. Uno dei vantaggi chiave della volta di Nubian è che può essere costruito senza alcun supporto o shuttering. I mattoni erano inclinzione posta ad un pendio piccolo contro le pareti gabble in una volta longitudinale. La tecnica antica di Nubian più successivamente è stata fatta rivivere dall'architetto egiziano Hassan Fathy nei 1940's.</Italian>
      <Spanish>[TAB]El Nubians tenía su propia manera de construir cámaras acorazadas, llamada la cámara acorazada de Nubian. Fue utilizado para construir varios edificios, tales como graneros. Una de las ventajas dominantes de la cámara acorazada de Nubian es que puede ser construido sin ninguna ayuda o shuttering. Los ladrillos eran el inclinarse puesto en una cuesta pequeña contra las paredes gabble en una cámara acorazada longitudinal. La técnica antigua de Nubian fue restablecida más adelante por el arquitecto egipcio Hassan Fathy en los años 40.</Spanish>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_VECHE_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]The word "veche" refers to popular assemblies in medieval Slavic countries.  In the Kievan Rus, a medieval Ukrainian kingdom is known to be the origin of many of the other veches throughout Slavic countries.  The earliest mentions of veches in Russian chronicles refer to examples in Belgorod, a city on the Dnieper in 977, the Novgorod Republic in 1016, and in Kiev in 1068.  The assemblies discussed matters of war and peace, adopted laws, and called for and expelled rulers.</English>
      <French>[TAB]Le mot « veche » se rapporte aux assemblées populaires dans les pays slaves médiévaux.  Dans le Kievan Rus, un royaume ukrainien médiéval est connu pour être l'origine de plusieurs des autres veches dans tous les pays slaves.  Les mentions les plus tôt des veches en chroniques russes se rapportent à des exemples dans Belgorod, à une ville sur le Dnieper dans 977, à la République de Novgorod en 1016, et à Kiev en 1068.  Les assemblées ont discuté des points de guerre et de paix, ont adopté des lois, et ont appelé pour et ont expulsé des règles.</French>
      <German>[TAB]Das Wort veche bezieht sich auf populäre Versammlungen in den mittelalterlichen Slavic Ländern.  Im Kievan Rus, bekannt ein mittelalterliches ukrainisches Königreich, um der Ursprung von vielen der anderen veches in Slavic Ländern zu sein.  Die frühesten Erwähnungen von veches in den russischen Chroniken beziehen sich Beispiele in Belgorod, eine Stadt auf dem Dnieper in 977, die auf Novgorod Republik 1016 und in Kiew 1068.  Die Versammlungen berieten über Sachen des Krieges und des Friedens, nahmen Gesetze an und verlangten und trieben Lehren weg.</German>
      <Italian>[TAB]La parola veche si riferisce ai complessivi popolari nei paesi medioevali di Slavic.  Nel Kievan Rus, un regno ucraino medioevale è conosciuto per essere l'origine di molti degli altri veches durante i paesi di Slavic.  Le menzioni più iniziali dei veches in chronicles russi si riferiscono agli esempi in Belgorod, ad una città sul Dnieper in 977, alla Repubblica di Novgorod in 1016 ed a Kiev in 1068.  I complessivi hanno discusso sugli argomenti della guerra e della pace, hanno adottato le leggi ed hanno richiesto ed hanno espulso i righelli.</Italian>
      <Spanish>[TAB]La palabra veche refiere a las asambleas populares en los países medievales de Slavic.  En el Kievan Rus, un reino ucraniano medieval se conoce para ser el origen de muchos de los otros veches a través de los países de Slavic.  Las menciones más tempranas de veches en los chronicles rusos refieren a ejemplos en Belgorod, a una ciudad en el Dnieper en 977, a la república de Novgorod en 1016, y en Kiev en 1068.  Las materias discutidas asambleas de la guerra y paz, leyes adoptados, y llamado para y reglas expelidas.</Spanish>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_VEDIC_VEDAS_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]The Vedas are a large corpus of texts originating in Ancient India. They form the oldest layer of Sanskrit literature and the oldest sacred texts of Hinduism. According to Hindu tradition, the Vedas "not human compositions", being supposed to have been directly revealed, and thus are called sruti ("what is heard"). Vedic mantras are recited at Hindu prayers, religious functions and other auspicious occasions.</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_VIETNAM_OPENMARKET_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]In 1986, the Sixth Party Congress introduced significant economic reforms with market economy elements as part of a broad economic reform package called "doi moi" (Renovation). Private ownership was encouraged in industries, commerce and agriculture. In many ways, this followed the Chinese model and achieved similar results. Vietnam achieved significant growth over the next decade-and-a-half, making it the world's second-fastest growing economy of the time.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Upon taking power, Vietnamese communists had created a command economy in the nation. Collectivization of farms, factories and economic capital was implemented, and millions of people put to work in government programs. For many decades, Vietnam's economy was plagued with inefficiency and corruption in state programs. This trend seems to be reversing as a free market begins to take hold within the country.</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_VILLU_STATUE_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB] Villu is a Mitanni fish-deity.  Mitanni was an ancient Hurrian kingdom that flourished in the 14th century BC.  Villu is known today by a few surviving clay statues of him as a cult object.  Villu was a god of water with influence over droughts and thirst.  He was used in a jurisdictional role.  People convicted of crimes involving the sea, water or blood would be stoned with the aforesaid statues to death.  Were a criminal to be punished in any other way, Villu would decrease the river flow, causing drought and famine.  Following the conquest of Mitanni by the Hittites, his cult and the punishment declined.</English>
      <French>[TAB] Villu Mitaniens est un poisson-divinité. Mitaniens hourrite est un ancien royaume qui prospéra dans le 14ème siècle avant JC. Villu est connue aujourd'hui par une poignée de survivants des statues d'argile de lui comme d'un objet-culte. Villu était un dieu de l'eau ayant une influence sur la sécheresse et la soif. Il a été utilisé dans un rôle juridictionnel. Les personnes condamnées pour des crimes liés à la mer, l'eau ou le sang sera lapidé avec lesdites statues à la mort. Étaient un criminel pour être punis de toute autre manière, Villu diminuerait le débit fluvial, entraînant la sécheresse et la famine. Après la conquête de Mitaniens par les Hittites, son culte et la sanction refusée.</French>
      <German>[TAB] Villu ist ein Mitanni Fisch-Gottheit. Mitanni war eine antike Hurrian Reich blühte, dass im 14. Jahrhundert v. Chr.. Villu bekannt ist heute von wenigen überlebenden Ton Statuen von ihm als Kult-Objekt. Villu war ein Gott des Wassers mit Einfluss auf Dürren und Durst. Er war in einer Gerichtsbarkeit Rolle. Die Leute sind, Straftaten im Zusammenhang mit dem Meer, das Wasser oder Blut wäre gesteinigt mit den genannten Statuen zu Tode. Waren ein Strafverfahren bestraft werden in irgendeiner anderen Art und Weise, Villu sinken würden den Fluss fließen, was Dürre und Hungersnot. Nach der Eroberung durch die Mitanni Hethiter, seinem Kult-und die Strafe abgelehnt.</German>
      <Italian>[TAB] Villu è un pesce Mitanni-divinità. Mitanni era un antico regno Hurrian che fiorirono nel 14 ° secolo aC. Villu oggi è conosciuto da pochi superstiti argilla statue di lui come un oggetto di culto. Villu era un dio delle acque con influenza sulla siccità e la sete. Egli è stato utilizzato in un ruolo giurisdizionale. Persone condannate per reati che comportano il mare, l'acqua o il sangue sarebbe lapidato con i suddetti statue a morte. Sono un criminale di essere punito in qualsiasi altro modo, Villu farebbe diminuire la portata del fiume, provocando siccità e carestia. In seguito alla conquista di Mitanni dagli Ittiti, il suo culto e la punizione rifiutato.</Italian>
      <Spanish>[TAB] Villu Mitanni pescado es una deidad-. Mitanni hurritas fue un antiguo reino que floreció en el siglo 14 antes de Cristo. Villu es conocida hoy por algunos supervivientes de las estatuas de arcilla como un objeto de culto. Villu era un dios de las aguas, con influencia en la sequía y la sed. Fue usado en una función jurisdiccional. Las personas condenadas por delitos relacionados con el mar, el agua o la sangre sería apedreado con las mencionadas estatuas a la muerte. Fueron un penal que se castiga de cualquier otra manera, Villu disminuiría el caudal del río, causando la sequía y el hambre. Tras la conquista de Mitanni por los hititas, su culto y la pena se redujo.</Spanish>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_WESTINDIES_CRICKETGROUND_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]Cricket has been an established team sport for hundreds of years and is thought to be the second most popular sport in the world. It is a bat-and-ball sport contested by two teams, usually of eleven players each. More than 100 countries are affiliated to the International Cricket Council, cricket's international governing body. The sport's modern form originated in England, and is most popular in the present and former members of the Commonwealth. In the countries of South Asia, including India, Pakistan, Bangladesh and Sri Lanka, cricket is the most popular sport. It is also a major sport in England, Australia, New Zealand, South Africa, Zimbabwe and the English-speaking countries of the Caribbean, which are collectively known in cricketing parlance as the West Indies.</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_XIONGNU_KURGAN_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]The Noin-Ula kurgans are located by the Selenga River in the northern Mongolia hills north of Ulan Bator. It was excavated in 1924-1925 by Pyotr Kozlov. One of Noin-Ula kurgans is notable for its rich burial of a Xiongnu ruler, Uchjulü-Chanuy. Most of the objects from Noin-Ula are now in the Hermitage Museum, while some artifacts unearthed later by Mongolian archaeologists are on display in the Mongolian National Museum, Ulan Bator. One kurgan contained a lacquer cup inscribed with the name of its Chinese maker and dated September 5, 13 AD.[PARAGRAPH:1]The Noin Ula burials consist of more than 200 large kurgans. Inside the kurgans are timber burial chambers. Noin Ula had horse burials and one tomb had especially lavish furnishings. The coffin was apparently made in China, and the interned person had many of his possessions buried with him. His horse trappings were elaborately decorated and his leather-covered saddle was threaded with black and red wool clipped to resemble velvet. Magnificent textiles included a woven wool rug lined with thin leather with purple, brown, and white felt appliqué work, and textiles of Greco-Bactrian, Parthian and Anatolian origin.[PARAGRAPH:1]Some objects are similar to the artifacts from Pazyryk in the Altay Mountains. As with the finds at Pazyryk, the Noin Ula graves had been flooded and subsequently frozen, thus preserving the organic material to an unprecedented degree. The tombs, plundered in antiquity, formed wooden burial chambers in deep shafts covered by earthen kurgans. Among the burial inventory were artifacts of the Hunnish craftsmen including weaponry, home utensils, art objects, and multiple Chinese artifacts from bronze, nephrite, lacquered wood and textiles. Many artifacts show that Huns actively participated in trade along the Great Silk Road.[PARAGRAPH:1]Among the Noin Ula art works are many imported objects and fragments of fabrics recognized as Greek. The fabric, color, weaving methods and embroidery of the cloth were similar to the cloth produced in the Greek colonies on the Black Sea coast for the Scythians, and from there they were flowing to the Huns, bringing along a knowledge about western countries. The Huns' later migration was planned and weighed: pushed from the borders of China and "Western Territory", they had to move to the borders of another agricultural culture, because isolation doomed them to poverty and obliteration.[PARAGRAPH:1]</English>
   </TEXT>
   <TEXT>
      <Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_YEMEN_QATFIELD_PEDIA</Tag>
      <English>[TAB]Qat is a flowering plant native to tropical East Africa, grown for use as a stimulant for centuries in the Horn of Africa and the Arabian Peninsula. Chewing khat predates the use of coffee and is used in a similar social context. Its fresh leaves and tops are chewed or, less frequently, dried and consumed as tea, in order to achieve a state of euphoria and stimulation. It is estimated that several million people are frequent users of qat.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Many of the users originate from countries between Sudan and Madagascar and in the southwestern part of the Arabian Peninsula, especially Yemen. In Yemen, a majority of people chew the plant daily for long periods of their life. The traditional form of qat chewing in Yemen involves only male users; qat chewing by females is less formal and less frequent. Despite it being outlawed in most Muslim countries, Yemeni clerics have adopted a lenient stance on its use.</English>
   </TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>
