<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<Civ4GameText>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_ABORIGINES_NULLA_NULLA_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]A nulla nulla, also known as as waddy or hunting stick, is an Australian Aboriginal war club.  The nulla nulla is a heavy club made of timber used in hand to hand combat.  Known to have the ability to split a shield, this powerful weapon was used for killing or stunning food.  It could also be used as a projectile or be used to make fire and ochre.  They could also be used as a punishment to those who broke Aboriginal law.  The nulla nulla was made by both men and women and could be painted or left unpainted.  Their construction varied from tribe to ribe, but were generall about one meter in length and sometimes had a stone head attached with bees wax and string.  They were made from where a branch met the tree, or from a young tree pulled up with its roots in the ground. </English>
        <French>[TAB]Un Nulla Nulla, également connue sous le nom de waddy ou bâton de chasse, est un club de la guerre des Aborigènes d'Australie. Le Nulla Nulla est un club de lourdes faites de bois utilisé dans une main à combattre. On sait qu'ils ont la possibilité de diviser un bouclier, cette puissante arme a été utilisée pour tuer ou de l'étourdissement nourriture. Elle pourrait aussi être utilisée comme un projectile ou être utilisés pour faire du feu et l'ocre. Ils pourraient aussi être utilisé comme un châtiment de ceux qui violent le droit autochtone. Le Nulla Nulla a été faite par les hommes et les femmes et peuvent être peintes ou non peintes gauche. Leur construction variaient d'une tribu à ribe, mais sont généralement, à environ un mètre de long et ont parfois une pierre tête attachée à la cire d'abeilles et de chaîne. Elles sont faites à partir duquel une succursale rencontré l'arbre, ou d'un jeune arbre arrachées avec ses racines dans le sol.</French>
        <German>[TAB] Ein ... nulla ... nulla, auch bekannt als als waddy oder Jagd halten, ist ein australischer Aborigines Krieg Verein. Die ... nulla ... nulla ist eine schwere Klub aus Holz in der Hand zu Hand bekämpfen. Bekannt, dass die Fähigkeit zur Spaltung ein Schild, dieses mächtige Waffe wurde zur Tötung oder Betäuben Nahrung. Es könnte auch dazu genutzt werden, ein Projektil oder verwendet werden können, um Feuer und Ocker. Sie könnten auch als eine Strafe für jene, die Aborigines Gesetz gebrochen. Die ... nulla ... nulla wurde von Männern und Frauen und könnte bemalt oder unbemalt links. Ihr Bau variierten von Stamm zu ribe, wurden aber generall über einen Meter in der Länge und manchmal hatte einen Stein Kopf befestigt mit Bienen Wachs und String. Sie waren aus, wenn ein Zweig mit dem Baum, oder von einem jungen Baum zog sich mit seinen Wurzeln in den Boden. </German>
        <Italian>[TAB]A nulla nulla, noto anche come come waddy o bastone di caccia, è una guerra Club aborigeni australiani. Il nulla è un nulla pesanti squadra fatta di legno utilizzato in mano in mano combattere. Noto che hanno la capacità di dividere un scudo, questa potente arma è stato usato per uccidere o di stordimento cibo. Essa potrebbe anche essere usato come un proiettile o essere usato per fare fuoco e ocra. Essi potrebbero anche essere utilizzato come una punizione per coloro che hanno rotto aborigeni legge. Il nulla nulla è stato fatto da uomini e donne e potrebbe essere dipinto o di sinistra non verniciata. La loro costruzione variava da tribù a ribe, ma sono stati generall circa un metro di lunghezza e talvolta aveva una testa di pietra collegata con cera d'api e la stringa. Esse sono state effettuate da una succursale, dove ha incontrato l'albero, o da un giovane albero tirato su con le sue radici nel terreno.</Italian>
        <Spanish>[TAB]Una de nulla de nulla, también conocido como la caza como waddy o palo, es un club de la guerra de aborígenes de Australia. El de nulla de nulla es un gran club de hecho de la madera utilizada en mano en mano de combate. Sabe que tiene la capacidad de dividir un escudo, esta poderosa arma fue utilizada para matar o aturdimiento alimentos. También podría ser utilizado como proyectil o ser utilizados para hacer fuego y ocre. También podrían ser utilizados como un castigo a aquellos que rompieron la ley aborígenes. El de nulla de nulla fue hecha por los hombres y las mujeres y pueden ser pintados o izquierda unpainted. Su construcción varía de tribu a ribe, pero se generall alrededor de un metro de largo y, a veces, había una piedra jefe adjunto con cera de abejas y de cadena. Ellos se hicieron desde una sucursal, donde se reunió con el árbol, o de un árbol joven se levantó con sus raíces en el terreno.</Spanish>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_AGEMA_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]The Baktrian Kingdom had its own elite guard, shown so beautifully in golden statuary throughout their prominent enclaves.  These men are armed with spear and blade, and armored in a tough cuirass and boeotian helmet of a design unique to their corps.  They are the elite infantry of Baktria, and form the bulwark of Baktrias opposition to its rabid enemies.  They are a versatile phalanx, adept at their prescribed task but equally proficient when charging as melee fighters.[NEWLINE][TAB]Historically, the Baktrians had a lack of professional guards, which they tried to rectify by training recent arrivals from independent and semi autonomous Greek settlements outside of their kingdom, seeking a secure region for protection after their succession from the Seleucid kingdom.  These Greeks eventually formed the nucleus of this powerful and feared group of soldiers, which was later supplemented by local Greeks.</English>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_AKKADIAN_COMPOSITE_BOWMAN_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[H1]The Composite Bow[\H1][PARAGRAPH:2]The Akkadians probably invented the composite bow during the reign of Naram-Sin (2254-2218). A stele from this period shows Naram-Sin holding a composite bow, which is its first appearance in history, suggesting an Akkadian origin.[PARAGRAPH:2]The structure of the composite bow allows a smaller sized bow to pack greater power. The curve of the bow creates a higher draw-weight, releasing more total energy when the arrow is fired. The higher power allowed arrows to pierce leather armor, and possibly even bronze armor, from a great distance. The smaller size makes the composite bow more suitable for use on horseback or chariots. The disadvantage is that a composite bow takes much more time and effort to make than a regular bow, and because it necessitates gluing materials together, it is susceptible to water and humidity.</English>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_ALAE_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]Tacitus described the Batavians as the bravest of the tribes in the area, hardened in the German wars, with cohorts under their own commanders transferred to Britannia.  They retained the honor of the ancient association with the Romans, not required to pay tribute or taxes and used by the Romans only for war: "They furinished the Empire nothing but men and arms", Tacitus remarked,  Well-regarded for their skills in horsemanship and swimming - for men and horses could cross the Rhine without losing formation, according to Tacitus.[NEWLINE][TAB]The Alae Miliaria was the cavalry arm of the Batavian Cohorts supplied to the Romans.  The Miliaria would be used to flank and enemy and pepper them with pila (Roman javelins) before closing in a full charge.  These men were superb horsemen and could cross rivers and streams in full battle armor without loosing formation.  An excellent example of this skill is best described by Dio Cassius as he refers to the Battle of the River Medway."The barbarians thought that Romans would not be able to cross it without a bridge, and consequently bivouacked in rather careless fashion on the opposite bank; but he sent across a detachment of Germans, who were accustomed to swim easily in full armor across the most turbulent streams.  Thence the Britons retired to the river Thames at a point near where it empties into the ocean and at flood-tide forms a lake. This they easily crossed because they knew where the firm ground and the easy passages in this region were to be found; but the Romans in attempting to follow them were not so successful. However, the Germans swam across again and some others got over by a bridge a little way up-stream, after which they assailed the barbarians from several sides at once and cut down many of them." (Cassius Dio, Roman History, Book 60:20)[NEWLINE][TAB]Batavians also supplied large numbers of horsemen for the Emperor's Imperial Horse Guard.</English>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_ALBANIAN_LIGHT_GUERILLA_CAVALRY_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]The Albanians under Gjergj Kastrioti's time developed and employed Guerilla Cavalry Tactics as a means of defense against the invading Ottoman armies.  The Kalorse, a type of "Light Guerilla Cavalry," was able to outrun any unit the Ottomans had to offer.  They made a habit of raiding enemy military encampments when they were least expected, wreaking havoc and causing confusion amongst enemy ranks before they withdrew from battle.</English>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_ANGLO_SAXON_HUSCARL_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>In Anglo-Saxon England there may have been as many as 3,000 royal housecarls, and a special tax was levied to provide pay in coin. They were housed and fed at the king's expense. They formed a standing army of professional soldiers and also had some administrative duties in peacetime as the King's representatives. The term was often used in contrast to the non-professional fyrd. These Housecarls used a tactic called the shieldwall. In this tactic the Housecarls formed a line with their shields locked blocking the invaders or enemies from penetrating their lines. The Saxons were an aggressive force, and did not like defending. Thus, this battle tactic was not used for a long time. Huscarls were often the only professional soldiers in the kingdom, the rest of the army being made up of militia called the fyrd, peasant levy, and occasionally mercenaries. They were usually armed with the long Danish axe and had shields and mail armour.</English>
        <French>in French</French>
        <German>in German</German>
        <Italian>in Italian</Italian>
        <Spanish>in Spanish</Spanish>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_ANIYONEGA_AYASTIGI_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]Ayastigi is the Cherokee word for Fighting Man or Warrior. The Cherokee warpath was made up of many trails that had been carved into the mountains from thousands of years of use by the warriors going to war. They would travel for thousands of miles to make war with their cousins of the Iroquois Nation, and other northern tribes.  Give the ayastigi a direction and a leader and they would follow it. When the war chief struck the atadedawasdodi (war pole), all ayastigi who wished to follow the chief gathered their war gear and struck out on one of their favorite "sports." The Cherokee were not a brutal tribe of war people.  They were just made up of warriors who would go to war over the smallest wrong done to them or one of their own. They were respected and feared by all. The war cry of the Cherokee brought fear through out the mountains when they came calling.</English>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_APACHE_REDSLEEVES_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]In 1837, Mangas Coloradas or Dasoda-hae (Red Sleeves) became principal chief and war leader and began a series of retaliatory raids against the Mexicans. When the United States went to war against Mexico, many Apache bands promised U.S. soldiers safe passage through their lands. When the U.S. claimed former territories of Mexico in 1846, Mangas Coloradas signed a peace treaty, respecting them as conquerors of the Mexican's land. An uneasy peace (a centuries old tradition) between the Apache and the now citizens of the United States held until the 1850s, when an influx of gold miners into the Santa Rita Mountains led to conflict. This period is sometimes called the Apache Wars.</English>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_ARGENTINA_CABALLO_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]Jose de San Martin was a well respected and highly decorated general. He was the sole founder of the "Regimiento de Granaderos a Caballo" (Mounted Grenadier Regiment of the Argentine Army). It served as a school which produced some of the best cavalry officers in the history of South American warfare. All of the members of this school were well disciplined, well mannered, and were superior in training to any force before it. The significance of these soldiers would soon be realized when it came time for San Martín to begin assembling the force that would lead the march towards Peru.</English>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_ARMENIA_FEDAYEE_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]Armenian militia better known as Fedayee, is a term referring to Armenian guerrillas who voluntarily leave their families in order to fight for Armenians. The term fedayee was also used by Armenian guerrillas in the Ottoman Empire before and during the First World War, who defended Armenians from persecution. The term was widely used and is still used to describe the volunteers, and can be found in literature and songs.</English>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_ARSIYAH_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]According to Muslim sources, the Arsiyah formed the core of the Khazar army and were extremely influential in Khazar politics, but these assertions may be designed to exaggerate the importance of the Muslim community in Khazaria. The Arsiyah did often act independently of their government. Part of the treaty binding them to Khazar service guaranteed that they would not be used to fight other Muslims. In 913, the Arsiyah ambushed a Viking fleet that had been granted passage to the Caspian Sea by the Khazar government, wiping out thousands of Rus warriors.</English>
        <French>[TAB]Selon des sources musulmanes, l'Arsiyah a formé le noyau de l'armée de Khazar et était extrêmement influent dans la politique de Khazar, mais ces affirmations peuvent être conçues exagèrent l'importance de la communauté musulmane dans Khazaria. L'Arsiyah souvent a agi indépendamment de leur gouvernement. Une partie du traité les liant au service de Khazar a garanti qu'ils ne seraient pas employés pour combattre d'autres musulmans. Dans 913, l'Arsiyah a attiré dans un guet-apens une flotte de Viking qui avait été accordée le passage vers la mer caspienne par le gouvernement de Khazar, éliminant des milliers de guerriers de Rus</French>
        <German>[TAB]Entsprechend moslemischen Quellen bildete das Arsiyah den Kern der Khazar Armee und war in der Khazar Politik extrem einflußreich, aber diese Behauptungen können entworfen werden übertreiben den Wert der moslemischen Gemeinschaft in Khazaria. Das Arsiyah fungierte häufig unabhängig von ihrer Regierung. Der Teil des Vertrags, der sie an Khazar Service bindet, garantierte, daß sie nicht benutzt würden, um andere Moslems zu kämpfen. In 913 ambushed das Arsiyah eine Viking Flotte, die Durchgang zum kaspischen Meer durch die Khazar Regierung bewilligt worden war und heraus wischte Tausenden Rus Krieger ab.</German>
        <Italian>[TAB]Secondo le fonti musulmane, il Arsiyah ha formato il nucleo dell'esercito di Khazar ed era estremamente influente nella politica di Khazar, ma queste asserzioni possono essere progettate esagerano l'importanza della Comunità musulmana in Khazaria. Il Arsiyah si è comportato spesso indipendentemente dal loro governo. La parte del trattato che li lega al servizio di Khazar ha garantito che non sarebbero usati per combattere altri musulmani. In 913, il Arsiyah ambushed una flotta di Viking che era stata assegnata il passaggio al mare caspico dal governo di Khazar, eliminante i migliaia dei guerrieri di Rus.</Italian>
        <Spanish>[TAB]Según fuentes musulmanas, el Arsiyah formó la base del ejército de Khazar y era extremadamente influyente en la política de Khazar, pero estas aserciones se pueden diseñar exageran la importancia de la comunidad musulmana en Khazaria. El Arsiyah actuaba a menudo independientemente de su gobierno. La parte del tratado que los ataba al servicio de Khazar garantizó que no serían utilizados para luchar a otros musulmanes. En 913, el Arsiyah ambushed una flota de Viking que había sido concedida el paso al mar caspio por el gobierno de Khazar, limpiando hacia fuera a millares de guerreros de Rus.</Spanish>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_ASHANTI_TWAFO_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]The Ashanti national army was elaborately organized into 6 parts, each with various sub-divisions, and muskets gradually replaced bows and arrows as the main weapons. On the move the army used this general breakdown- advance guard, main body, rearguard, and right and left wings. This detailed organization had several advantages, enabling the Ashanti generals to maneuver their forces with flexibility.  The Twafo was the advance guard within the system.</English>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_ATLANTES_WARRIOR_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>The Atlantes Warriors were the elite of the elite of the Toltec armies, generals, soldiers of prestige and honor among the masses. So named after the legendary statues outside the old toltec capital city, these warriors were almost without peer during their day.</English>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_BANGLADESH_BAHINI_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]The Sena Bahini has specialized its peacekeeping operations capabilities around the world through participation in peacekeeping and nation building. It has created BIPSOT (Bangladesh Institute of Peace Support Operation Training) which is dedicated to training of peacekeepers for employment in all types of UNPSO (UN Peace Support Operations). </English>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_BELGIUM_PIRON_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]Belgian 1st Infantry Brigade, also known by the name of its commander as the "Brigade Piron", began as miscellaneous small elements in the United Kingdom, expanded to a "fusilier" battalion by the end of 1940, mustered a pair of such battalions in 1941, and in January 1943 assumed the official brigade designation. Various schemes were considered during this time for utilizing the brigade overseas, but it was decided to reserve it for the actual liberation of Belgium.</English>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_BOLIVARIAN_LIBERATADOR_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]Known as "El Liberatador", Simon Bolivar waged a war against the Spanish in several regions of South America. After his defeat in the Venezuelan War of Independence in 1811-1812. rebel leader Simon Bolivar fled to New Granada. He later returned with a new army, while the war had entered a tremendously violent phase. After much of the local aristocracy had abandoned the cause of independence, blacks and mulattos carried on the struggle. Elites reacted with open distrust and opposition to the efforts of these common people. Bolivar's forces invaded Venezuela from New Granada in 1813, waging a campaign with a ferocity captured perfectly by their motto, "guerra a muerte" ("war to the death"). Bolivar's forces defeated Juan Monteverde's Spanish army in a series of battles, taking Caracas in August 6, 1813 and besieging Monteverde at Puerto Cabello in September 1813.</English>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_BRAZIL_PRACINHA_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]It is the main unit that fought against the Brazilian Federation in the Revolution of 32, when the state of Sao Paulo has separated of the rest of the nation and lately was the main Brazilian unit in the World War II. This revolution occurred in 1932, when the Paulistas has not accepted the new rules for the states of the dictator Getúlio Vargas and for 3 months São Paulo was an independent nation. The Revolution was over after bombards of aircrafts and cannons and when the state didn't receive necessary help of allied states.</English>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_BURMA_MON_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]Humans lived in the region that is now Myanmar as early as 11,000 years ago, but the first identifiable civilisation is that of the Mon. The Mon probably began migrating into the area southward from western China in the period from 3000 BC to 1500 BC and settled in the Chao Phraya River basin of southern Thailand around the 6th century AD. </English>
        <French>[TAB]Humans lived in the region that is now Myanmar as early as 11,000 years ago, but the first identifiable civilisation is that of the Mon. The Mon probably began migrating into the area southward from western China in the period from 3000 BC to 1500 BC and settled in the Chao Phraya River basin of southern Thailand around the 6th century AD.</French>
        <Italian>[TAB]Humans lived in the region that is now Myanmar as early as 11,000 years ago, but the first identifiable civilisation is that of the Mon. The Mon probably began migrating into the area southward from western China in the period from 3000 BC to 1500 BC and settled in the Chao Phraya River basin of southern Thailand around the 6th century AD.</Italian>
        <Spanish>[TAB]Humans lived in the region that is now Myanmar as early as 11,000 years ago, but the first identifiable civilisation is that of the Mon. The Mon probably began migrating into the area southward from western China in the period from 3000 BC to 1500 BC and settled in the Chao Phraya River basin of southern Thailand around the 6th century AD.</Spanish>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_CAROLEAN_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]The Caroleans were soldiers of the Swedish kings Charles XI and Charles XII.  They were part of the yearly Swedish allotment system.  The Caroleans' tactics were to attack fiercely and remain unafraid.  The soldiers also sustained stern discipline, which over the extensive course of a twenty-year-long war would prove vital.  The Swedish army tactics of the time did not teach retreat, so the soldiers were known to never withdraw from battle.</English>
        <French>[TAB]Le Caroleans étaient des soldats des Rois suédois Charles XI et Charles XII.  Ils faisaient partie du système suédois annuel d'attribution.  La tactique du Caroleans était d'attaquer violemment et rester sans peur.  Les soldats ont également soutenu la discipline sévère, qui au-dessus du cours étendu d'une vingt-année-longue guerre prouverait essentiel.  La tactique suédoise d'armée du temps n'a pas enseigné la retraite, ainsi les soldats ont été connus pour ne jamais se retirer de la bataille.</French>
        <German>[TAB]Das Caroleans waren Soldaten der schwedischen Könige Charles XI und Charles XII.  Sie waren ein Teil des jährlichen schwedischen Zuteilung Systems.  Die Taktiken des Caroleans waren, wütend anzugreifen und furchtlos zu bleiben.  Die Soldaten unterstützten auch stern Disziplin, die über dem umfangreichen Kurs eines Zwanzig-Jahr-langen Krieges lebenswichtiges prüfen würde.  Die schwedischen Armeetaktiken der Zeit unterrichteten nicht Rückzug, also bekannt die Soldaten, um nie von der Schlacht zurückzutreten.</German>
        <Italian>[TAB]Il Caroleans era soldati dei re svedesi Charles XI e Charles XII.  Facevano parte del sistema svedese annuale di assegnazione.  Le tattiche del Caroleans erano di attacare ferocemente e rimanere unafraid.  I soldati inoltre hanno sostenuto la disciplina severa, che sopra il vasto corso di una guerra venti-anno-lunga dimostrerebbe vitale.  Le tattiche svedesi dell'esercito del tempo non hanno insegnato la ritirata, in modo da i soldati sono stati conosciuti per non ritirarsi mai dalla battaglia.</Italian>
        <Spanish>[TAB]El Caroleans era soldados de los reyes suecos Charles XI y Charles XII.  Eran parte del sistema sueco anual de la asignación.  Las táctica del Caroleans eran atacar ferozmente y seguir siendo sin miedo.  Los soldados también sostuvieron la disciplina severa, que sobre el curso extenso de una guerra veinte-año-larga probaría vital.  Las táctica suecas del ejército del tiempo no enseñaron el retratamiento, así que conocían a los soldados nunca para retirarse de batalla.</Spanish>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_CHILE_CARABINIERS_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]Carabineros de Chile are the uniformed Chilean national police force and gendarmery, created on April 27, 1927. Their mission is to maintain the order and create public respect for the laws of the country. They depend on the Ministerio de Defensa Nacional (Ministry of National Defense) through the Undersecretary of Carabiniers and the Ministerio del Interior (Ministry of the Interior). Chile also has an investigative police force, the Policia de Investigaciones.</English>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_CHOLA_KALLARANI_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]Technically, the Kallarani weren't employed by either the sovereign or the state. Rather, they were pirates who received tng military unit that could easily go from place to place in a relatively short amount of time. Their elusiveness (when needed) and their knowledge of the terrain made them extremely difficult fighters. The Viet Cong were also highly motivatived and would endure terrible conditions to keep up the fight against the enemy no matter how long it lasted.</English>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_COLOMBIA_AUC_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]The United Self-Defense Forces of Colombia (Autodefensas Unidas de Colombia, or AUC, in Spanish) was created as an umbrella organization of regional far-right paramilitary groups in Colombia, each intending to protect different local economic, social and political interests by fighting insurgents in their areas. It is estimated that it has more than 20,000 militants. The AUC has been considered to be a terrorist organization by many countries and organizations, including the United States and the European Union. The organization was formed in April 1997.  The AUC claimed its primary objective was to protect its sponsors and its supporters from insurgents and their activities, because the Colombian state had historically failed to do so. The AUC asserted itself as a regional and national counter-insurgency force. Former AUC leader Carlos Castaño Gil in 2000 claimed 70 percent of the AUC's operational costs were financed with cocaine-related earnings, the rest coming from "donations" from its sponsors. The group's sponsors have included landowners, cattle ranchers, mining or petroleum companies and politicians.  The AUC has also been linked to elements within the Colombian Army with whom they maintained cooperation, including their participation in joint operatives. The Colombian military has been accused of delegating to AUC paramilitaries the task of murdering peasants and labor union leaders, among others, targeted by the group under the suspicion of being guerrilla infiltrators.  The bulk of the AUC's blocks demobilized by early 2006 and its former top leadership was extradited to the U.S. in 2008. However, local successors such as the Black Eagles continue to exist and death threats have been made using its name. On May 8, 2008, employees of a community radio station (Sarare FM Stereo) received a message stating: "For the wellbeing of you and your loved ones, do not meddle in subjects that do not concern the radio station. AUC, Arauca". A few days later the letters AUC were daubed on the front of their office. This threat was made due to their participation in a public meeting attended by members of a Congressional Human Rights Commission on the 27 September 2007. Here, members of the public denounced human rights abuses committed in Arauca Department by different parties to the armed conflict, including the AUC.</English>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_CONGO_FIDALGO_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]The Congo kingdom's army consisted of a mass levy of archers, drawn from the general male population, and a smaller corps of heavy infantry, who fought with swords and carried shields for protection. Portuguese documents typically referred to heavy infantry, considered nobles, as fidalgos in documents.</English>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_COPPER_AXEMAN_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB] Although not much evidence of warfare in the Indus Valley Civilization has been found, many specimens of weapons have been discovered in the ruins of Harappa and Mohenjo-Daro.  Remains of axes made from copper or bronze have been found and could have been used by hunters in the area.  Some axes that are found contain inscriptions about deities or gods written in Indus Script.  Some of the axes found can be dated to as far back as 1500 BC,</English>
        <French>[TAB] Bien que peu de preuves de la guerre dans la civilisation de l'Indus a été trouvé, de nombreux spécimens d'armes ont été découvertes dans les ruines de Harappa et Mohenjo-Daro. Restes d'axes faits de cuivre ou de bronze ont été découverts et auraient pu être utilisés par les chasseurs dans la région. Certains axes que l'on trouve sur les inscriptions contiennent des divinités ou des dieux écrit en script de l'Indus. Certains de ces axes peut être trouvée à la date d'aussi loin que 1500 av.</French>
        <German>[TAB] Obwohl noch nicht viele Beweise für Kriegsführung in der Indus-Tal Zivilisation gefunden wurde, viele Exemplare von Waffen gefunden wurden, in den Ruinen der Harappa-und Mohenjo-Daro. Reste von Achsen aus Kupfer oder Bronze wurden gefunden und konnte die von Jägern in der Gegend. Einige Achsen, die sich mit Inschriften über Gottheiten oder Götter in Indus Script. Einige der Achsen gefunden werden können, um so weit vom als 1500 v. Chr. zurück.</German>
        <Italian>[TAB] Anche se non molto la prova della guerra e la Civiltà della valle dell'Indo è stato trovato, molti esemplari di armi sono state scoperte e le rovine di Harappa e Mohenjo-Daro. Resti di assi fatta da rame o bronzo, sono stati trovati e potrebbe essere stata usata dai cacciatori della zona. Alcuni assi che si trovano iscrizioni contenere circa divinità o dèi scritto in Indus Script. Alcuni degli assi possono essere trovati a datata nel lontano 1500 aC.</Italian>
        <Spanish>[TAB] Aunque no es mucho pruebas de la guerra en el valle de Indus la civilización se ha encontrado, muchos especímenes de las armas que se han descubierto en las ruinas de Harapa y Mohenjo-Daro. Restos de ejes hechos de cobre o de bronce se han encontrado y podría haber sido utilizado por los cazadores en la zona. Algunos ejes que se encuentran contienen inscripciones acerca de las deidades o dioses escrito en Indus Script. Algunos de los ejes puede ser encontrado a la fecha en fechas tan remotas como 1500 AC.</Spanish>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_CREE_TRACKER_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]The European's earliest knowledge of the Cree placed them in the woodlands around James Bay in Quebec, where they lived in small family groups. From there the Cree gradually spread westward and eventually the lands they occupied stretched from Quebec across the Great Plains to the mountain ranges near the Pacific Ocean. With the arrival of first the French, and later the British, the Cree became engaged in the fur trade. They traded guns to the Blackfeet for the horses they needed to prosper on the plains.  the nineteenth century the Cree had been drastically reduced by disease, especially smallpox, and recurrent wars with other tribes retreating north to escape white settlers pushing up the Missouri River. With the fur trade dropping off and the buffalo disappearing, Cree leaders began working toward creating a safe homeland. They wanted a large native reserve where they could adapt to the European farming lifestyle, yet live according to their own culture, but the government denied their plan. When other tribes tried to fight, the Cree were swept up in the military action and most were settled on small reserves.  Many Cree in the far north escaped forced settlement and maintained their independent life style well into the twentieth century.</English>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_CROATIA_GUARD_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]The Armed Forces of the Republic of Croatia have grown into a respectable and well-organised armed force during the Homeland War of independence. Many military analysts consider that the defense of the Croatian territory was successful, resulting in final military victory. Military tactics and strategy were carried out directly in practice and that is unique in the world. Croatian Armed Forces carried out many successful military operations such as Oluja (Storm) and Bljesak (Flash) in 1995 and Maslenica in 1994.</English>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_CZECH_HUSSITE_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]The Hussite wars also marked the earliest successful use of pistols on the battlefield. The Czechs called the handgun a pítala, and anti-infantry field guns houfnice, from which the English words "pistol" and "howitzer" have been derived. The Germans had just started corning gunpowder, making it suitable for use in smaller, tactical weapons. A gunman on an open field armed with only a single-shot weapon was no match for a charging knight on a horseback; however, from behind a castle wall, or from within the enclosure of the wagenburg, massed and disciplined gunmen could use the handgun to its greatest potential. From his experiences at the Battle of Grunwald, ika knew exactly how his enemies would attack, and he found new ways to defeat forces numerically superior to his own.</English>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_DENMARK_GUARD_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]Although the Guard Hussars (Gardehusarregimentet) themselves date from 1762, the Danish Army takes the date of the founding of a regiment from its oldest part, in this case the Zealand Life Regiment, which was founded in 1614. This makes the Guard Hussars the oldest regiment of hussars in the world still operational. In addition to its operational role, the Guard Hussar Regiment is one of two regiments in the Danish Army (along with the Den Kongelige Livgarde) to be classed as 'Guards'; in this case, the Guard Hussars perform the same role as the Household Cavalry do in the British Army. The ceremonial uniform of the Guard Hussar Regiment dates from 1860.[PARAGRAPH:1]The motto of the regiment is not in Danish but in Latin: In actis esto volucris, which translates to Be swift in action.</English>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_DINNEHIH_CODETALKER_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]The Navajo Code Talkers, whose ranks exceed 400 during the course of World War II in the Pacific Theater.  Have been credited with saving countless lives and hastening the end of the war. The Code Talker's served in all six Marine divisions from 1942 to 1945. The Code Talker's primary job was to talk and transmit information on tactics, troop movements, orders and other vital battlefield information via telegraphs and radios in their native dialect.  A major advantage of the code talker system was its speed. The method of using Morse code often took hours where as, the Navajos handled a message in minutes.   It has been said that if was not for the Navajo Code Talker's, the Marines would have never taken Iwo Jima. The Navajo's unwritten language was understood by fewer than 30 non-Navajo's at the time of WWII.  The size and complexity of the language made the code extremely difficult to comprehend, much less decipher.  It was not until 1968 that the code became declassified by the US Government.</English>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_ETRURIA_ETRUSCANCHARIOT_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]The only Etruscan chariot found intact dates to ca. 530 BC and is now kept at the Metropolitan Museum in New York City.[PARAGRAPH:1]The chariot was part of a chariot burial, containing the remains of two human corpses, along with two drinking cups. It is decorated with bronze plates, depicting mythological scenes in relief, and ivory, measuring 131 cm in height. The chariot's wheels have nine spokes (rather than the classical Greek four, the Egyptian six, or the Assyrian and Persian eight; excavated chariots from Celtic burials have up to twelve spokes).[PARAGRAPH:1]It was found in 1902 in Monteleone di Spoleto near Spoleto in the province of Perugia of Umbria, by a farmer,called Isidoro Vannozzi, when he was digging a wine cellar. Vannozzi hid it in his barn, concerned that the authorities might confiscate it, and later sold it to two Frenchmen in exchange for, according to family lore, two cows (or according to the local mayor, for 30 terracotta tiles). It was sold to the Metropolitan museum from Florence in 1903, and was illegally exported from Italy. The comune of Monteleone as of January, 2005 is attempting to recuperate the chariot from the Metropolitan museum, but museum representatives have "respectfully declined" to return it.[PARAGRAPH:1]There are also persistent rumors in Monteleone, if unverified, that other related finds were made at the same time, that were sold separately on the black market. A full-size copy was made in the mid-20th century, which is on display in Monteleone.</English>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_FALXMAN_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]The Drapanai contingents are made up of resolute warriors, well aware of their role on the battlefield as shock troops. While the average Getic soldier tells himself he is immortal, the Drapanai, more than any others, join battle without fear of death. They fight bare-chested and with only baggy trousers, not for protection but to keep some warmth. Their trademark though is the falx, a vicious blade capable of severing limbs and causing horrible wounds with a single, crushing blow. These warriors are best used as shock troops against enemy infantry. If used properly, they can cut their way through and open a gap in the enemy battle line, allowing other Getic warriors to exploit the opening. Their lack of armor might be a drawback against concentrated enemy missile fire and they should thus not be exposed to enemy ranged infantry needlessly.[NEWLINE][TAB]Historically, a Drapanai soldier is the archetype of the Getic warrior, bare-chested and armed with the falx. The falx weapon was developed from the Thracian rhomphaia and it became a traditional weapon among the Getai. The ones wielding it and who often made up the Drapanai were young vigorous warriors, striving to achieve recognition among their kin and fellow men. The religious aspects should not be overlooked either, as these men formed the frontline and served as shock troops which meant they were more exposed to the enemy, where the Getic religious zeal was of immense importance as these warriors did not fear death, because death was the gateway to their prophet-god Zalmoxis. Their valor is best shown during the Second Dacian War, when the Roman soldiers were issued new types of armor, greaves, modified helmets and especially stronger armguards to protect themselves against the falx, and Roman troops stationed in Dacia, as the Romans called Getia, in the later first century AD were still issued these armguards and armor pieces so not to lose their limbs!</English>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_FIANNA_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB] In early Ireland, fianna were small, semi-independent warrior bands who lived in the forests as mercenaries, bandits, and hunters.  They lived seperate from the rest of society and could be called by kings in times of war.  They appear in Irish mythology, most notably in the stories of the Fenian Cycle.  In these stories, the fianna are lead by Fionn mac Cumhail.  The name Fianna Éireann has been used in a number of Irish Republican scouting organizations.  The historical institution of the fian is known from references in early medieval Irish law tracts.  A fian was made up of landless young men, often aristocrats, who hadn't yet come into inheritance of their land.  In the winter, fianna were quartered and fed by the nobility, during which they would keep order on their behalf.  During the summer, they had to live by hunting or selling pelts. [PARAGRAPH: 1]In the stories of the Fenian Cycle, the fianna are depicted as a single standing army in the service of the high sing.  It contained two rival factions, the Clan Baíscne of Leinster and the Clan Morna of Conacht.  Membership to the fianna was subject to rigorous texts.  For example, the applicant would stand waste deep in a hole armed with a shield while nine warriors threw spears at him.  If wounded, the applicant would fail.  In another text, his hair would be braided and he would be pursued through the forest and would fail if caught.  He would also fail if a branch cracked under his feet, or if the braids in his hair were disturbed.  He would have to be able to leap over a branch the height of his forehead, pass under one as low as his knee, and pull a thorn from his foot without slowing down. He also needed to be a skilled poet.</English>
        <French>[TAB] Au début de l'Irlande, fianna étaient petites, semi indépendant guerrier bandes qui vivent dans les forêts comme des mercenaires, des bandits, et de faim. Ils vivaient séparés du reste de la société et pourraient être appelés par les rois en temps de guerre. Elles apparaissent dans la mythologie irlandaise, et plus particulièrement dans les récits du Cycle Fenian. Dans ces histoires, la fianna sont dirigés par Finn Mac Cumaill. Fianna Éireann le nom a été utilisé dans un certain nombre d'organisations de scoutisme républicaine irlandaise. L'institution historique de la fian est connu au début de références médiévales droit irlandais des tracts. Un fian était composée de jeunes hommes sans terre, souvent aristocrates, qui n'avaient pas encore entré en héritage de leurs terres. En hiver, fianna étaient cantonnés et nourris par e enobility, au cours de laquelle ils maintien de l'ordre en leur nom. Pendant l'été, ils ont dû vivre de la chasse ou de la vente de peaux. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Dans les récits de la Fenian Cycle, le fianna sont dépeints comme une seule armée permanente au service de la haute chanter. Il contenait deux factions rivales, le Clan Baíscne de Leinster et le Clan Morna de Conacht. L'adhésion à la fianna était soumis à la rigueur des textes. Par exemple, la requérante se tiendrait déchets profondeur, dans un trou armé d'un bouclier tandis que neuf guerriers jeté lances à lui. Si blessés, le demandeur serait vouée à l'échec. Dans un autre texte, ses cheveux seraient tressés et il sera poursuivi à travers la forêt et serait vouée à l'échec si capturés. Il souhaiterait également échouer si une branche craqué sous ses pieds, ou si les tresses dans ses cheveux ont été perturbés. Il devrait être en mesure de sauter sur une branche de la hauteur de son front, passe sous un aussi faible que son genou, et tirer une épine de son pied sans ralentir. Il a également besoin d'être un habile poète.</French>
        <German>[TAB] In den frühen Irland, fianna noch klein waren, teilweise unabhängigen Krieger Bands lebte in den Wäldern als Söldner, Banditen und Hunger. Sie lebten getrennt von der übrigen Gesellschaft und könnte durch Könige in Zeiten des Krieges. Sie erscheinen in der irischen Mythologie, vor allem in den Geschichten der Fenian Cycle. In diesen Geschichten, die fianna werden von Fionn Mac Cumhail. Der Name Fianna Éireann wurde in einer Reihe von Irish Republican Pfadfinderbewegung Organisationen. Die historische Einrichtung der fian ist bekannt aus Referenzen in der frühen mittelalterlichen irischen Rechts Schriften. Ein fian wurde von landlosen junge Männer, die oft Aristokraten, die noch nicht in Berührung kommen, Vererbung von ihrem Land. Im Winter, fianna wurden Vierteilung und gefüttert von Th enobility, in denen sie sich zu halten, um auf ihren Namen. Während des Sommers, hatten sie von der Jagd zu leben oder zu verkaufen Pelze. [PARAGRAPH: 1] In den Geschichten der Fenian Cycle, die fianna dargestellt als eine einzige stehende Heer in den Dienst der hohen singen. Es enthielt zwei rivalisierenden Gruppen, die Clan Baíscne Leinster und der Clan Morna von Conacht. Mitgliedschaft in der fianna war Gegenstand einer rigorosen Texte. Zum Beispiel, die Klägerin würde Abfälle tief in ein Loch bewaffnet mit einem Schild, während neun Krieger warf Speere auf ihn. Wenn Verwundete, die Klägerin würde scheitern. In einem anderen Text, sein Haar wäre geflochten und er würde verfolgt werden durch den Wald und würde scheitern, wenn gefangen. Er würde auch nicht, wenn ein Zweig geknackt unter seinen Füßen, oder wenn die Zöpfe in seinem Haar wurden gestört. Er würde in der Lage sein müssen Sprung über eine Zweigstelle der Höhe seiner Stirn, Pass unter einem so niedrig wie seine Knie, und ziehen Sie ein Dorn aus seinem Fuß und ohne Abbremsen. Er wird auch benötigt, um eine qualifizierte Dichter.</German>
        <Italian>[TAB] All'inizio di Irlanda, fianna erano piccole, semi indipendente guerriero bande che vivevano nelle foreste come mercenari, briganti, e di fame. Essi vivevano separati dal resto della società e potrebbe essere chiamato dal re in tempi di guerra. Esse appaiono nella mitologia irlandese, in particolare nelle storie dei Fenian Cycle. In queste storie, il fianna sono guidati da Fionn Mac Cumhail. Fianna Éireann il nome è stato usato in un certo numero di organizzazioni di scout repubblicano irlandese. La storica istituzione del fian è conosciuto da riferimenti agli inizi di diritto irlandese tratti medievali. Un fian era composta da giovani uomini senza terra, spesso nobili, che non era ancora entrato in eredità della loro terra. In inverno, fianna erano squartato e alimentato da ° enobility, durante il quale essi avrebbero mantenere l'ordine a loro nome. Durante l'estate, che il vivere di caccia o di vendita di pellicce. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Nelle storie dei Fenian Cycle, il fianna sono descritti come un unico esercito permanente nel servizio di alta cantare. Essa conteneva due fazioni rivali, il Clan Baíscne di Leinster e Clan Morna di Conacht. Adesione alla fianna è stato oggetto di rigorosa testi. Per esempio, la ricorrente avrebbe rifiuti profondo in un foro armato di uno scudo, mentre nove guerrieri gettato lance a lui. Se feriti, il ricorrente sarebbe ininfluente. In un altro testo, il suo sarebbe treccia di capelli e sarebbe perseguito attraverso la foresta e che se non catturati. Egli avrebbe anche se non una succursale incrinate sotto i suoi piedi, o se il trecce nei suoi capelli sono stati disturbati. Egli avrebbe dovuto essere in grado di saltare più di un ramo l'altezza del suo fronte, passare sotto uno basse come il suo ginocchio, e tirare una spina dal suo piede senza rallentamento. Egli ha anche bisogno di essere un bravo poeta.</Italian>
        <Spanish>[TAB] A principios de Irlanda, fianna eran pequeños, semiáridas bandas independientes guerrero que vivió en los bosques como mercenarios, bandidos, y tiene hambre. Vivían separadas del resto de la sociedad y puede ser llamado por los reyes en tiempos de guerra. Ellos aparecen en la mitología irlandesa, especialmente en las historias de la Fenian Cycle. En estas historias, la fianna se conducen por Fionn Mac Cumhail. El nombre Fianna Éireann ha sido utilizado en una serie de organizaciones de escultismo Republicano Irlandés. La histórica institución de la fian es conocido a partir de las referencias medievales a principios de la legislación irlandesa extensiones. A fian está formada por campesinos sin tierra de los hombres jóvenes, a menudo aristócratas, que todavía no ha entrado en la herencia de sus tierras. En el invierno, fianna fueron acuartelados y alimentado por ª enobility, durante la cual se debería mantener el orden en su nombre. Durante el verano, habían tenido que vivir de la caza o la venta de pieles. [PARAGRAPH: 1] En las historias de la Fenian Cycle, la fianna son presentados como un solo ejército permanente al servicio de la alta cantar. Contiene dos facciones rivales, el Clan Baíscne de Leinster y el Clan Morna de Conacht. Membresía a la fianna se sancionará con la pena de textos. Por ejemplo, el solicitante de pie de residuos en un profundo agujero armado con un escudo mientras que nueve guerreros arrojaron lanzas en él. Si heridos, la demandante no funcionaría. En otro texto, el pelo trenzado y sería él se llevaría a cabo a través del bosque y si no se captura. Asimismo, si no una sucursal agrietada debajo de sus pies, o si las trenzas en el pelo se inquieta. Él tendría que ser capaz de saltar sobre una rama la altura de su frente, en virtud de un pase tan bajo como su rodilla, y tire de una espina de su pie sin reducir la velocidad de. También tiene que ser un experto poeta.</Spanish>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_FINNISH_JAEGER_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]Modern infantry is given the challenging task of taking and holding terrain, which often involves dangerous,close range fighting. Organized into small squads, their strength lies in their training and equipment (rifle, grenades, helmet, and other critical gear). Often individuals in the squad are trained to be specialists, allowing them access to anti-tank weapons or light machine guns. Experienced in concealment and patrolling close to the enemy, these hard-fighting men play an important and versatile role in modern military conflict.</English>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_GALLEAS_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]The galleass or "galliass" developed from large merchant galleys. Converted for military use they were higher and larger than regular ("light") galleys. They had up to 32 oars, each worked by up to 5 men. They usually had three masts and a forecastle and aftcastle. Much effort was made in Venice to make these galleasses as fast as possible to compete with regular galleys. The gun-deck usually ran over the rowers' heads, but there are also pictures showing the opposite arrangement.[PARAGRAPH:1]	Galleasses usually carried more sails than true galleys, and were far deadlier; a galley caught broadside lay all but helpless, but coming broadside to a galleass, as with a ship of the line, exposed an attacker to her gunfire. The galleass exemplified an intermediate type between the galley and the true man-of-war. Relatively few galleasses were built ? one disadvantage was that, being more reliant on sails, their position at the front of the galley line at the start of a battle could not be guaranteed ? but they were used at the Battle of Lepanto (7 October 1571), their firepower helping to win victory for the Christian fleet, and some sufficiently seaworthy galleasses accompanied the Spanish Armada in 1588 (e.g. La Girona).[PARAGRAPH:1]	In the Mediterranean, with its shallower waters, less dangerous weather and fickle winds, both galleasses and galleys continued in use, particularly in Venice and Turkey, long after they became obsolete elsewhere. Later, "round ships" and galleasses were replaced by galleons and ships of the line which originated in northern Europe. The first Venetian ship of the line was built in 1660.</English>
        <French>[TAB]Les galéasses se développèrent à partir de larges galères marchandes. Converties ensuite à un usage militaire, elles étaient plus hautes et plus larges que les galères "légères" traditionnelles. Elles avaient jusqu'à 32 rames, chacune maniée par jusqu'à 5 hommes. Elles avaient habituellement 3 mats, un poste d'équipage à l'avant et un château arrière. Venise fit beaucoup d'efforts pour rendre ses galéasses aussi rapides que possible pour qu'elles soient aussi compétitives que les galères régulières. Le pont des canons se trouvait habituellement au dessus de la tête des rameurs, mais il existe des images anciennes montrant l'arrangement inverse. [PARAGRAPH:1]Les galéasses disposaient habituellement de plus de voiles que les véritables galères et étaient bien plus mortelles. Une galère prise de flanc n'avait aucune chance, mais venir à flanc d'une galéasse, de la même manière qu'avec un navire de ligne, c'était s'exposer à ses tirs de canons. La galéasse est un intermédiaire entre la galère et le véritable navire de ligne. Peu de galéasses furent construites. Un de leurs désavantages était que, étant tributaire de leurs voiles, leur position devant la ligne de galère au début des batailles ne pouvait être garantie. Elles furent cependant utilisées à la bataille de Lépante (7 octobre 1571), où leur puissance de feu contribua à la victoire de la flotte chrétienne. Certaines galéasses suffisamment en état pour naviguer en haute mer accompagnèrent l'a Grande Armada espagnole en 1588.[PARAGRAPH:1]En Méditerranée, avec ses eaux moins profondes, un temps moins dangereux et des vents changeants, les galéasses et les galères continuèrent à être utilisées, particulièrement par Venise et l'Empire Ottoman, bien longtemps après qu'elles soient devenues obsolètes ailleurs. Plus tard, les caravelles et les galéasses furent remplacées par les galions et les vaisseaux de ligne originaires d'Europe du nord. Le premier navire de ligne vénitien fut construit en 1660.</French>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_GASINDII_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>Before the invasion of Charlemagne, the Lombards had been building up a force of retainers known as gasindii.  These were some of the best trained troops in Europe, consisting of men in Avar style armor.  They were particularly well trained.  They formed not only the backbone of Carolingian armies in Italy, but of other countries that invaded.  Gasindii could be found in Avar armies as well.  After the Carolingians conquered Lombardy, efforts were made to form private gasindii armies.</English>
        <French>Avant l'invasion de Charlemagne, le Lombards avait accumulé une force des arrêtoirs connus sous le nom de gasindii. C'étaient certaines des meilleures troupes qualifiées en Europe, se composant des hommes dans l'armure de modèle d'Avar. Elles étaient particulièrement bien élevées. Elles ont formé non seulement l'épine dorsale des armées de Carolingian en Italie, mais d'autres pays qui ont envahi. Gasindii a pu être aussi bien trouvé dans des armées d'Avar. Après que le Carolingians ait conquis la Lombardie, des efforts ont été faits de former les armées privées de gasindii.</French>
        <German>Vor der Invasion von Karl der Große, hatte das Lombards eine Kraft der Halter aufgebaut, die als gasindii bekannt sind. Diese waren einige der besten ausgebildeten Truppen in Europa und bestanden aus Männern in der Avar Artrüstung. Sie waren besonders gut ausgebildet. Sie bildeten nicht nur das Rückgrat der Carolingian Armeen in Italien, aber anderer Länder, die eindrangen. Gasindii konnte in den Avar Armeen außerdem gefunden werden. Nachdem das Carolingians Lombardei eroberte, wurden Bemühungen, private gasindii Armeen zu bilden gebildet.</German>
        <Italian>Prima dell'invasione di Charlemagne, il Lombards stava sviluppando una forza dei fermi conosciuti come il gasindii. Questi erano alcune delle truppe addestrate migliori in Europa, consistendo degli uomini in armatura di stile di Avar. Erano particolarmente ben educate. Hanno formato non solo la base degli eserciti di Carolingian in Italia, ma di altri paesi che hanno invaso. Gasindii ha potuto essere trovato negli eserciti di Avar pure. Dopo che il Carolingians conquisti la Lombardia, gli sforzi sono stati fatti formare gli eserciti riservati di gasindii.</Italian>
        <Spanish>Antes de la invasión de Charlemagne, el Lombards había estado acumulando una fuerza de los detenedores conocidos como gasindii. Éstos eran algunas de las mejores tropas entrenadas de Europa, consistiendo en hombres en armadura del estilo de Avar. Eran particularmente bien ensen$ada. Formaron no sólo la espina dorsal de los ejércitos de Carolingian en Italia, pero de otros países que invadieron. Gasindii se podía encontrar en los ejércitos de Avar también. Después de que el Carolingians conquistara Lombardía, los esfuerzos fueron hechos de formar a ejércitos privados del gasindii.</Spanish>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_GEORGIA_HORSEMAN_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]The history of Georgia has been marked by a series of invasions and subjugation by several empires (such as Rome, Persia, Arabian Caliphate, Mongol Empire, the Ottoman Empire and the Russian Empire). Like in many cultures of the region, horsemen have traditionally played a role in the defence of the small nation.</English>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_GOTHIC_CAVALRY_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]The goths fought primarly on foot, but unlike other germanic tribes they also employed a large amount of heavy cavalry. The effectiveness of the Gothic heavy-cavalry was substantially heightened by their (innovative in Europe) use of stirrups. Particularly for heavy cavalry, this allows the use of heavier weapons and more cumbersome, but effective armour. Cavalry now had the ability to make head-on attacks on massed infantry, ie the "shock-troops" function of cavalry. They are also less likely to be dismounted at the first charge. The advantages of those improvements were one of the most important reasons for gothic victory at Adrianople (August 9, 378), the worst roman defeat since Battle of Cannae (216 BC). It showed weakness of roman army and led to sack of Rome by Visigoths in 410, first since Gallic invasion in 390 BC. Eventually it led to the fall of Western Empire and influenced change of Eastern Empire into Byzantium, with a switch from haevy infantry to heavy cavalry as the main part of the army.</English>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_GRENZER_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]In various Austrian Empires, Grenzers were troops who came from the Croatian and Transylvanian Military Frontier.  The troops were originally founded to defend Austria from the Ottomans, however when no danger lurked, the Grenzers were employed by the Habsburgs in other frontiers of war.  Still, at least one battalion of each regiment would remain guarding the border from invasion threats. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Grenzers were successors of the irregular army of Pandurs, which were also raised by the Habsburgs to defend the border and serve as skirmishers in the Seven Years' War.  By the time of the Napoleonic Wars, the troops formed more regular line infantry regiments.  They were given training in marksmanship, linear tactics, and skirmishing.  At the start of the war, 18 Grenzer regiments formed about a quarter of the Austrian Army. [PARAGRAPH: 1] However, because the Grenzers were not as good in the role of line infantry as the regular regiments, the Austrian military command never gave them much credit, and following a mutiny in 1800, their numbers were reduced.  Despite these setbacks, Grenzers preformed exceptionally well at Marengo and Austerlitz, earning them respect from the French.  Napoleon even considered them the only warlike troops in the entire Austrian Army.  Grenzer troops served for Napoleon until his defeat after the Austrians ceded territories in the War of the Fifth Coalition. [PARAGRAPH: 1] During the 19th century, the Ottoman thread diminished and thus there was less need for troops defending the Frontier.  Additionally, with rise of Slav nationalism and self-determination, the Austrian high command grew suspicious of the Grenzers and a possible revolt.  With these factors, the number of Grenzers was steadily reduced, although they remained in service in the Austrian and later Austro-Hungarian army until the World War II.</English>
        <French>[TAB]Dans divers Empires autrichien, Grenzers étaient soldats venus de la Croatie et de Transylvanie militaire aux frontières. Les troupes ont été initialement fondée pour la défense de l'Autriche Ottomans, mais quand aucun danger m'attendait, le Grenzers étaient employés par les Habsbourg dans d'autres frontières de la guerre. Pourtant, au moins sur le bataillon de chaque régiment resterait protégeant la frontière de l'invasion de menaces. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Grenzers étaient successeurs de l'armée irrégulière de Pandurs, qui ont également été soulevés par les Habsbourg pour défendre la frontière et de servir de tirailleurs dans la guerre de Sept Ans. Au moment des guerres napoléoniennes, les troupes formé plus régulier régiments d'infanterie de ligne. Ils ont reçu une formation en aptitudes, linéaire tactiques, et escarmouches. Au début de la guerre, 18 Grenzer régiments forment environ un quart de l'armée autrichienne. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Toutefois, parce que le Grenzers n'étaient pas aussi bien dans le rôle de l'infanterie de ligne que les régiments réguliers, le commandement militaire autrichien ne leur a donné beaucoup de crédit, et la suite d'une mutinerie en 1800, leur nombre a été réduit. Malgré ces revers, Grenzers préformés exceptionnellement bien à la bataille de Marengo et Austerlitz, qui lui a valu le respect de la société française. Napoléon même envisagé eux la seule guerrière des troupes dans l'ensemble de l'armée autrichienne. Grenzer troupes servi de Napoléon jusqu'à sa défaite après les Autrichiens cédée territoires de la guerre de la Cinquième Coalition. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Au cours du 19e siècle, les ottomans fil diminué et il n'y avait donc moins besoin de troupes de la défense des frontières. En outre, avec montée du nationalisme slave et de l'autodétermination, le haut commandement autrichien a crû suspectes de la Grenzers et d'une éventuelle révolte. Compte tenu de ces facteurs, le nombre de Grenzers a été réduite progressivement, mais ils sont restés en service dans la autrichienne et, plus tard, l'armée austro-hongroise jusqu'à la Seconde Guerre mondiale.</French>
        <German>[TAB]In verschiedenen österreichischen Empires, Grenzers waren Soldaten, die aus dem kroatischen und siebenbürgischen Military Frontier. Die Truppen waren ursprünglich gegründet zu verteidigen Österreich von den Osmanen, aber, wenn keine Gefahr drohte, die Grenzers wurden von den Habsburgern in anderen Grenzen des Krieges. Noch, zumindest auf jedes Bataillon Regiment bleiben würde Bewachung der Grenze von Invasion bedroht. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Grenzers wurden Nachfolger der irregulären Armee von Panduren-Oberst, die auch von den Habsburgern zur Verteidigung der Grenze und dienen als skirmishers in der Siebenjährigen Krieges. Nach der Zeit der Napoleonischen Kriege, die Truppen aus mehr regelmäßige Linie Infanterie Regimenter. Sie erhielten Ausbildung in Schießkunst, lineare Taktik, und plänkelnd. Zu Beginn des Krieges, 18 Grenzer Regimenter bildeten etwa ein Viertel der österreichischen Armee. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Da die Grenzers waren nicht so gut, in der Rolle der Linie Infanterie als die regelmäßigen Regimenter, der österreichischen militärischen Befehl nie gab ihnen viel Kredit, und nach einer Meuterei im 1800, ihre Zahl reduziert wurden. Trotz dieser Rückschläge, Grenzers vorgeformte außergewöhnlich gut bei Marengo und Austerlitz, verdienen sie Respekt von den französischen. Napoleon selbst als sie die einzige militärische Truppen in die gesamte österreichische Armee. Grenzer Truppen diente Napoleon bis zu seiner Niederlage, nachdem die Österreicher abgetretenen Gebiete, in dem Krieg des Fünften Koalition. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Im Verlauf des 19. Jahrhunderts, des Osmanischen Faden verringert und damit gab es weniger Aufwand für die Truppen der Verteidigung der Grenzen. Darüber hinaus steigt mit der slawischen Nationalismus und Selbstbestimmung, der österreichischen hohe Befehl wuchs verdächtige des Grenzers und eine mögliche Revolte. Mit diesen Faktoren, die Zahl der Grenzers wurde stetig reduziert, obwohl sie noch im Dienst in der österreichischen und später österreichisch-ungarischen Armee bis zum Zweiten Weltkrieg.</German>
        <Italian>[TAB]In vari imperi austriaco, Grenzers erano truppe che è venuto dalla Transilvania militare croato e di frontiera. Le truppe sono state originariamente fondata per difendere l'Austria dal ottomani, tuttavia quando nessun pericolo lurked, il Grenzers sono stati impiegati dal Asburgo in altre frontiere della guerra. Ancora, almeno sul battaglione di ogni reggimento sarebbero rimasti a guardia della frontiera da minacce di invasione. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Grenzers sono stati successori degli irregolari esercito di Pandurs, che sono state sollevate anche dalla Asburgo per difendere il confine e servire come skirmishers nel Sette Anni 'guerra. Con il tempo della guerre napoleoniche, il formato più truppe regolari linea reggimenti di fanteria. Esse sono state date formazione in marksmanship, lineare tattiche, e skirmishing. All'inizio della guerra, 18 Grenzer reggimenti costituito circa un quarto del esercito austriaco. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Tuttavia, poiché il Grenzers non erano così bene nel ruolo di fanteria di linea regolari reggimenti, il comando militare austriaco non ha dato loro molto credito, e a seguito di una rivolta nel 1800, il loro numero è stato ridotto. Nonostante questi contrattempi, Grenzers preformata eccezionalmente bene a Marengo e di Austerlitz, guadagnandosi loro confronti dal francese. Napoleone, anche in considerazione solo le loro truppe in guerra l'intero esercito austriaco. Grenzer truppe servito per Napoleone fino alla sua sconfitta dopo gli austriaci ceduto territori in guerra della Quinta Coalizione. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Nel corso del 19 ° secolo, il filo ottomano diminuita e, quindi, non vi è meno bisogno di truppe per difendere la frontiera. Inoltre, con il sorgere del nazionalismo slavo e di autodeterminazione, l'alto comando austriaco sospette è cresciuto del Grenzers e di una possibile rivolta. Con questi fattori, il numero di Grenzers era costantemente ridotta, anche se è rimasto in servizio in Austria e, successivamente, l'esercito austro-ungarico fino alla seconda guerra mondiale.</Italian>
        <Spanish>[TAB]En diversos imperios de Austria, Grenzers fueron las tropas que vinieron de los croatas y Transilvania Militar Frontier. Las tropas fueron originalmente a la defensa de Austria de los otomanos, sin embargo, cuando se escondían ningún peligro, la Grenzers fueron empleados por los Habsburgo en otras fronteras de la guerra. Sin embargo, por lo menos en cada batallón del regimiento se mantendrá la vigilancia de la frontera de la invasión amenazas. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Grenzers eran sucesores de los irregulares ejército de Pandurs, que también fueron planteadas por los Habsburgo para defender la frontera y servir de jabalina en el Seven Years' War. En la época de las guerras napoleónicas, las tropas regulares formadas más regimientos de infantería de línea. Se les dio capacitación en tiro, la táctica lineal, y skirmishing. Al comienzo de la guerra, el 18 Grenzer regimientos formado alrededor de la cuarta parte del ejército austriaco. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Sin embargo, debido a que el Grenzers no eran tan buenas en el papel de infantería de línea regular como regimientos, de Austria mando militar nunca les dio mucho crédito, y después de un motín en 1800, su número es reducido. A pesar de estos reveses, Grenzers preformados excepcionalmente bien en Marengo y Austerlitz, ellos ganan el respeto de los franceses. Napoleón incluso consideraba el único militar que las tropas en todo el Ejército austríaco. Grenzer tropas de Napoleón sirvió hasta su derrota después de los austriacos cedió territorios en la Guerra de la Quinta Coalición. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Durante el siglo 19, el otomano hilo disminuido y, por lo tanto hay menos necesidad de que tropas de la defensa de la frontera. Además, con el aumento del nacionalismo eslavo y de la libre determinación, el alto mando de Austria creció sospechosas de la Grenzers y una posible rebelión. Con estos factores, el número de Grenzers fue reducido de manera constante, a pesar de que permaneció en servicio en la de Austria y más tarde Austrohúngaro hasta que el ejército de la Segunda Guerra Mundial.</Spanish>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_GRIVPANVAR_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]The Grivpanvar are nobles from the highest level of cataphracts that the Pahlava have to draw on. The elite of the clan host form this armoured fist that represents one of the most powerful armoured cavalry the world has ever seen. They deploy in the heaviest armour available and use the kontos as their primary shock weapon. Armoured in iron lamellar corselets, covered by a leather tabard, laminated leg and arm guards and with iron shining from the scale horse barding, these are truly men of iron, in bright armour for horse and man. The horse bearing such loads must be both large and strong, and both the Parthians and Achaemenid Persians bred just such horses, the Nisaean breed of Persia.[NEWLINE][TAB]Historical evidence suggests that the Parthian, heavily-armoured Grivpanvar were, at least partially, a product of military influence from the Central Asian steppes which had inherited the armoured cavalry traditions of the Massagetae and the late Achaemenid Persians. Their name derives from the Pahlavi griwban "neck-guard", a helmet armour guard, from whence "Grivpan" warrior. In the 3rd century AD, the Romans would begin to deploy such cavalry calling them clibanarii, the name thought to derive from griwbanwar or griva-pana-bara.</English>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_HAJDUK_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]Hajduk is a term that refers to outlaws, highwaymen, and freedom fighters in the Balkans.  In Balkan folkloric custom, hajduci are heroes who lead soldiers into battle against the Ottoman oppressors.  They are comparable to the English legend of Robin Hood and his merry men, who stole from the rich and gave to the poor.  In reality, the hajduci of the 17th, 18th, and 19th centuries were bandits who preyed on Ottoman representatives and local merchants and travelers.  Traditionally, hajduci follow a moral code that prohibited stealing from the poor and unprovoked murder.</English>
        <French>[TAB]Hajduk est une limite qui se rapporte proscrit, des highwaymen, et des combattants de liberté aux Balkans.  Dans la coutume folklorique balkanique, le hajduci sont des héros qui mènent des soldats dans la bataille contre les oppresseurs de tabouret.  Ils sont comparables à la légende anglaise de Robin Hood et de ses joyeux hommes, qui a volé des riches et a donné aux pauvres.  En réalité, le hajduci des 17èmes, 18èmes, et 19èmes siècles étaient des bandits qui ont attaqué sur des représentants de tabouret et des négociants et des voyageurs locaux.  Traditionnellement, le hajduci suivent un code moral qui a interdit voler des pauvres et unprovoked le meurtre.</French>
        <German>[TAB]Hajduk ist eine Bezeichnung, die ächtet, Highwaymen und Freiheit Kämpfer in den Balkan sich bezieht.  In der Balkan folkloric Gewohnheit sind hajduci Helder, die Soldaten in Schlacht gegen die Ottomanunterdrücker führen.  Sie sind mit der englischen Legende von Robin Hood und von seinen fröhlichen Männern vergleichbar, die von den Rich stahl und den Armen gab.  In der Wirklichkeit waren das hajduci der 17., 18. und 19. Jahrhunderte Banditen, die auf Ottomanrepräsentanten und lokale Kaufleute und Reisende preyed.  Traditionsgemäß folgen hajduci einem moralischen Code, der verbot zu stehlen von den Armen und Mord unprovoked.</German>
        <Italian>[TAB]Hajduk è un termine che si riferisce a proscrive, highwaymen e combattenti di libertà nei Balcani.  Nell'abitudine folkloric Balkan, il hajduci è eroi che conducono i soldati nella battaglia contro i oppressors del Ottoman.  Sono paragonabili alla leggenda inglese di Robin Hood e dei suoi uomini allegri, che ha rubato dai rich ed ha dato ai poveri.  In realtà, il hajduci dei diciassettesimi, diciottesimi e diciannovesimi secoli era banditi che hanno predato ai rappresentanti del Ottoman e commercianti e viaggiatori locali.  Tradizionalmente, il hajduci segue un codice morale che ha proibito rubare dai poveri e unprovoked l'omicidio.</Italian>
        <Spanish>[TAB]Hajduk es un término que se refiere proscribe, los highwaymen, y los combatientes de la libertad en los Balcanes.  En costumbre folkloric balcánico, el hajduci es los héroes que conducen a soldados en batalla contra los opresores del otomano.  Son comparables a la leyenda inglesa de Robin Hood y de sus felices hombres, que robó de los ricos y dio a los pobres.  En realidad, el hajduci de los 17mos, décimo octavos, y diecinueveavo siglos era los bandidos que cazaron en representantes del otomano y los comerciantes y los viajeros locales.  Tradicionalmente, el hajduci sigue un código moral que prohibió el robar de los pobres y unprovoked asesinato.</Spanish>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_HEAVY_HUSSAR_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]The first hussar units in the Kingdom of Poland were formed by the Sejm, the Polish Parliament, in 1503 which hired three banners of Hungarian mercenaries.  Soon, recruitment also began among Polish and Lithuanian citizens.  The Hussars proved vital to Poland because they were more maneuverable than the previously used lancers.  But the reign of King Stefan Batory, the hussars formed the bulk of the Polish and Lithuanian cavalry.  Over many years, hussars in Hungary became heavier.  When Stefan Batory was elected king of Poland, he reorganized the Polish-Lithuanian hussars of his Royal Guard making them a heavy formation, and equipping lancers as their main weapon. These Polish 'heavy' hussars were known in their homeland as "husaria" [PARAGRAPH: 1] With the Battle of Lubiszew in 1577, the "Golden Age" of the hussar began.  Until the Battle of Vienna, Polish-Lithuanian hussars rarely lost in battle.  Throughout many battles the Polish-Lithuanian hussars would prove to be an important factor against overwhelming odds. [PARAGRAPH: 1] The primary battle tactic of the Polish-Lithuanian hussars was the charge.  They also tended to repeat the charge until the enemy formation broke.  The hussars fought with a long lance, a szabla, one or two pistols, and a carbine or arquebus, known in Polish as a "bandolet".  Polish hussars were also famous for the wings they wore on their backs.  According to some theories, they were designed to foil attacks by Tatar lassos, another theory being that the vibrating of feathers made a strange sound that frightened enemy horses.  However, experiments carried out by re-enactors and movie-makers since the 1970s and more recently by Polish historians in 2001 contradict such ideas. Possibly the wings were worn only during parades and not during combat, but this explanation is also disputed.</English>
        <French>[TAB]La première hussarde unités dans le Royaume de Pologne ont été formés par le Sejm, le Parlement polonais, en 1503, qui a engagé trois bannières de mercenaires hongrois. Bientôt, le recrutement a commencé entre les citoyens polonais et lituaniens. Les Hussards avérée vitale pour la Pologne, parce qu'ils étaient plus manoeuvrable que les lanciers précédemment utilisés. But le règne du roi Stefan Batory, les hussards formaient le gros de la cavalerie polonaise et lituanienne. Depuis de nombreuses années, hussards en Hongrie est devenue plus lourde. Lorsque Stefan Batory est élu roi de Pologne, il a réorganisé le polonais-lituanien hussards de sa garde royale rendant une lourde formation et l'équipement des lanciers comme leur principale arme. Ces polonais "lourds" hussards étaient connus dans leur pays comme "husaria" [PARAGRAPH: 1] Avec la bataille de Lubiszew en 1577, l'âge d'or "de la hussarde a commencé. Jusqu'à la bataille de Vienne, polonais-lituanien hussards rarement perdu dans la bataille. Tout au long de nombreuses batailles l'polonais-lituanien hussards se révéler être un important facteur écrasante contre chances. [PARAGRAPH: 1] La principale bataille tactique de la polonais-lituanien hussards a la charge. Ils ont également tendance à répéter les frais jusqu'à la formation ennemie a éclaté. Les hussards combattu avec une longue Lance, un szabla, un ou deux pistolets, et un mousqueton ou arquebuse, connue en polonais comme un "bandolet". Hussards polonais étaient reconnus pour les ailes, ils portaient sur leur dos. Selon certaines théories, mais ils ont été conçus pour déjouer les attaques menées par des lassos tatare, une autre théorie est que la vibration de plumes fait une étrange que le son ennemi effrayé les chevaux. Toutefois, les expériences menées par la réorientation enactors et film décideurs depuis les années 1970 et, plus récemment, par les historiens polonais en 2001 contredisent de telles idées. Eventuellement les ailes ont été portées seulement pendant les parades et non pas pendant le combat, mais cette explication est également contesté.</French>
        <German>[TAB]Die ersten Husaren in das Königreich Polen wurden durch den Sejm, das polnische Parlament, in der 1503 die drei gemietet Banner der ungarischen Söldnern. Bald begann auch die Einstellung der polnischen und litauischen Bürger. Die Husaren als entscheidend für Polen, weil sie mehr wendiger als die bisher verwendeten Speerträger. But der Regierungszeit von König Stefan Batory, die Husaren bilden den größten Teil der polnischen und litauischen Kavallerie. Über viele Jahre, Husaren in Ungarn wurde schwerer. Wenn Stefan Batory gewählt wurde König von Polen, er hat die Polnisch Husaren seiner Royal Guard und machen sie zu einer schweren Ausbildung, Ausrüstung und Speerträger als ihre wichtigste Waffe. Diese polnischen "schwere" Husaren bekannt waren, in ihrer eigenen Heimat als "husaria" [PARAGRAPH: 1] Mit der Schlacht von Lubiszew im 1577, das "Goldene Zeitalter" der Husaren begann. Bis in die Schlacht von Wien, Polnisch Husaren selten verloren in der Schlacht. In vielen Schlachten der polnischen Husaren - Litauisch würde sich als ein wichtiger Faktor gegen die überwältigende Quoten. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Der primäre Kampf Taktik der polnisch-litauischen Husaren war. Darüber hinaus neigten die Gebühr zu wiederholen, bis der Feind Bildung pleite. Die Husaren kämpften mit einer langen Lanze, ein szabla, ein oder zwei Pistolen, und einem Karabiner oder arquebus, die in der polnischen als "bandolet." Polnischen Husaren waren auch berühmt für die Flügel trugen sie auf dem Rücken. Nach einigen Theorien, sie wurden so gestaltet, dass Folie Angriffe von Tataren Lassos, eine andere Theorie ist, dass die Vibrationen von Federn, die ein seltsames Geräusch, Angst Feind Pferde. Allerdings, Experimente durchgeführt erneut enactors und Film Entscheidungsträger seit den 1970er Jahren und in jüngster Zeit von den polnischen Historiker in der 2001 im Widerspruch zu solchen Ideen. Möglicherweise die Flügel getragen wurden nur während der Paraden und nicht während des Kampfes, aber diese Erklärung ist auch umstritten.</German>
        <Italian>[TAB]La prima unità ussaro nel Regno di Polonia si sono formati dal Sejm, il parlamento polacco, nel 1503, che noleggiati tre bandiere ungheresi di mercenari. Presto, ha iniziato il reclutamento anche tra i cittadini polacchi e lituani. Il Ussari rivelato fondamentale per la Polonia perché erano più manovrabile da quella usata in precedenza lance. Ma il regno di Stefan Batory, la ussari formata la maggior parte della cavalleria polacco e lituano. Nel corso di molti anni, ussari in Ungheria è diventata più pesante. Stefan Batory, quando è stato eletto re di Polonia, ha riorganizzato il Polacco-Lituana ussari del suo Royal Guard rendendoli un pesante formazione, e di dotare le lance come loro principale arma. Questi polacco 'pesanti' ussari erano conosciuti in patria come "husaria" [N: 1] Con la Battaglia di Lubiszew nel 1577, il "Golden Age" del ussaro iniziato. Fino alla battaglia di Vienna, polacco - lituano ussari raramente perso in battaglia. In molti battaglie polacco - lituano ussari sarebbe rivelato un fattore importante contro la stragrande quota. [PARAGRAPH: 1] La principale battaglia tattica del Polacco-Lituana ussari era l'accusa. Essi hanno anche la tendenza a ripetere la carica fino a quando il nemico formazione rotto. Il ussari combattuto con una lunga lancia, un szabla, uno o due pistole, e di una carabina o arquebus, in polacco noto come "bandolet". Ussari polacchi sono stati anche famosa per le ali che indossavano sulle loro spalle. Secondo alcune teorie, che sono stati progettati per sventare attacchi da Tataro lassos, un'altra teoria è che la vibrazione di piume fatto uno strano suono che spaventati nemico cavalli. Tuttavia, gli esperimenti effettuati da ristabilire enactors movie e responsabili dal 1970 e, più recentemente, dal polacco storici nel 2001 in contrasto con tali idee. Eventualmente, le ali sono stati indossati solo durante parate, e non durante il combattimento, ma questa spiegazione è anche contestato.</Italian>
        <Spanish>[TAB]La primera hussar unidades en el Reino de Polonia se formaron por el Sejm, el Parlamento polaco, en 1503, que contrató a tres pancartas húngaro de los mercenarios. En breve, también se inició la contratación entre los ciudadanos polacos y lituanos. El Hussars resultó vital para Polonia, ya que fueron más maniobrable que los utilizados anteriormente lancers. But el reinado del rey Stefan Batory, la hussars forman el grueso de la caballería polaco y lituano. Durante muchos años, hussars en Hungría se convirtió en más pesadas. Cuando Stefan Batory fue elegido rey de Polonia, se reorganizó el polaco - lituano hussars de su Guardia Real convierten en una pesada formación, y el equipamiento lancers como su principal arma. Estos polaco 'pesadas' hussars eran conocidos en su tierra natal como "husaria" [PARAGRAPH: 1] Con la Batalla de Lubiszew en 1577, la "Edad de Oro" de la hussar comenzó. Hasta la Batalla de Viena, polaco, lituano hussars rara vez perdió en la batalla. Muchas batallas en todo el polaco - lituano hussars resultaría ser un factor importante en contra de enormes dificultades. [PARAGRAPH: 1] La principal batalla de la táctica polaca y lituana hussars era el cargo. También tienden a repetir el cargo hasta que el enemigo rompió la formación. El hussars luchó con una larga lanza, un szabla, una o dos pistolas, y una carabina o arquebus, conocido en Polonia como una "bandolet". Polish hussars también famoso por las alas que llevaban en sus espaldas. Según algunas teorías, que estaban diseñadas para frustrar los ataques de tártaro lassos, otra teoría es que la vibración de plumas hizo un extraño sonido que asustados caballos enemigo. Sin embargo, los experimentos llevados a cabo por volver a enactors y de la película de la formulación desde el decenio de 1970 y más recientemente por historiadores de Polonia en 2001 contradice esas ideas. Posiblemente las alas se usaron sólo durante los desfiles y no durante el combate, pero esta explicación es también controvertida.</Spanish>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_HIGHLANDER_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]Highlanders were the troops that consisted of the common men of the Scottish Highlands. The were usually formed from local clans and acted to preserve order within their communities. Highlanders were particular prominent once the King James VI of Scotland inherited the throne of the Kingdom of England, and became also "James I" of England. After the Glorious Revolution and the overthrow of the Roman Catholic James VII by William and Mary, Scotland briefly threatened to select a different Protestant monarch from England. In 1707, however, the Parliament of Scotland and the Parliament of England enacted the twin Acts of Union, which created the Kingdom of Great Britain.</English>
        <French>[TAB]Highlanders were the troops that consisted of the common men of the Scottish Highlands</French>
        <German>[TAB]Highlanders were the troops that consisted of the common men of the Scottish Highlands</German>
        <Italian>[TAB]Highlanders were the troops that consisted of the common men of the Scottish Highlands</Italian>
        <Spanish>[TAB]Highlanders were the troops that consisted of the common men of the Scottish Highlands</Spanish>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_HUNS_TARKAN_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]These light hussars were ideal for reconnaissance and raiding sources of fodder and provisions in advance of the army. In battle, they were used in such light cavalry roles as harassing enemy skirmishers, overrunning cannon positions, and pursuing fleeing troops. Tarkans also had a reputation for being the dashing, if unruly, adventurers of the army. The traditional image of the tarkan is of a reckless, hard-drinking, hard-swearing, womanising, moustachioed swashbuckler. Less romantically, tarkans were also known (and feared) for their poor treatment of local civilians. In addition to commandeering local food-stocks for the army, hussars were known to also use the opportunity for personal looting and pillaging.</English>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_HUSZAR_CAVALRY_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]The original hussars were from Hungary, known to the Hungarians as huszars.  Originally, the huszars fought in small bands, but were reorganized, well-trained, and motivated formation during the reign of Matthias Corvinus.  The huszars under Matthias fought the Turks and proved successful.  They also showed signs of success against the Bohemians and Poles.  After the king's death, many huszars fled to other European countries, usually as mercenaries for war.  Frederick the Great, for instance, used hussar units widely throughout the War of the Austrian Succession.  Great Britain also hired hussar units to fight in the American War of Independence.</English>
        <French>[TAB]Les originaux ont été hussards de la Hongrie, connue pour les Hongrois comme huszars. Al'origine, le huszars combattu en petits groupes, mais ont été réorganisées, bien formés, motivés et de la formation pendant le règne de Matthias Ier. Le huszars sous Matthias combattu les Turcs et donné de bons résultats. Ils ont également montré des signes de succès contre les Bohemians et les Polonais. Après la mort du roi, de nombreux huszars ont fui vers d'autres pays européens, généralement en tant que mercenaires pour la guerre. Frédéric le Grand, par exemple, les unités hussarde largement utilisé pendant toute la guerre de la Succession d'Autriche. La Grande-Bretagne a également engagé des unités de lutte contre la hussarde dans la guerre d'indépendance américaine.</French>
        <German>[TAB]Die ursprüngliche Husaren waren aus Ungarn, bekannt, dass die Ungarn als huszars. Ursprünglich, die huszars kämpften in kleinen Gruppen, sondern wurden reorganisiert, gut ausgebildete, motivierte und Bildung während der Herrschaft von Matthias Corvinus. Die huszars unter Matthias kämpften die Türken und erwies sich als erfolgreich. Darüber hinaus zeigte sich der Erfolg gegen die Böhmen und Polen. Nach dem Tod des Königs, viele huszars flohen in andere europäische Länder, die in der Regel als Söldner für den Krieg. Friedrichs des Großen, zum Beispiel, die Husaren Einheiten weitgehend in der gesamten Krieg der österreichischen Erbfolgekrieg. Großbritannien auch gemietet Husaren Einheiten zur Bekämpfung der im amerikanischen Unabhängigkeitskrieg.</German>
        <Italian>[TAB]L'originale ussari erano da Ungheria, noto per gli ungheresi come huszars. Originariamente, il huszars combattuto in piccoli gruppi, ma sono stati riorganizzati, e ben preparati, motivati e formazione durante il regno di Mattia Corvinus. Il huszars sotto Matthias combattuto i turchi e di un successo. Essi hanno anche mostrato segni di successo contro il Bohemians e polacchi. Dopo la morte del re, molti huszars fuggiti in altri paesi europei, di solito come mercenari per la guerra. Federico il Grande, per esempio, ussaro unità ampiamente utilizzato in tutta la guerra di successione austriaca. Gran Bretagna anche assunto ussaro unità per la lotta alla guerra di indipendenza americana.</Italian>
        <Spanish>[TAB]El original hussars eran de Hungría, conocida por los húngaros como huszars. Originalmente, la huszars lucharon en pequeñas bandas, pero se reorganizaron, bien capacitados, motivados y formación durante el reinado de Matthias Corvinus. El huszars bajo Matthias combatieron a los turcos y probada con éxito. También mostró signos de éxito contra los Bohemios y polacos. Después de la muerte del rey, muchos huszars huido a otros países europeos, por lo general como mercenarios para la guerra. Federico el Grande, por ejemplo, utiliza hussar unidades ampliamente en toda la Guerra de la Sucesión de Austria. Gran Bretaña también contrató hussar unidades para combatir en la Guerra de la Independencia Americana.</Spanish>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_INDONESIA_KOPASSUS_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]Kopassus has played a pivotal role in Indonesia's modern history since its inception in 1952. Kopassus' main role in shaping history came in 1965 when it became the backbone of the Army, then politically fractured between pro and anticommunist camps, to crush the abortive coup blamed on the Indonesian Communist Party (PKI). The force's contributions were not limited to the military operations they were involved in. Probably much more significant was its success in producing some of the finest and most disciplined Army men, who went on to become statesmen long after they retired from Kopassus and the military. A quick glance at the list of Kopassus men who appear in the book reads like a who's who of the Indonesian Military.</English>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_IRAN_REVOLUTIONARY_GUARD_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]The Army of the Guardians of the Islamic Revolution, is a branch of Iran's military, founded after the Iranian revolution.  Sepah has 125,000 military personnel including ground, air and naval forces. It also controls the paramilitary Basij militia which has 90,000 active personnel, and in recent years has developed into a "multibillion-dollar business empire." The Chief Commander of the Guardians is Mohammad Ali Jafari, who was preceded by Yahya Rahim Safavi.Like many young Iranians during the 1980-88 IranIraq War, Iran's president Mahmoud Ahmadinejad was a member of the Army of Guardians, in the Basij militia. In recent years the Iranian Revolutionary Guard Corps has become a vast military-based conglomerate. It is active in oil and gas, telecom, and farming, to name a few sections, and has considerable economic and political influence. The Guard's expanding economic role is mirrored by an even greater role in politics and security since the presidential election in June 2009.Since its origin as an ideologically driven militia, the Army of the Guardians of the Islamic Revolution has taken an ever more assertive role in virtually every aspect of Iranian society. Its expanded social, political, military, and economic role under president Ahmadinejad's administration  especially during the 2009 presidential election and post-election suppression of protest  has led many analysts to argue that its political power has surpassed even that of the Shiite clerical system.</English>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_IRAQ_REPUBLICAN_GUARD_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]The Republican Guard was charged with protecting the president, Saddam Hussein, and responding to any threat to his power, such as a rebellion or coup, and protecting Baghdad. In 2002 there were reportedly 12,000 members of the Special Republican Guard, drawn primarily from clans loyal to Saddam Hussein and his regime.</English>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_ITALY_ALPINO_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]During the Italian Risorgimento, the volunteers who followed Giuseppe Garibaldi in southern Italy were called Redshirts (Camicie rosse) because of the colour of their shirts (complete uniforms were beyond the finances of the Italian patriots). They were also called i Mille ("the thousand"), because that was the number that first set off with Garibaldi from Genoa.</English>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_KANEMBORNU_IRONHELM_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]Alooma's innovations for the Kanem-Bornu army included the employment of fixed military camps (with walls); permanent sieges and "scorched earth" tactics, where soldiers burned everything in their path; armored horses and riders; and the use of Berber camelry, Kotoko boatmen, and iron-helmeted musketeers trained by Turkish military advisers.</English>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_KAZAKH_BATYR_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]Baghatur is an old Altaic term for a warrior, a military commander, or an epic hero. The word was introduced in the Middle Ages to many non-Altaic languages by conquering Turkic- and Mongol-speaking nomads, and now exists in different forms such as the Russian Bogatyr', Polish Bohater (meaning hero), Persian and North Indian Bahadur, and Georgian Bagatur. It is also preserved in the modern Turkic and Mongol languages as Turkish Batur, Tatar and Kazakh Batyr, Uzbek Batyr and Mongolian Baatar (as in Ulaanbaatar).</English>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_KHAMPA_HORSEMAN_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]Most people think of Tibetans as a kind, peaceful, and religious culture.  For the Kham region of Tibet, this statement is untrue.  Kham Tibetans have long been known as a violent group of bandits terrorizing the Tibetan Plateau on horseback.  They were employed by Tibetan Kings in fields of war to fight for them.  In Heinrich Harrer's book "Seven Years in Tibet", the Kham Tibetans are described as forcing their way into nomad tents stealing anything of value.  He also reported that they would sometimes kill pilgrims, monks and nuns.  Even today, it is rare to find a Kham man without a large knife on his side.  It was these same people that gave the Chinese communist government the most resistance.  Long after the Tibetans of Lhasa gave up, the Tibetans of Kham continued to fight.  The Chinese who live in the Kham region are often fearful of Kham Tibetans.</English>
        <French>[TAB] La plupart des gens pensent que des Tibétains en tant que genre, pacifique, et de culture religieuse. Pour la région du Kham, Tibet, cette affirmation est fausse. Kham Tibétains ont longtemps été connu comme un violent groupe de bandits qui terrorisent la plateau tibétain à cheval. Ils étaient employés par des rois tibétains dans les domaines de la guerre de se battre pour eux. Heinrich Harrer dans son livre "Sept ans au Tibet", le Kham, les Tibétains sont décrits comme forçant leur chemin vers tentes nomades volé tout équipement de valeur. Il a également indiqué qu'ils seraient capables de tuer des pèlerins, des moines et des nonnes. Même aujourd'hui, il est rare de trouver un homme sans Kham un grand couteau sur son côté. Ce sont ces mêmes personnes qui ont donné le gouvernement communiste chinois le plus de résistance. Longtemps après que les Tibétains de Lhassa a renoncé, les Tibétains du Kham a continué à la combattre. Les Chinois qui habitent dans la région de Kham sont souvent peur de Kham Tibétains.</French>
        <German>[TAB] Die meisten Leute denken, der Tibeter als eine Art, friedlichen und religiösen Kultur. Für die Kham Region Tibet, diese Aussage ist falsch. Kham Tibeter sind seit langem bekannt als einer gewalttätigen Gruppe von Banditen terrorisieren der tibetischen Hochebene auf dem Pferderücken. Sie wurden von der tibetischen Könige Beschäftigten in den Bereichen der Krieg für sie zu kämpfen. In Heinrich Harrer's Buch "Sieben Jahre in Tibet", die Kham Tibeter sind gezwungen ihren Weg als Nomaden in Zelten zu stehlen Dinge von Wert. Er berichtete auch, dass sie sich manchmal töten Pilger, Mönche und Nonnen. Auch heute noch, es ist selten zu finden, ein Mann ohne Kham ein großes Messer auf seiner Seite. Es war eben diese Menschen gab, dass die chinesische kommunistische Regierung den Widerstand. Lange nach der Tibeter in Lhasa gab, die Tibeter von Kham weiterhin zu kämpfen. Die Chinesen leben in der Region Kham sind oft ängstlich von Kham Tibeter. </German>
        <Italian>[TAB] La maggior parte della gente pensa di tibetani come una specie, pacifico, e di cultura religiosa. Kham per la regione del Tibet, questa affermazione è falsa. Kham tibetani sono stati per lungo tempo conosciuto come un violento gruppo di banditi terrorizzano l'altopiano tibetano a cavallo. Essi sono stati impiegati da tibetano Kings campi di guerra e di lotta per loro. Heinrich Harrer e il libro "Sette anni in Tibet", il Kham tibetani sono descritti come costringendo il loro modo in nomade tende a rubare qualcosa di valore. Egli ha inoltre riferito che avrebbero talvolta uccidere pellegrini, monaci e monache. Anche oggi, è raro trovare un uomo senza Kham un grande coltello, per la sua parte. Fu queste stesse persone che hanno dato il governo comunista cinese più resistenza. Molto tempo dopo i tibetani di Lhasa ha dato, i tibetani di Kham continuato a combattere. I cinesi che vivono nella regione del Kham sono spesso timorosi di Kham tibetani.</Italian>
        <Spanish>[TAB] La mayoría de la gente piensa de los tibetanos como un tipo, pacífica, y la cultura religiosa. Para la región de Kham Tíbet, esta declaración es falsa. Kham tibetanos han sido durante mucho tiempo conocido como un violento grupo de bandidos que aterrorizan la meseta tibetana a caballo. Fueron empleados por tibetano Kings en los campos de la guerra a luchar por ellos. Heinrich Harrer en el libro de "Siete Años en el Tíbet", los tibetanos Kham se describen como obligar a su forma nómada en tiendas de campaña robar cualquier cosa de valor. También informó de que a veces matar a los peregrinos, monjes y monjas. Incluso hoy en día, es raro encontrar una Kham hombre sin un gran cuchillo en el costado. Es esta misma gente que dio el gobierno comunista chino la mayoría de la resistencia. Mucho después de los tibetanos de Lhasa entregó, a los tibetanos de Kham continuaron luchando. Los chinos que viven en la región de Kham a menudo temen Kham tibetanos.</Spanish>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_KOA_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]Warfare among tribal chieftains in Hawaii was common, with fierce battles raging frequently.  By the 1780s, warfare was institutionalized, with formal rules and rituals.  The chiefs built temples to pray, sacrifice, and perform ceremonies before launching campaigns.  Warriors were known as koa, and gave their name to the koa tree, whose hard wood provided for many of their weapons.  Hawaiian chieftains were practice of lua, a type of martial arts, and participated in annual festivals to test their abilities.  The warrior code was brutal, and punishment was harsh and violent.  An enemy captured in battle might have his entrails removed and every bone methodically broken while still alive. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Warriors usually wore a loincloth and shaved and oiled their skin to prevent enemies from gripping them in combat.  Nobles also wore a cape, as well as helmets made of wicker or gourds for protection.  These warriors used a variety of weapons such as the ihe (short spear), pololu (long spear), pahoa (wooden dagger), and other weapons.</English>
        <French>[TAB] La guerre entre les chefs tribaux à Hawaii était commun, avec féroces batailles font rage souvent. Par les années 1780, la guerre a été institutionnalisée, avec les règles formelles et les rites. Les chefs ont construit des temples pour prier, le sacrifice, et effectuer des cérémonies avant le lancement de campagnes. Warriors étaient connus comme koa, et a donné son nom à l'arbre koa, dont les bois durs fournis pour beaucoup de leurs armes. Hawaiian chefs étaient pratique de la lua, un type d'arts martiaux, et participé à des festivals annuels de tester leurs capacités. Le guerrier code a été brutale, et de la répression est sévère et violent. Un ennemi capturé dans la bataille pourrait avoir enlevé ses entrailles et les os brisés méthodiquement tout encore en vie. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Warriors généralement portaient un pagne et rasé huilé leur peau et pour empêcher les ennemis de préhension eux dans le combat. Nobles portait aussi une cape, ainsi que les casques en osier ou gourdes pour la protection. Ces guerriers utilisé une variété d'armes telles que les ihe (lance courte), pololu (longue lance), pahoa (poignard en bois), et d'autres armes.</French>
        <German>[TAB] Warfare unter den Stämmen Häuptlinge auf Hawaii war häufig mit heftigen Kämpfe wüteten häufig. Mit dem 1780er, Kriegsführung war institutionalisiert, mit formalen Regeln und Rituale. Die Häupter gebaut Tempel zu beten, opfern, und Zeremonien vor dem Start Kampagnen. Krieger wurden bekannt als koa, und gab ihr den Namen zu koa Baum, dessen hartem Holz, die für viele ihrer Waffen. Hawaiian Häuptlinge wurden Praxis der lua, eine Art von Kampfkunst, und nahm an jährlichen Festivals zu testen ihre Fähigkeiten. Der Krieger Code war brutal, und die Strafe war hart und gewalttätig. Ein Feind gefangen in der Schlacht hätte seine Eingeweide entfernt, und alle Knochen gebrochen, während methodisch noch am Leben. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Warriors Regel trug einen Lendenschurz und rasiert und geölt ihre Haut, um zu verhindern, Feinde Greifen von ihnen im Kampf. Nobles trug einen Umhang, sowie Helme aus Rattan oder Kürbisse für den Schutz. Diese Krieger verwendet eine Vielzahl von Waffen wie die ihe (kurz Speer), pololu (lange Speer), pahoa (Holz Dolch), und andere Waffen.</German>
        <Italian>[TAB] guerra tra i notabili tribali nelle Hawaii era comune, con una feroce battaglia infuria frequentemente. Per il 1780s, la guerra è stata istituzionalizzata, con regole formali e rituali. Capi costruito templi a pregare, di sacrificio, e di eseguire le cerimonie prima di lanciare campagne. Guerrieri erano conosciuti come koa, e ha dato il nome alla koa albero, il cui legno duro di molte delle loro armi. Hawaiian notabili erano pratica di lua, un tipo di arti marziali, e ha partecipato a festival annuale per verificare la loro capacità. Il codice è stato brutale guerriero, e la punizione fu duro e violento. Un nemico catturato in battaglia potrebbe avere rimosso il suo viscere e metodicamente ogni osso rotto, mentre ancora vivo. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Warriors solitamente indossava una loincloth e rasato e oleato loro pelle per evitare che i nemici da loro presa in combattimento. Nobili anche indossato un mantello, come pure i caschi di vimini o gourdes per la protezione. Questi guerrieri utilizzato una varietà di armi, come il ihe (breve lancia), pololu (lunga lancia), pahoa (pugnale di legno), e di altre armi.</Italian>
        <Spanish>[TAB] La guerra entre los jefes tribales en Hawai era común, con feroces batallas azotan con frecuencia. Por los 1780s, la guerra fue institucionalizada, con reglas formales y rituales. Los jefes construido templos de oración, sacrificio, y realizar ceremonias antes de la iniciación de campañas. Warriors se conoce como koa, y dio su nombre a la koa árbol, cuya madera dura para siempre muchas de sus armas. Hawaiian eran jefes de lua práctica, un tipo de artes marciales, y ha participado en festivales anuales de poner a prueba sus habilidades. El código guerrero fue brutal, y el castigo era duro y violento. Un enemigo capturado en la batalla podría haber eliminado sus entrañas y metódicamente cada hueso roto mientras siguen vivos. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Warriors generalmente llevaba una taparrabos y afeitado y su piel engrasada para evitar que los enemigos de prensión ellos en combate. Nobles también llevaba una capa, así como los cascos hechos de mimbre o calabazas para la protección. Estos guerreros utilizan una variedad de armas, como la ihe (lanza corta), pololu (lanza larga), pahoa (daga de madera), y otras armas.</Spanish>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_KONNIK_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]The Bulgars were highly skilled in the equestrian arts.  Their army mainly consisted of horseman because of their high skill.  Every Bulgar horseman had high discipline and had several horses.  However, only a single horse could be used for wartime matters, and it was forbidden to do anything else with it.  It is believed that the Bulgars were the first who brought the stirrups to Europe.  This gave them advantages above the other European armies of this time.  The Bulgars could use bows still mounted on horses.  Swords and spears were also used in war.  The stirrups also increased the stability and speed of the rider.</English>
        <French>[TAB]Le Bulgars étaient fortement habile dans les arts équestres.  Leur armée s'est principalement composée du cavalier en raison de leur compétence élevée.  Chaque cavalier de Bulgar a eu la discipline élevée et a eu plusieurs chevaux.  Cependant, seulement un cheval simple pourrait être employé pour des sujets de temps de guerre, et on l'a interdit de faire toute autre chose avec lui.  On le croit que le Bulgars étaient le premier qui a apporté les étriers à l'Europe.  Ceci leur a donné des avantages au-dessus des autres armées européennes de ce temps.  Le Bulgars a pu employer des arcs toujours montés sur des chevaux.  Des épées et les lances ont été également utilisées dans la guerre.  Les étriers ont également augmenté la stabilité et la vitesse du cavalier.</French>
        <German>[TAB]Das Bulgars waren in die Reiterkünste in hohem Grade erfahren.  Ihre Armee bestand hauptsächlich aus Reiter wegen ihrer hohen Fähigkeit.  Jeder Bulgar Reiter hatte hohe Disziplin und hatte einige Pferde.  Jedoch nur ein einzelnes Pferd könnte für Kriegangelegenheiten benutzt werden, und es war verboten, um noch etwas mit ihm zu tun.  Es wird geglaubt, daß das Bulgars das erste waren, wer die Steigbügel zu Europa holte.  Dieses gab ihnen Vorteile über den anderen europäischen Armeen dieser Zeit.  Das Bulgars konnte die Bögen benutzen, die noch an den Pferden angebracht wurden.  Klingen und Stangen wurden auch im Krieg benutzt.  Die Steigbügel erhöhten auch die Stabilität und die Geschwindigkeit des Mitfahrers.</German>
        <Italian>[TAB]Il Bulgars era altamente esperto nelle arti equestrian.  Il loro esercito pricipalmente ha consistito del horseman a causa dell'loro elevata specializzazione.  Ogni horseman di Bulgar ha avuto alta disciplina ed ha avuto parecchi cavalli.  Tuttavia, soltanto un singolo cavallo potrebbe essere usato per gli argomenti di wartime ed è stato proibito a per fargli niente altro con.  Si crede che il Bulgars sia stato il primo chi ha portato le staffe ad Europa.  Ciò ha dato loro i vantaggi sopra gli altri eserciti europei di questo tempo.  Il Bulgars ha potuto usare gli archi ancora montati sui cavalli.  Le spade ed i germogli inoltre sono stati utilizzati nella guerra.  Le staffe inoltre hanno aumentato la stabilità e la velocità del rider.</Italian>
        <Spanish>[TAB]El Bulgars era altamente experto en los artes ecuestres.  Su ejército consistió en principalmente el jinete debido a su alta habilidad.  Cada jinete de Bulgar tenía alta disciplina y tenía varios caballos.  Sin embargo, solamente un solo caballo podría ser utilizado para las materias del tiempo de guerra, y fue prohibido para hacer todo lo demás con él.  Se cree que el Bulgars era el primer quién trajo los estribos a Europa.  Esto les dio ventajas sobre los otros ejércitos europeos de este tiempo.  El Bulgars podía utilizar los arcos todavía montados en caballos.  Las espadas y las lanzas también fueron utilizadas en guerra.  Los estribos también aumentaron la estabilidad y la velocidad del jinete.</Spanish>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_LAWAGETAS_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]In Mycenaean society, the lawagetas were the "leader of the people".  The word "people" refers to the army, and the lawagetas were commanders of that army.  The lawagetas were powerful men who lead the armies, and received land from the king.</English>
        <French>[TAB]Dans la société de Mycénienne, les lawagetas étaient le « chef du peuple ». Le mot les « gens » se rapporte à l'armée, et les lawagetas étaient des commandants de cette armée. Les lawagetas étaient des hommes puissants qui mènent les armées, et terre reçue du roi.</French>
        <German>[TAB]In der Mykenische Gesellschaft waren die lawagetas der Führer der Leute. Das Wort Leute bezieht sich die auf Armee, und die lawagetas waren Kommandanten dieser Armee. Die lawagetas waren leistungsfähige Männer, die die Armeen führen, und empfangenes Land vom König.</German>
        <Italian>[TAB]Nella società di Micenea, i lawagetas erano il capo della gente. La parola la gente si riferisce all'esercito e i lawagetas erano comandanti di quell'esercito. I lawagetas erano uomini potenti che conducono gli eserciti e terra ricevuta dal re.</Italian>
        <Spanish>[TAB]En la sociedad de Micénica, los lawagetas eran el líder de la gente. La palabra gente refiere al ejército, y los lawagetas eran comandantes de ese ejército. Los lawagetas eran los hombres de gran alcance que conducen a ejércitos, y tierra recibida del rey.</Spanish>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_LIGHT_HORSE_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]The Australian Light Horse were mounted troops that combined the characteristics of both cavalry and mounted infantry.  They served during the Second Boer War and World War I.  Their purpose as both cavalry and mounted infantry was a result of the debate in military groups in Australia concerning the future of mounted troops.  On one hand, the battlefield had become dominated by machine guns and artillery and was too dangerous for mounted troops.  On the other hand, the distances in Australia were too great, and the small amount and poor condition of roads were unable to support mechanized warfare.  Light Horse were like mounted infantry in that they usually fought dismounted, using their horses as transport to the battlefield and as means of quick disengagement when withdrawing or retiring from a battle.  Over time, most Light Horse regiments were converted to motorized infantry, armored car or armored regiments during World War II.  However, a few light horse units still exist today as Royal Australian Armored Corps Cavalry units.</English>
        <French>[TAB]Le cheval de sang australien étaient des troupes montées qui ont combiné les caractéristiques de la cavalerie et de l'infanterie montée.  Ils ont servi pendant la deuxièmes guerre de Boer et Première Guerre Mondiale.  Leur but en tant que la cavalerie et infanterie montée était un résultat de la discussion dans les groupes militaires en Australie au sujet du futur des troupes montées.  D'une part, le champ de bataille était devenu dominé par les mitrailleuses et l'artillerie et était trop dangereux pour les troupes montées.  D'une part, les distances en Australie étaient trop grandes, et un peu et l'état pauvre des routes ne pouvaient pas soutenir la guerre mécanisée.  Le cheval de sang étaient comme l'infanterie montée du fait elles ont habituellement combattu démonté, en utilisant leurs chevaux en tant que transport au champ de bataille et en tant que moyens du dégagement rapide en se retirant ou en se retirant d'une bataille.  Avec le temps, la plupart des régiments de cheval de sang ont été convertis en infanterie motorisée, véhicule blindé ou régiments blindés pendant la deuxième guerre mondiale.  Cependant, quelques unités de cheval de sang existent toujours aujourd'hui en tant qu'unités blindées australiennes royales de cavalerie de corps.</French>
        <German>[TAB]Das australische helle Pferd waren angebrachte Truppen, die die Eigenschaften der Kavallerie und der angebrachten Infanterie kombinierten.  Sie dienten während des zweiten Boer-Krieges und des Ersten Weltkrieges.  Ihr Zweck als Kavallerie und angebrachte Infanterie war ein Resultat der Debatte in den militärischen Gruppen in Australien hinsichtlich ist der Zukunft der angebrachten Truppen.  Einerseits war das Schlachtfeld durch Maschine Gewehren und Artillerie vorherrsch geworden und war für angebrachte Truppen zu gefährlich.  Einerseits waren die Abstände in Australien zu groß, und etwas und der schlechte Zustand der Straßen waren nicht imstande, mechanisierte Kriegsführung zu stützen.  Helles Pferd waren wie angebrachte Infanterie dadurch, daß sie normalerweise abgenommen kämpften mit ihren Pferden als Transport zum Schlachtfeld und als Mittel der schnellen Befreiung, als, zurücktretend oder von einer Schlacht zurückziehend.  Über Zeit wurden die meisten helles Pferd Regimente in motorisierte Infanterie, Panzerkampfwagen oder gepanzerte Regimente während des Zweiten Weltkrieges umgewandelt.  Jedoch bestehen einige helles Pferd Maßeinheiten noch heute als königliche australische gepanzerte Korps-Kavalleriemaßeinheiten.</German>
        <Italian>[TAB]Il cavallo chiaro australiano era truppe montate che hanno unito le caratteristiche sia di cavalry che di fanteria montata.  Hanno servito durante la seconda guerra di Boer e la guerra mondiale I.  Il loro scopo come sia cavalry che fanteria montata era un risultato del dibattito nei gruppi militari in Australia riguardo al futuro delle truppe montate.  Su una mano, il campo di battaglia era stato dominato dalle pistole e dall'artiglieria di macchina ed era troppo pericoloso per le truppe montate.  D'altra parte, le distanze in Australia erano troppo grandi e piccola lo stato dei poveri e di quantità delle strade non poteva sostenere la guerra meccanizzata.  Il cavallo chiaro era come fanteria montata in quanto hanno combattuto solitamente smontato, usando i loro cavalli come trasporto al campo di battaglia e come mezzi di disimpegno rapido quando si ritira o lasciando una battaglia.  Col tempo, la maggior parte dei regiments del cavallo chiaro sono stati convertiti in fanteria motorizzata, in autoblindata o in regiments corazzati durante la seconda guerra mondiale.  Tuttavia, alcune unità del cavallo chiaro ancora esistono oggi come unità corazzate australiane reali del Cavalry di corpo.</Italian>
        <Spanish>[TAB]El caballo ligero australiano era las tropas montadas que combinaron las características de la caballería y de la infantería montada.  Sirvieron durante la segunda guerra de Boer y Primera Guerra Mundial.  Su propósito como la caballería e infantería montada era un resultado del discusión en grupos militares en Australia referente al futuro de tropas montadas.  Por un lado, el campo de batalla se había dominado por las ametralladoras y la artillería y era demasiado peligroso para las tropas montadas.  Por otra parte, las distancias en Australia eran demasiado grandes, y la cantidad pequeña y la condición pobre de caminos no podían apoyar la guerra mecanizada.  El caballo ligero era como la infantería montada en que ella luchó generalmente desmontado, usando sus caballos como transporte al campo de batalla y como medios de la retirada rápida al retirarse o retirándose de una batalla.  En un cierto plazo, la mayoría de los regimientos del caballo ligero fueron convertidos a la infantería motorizada, al vehículo blindado o a los regimientos armados durante la Segunda Guerra Mundial.  Sin embargo, algunas unidades del caballo ligero todavía existen hoy como unidades armadas australianas reales de la caballería del cuerpo.</Spanish>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_MACCABEE_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>The Maccabees were a Jewish national liberation movement that fought for independence from Antiochus IV Epiphanes.  The Maccabees founded the Hasmonean Dynasty of Israel.  In 167 BC, after Antiochus forbade Jewish practice, a priest from Modiin, Mattathias the Hasmonean, sparked a revolt by refusing to worship Greek gods.  After Mattathiass death, his son Judah Maccabee led an army of Jews against the Seleucid Dynasty.  The term Maccabees is used to describe the army of Judah Maccabee. [PARAGRAPH:1] The revolt included many individual battles.  In many, the Maccabeean forces won victory for their use of guerrilla tactics.  After the revolt, the Maccabees cleansed the temple, and declared Judah Maccabee a priest.  A Syrian army was sent to destroy the revolt, but returned after the death of Antiochus. [PARAGRAPH:1] After the revolt, the Maccabees were unsure whether to continue fighting, seeing their military success in the revolt.  Those who continued to fight were led by Judah Maccabee.  Judah Maccabee died in 160 BC in battle.  Judah was succeeded by his younger brother Jonathan, who was already a high priest.  Jonathan made treaties with foreign nations, causing more disputes between those who wanted religious freedom over political power.  In 142 BC, Jonathan died.  He was succeeded by the last son of Mattathias, Simon.  That same year, Demetrius, king of Syria, granted the Jews independence from Syria and Simon went on to found the Hasmonean dynasty. [PARAGRAPH:1] Every year, Jews celebrate Hannukah to celebrate and recognize Judah Maccabees victory over the Seleucids and related miracles.</English>
        <French>Le Maccabees étaient un mouvement national juif de libération qui a combattu pour l'indépendance d'Antiochus IV Epiphanes. Le Maccabees a fondé la dynastie de Hasmonean de l'Israel. Dans 167 AVANT JÉSUS CHRIST, après qu'Antiochus ait interdit la pratique juive, un prêtre de Modiin, Mattathias le Hasmonean, a étincelé une révolte en refusant d'adorer les dieux grecs. Après la mort de Mattathias, son fils Judah Maccabee a mené une armée des juifs contre la dynastie de Seleucid. Le terme Maccabees est employé pour décrire l'armée de Judah Maccabee. [PARAGRAPH : 1] La révolte a inclus beaucoup de différentes batailles. Dans beaucoup, les forces de Maccabeean ont gagné la victoire pour leur usage de la tactique de guérillero. Après la révolte, le Maccabees a nettoyé le temple, et a déclaré Judah Maccabee un prêtre. Une armée syrienne a été envoyée pour détruire la révolte, mais est retournée après la mort d'Antiochus. [PARAGRAPH : 1] Après la révolte, le Maccabees étaient incertain si continuer de combattre, voyant leur succès militaire dans la révolte. Ceux qui ont continué à combattre ont été menés par Judah Maccabee. Judah Maccabee est mort dans 160 AVANT JÉSUS CHRIST dans la bataille. Judah a été réussi par son plus jeune frère Jonathan, qui était déjà un haut prêtre. Jonathan a fait des traités avec des nations étrangères, causant plus de conflits entre ceux qui ont voulu la puissance politique d'excédent religieux de liberté. Dans 142 AVANT JÉSUS CHRIST, Jonathan est mort. Il a été réussi par le dernier fils de Mattathias, Simon. Que la même année, Demetrius, roi de la Syrie, a accordé aux juifs l'indépendance de Syrie et Simon a continué à a trouvé la dynastie de Hasmonean. [PARAGRAPH : 1] Chaque année, juifs célèbrent Hannukah pour célébrer et identifier la victoire de Judah Maccabee sur le Seleucids et les miracles relatifs.</French>
        <German>Das Maccabees waren eine jüdische nationale Befreiungbewegung, die für Unabhängigkeit von Antiochus IV Epiphanes kämpfte. Das Maccabees gründete die Hasmonean Dynastie von Israel. In 167 BC, nachdem Antiochus jüdische Praxis verbot, funkte ein Priester von Modiin, Mattathias das Hasmonean, ein Aufruhr, indem er ablehnte, griechische Götter anzubeten. Nach Tod Mattathiass führte sein Sohn Judah Maccabee eine Armee der Juden gegen die Seleucid Dynastie. Die Bezeichnung Maccabees wird verwendet, um die Armee von Judah Maccabee zu beschreiben. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Der Aufruhr schloß viele einzelne Schlachten ein. In vielen gewannen die Maccabeean Kräfte Sieg für ihren Gebrauch von Bandenkämpfertaktiken. Nach dem Aufruhr reinigte das Maccabees den Bügel und erklärte Judah Maccabee ein Priester. Eine syrische Armee wurde gesendet, um den Aufruhr zu zerstören, aber zurückging nach dem Tod von Antiochus. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Nach dem Aufruhr waren das Maccabees unsicher, ob man fortfährt zu kämpfen und ihren militärischen Erfolg im Aufruhr sieht. Die, die fortfuhren zu kämpfen, wurden von Judah Maccabee geführt. Judah Maccabee starb in 160 BC in der Schlacht. Judah wurde von seinem jüngeren Bruder Jonathan gefolgt, der bereits ein hoher Priester war. Jonathan bildete Verträge mit den fremden Nationen und verursachte mehr Debatten zwischen denen, die politische Energie des frommen Freiheit überschusses wünschten. In 142 BC, starb Jonathan. Er wurde vom letzten Sohn von Mattathias, Simon gefolgt. Daß das gleiche Jahr, Demetrius, König von Syrien, den Juden Unabhängigkeit von Syrien und von Simon bewilligte, gingen an zu fanden die Hasmonean Dynastie. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Jedes Jahr, Juden feiern Hannukah, um Judah Maccabees Sieg über dem Seleucids und den in Verbindung stehenden Wundern zu feiern und zu erkennen.</German>
        <Italian>Il Maccabees era un movimento nazionale ebreo di liberazione che ha combattuto per indipendenza da Antiochus IV Epiphanes. Il Maccabees ha fondato il Dynasty di Hasmonean dell'Israele. In 167 BC, dopo che Antiochus proibisse alla pratica ebrea, un priest da Modiin, Mattathias il Hasmonean, ha scintillato una sommossa rifiutando di adorare i dii greci. Dopo la morte del Mattathias, il suo figlio Judah Maccabee ha condotto un esercito degli ebrei contro il Dynasty di Seleucid. Il termine Maccabees è usato per descrivere l'esercito di Judah Maccabee. [PARAGRAPH: 1] La sommossa ha incluso molte diverse battaglie. In molti, le forze di Maccabeean hanno vinto la vittoria per il loro uso delle tattiche del guerrigliero. Dopo la sommossa, il Maccabees ha pulito il tempiale ed ha dichiarato Judah Maccabee un priest. Un esercito siriano è stato trasmesso per distruggere la sommossa, ma ha rinviato dopo la morte di Antiochus. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Dopo la sommossa, il Maccabees era incerto se continuare il combattimento, vedente il loro successo militare nella sommossa. Coloro che ha continuato a combattere sono stati condotti da Judah Maccabee. Judah Maccabee è morto BC in 160 nella battaglia. Judah è stato riuscito dal suo fratello più giovane Jonathan, che era già un alto priest. Jonathan ha fatto i trattati con le nazioni straniere, causanti più dispute fra coloro che ha desiderato l'alimentazione politica dell'eccedenza religiosa di libertà. In 142 BC, Jonathan morto. È stato riuscito dall'ultimo figlio di Mattathias, Simon. Che lo stesso anno, Demetrius, re della Siria, ha assegnato agli ebrei l'indipendenza dalla Siria e da Simon ha continuato a ha trovato il dynasty di Hasmonean. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Ogni anno, ebrei celebra Hannukah per celebrare e riconoscere la vittoria del Judah Maccabee sopra il Seleucids ed i miracoli relativi.</Italian>
        <Spanish>El Maccabees era un movimiento nacional judío de la liberación que luchó para la independencia de Antiochus IV Epiphanes. El Maccabees fundó la dinastía de Hasmonean de Israel. En 167 A.C., después de que Antiochus prohibiera práctica judía, un sacerdote de Modiin, Mattathias el Hasmonean, chispeó una rebelión rechazando adorar a dioses griegos. Después de la muerte de Mattathias, su hijo Judah Maccabee condujo a ejército de judíos contra la dinastía de Seleucid. El término Maccabees se utiliza para describir al ejército de Judah Maccabee. [PARAGRAPH: 1] La rebelión incluyó muchas batallas individuales. En muchos, las fuerzas de Maccabeean ganaron la victoria para su uso de las táctica del guerrilla. Después de la rebelión, el Maccabees limpió el templo, y declaró a Judah Maccabee un sacerdote. Enviaron para destruir la rebelión, pero volvió un ejército sirio después de la muerte de Antiochus. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Después de la rebelión, el Maccabees era inseguro si continuar luchando, viendo su éxito militar en la rebelión. A Judah Maccabee condujeron los que continuaron luchando. Judah Maccabee murió en 160 A.C. en batalla. A su hermano más joven Jonatán tuvo éxito a Judah, que era ya sacerdote alto. Jonatán hizo tratados con las naciones extranjeras, causando más conflictos entre los que desearon energía política del excedente religioso de la libertad. En 142 A.C., Jonatán muerto. Al hijo pasado de Mattathias lo tuvo éxito, Simon. Que el mismo año, Demetrius, rey de Siria, concedió a judíos independencia de Siria y de Simon fue encendido a encontró la dinastía de Hasmonean. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Cada año, judíos celebra Hannukah para celebrar y para reconocer la victoria de Judah Maccabee sobre el Seleucids y los milagros relacionados.</Spanish>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_MAGHREB_CAVALRY_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]In 711, the Moors invaded Visigoth, Christian Hispania. Under their leader, an African Berber general named Tariq ibn-Ziyad, they brought most of the Iberian Peninsula under Islamic rule in an eight-year campaign. They attempted to move northeast across the Pyrenees Mountains but were defeated by the Frank, Charles Martel, at the Battle of Tours in 732. The Moors ruled in the Iberian peninsula, except for areas in the northwest and the largely Basque regions in the Pyrenees, and in North Africa for several decades. Though the number of "Moors" remained small, they gained large numbers of converts. According to Ronald Segal, author of "Islam's Black Slaves", some 5.6 million of Iberia's 7 million inhabitants were Muslim by 1200, virtually all of them native inhabitants.</English>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_MAJAPAHIT_SILAT_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]Pencak Silat is a Malay word meaning "Self-defense" or "Fighting" and its roots go very far back into the islands of Indonesia in the far east. The exact origins of Pencak Silat are not known but what is known is that it is a Martial tradition that extends to many different regions of the world and that it is an effective form of combative movement.[PARAGRAPH:1]The Hindu Empire of Majapahit created the foundation and systemization of the indigenous fighting techniques of Indonesia. The Majapahit warriors were a steeled group of men and were able to drive back the attacks of ruthless generals like Kau Sing and Kublai Khan with the methods they employed for close combat. It was in this empire that we see the famous Kris sword being truly perfected and becoming part and parcel with Silat.</English>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_MALAGASY_MENALAMBA_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]The rising of the menalamba, the Red Shawls, was a revolt against French colonial rule in Madagascar in the 1890s. In the century before the French conquest, rising tensions between modernising kings, self-seeking Christian oligarchs and reactionary guardians of the ancient talismans had weakened the capacity of the kingdom to resist. But just two months after the French occupation of the capital the menalamba revivalist movement sought to restore the customs of the ancestors and expel the French from the island. The civil war of 1895 fully described here for the first time, has cast a shadow on Malagasy politics ever since.</English>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_MAMBISE_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]The word "mambises" originated in Santo Domingo, after a brave Negro Spanish officer (Juan Ethninius Mamby) joined the Dominicans in the fight for independence in 1846. The Spanish soldiers referred to the insurgents as "the men of Mamby," and "mambies." When Cuba's first war of independence (known as the Ten Year War) broke out in 1868, some of the same soldiers were assigned to the island, importing what had, by then, become a derogatory Spanish slur. The Cuban rebels adopted the name with pride. The rebels had no choice but to become effective guerrilla-style warriors using the environment, the element of surprise, a fast horse and a machete.</English>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_MANDE_SONGHAICAVALRY_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]The kingdom of Songhai provides another prominent body of documented achievements in the use of light cavalry for the purposes of territorial gain and empire building. Malian and Songhai battle formations, or mandekalu, entailed the use of light cavalry forces bearing padded armor, spears or javelins, and imported swords. Such forces were highly effective in combat with enemy soldiers within the range of the savanna; however, these same cavalry forces were far less effective in the forested areas to the south of the Niger River or within tsetse-fly-ridden regions where horses were vulnerable. Following on the heels of the cavalry were the infantrymen, who typically bore full armor, iron-tipped spears, and poisoned arrows.[PARAGRAPH:1]Ultimately, the development of sophisticated military organizations, advanced strategies and tactics, effective diplomacy, and weaponry of the kingdoms of Mali, Songhai, and successor states of West Africa, was such that these kingdoms largely dictated the conditions of European and Arabic commerce in West Africa well into the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries.</English>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_MAPUCHE_PICUNCHE_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]The Picunche (a mapudungun word meaning "North People"), also referred to as picones by the Spanish, were a mapudungun speaking Chilean people living to the north of the Mapuches or Araucanians (a name given to those Mapuche living between the Itata and Toltén Rivers) and south of the Choapa River and the Diaguitas. Until the Conquest of Chile the Itata was the natural limit between the Mapuche, located to the south, and Picunche, to the north. During the Inca attempt to conquer Chile the southern Picunche peoples that successfully resisted them were later known as the Promaucaes.  The Picunche living north of the Promaucaes were called Quillotanes (those living in the Aconcagua River valley north to the Choapa) and Mapochoes (those living in the Maipo River basin) by the Spanish, and were part of the Inca Empire at the time when the first Spaniards arrived in Chile.  Among the peoples the Spanish called the Promaucaes, the people of the Rapel River valley were particularly called by this name by the Spanish. Those of the Mataquito River valley were called the Cures.  The people in the Maule River valley and to the south were distinguished as Maules and those to the south of the Maules and north of the Itata were known as Cauqui by the Inca and Cauquenes by the Spanish and that gave their name to Cauquenes River.  They did not survive into the present day, having died out during the colonial period.</English>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_MARYANNU_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB] The most influential Hurrian state, Mitanni, gained much of its power through military might.  The elite warriors of their army were charioteers, called maryannu.  The maryannu were nobles who could afford chariots, and each had a handful of attendants, including an archer that would fight with them from the chariot and servants that would take care of the horses.  The Mitanni chariots themselves served as a model for the chariots of neighboring empires.  It could even be said that the system of having elite nobles who formed the chariot army was started by the Mitanni.  Mitanni chariots were sleek, with two wheels and a team of two horses.  Both the horses and the maryannu were well armored, being covered in scale armor made of bronze or iron.  The tactic of surrounding an enemy with chariots to constantly attack them with missile fire was developed by the Mitanni.  The Mitanni even created the tactic of using chariots as an impact weapon.</English>
        <French>[TAB] Le plus influents hourrite état, Mitaniens, a gagné une grande partie de son pouvoir par la force militaire. Les guerriers d'élite de leur armée de char, appelé maryannu. Le maryannu étaient nobles qui en avaient les moyens chars, et chacun avait une poignée de participants, y compris un archer qui lutte avec eux dès le char et des serviteurs qui prennent soin des chevaux. Le Mitaniens chars eux-mêmes servi de modèle pour les chars des empires voisins. On pourrait même dire que le système d'élite des nobles qui ont formé le char armée a été lancée par les Mitaniens. Mitaniens chars ont été épurées, avec deux roues et une équipe de deux chevaux. Les chevaux et les maryannu étaient bien blindée, étant traitées dans l'échelle d'armure en bronze ou en fer. La tactique de l'ennemi avec environnantes chars de constamment les attaquer avec des missiles de feu a été mis au point par le Mitaniens. Le Mitaniens même créé en utilisant la tactique de chars comme une arme d'impact.</French>
        <German>[TAB] Die einflussreichsten Hurrian Staat, Mitanni, erhielt viel von ihrer Macht durch militärische Macht. Die Elite-Krieger der Armee wurden charioteers, genannt maryannu. Die maryannu waren Adligen, der Wagen leisten könnte, und jeder hatte eine Handvoll der Teilnehmer, darunter ein Bogenschütze, würde Kampf mit ihnen aus dem Wagen und Knechte, die kümmern sich um die Pferde. Die Mitanni Wagen selbst diente als Vorbild für die Wagen der benachbarten Imperien. Man könnte sogar sagen, dass das System mit der Elite, die Adligen bildeten den Wagen Armee wurde von der Mitanni. Mitanni Wagen waren schnörkellose, mit zwei Rädern und einem Team von zwei Pferden. Sowohl die Pferde und die maryannu waren gut gepanzert, die in Umfang Rüstungen aus Bronze oder Eisen. Die Taktik der Umgebung ein Feind mit Wagen ständig mit Raketen angreifen Feuer wurde von der Mitanni. Die Mitanni auch die Taktik der Verwendung von Wagen als Waffe Auswirkungen.</German>
        <Italian>[TAB] Il più influenti Hurrian Stato, Mitanni, guadagnato molto del suo potere attraverso la forza militare. L'élite del loro esercito di guerrieri erano charioteers, chiamato maryannu. Il maryannu erano nobili, che potevano permettersi carri, e ciascuno ha avuto una manciata di partecipanti, tra cui un arciere che si lotta con loro dal carro e servitori che si occupa di cavalli. Il Mitanni carri stessi servita come modello per i carri di imperi vicini. Si potrebbe anche dire che il sistema di élite nobili che formavano il carro esercito è stato avviato dalla Mitanni. Mitanni carri erano eleganti, con due ruote e un team di due cavalli. Entrambi i cavalli e la maryannu erano ben armate, possono essere coperti in scala armatura in bronzo o in ferro. La tattica di un nemico circostante con carri costantemente al loro attacco con missili fuoco è stato sviluppato dalla Mitanni. Il Mitanni anche creato la tattica di carri utilizzando come arma un impatto.</Italian>
        <Spanish>[TAB] El estado más influyentes hurritas, Mitanni, obtuvo gran parte de su poder a través de la fuerza militar. Los guerreros de élite de su ejército se charioteers, llamado maryannu. El maryannu fueron nobles que podían permitirse carros, y cada uno de ellos había un puñado de asistentes, incluido un arquero que lucha con ellos de todo corazón, y los funcionarios que se ocupan de los caballos. El Mitanni carros propios servido de modelo para los carros de los imperios vecinos. Incluso podría decirse que el sistema de tener élite nobles que formaban el ejército carro fue iniciado por la Mitanni. Mitanni carros fueron elegante, con dos ruedas y un equipo de dos caballos. Tanto los caballos y los maryannu estaban bien blindados, que se tratan en la escala armadura de bronce o de hierro. La táctica de en torno a un enemigo con carros a ellos constantemente ataque con fuego de misiles fue desarrollado por el Mitanni. El Mitanni incluso creó la táctica de utilizar un impacto carros como arma.</Spanish>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_MEDJAY_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]The Medjay were Nubian nomads who became part of the Egyptian police force during the Eighteenth Dynasty.  Perhaps because the Medjay had previously established a history of serving in the Egyptian army that they blended well into Egyptian society.  They had the responsibility of protecting towns in western Thebes and being responsible to its mayor.[PARAGRAPH: 2]  The Medjay also served as tomb guardians during the contruction of the royal necropolis at Deir el-Medina.  The Medjay had the responsibility of ensuring the tomb's safety, inspecting the tomb, protecting the workers, ensuring that the workers were behaving well, and sometimes helping the workers.  Some of their other obligations included acting as messengers, interrogating thieves, being witnesses for administrative functions, and inflicting punishments.</English>
        <French>[TAB]Le Medjay étaient les nomades de Nubian qui sont devenus une partie de la force égyptienne de police pendant la dix-huitième dynastie. Peut-être parce que le Medjay avait précédemment établi une histoire de servir dans l'armée égyptienne qu'elle a bien mélangée dans la société égyptienne. Elle a eu la responsabilité de protéger des villes dans Thebes occidental et d'être responsable à son maire. Le Medjay a également servi de gardiens de tombeau pendant le contruction de la nécropole royale à EL-Medina de Deir. Le Medjay a eu la responsabilité d'assurer la sûreté du tombeau, d'inspecter le tombeau, de protéger les ouvriers, de s'assurer que les ouvriers se comportaient bien, et d'aider parfois les ouvriers. Certains de leurs autres engagements ont inclus agir en tant que messagers, interroger des voleurs, être des témoins pour des fonctions administratives, et infliger des punitions.</French>
        <German>[TAB]Das Medjay waren Nubian Nomaden, die Teil der ägyptischen Polizeikraft während der achtzehnten Dynastie wurden. Möglicherweise, weil das Medjay vorher eine Geschichte des Dienens in der ägyptischen Armee hergestellt hatte, die sie gut in ägyptische Gesellschaft mischten. Sie hatten die Verantwortlichkeit des Schützens der Städte in WestThebes und des Seins verantwortlich zu seinem Bürgermeister. Das Medjay diente auch als Grabwächter während des contruction des königlichen Necropolis an Deir EL-Medina. Das Medjay hatte die Verantwortlichkeit des Sicherstellens der Sicherheit des Grabs, des Kontrollierens des Grabs, des Schützens der Arbeiter, des Sicherstellens, daß die Arbeiter sich gut benahmen, und den Arbeitern manchmal helfen. Einige ihrer anderen Verpflichtungen schlossen das Dienen als Kuriere, die Abfragung der Diebe, Sein Zeugen für administrative Funktionen und das Zufügen von Bestrafungen mit ein.</German>
        <Italian>[TAB]Il Medjay era nomads di Nubian che si sono trasformati in in parte della forza egiziana della polizia durante il diciottesimo Dynasty. Forse perché il Medjay precedentemente aveva stabilito una storia di servire nell'esercito egiziano che ha mescolato bene nella società egiziana. Ha avuta la responsabilità di protezione delle città in Thebes occidentale e dell'essere responsabili al relativo sindaco. Il Medjay inoltre ha servito da guardiani della tomba durante il contruction del necropolis reale a EL-Medina di Deir. Il Medjay ha avuto la responsabilità di accertare la sicurezza della tomba, di controllo della tomba, di protezione degli operai, di accertarsi che gli operai stessero comportando bene ed a volte di assistenza degli operai. Alcuni dei loro altri obblighi hanno incluso fungere da messaggeri, la consultazione dei ladri, essere testimoni per le funzioni amministrative ed infliggere le punizioni.</Italian>
        <Spanish>[TAB]El Medjay era los nómadas de Nubian que hicieron parte de la fuerza egipcia del policía durante la décimo octava dinastía. Quizás porque el Medjay había establecido previamente una historia de servir en el ejército egipcio a que él mezcló bien en sociedad egipcia. Él tenía la responsabilidad de proteger ciudades en Thebes occidental y de ser responsable a su alcalde. El Medjay también sirvió como guardas de la tumba durante el contruction de la necrópolis real en EL-Medina de Deir. El Medjay tenía la responsabilidad de asegurar la seguridad de la tumba, de examinar la tumba, de proteger a los trabajadores, de asegurarse de que los trabajadores se comportaban bien, y a veces de ayudar a los trabajadores. Algunas de sus otras obligaciones incluyeron actuar como mensajeros, la interrogación de ladrones, ser testigos para las funciones administrativas, e infligir castigos.</Spanish>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_MEGYPT_MAMLUK_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]The mamluks were slaves trained as warriors by various Arab leaders, partially because early believers in Islam would not fight each other.  Slave warriors got around this ban.  The mamluks were well trained and highly motivated.  A mamluk army from Egypt won a rare victory against the Mongols in Syria, turning these barbarian horsemen back from the Nile and North Africa.  In time the mamluks rose up against their Arab rulers and took control themselves.  When Napoleon invaded Egypt in the eighteenth century, he defeated a mamluk army at the Battle of the Pyramids.</English>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_MEXICO_RURALES_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]Rurales was the name commonly used to designate the Mexican Guardia Rural (Rural Guard): a force of mounted police or gendarmerie that existed between 1861 and 1914. In modern Mexico the name is applied to members of a part-time rural defence corps.[PARAGRAPH:1]The image of the Rurales as a ruthless and efficient organisation, which seldom took prisoners under the notorious ley fuga and inevitably got its man, was deliberately fostered under the Porfirian regime. However, research during the 1970s involving detailed examination of the records of the corps indicated that the Rurales were neither as effective nor as brutal as regime publicists had suggested. Never numbering more than about 4,000 men located in small detachments, the Rurales were too thinly spread to ever completely eliminate unrest in the Mexican countryside. They did however impose a superficial order, especially in the central regions around Mexico City, which encouraged the foreign investment sought by Díaz and his científico advisers . To a certain extent the regime saw the Rurales as a counterweight to the much larger Federal army and in the later years of the regime they were increasingly used to control industrial unrest, in addition to their traditional task of patrolling country areas.</English>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_MINOA_XIFOS_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]The archeological evidence shows presence of huge watchtowers and warlike longboats from the Minoan era. However, there is no evidence of real war or any type of standing army in the Minoan Civilzation. It is possible that these were all elements to show status among the Minoan City States. Still the Minoans housed remerkable smith skills and Minoan smiths were renowned in the classical world and many of them worked abroud in Mainland Greece.[PARAGRAPH:1](Wikipedia: Minoan Civilization)</English>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_MOCHE_JEQUE_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB] Moche settlements in the Jequetepeque Valley were characterized by fortifications and defensive works. While there is no evidence of a foreign invasion, as many scholars have suggested in the past (i.e. a Huari invasion), there is some evidence of social unrest, possibly the result of climatic changes as factions fought for control over scarce resources. </English>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_MOUNTIE_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]The Royal Canadian Mounted Police was organized as the Northwest Mounted Police to bring law and order to the Canadian West.  In 1920, the name was changed to its present title.  The corps gained a romantic reputation for daring missions and persistence in trailing criminals.  The force originally numbered to 300 men and came to be known as Red Coats, Riders of the Plains, and, most commonly, Mounties.  The force later absorbed the provincial police forces of the all the territories and provinces except Quebec and Ontario.  It enforces all federal and provincial laws and takes part in selected international peacekeeping activities.  The force currently numbers to about 16,000.</English>
        <French>[TAB]La police montée canadienne royale a été organisée en tant que police montée du nord-ouest pour apporter la loi et l'ordre à l'ouest canadien.  En 1920, le nom a été changé en son titre actuel.  Les corps ont gagné une réputation romantique pour des missions audacieuses et la persistance dans les criminels de remorquage.  La force à l'origine numérotée à 300 hommes et est venue pour être connue en tant que les manteaux rouges, les cavaliers des plaines, et, le plus généralement, Mounties.  La force plus tard a absorbé les forces provinciales de police des tous territoires et provinces excepté le Québec et l'Ontario.  Il impose toutes les lois fédérales et provinciales et participe aux activités internationales choisies de maintien de la paix.  La force numérote actuellement environ à 16.000.</French>
        <German>[TAB]Die königliche kanadische berittene Polizei wurde als die berittene Nordwestpolizei organisiert, um Gesetz und Auftrag zum kanadischen Westen zu holen.  1920 wurde der Name zu seinem anwesenden Titel geändert.  Das Korps gewann ein romantisches Renommee für verwegene Missionen und Ausdauer in schleppenden Verbrechern.  Die Kraft ursprünglich numerierte zu 300 Männern und kam, als rote Mäntel, Mitfahrer der Ebenen und, Mounties am allgemeinsten bekannt.  Die Kraft sog später die provinziellen Polizeikräfte der aller Gegenden und der Provinzen ausgenommen Quebec und Ontario auf.  Es erzwingt alle Bundes- und provinziellen Gesetze und nimmt an vorgewählten internationalen Friedenssicherungtätigkeiten teil.  Die Kraft numeriert z.Z. bis ungefähr 16.000.</German>
        <Italian>[TAB]La polizia montata canadese reale è stata organizzata come la polizia montata di nord-ovest per portare la legge e l'ordine all'ovest canadese.  In 1920, il nome è stato cambiato al relativo titolo attuale.  Il corpo ha guadagnato una reputazione romantica per le missioni daring e la persistenza in criminali strascicanti.  La forza originalmente numerata a 300 uomini ed è venuto essere conosciuta il più comunemente come i cappotti rossi, i Riders delle pianure e, Mounties.  La forza più successivamente ha assorbito le forze provinciali della polizia dei tutti i territori e province tranne la Quebec ed Ontario.  Fa rispettare tutte le leggi federali e provinciali e partecipa alle attività internazionali selezionate di mantenimento della pace.  La forza attualmente numera a circa 16.000.</Italian>
        <Spanish>[TAB]Organizaron al policía montado canadiense real como el policía montado del noroeste para traer ley y orden al oeste canadiense.  En 1920, el nombre fue cambiado a su actual título.  El cuerpo ganó una reputación romántica para las misiones atrevidas y persistencia en criminales que se arrastraban.  La fuerza numeró a 300 hombres y vino originalmente ser conocida como las capas rojas, los jinetes de los llanos, y, lo más comúnmente posible, Mounties.  La fuerza absorbió más adelante las fuerzas provinciales del policía de los todos los territorios y provincias excepto Quebec y Ontario.  Hace cumplir todos los leyes federales y provinciales y participa en actividades pacificadoras internacionales seleccionadas.  La fuerza numera actualmente a cerca de 16.000.</Spanish>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_MUTAPA_ROZVI_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]In 1693 the Portuguese were defeated by the Rozwi. The Rozwi were formed from several Shona states that dominated the plateau of present-day Zimbabwe at the time. The Portuguese were driven off the central plateau and only retained a nominal presence at one of the fairs in the eastern highlands. The whole of present-day Zimbabwe was brought under the control of Changamire and became known as the Rozwi Empire. This fierce tribe of warriors was to be known as the Rozvi people and after driving the Portuguese out of the area, went on to establish the Rozvi Empire.</English>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_NEWZEALAND_DIGGER_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]Digger is New Zealand and Australian military slang term for soldiers from New Zealand and Australia. It originated during World War I. There are numerous theories about the origin of the term. Before the war, the term "digger" had been widely used in Australasia to mean a miner, or a Kauri gum-digger in New Zealand. On 25 April 1915, General Sir Ian Hamilton sent a message to the commander of the Australian and New Zealand Army Corps (ANZAC), General William Birdwood, following the landing at Gallipoli. It contained the postscript: "P.S.-You have got through the difficult business, now you have only to dig, dig, dig, until you are safe."</English>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_NIGERIA_NAARTILLERY_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]The NA Divisions are supported by Combat Support Arms namely; artillery, engineers and signals. The type of support they provide and the sizes of the supported formation determine the size and composition of each support arm. The NA Artillery is divided into field and air defence artillery based on the roles they perform. The artillery acquires targets, coordinates all fire power resources available and delivers such firepower in the battlefield so that the enemy can neither interfere with our operations from air and ground nor develop its own resources effectively.</English>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_NORWAY_HERSIR_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]A hersir was a local military commander of a hundred and owed allegiance to a jarl or king. They were also aspiring landowners, and, like the middle class in many feudal societies, supported the kings in their centralization of power. The hersir was often equipped with a conical helmet and a short mail coat. Most would wield an iron sword, mostly augmented with a wooden shield. They were also known to wield one- or even two-handed axes. The hersir would always fight on foot, usually as part of a shield wall formation. Another formation was also used, the Svinfylking, which was a variation to the shield wall but with several wedge like formations pointing towards the enemy creating a zig zag pattern. Although excellent against other foot troops the Vikings were frequently defeated by mounted troops.</English>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_OLMEC_BLACKAXE_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]Obsidian was used by American Indians and many other primitive peoples for weapons, implements, tools, and ornaments and by the ancient Aztecs, Olmecs and Greeks for mirrors. Because of its conchoidal fracture (smooth curved surfaces and sharp edges), the sharpest stone artifacts were fashioned from obsidian; some of these, mostly arrowheads, have been dated by means of the hydration rinds that form on. Meso-American cultures often employed jade, flint and obsidian in the crafting of items of warfare, ritual and ceremony. The Omlecs used obsidian to create black axes, often polished with flint handles.</English>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_PAKISTAN_SSG_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]Special Services Group (SSG) is an independent commando brigade of the Pakistan Army. It is an elite special operations force similar to the ,Special Air Service and United States Army Special Forces(Green Berets). Official numbers are put at 2,100 men, in 3 Battalions; however the actual strength is classified. It is estimated to have been increased to 4 Battalions, with the eventual formation of 2 Brigades of Special Forces (6 Battalions).</English>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_PHILIPPINES_KATIPUNEROS_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]The Katipunan (also known as the Katipuneros) was a Philippine revolutionary organization founded by Filipino rebels in Manila, in 1892, which aimed to gain independence from Spain. The word "Katipunan" comes from the root word "tipon", an indigenous Tagalog word, meaning: "society" or "gather". Its official revolutionary meanings are translated as Kataas-taasang, Kagalang-galangang Katipunan ng mga Anak ng Bayan (Supreme and Venerable Society of the Children of the Nation). The word were used by Filipino revolutionary rebel leaders. The word were used by Filipino revolutionary rebel leaders. Katipunan is also known by its acronym, KKK (not to be mistaken with the "Ku Klux Klan").[PARAGRAPH:1]The KKK had 3 kinds of members. The Katipon (member), the Kawal (soldier), and the Bayani (hero). Each kind of member has different passwords that are secretly used for passage during meetings or entering hideouts.</English>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_PHOENICIA_BIREME_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]The bireme was introduced by the Phoenicians around 800 BC and became the leading warship of the Mediterranean world in the centuries to follow.[PARAGRAPH:1]The Phoenicians were astute naval architects. They lowered the platforms where the oarsmen were seated (crinolines) to increase vessel stability. The battering ram was covered in bronze. The decorative poop was bent and resembled the tail of a scorpion. The balustrade of the battle platform was covered with the shields of warriors, the bireme was thus partially covered in a primitive 'armor'. These war biremes were typically 30 meters in length and 5 meters wide. Phoenicians were the finest seamen of their time, and were often employed as mercenaries.</English>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_PICTS_CRUITHNI_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]The Romans called this pre-Celtic people Pictii, or "Painted," although Claudius' words are proof that (as claimed by many historians), the ancient Picts actually tattooed their bodies with designs. To the non-Roman Celtic world of Scots and Irish and the many tribes of Belgic England and Wales they were known as "Cruithni" and for many centuries they represented the unbridled fury of a people who refused to be brought under the yoke of Rome or any foreign invader.</English>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_PILIWNI_GHOSTDANCER_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]The Ghost Dance is a millennialist spiritual movement among Native Americans in the United States that began toward the end of 1888 and reached its peak just before the Wounded Knee Massacre of 1890. Although the religion is still practiced, it enjoyed only a short period of popularity. Believers in the Ghost Dance spirituality are convinced that performing the Ghost Dance will eventually reunite them with their ancestors coming by railway from the spirit world. The ancestor spirits are called upon to heal the sick and to help protect Mother Earth. Meanwhile, the world will return to a primordial state of natural beauty, opening up to swallow up all other those who do not have a strong spirituality based upon the earth.</English>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_SCYTHIA_SCYTHIAN_RIDER_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]These nomadic tribes live for war. War, and horses. A Scythian rider will drink the blood of their first kill as a right of passage. They scalp their victims and wear their skin like handkerchiefs as a sign of status in their tribe. They're even known to flay an entire enemy and use their hide as a cloak, or as a cover for their quivers. In fact, if a Scythian tribesman doesn't make a kill during a given year, they're left out of their main annual ceremony, where warriors drink wine from the gilded skulls of their enemies.</English>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_SELJUK_GHULAM_WARRIOR_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]The Ghulam warriors were slave-soldiers in service of kings and generals throughout the Turkish and Persian Empires of the Medieval and Early Modern eras. Since the break-up of the Abbasid Caliphate, the Ghulam were grouped into whole armies. They were usually Turkic in origin and fought as cavalrymen. The Ghulam seem to have lived celibate lives. The absence of family life and offspring was one of the reasons why Ghulam, even when attaining power, generally failed to start dynasties or proclaim their independence. The only exception to this was the Ghaznavid dynasty of Afghanistan, which originated amongst the Ghulam of the Samanid dynasty.</English>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_SOMALIA_GUULWADAYAAL_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]In August 1972, the government established the People's Militia, known as the Victory Pioneers (Guulwadayaal). Although a wing of the army, the militia worked under the supervision of the Political Bureau of the presidency. After the SRSP's formation in 1976, the militia became part of the party apparatus. Largely because of the need for military reserves, militia membership increased from 2,500 in 1977 to about 10,000 in 1979, and to approximately 20,000 by 1990. After the collapse of Siad Barre's regime, the People's Militia, like other military elements, disintegrated. </English>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_SOUTHAFRICA_BOERCOMMANDO_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]Guerrilla tactics were used extensively by the forces of the Afrikaner republics in the Second Boer War in South Africa 1899-1902. After the British defeated the Boer armies in conventional warfare and occupied their capitals of Pretoria and Bloemfontein, Boer commandos reverted to mobile warfare. Units led by leaders such as Christian de Wet harassed slow-moving British columns and attacked railway lines and encampments. The Boers were almost all mounted and possessed long range magazine loaded rifles. This gave them the ability to attack quickly and cause many casualties before retreating rapidly when British reinforcements arrived. In the early period of the guerrilla war, Boer commandoes could be very large, containing several thousand men and even field artillery. However, as their supplies of food and ammunition gave out, the Boers increasingly broke up into smaller units and relied on captured British arms and ammunition.</English>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_SPEAR_ELEPHANT_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]The Champa warriors used elephants as their main battle force.  The Champa placed a single warrior atop a platform on the elephant's back.  The warrior would weild a spear or shoot arrows at his enemies.  The Cham armies are regarded as being warlike and cruel.  A Chinese writer described a troop of Cham imperial guards who fought with bows made of bamboo, crossbows, javelins, and spears who rode elephants into battle.</English>
        <French>[TAB]Les guerriers de Champa ont employé des éléphants en tant que leur force principale de bataille. Le champa a placé un guerrier simple placé sur une plateforme sur l'éléphant en arrière. Le guerrier weild une lance ou des flèches de pousse à ses ennemis. Les armées de Cham sont considérées comme étant guerrières et cruelles. Un auteur chinois a décrit une troupe de gardes impériales de Cham qui ont combattu avec des arcs faits de bambou, arbalètes, javelots, et lances qui sont montées des éléphants dans la bataille.</French>
        <German>[TAB]Die Champa Krieger benutzten Elefanten als ihre Hauptschlachtkraft. Das champa setzte einen einzelnen Krieger auf einer Plattform auf den Elefanten zurück. Der Krieger wurde weild eine Stange oder Eintragfadenpfeile an seinen Feinden. Die Chamarmeen werden als seiend kriegerisch und grausam angesehen. Ein chinesischer Verfasser beschrieb eine Truppe des imperialen Schutzes des Cham, der mit den Bögen kämpfte, die vom Bambus, von den crossbows, von den Speeren und von den Stangen, die, gebildet wurden Elefanten in Schlacht ritten.</German>
        <Italian>[TAB]I guerrieri di Champa hanno usato gli elefanti come loro forza principale di battaglia. Il champa ha disposto un singolo guerriero in cima ad una piattaforma sull'elefante indietro. Il guerriero weild un germoglio o frecce del tiro ai suoi nemici. Gli eserciti del Cham sono considerare come essendo warlike e crudeli. Un produttore cinese ha descritto una truppa delle protezioni imperiali del Cham che hanno combattuto con gli archi fatti di bambù, di crossbows, dei javelins e dei germogli che hanno guidato gli elefanti nella battaglia.</Italian>
        <Spanish>[TAB]Los guerreros de Champa utilizaron elefantes como su fuerza principal de la batalla. El champa colocó a solo guerrero encima de una plataforma en el elefante detrás. El guerrero weild una lanza o las flechas del lanzamiento en sus enemigos. Miran a los ejércitos del Cham como siendo guerreros y crueles. Un escritor chino describió a tropa de los protectores imperiales del Cham que lucharon con los arcos hechos de bambú, de crossbows, de javelins, y de las lanzas que montaron elefantes en batalla.</Spanish>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_SWISS_HELLEBARDIER_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]During the Late Middle Ages, mercenary forces grew in importance in Europe, as veterans from the Hundred Years War and other conflicts came to see soldiering as a profession rather than a temporary activity, and commanders sought long-term professionals rather than temporary feudal levies to fight their wars. Swiss mercenaries (Reisläufer) were valued throughout Late Medieval Europe for the power of their determined mass attack in deep columns with the pike and halberd. Hiring them was made even more attractive because entire ready-made Swiss mercenary contingents could be obtained by simply contracting with their local governments, the various Swiss cantonsthe cantons had a form of militia system in which the soldiers were bound to serve and were trained and equipped to do so. It should be noted, however, that the Swiss also hired themselves out individually or in small bands.[PARAGRAPH:1]The warriors of the Swiss cantons had gradually developed a reputation throughout Europe as skilled soldiers, due to their successful defense of their liberties against their Austrian Habsburg overlords, starting as early as the late thirteenth century, including such remarkable upset victories over heavily-armoured knights as Morgarten and Laupen. This was furthered by later successful campaigns of regional expansion (mainly into Italy). By the fifteenth century they were greatly valued as mercenary soldiers, particularly following their series of notable victories in the Burgundian Wars in the latter part of the century. As a result, bands of men, sometime acting independently, other times under the banners of their cantons, marched off to foreign lands to fight in the causes of others, for pay. The native term Reisläufer literally means "one who goes to war" and is derived from Middle High German Reise, meaning "military campaign."[PARAGRAPH:1]The Swiss, with their head-down attack in huge columns with the long pike, refusal to take prisoners, and consistent record of victory, were greatly feared and admiredfor instance, Machiavelli addresses their system of combat at length in The Prince. The Valois Kings of France, in fact, considered it a virtual impossibility to take the field of battle without Swiss pikemen as the infantry core of their armies. (Although often referred to as "pikemen," the Swiss mercenary units also contained halberdiers  as well until several decades into the sixteenth century, as well as a small number of skirmishers armed with crossbows or crude firearms to precede the rapid advance of the attack column.)[PARAGRAPH:1]The young men who went off to fight, and sometimes die, in foreign service had several incentiveslimited economic options in the still largely-rural cantons; adventure; pride in the reputation of the Swiss as soldiers; and finally what military historian Sir Charles Oman describes as a pure love of combat and warfighting in and of itself, forged by two centuries of conflict.</English>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_THORAKITAI_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]The Seleukidoi took to the thureophoroi and went one better, armoring their improved unit to the teeth and giving him a longer spear with a wider blade. These men are exceedingly well trained and often can make the difference in any battle simply by making their fearsome appearance known. They carry theuros shields with silver medusa heads emblazoned on the front and wear helmets that are strengthened with mail 'veils', making their appearance even more fearsome. As if this was not enough, they carry heavy javelins to break enemy lines and long spears to drive the charge home when they are finished with their javelin throwing. They fight in an organized formation, but not in a phalanx, and are thus more mobile than the Phalanx. They are the best and fittest men within the Hypastistai and are often able to break an enemy line. They have no real weakness in battle, but are extremely expensive to maintain, so their numbers are always few and far between. They should be used as an elite shock infantry, because this is the role for which they were made. They should be well supported, because if these hardy and grizzled veterans rout, it could induce the rest of the army to do so as well![NEWLINE][TAB]Historically, the Seleukidos Thorakitai Argyraspidai were a small elite unit of the Hypastistai that were the leaders of an infantry charge. Their heavy armor was elaborate and expensive, making their numbers never more than one thousand (among six thousand Hypastistai). They were used during many battles, but were notoriously absent from Raphia due to their being refitted after a battle with rebels supported by the Parthai. They slowly dwindled in number as the kingdom's finances did the same. They were no longer a factor when the Seleukidod king fought the Romaioi in Makedonia, a battle at which they would have been very much appreciated. If a capable ruler were to take the Seleukidos throne and carefully manage the kingdom's finances, perhaps he could utilize these fine soldiers far longer than happened historically.</English>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_TIMURID_BARLAS_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]The Barlas were a Turko-Mongol nomadic confederation of Central Asia and the chief tribe of the Timurid emperors who ruled much of Central Asia, Iran, and South Asia in the Middle Ages. The Barlas were descendants of the Mongol warlord Bodonchir who was also considered the direct ancestor of Genghis Khan. The Turko-Mongol conqueror Timur was from a noble family of the Barlas clan.[PARAGRAPH:1]The Mughal Empire of South Asia was founded by Zahir ud-din Muhammad Babur, a descendent of the Timurids. The Barlas family name is used by the descendents of Mughals in Pakistan.</English>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_TROY_GUARD_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]The Apollonian Guard was a unit of the Trojan Army, named after the largest and most important gate of Troy, the Apallonian Gate, and were noted as some of the greatest and most experienced soldiers of the Trojans. These soldiers were usually put into the front-line of battles, and were noted to be a unit of perfection in javelin-throwing and horse-riding. They were led solely by Poludamas, an important general and military advisor of King Priam, and a lueitenant and friend of Hector. Much of the unit was destroyed in the first battle of the Trojan War, when Hector and Poludamas led the Apallonian Guard against Achilles and his elite soldiers when they raided the Grand Temple of Apollo, the patron god of Troy. The rest were wiped out in a final stand at the Citadel of Troy, the area were the palace, temples and the Towers of Ilium laid. There Poludamas died, seven days after Hector's death at the hands of Achilles, and directly before Paris, also known as Alexandros, killed Achilles in the Gardens of Troy, and then was killed in combat, then afterwards Helen did a whorish act, and took of her top to seduce King Meneleus of Sparta, her ex-husband, to spare her.</English>
        <Spanish>[[TAB]The Apollonian Guard was a unit of the Trojan Army, named after the largest and most important gate of Troy, the Apallonian Gate, and were noted as some of the greatest and most experienced soldiers of the Trojans. These soldiers were usually put into the front-line of battles, and were noted to be a unit of perfection in javelin-throwing and horse-riding. They were led solely by Poludamas, an important general and military advisor of King Priam, and a lueitenant and friend of Hector. Much of the unit was destroyed in the first battle of the Trojan War, when Hector and Poludamas led the Apallonian Guard against Achilles and his elite soldiers when they raided the Grand Temple of Apollo, the patron god of Troy. The rest were wiped out in a final stand at the Citadel of Troy, the area were the palace, temples and the Towers of Ilium laid. There Poludamas died, seven days after Hector's death at the hands of Achilles, and directly before Paris, also known as Alexandros, killed Achilles in the Gardens of Troy, and then was killed in combat, then afterwards Helen did a whorish act, and took of her top to seduce King Meneleus of Sparta, her ex-husband, to spare her.</Spanish>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_TUPI_TOMOIO_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]The Tomoios are one of many tribes that make up the Tupi family. Like other natives from the region, they were assimilated, enslaved or simply exterminated by Portuguese and Spanish settlers, nearly leading to their complete annihilation, with the exception of a few isolated communities. The remnants of these tribes are today confined to indigenous reservations or acculturated to some degree into the dominant society. The Tomoios were a formidable presence within the Amazon rain forests when the Poruguese first arrived in Brazil.</English>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_UYGHUR_ALTAICRIDER_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]Uyghur history is the story of an obscure nomadic tribe from the Altai Mountains rising to challenge the Chinese Empire and ultimately becoming the diplomatic arm of the Mongol invasion. The ancestors of the Uyghur include the nomadic Gaoche people and possibly the Tocharian peoples of the Tarim Basin. The Uyghur participated in a coalition of Tiele under the leadership of the Syr-Tardush tribe, who allied with the Chinese Sui Empire in 603 to defeat Tardu Khan and win their independence. In 744 the Uyghur, together with other related subject tribes (the Basmil and Qarluq), defeated the Gokturk Khanate and founded the Uyghur Empire at Mount Ötüken, which lasted for about 100 years.</English>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_VANATORI_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]The Mountain Hunters are one of the oldest types of units in the Romanian military. This is an "infantry with special abilities" branch and it is dedicated to mountain warfare.[NEWLINE][TAB] The Mountain Hunters do not consider themselves "special forces". "We like others to call us that way", said Lt-Col Cristinel Cernea, commander of the 21st battalion, 2nd Brigade, the most elite Mountain Hunters battalion in the country. The Mountain Hunters are locally called Vanatori de Munte, or VM's for short.[NEWLINE][TAB]On the 3rd of November, 1916, the 1st Mountain Corps was established, opening a very important chapter in the history of this elite branch.  This event was remembered on the 3rd of November 2001, when the Mountain Hunters celebrated 85 years of existence.  The elite branch of the infantry existed in the past as well, however it was in 1916 when they started to be called "Vanatori de Munte" (Mountain Hunters) and when their main purpose was set to be fighting in mountainous regions.</English>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_VEDIC_RATHIN_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]The main duty of the king in Vedic civilizations was to protect the tribe. He was aided by two functionaries, the "purohita" (chaplain) and the "senani" (army chief; "sena": army). The former not only gave advice to the ruler but also practiced spells and charms for success in war. Soldiers on foot ("patti") and on chariots ("rathin"), armed with bow and arrow were common. The king employed "spasa" (spies) and "duta"s (messengers). He often got a ceremonial gift, "bali", from the people. </English>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_VIETNAM_VIETCONG_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]The Viet Cong is a special unit for the Vietnamese civilization. Viet Cong were used by the Vietnamese army as a fast-moving military unit that could easily go from place to place in a relatively short amount of time. Their elusiveness (when needed) and their knowledge of the terrain made them extremely difficult fighters. The Viet Cong were also highly motivatived and would endure terrible conditions to keep up the fight against the enemy no matter how long it lasted.</English>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_VYTIS_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB] The Vytis, or the Chaser, represents the knight on the Coat of Arms of Lithuania.  Various interpretations about what it represents exist; one being that Vytis represents the Lithuanian god of thunder.  The Vytis may also represent a Lithuanian war god.  The Lithuanian Coat of Arms is one of the oldest coats of arms in Europe, and rather than containing symbols adopted from the coat of arms of dynasties, the symbols are adopted from duke portrait seals.  This greatly differs from the traditional coat of arms of other European countries.</English>
        <French>[TAB] Le Vytis, ou le Chaser, représente le chevalier sur le Blason de la Lituanie. Diverses interprétations sur ce qu'il représente existent, l'une étant que représente le lituanien Vytis dieu de la foudre. Le Vytis peuvent également représenter un dieu de guerre lituanien. Les armoiries du lituanien est l'un des plus vieux blasons en Europe, et plutôt que d'adopter des symboles contenant le blason de dynasties, les symboles sont adoptées portrait du duc phoques. Cela diffère grandement de la traditionnelle armoiries des autres pays européens.</French>
        <German>[TAB] Die Vytis, oder die Chaser, der Ritter ist auf dem Wappen von Litauen. Verschiedene Interpretationen über das, was sie existieren; ein, dass die litauische Vytis ist Gott der Donner. Die Vytis Mai auch eine litauische Krieg Gott. Die litauische Wappen ist eines der ältesten Wappen in Europa, und anstatt mit Symbolen aus nahm das Wappen von Dynastien, die Symbole werden angenommen Porträt von Herzog Dichtungen. Dies unterscheidet sich erheblich von der traditionellen Wappen von anderen europäischen Ländern.</German>
        <Italian>[TAB] Il Vytis, o il Chaser, rappresenta il cavaliere sul Stemma della Lituania. Diverse interpretazioni su ciò che essa rappresenta esistono; uno che rappresenta il lituano Vytis dio del tuono. Il Vytis può anche rappresentare un dio lituano guerra. Il lituano Stemma è uno dei più antichi stemmi in Europa, e piuttosto che contengono simboli adottati dal stemma di dinastie, i simboli sono adottati dal duca ritratto sigilli. Questo si differenzia notevolmente dal tradizionale stemma di altri paesi europei.</Italian>
        <Spanish>[TAB] El Vytis, o el Chaser, representa el caballo en el Escudo de Armas de Lituania. Diversas interpretaciones sobre lo que representa existen; siendo uno de ellos que representa el lituano Vytis dios del trueno. El Vytis también puede representar un dios de la guerra lituano. El lituano Escudo de Armas es uno de los más antiguos escudos de armas en Europa, y en lugar de símbolos que contiene entre el escudo de armas de las dinastías, los símbolos se aprobó duque retrato de las focas. Esto difiere de la tradicional escudo de armas de otros países europeos.</Spanish>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_WELSH_LONGBOWMAN_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>During the Anglo-Norman invasion of Wales, the Welsh Longbow was put into use.  The English soon learned how powerful this weapon could be, and began to recruit Welsh Longbowmen into their own army.  The Welsh Longbow is most famous for its role in the Battle of Agincourt, and the Hundred Years' War.  The Longbowmen, using the Welsh Longbow, would fire a rain of arrows and the enemy.  The Welsh Longbow was used unil the development of gunpowder.  Overall, the weapon was a powerful type of medieval longbow.  The Welsh Longbow was difficult to master because of its draw weight.  Because of the difficulty, many users of the Welsh Longbow were eventually deformed in their arms and wrists.</English>
        <French>Pendant l'invasion Anglo-Normande du Pays de Gales, l'arc de Gallois a été mis dans l'utilisation. L'anglais a bientôt appris comment puissant cette arme pourrait être, et a commencé à recruter des Longbowmen de Gallois dans leur propre armée. L'arc de Gallois est le plus célèbre pour son rôle dans la bataille d'Agincourt, et les cent guerres des ans. Les Longbowmen, en utilisant l'arc de Gallois, mettraient le feu à une pluie des flèches et de l'ennemi. L'arc de Gallois était unil utilisé le développement de la poudre. De façon générale, l'arme était un type puissant d'arc médiéval. Il était difficile maîtriser l'arc de Gallois en raison de son poids d'aspiration. En raison de la difficulté, beaucoup d'utilisateurs de l'arc de Gallois ont été par la suite déformés dans leurs bras et poignets.</French>
        <German>Während der Anglo-Normannischen Invasion von Wales, wurde der Waliser Longbow in Gebrauch gesetzt. Englisch erlernte bald, wie leistungsfähig diese Waffe sein könnte, und fing an, Waliser Longbowmen in ihre eigene Armee einzuziehen. Der Waliser Longbow ist für seine Rolle in der Schlacht von Agincourt und der Hundertjährigen Kriege am berühmtesten. Die Longbowmen mit dem Waliser Longbow, würden einen Regen der Pfeile und des Feindes abfeuern. Der Waliser Longbow war verwendetes unil die Entwicklung des Schießpulvers. Gesamt, war die Waffe eine leistungsfähige Art mittelalterliches longbow. Der Waliser Longbow war schwierig, wegen seines Betraggewichts zu erarbeiten. Wegen der Schwierigkeit wurden viele Benutzer des Walisers Longbow schließlich in ihren Armen und in Handgelenken verformt.</German>
        <Italian>Durante l'invasione Anglo-Normanna del Galles, la Lingua gallese Longbow è stata messa in uso. L'inglese presto ha imparato quanto potente questa arma potrebbe essere ed ha cominciato a reclutare i Longbowmen di Lingua gallese nel loro proprio esercito. La Lingua gallese Longbow è più famosa per il relativo ruolo nella battaglia di Agincourt e le cento guerre degli anni. I Longbowmen, usando la Lingua gallese Longbow, infornerebbero una pioggia delle frecce e del nemico. La Lingua gallese Longbow era unil usato lo sviluppo di polvere nera. In generale, l'arma era un tipo potente di longbow medioevale. La Lingua gallese Longbow era difficile da acquistare padronanza di a causa del relativo peso di tiraggio. A causa della difficoltà, molti utenti della Lingua gallese Longbow finalmente sono stati deformati in loro armi e polsi.</Italian>
        <Spanish>Durante la invasión Anglo-Normanda de País de Gales, el Galés Longbow fue puesto en uso. El inglés pronto aprendió cómo es de gran alcance esta arma podría ser, y comenzó a reclutar a Longbowmen Galés en su propio ejército. El Galés Longbow es el más famoso por su papel en la batalla de Agincourt, y las cientos guerras de años. Los Longbowmen, usando el Galés Longbow, encenderían una lluvia de las flechas y del enemigo. El Galés Longbow era unil usado el desarrollo de la pólvora. Total, la arma era un tipo de gran alcance de longbow medieval. El Galés Longbow era difícil de dominar debido a su peso del drenaje. Debido a la dificultad, muchos usuarios del Galés Longbow fueron deformidos eventual en sus brazos y muñecas.</Spanish>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_WESTINDIES_JDFENGINEER_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]1 Engineer Regiment (JDF) is a unit of the Jamaica Defence Force primarily responsible for providing military and civil engineering. The regiment was formed in 1992 after a requirement was identified for increased military and civil engineering capability for the JDF than could be provided by the then existing structure. At the time, all JDF engineering capacity was provided by the Construction Squadron and the Engineering Unit of the Support and Services Battalion. The regiment today consists of a total of four distinct sub-units.</English>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_XIONGNU_ELITE_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]In the winter of 200 BC, following a siege of Taiyuan, Emperor Gao of China personally led a military campaign against Modu. At the battle of Baideng, he was ambushed reputedly by 300,000 elite Xiongnu cavalry. The emperor was cut off from supplies and reinforcements for seven days, only narrowly escaping capture.[PARAGRAPH:1]After the defeat at Pingcheng, the Han emperor abandoned a military solution to the Xiongnu threat. Instead, in 198 BC, the courtier Liu Jing was despatched for negotiations. The peace settlement eventually reached between the parties included a Han princess given in marriage to the shanyu (called heqin or "harmonious kinship"); periodic gifts of silk, liquor and rice to the Xiongnu; equal status between the states; and the Great Wall as mutual border.</English>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_YEMEN_MAQILWARRIOR_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]The people of the Western Sahara are descended from two known tribes that were the original inhabitants of the territory: the Zenata and the Sanhaja. Beginning in the seventh century, they resisted the invasion of Muslim Arab peoples from the east, but they accepted Islam. Under the influence of Islam, the first unified movement of the population was created, resulting in the establishment of the Almoravid dynasty. At the end of the 13th century, Arab Yeminite people, known as Maqil, invaded the Western Sahara and created a new political and social culture. The Mauritanian Thirty-Year War (1644-74) was the unsuccessful final effort to repel the Yemeni Maqil Arab invaders led by the Beni Hassan tribe. The descendants of the Yemeni Beni Hassan warriors became the upper stratum of Moorish society.</English>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_YORUBA_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>The Yoruba had their own Art of War. As part of rituals, which the male Yoruba needed to become men, they were trained from their early childhood on to be specialists in disciplines like horseback riding, swimming and hunting.</English>
        <German>Die Yoruba hatten seit jeher ihre eigenen Kampfkünste. Als Teil der Rituale, die die Männer der Yoruba zum Eintritt in die "Männlichkeit" benötigen, werden sie von frühauf darauf getrimmt in Disziplinen wie Reiten, Schwimmen und der Jagd Spezialisten zu sein.</German>
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_ZAPOROZHIAN_COSSACK_PEDIA</Tag>
        <English>[TAB]The Zaporozhian Cossacks were Cossacks who lived in Zaporizhya, a region in Central Ukraine.  The Zaporozhian Host grew rapidly in the 15th century by serfs escaping the Polish Lithuanian Commonwealth.  The base and fortress of the Cossacks was the Zaporozhian Sich, which was originally built in the area known as Zaporizhia.  During the course of the 16th, 17th and well into the 18th century, the Zaporozhian Cossacks became a strong political and military forced that challenged the authority of the Poland-Lithuania, the Ottoman Empire and its vassal, the Crimean Khanate, and the Tsardom of Russia.  The Host underwent a sequence of conflicts and alliances involving the three powers before being destroyed in the late 18th century by the Russian Empire.</English>
        <French>[TAB]Les Cosaques de Zaporozhian étaient les Cosaques qui ont habité dans Zaporizhya, une région en Ukraine centrale.  Le centre serveur de Zaporozhian s'est développé rapidement au 15ème siècle par des serfs échappant au Commonwealth lithuanien polonais.  La base et la forteresse des Cosaques étaient le Zaporozhian Sich, qui a été à l'origine construit dans le secteur connu sous le nom de Zaporizhia.  Pendant le 16ème, le 17ème et bien dans le 18ème siècle, les Cosaques de Zaporozhian est devenu un obligatoire politique et militaire fort qui a défié l'autorité de la Pologne-Lithuanie, l'empire de tabouret et son vassal, le Khanate criméen, et le Tsardom de la Russie.  Le centre serveur a subi un ordre des conflits et des alliances impliquant les trois puissances avant d'être détruit vers la fin du 18ème siècle par l'empire russe.</French>
        <German>[TAB]Die Zaporozhian Kosaken waren Kosaken, die in Zaporizhya wohnten, eine Region in zentraler Ukraine.  Der Zaporozhian Wirt wuchs schnell im 15. Jahrhundert durch die Sklaven, die dem polnischen litauischen Commonwealth entgehen.  Die Unterseite und die Festung der Kosaken waren das Zaporozhian Sich, das ursprünglich im Bereich errichtet wurde, der als Zaporizhia bekannt ist.  Während des 16. wurde 17. und gut in das 18. Jahrhundert, die Zaporozhian Kosaken ein starkes politisches und militärisches Zwangs-, das die Berechtigung des Polen-Litauens, des Ottoman-Reiches und seines vassal herausforderten, das KrimKhanate und das Tsardom von Rußland.  Der Wirt machte eine Reihenfolge der Konflikte und der Bündnisse durch, welche die drei Energien mit einbeziehen, bevor er Ende des 18. Jahrhunderts durch das russische Reich zerstört wurde.</German>
        <Italian>[TAB]I Cossacks di Zaporozhian erano Cossacks che hanno vissuto in Zaporizhya, una regione in Ucraina centrale.  L'ospite di Zaporozhian si è sviluppato velocemente nel quindicesimo secolo dai servi che fuoriescono il commonwealth lituano polacco.  La base ed il fortress dei Cossacks erano lo Zaporozhian Sich, che originalmente è stato costruito nella zona conosciuta come Zaporizhia.  Durante il corso del sedicesimo, il diciassettesimo e facilmente per il diciottesimo secolo, i Cossacks di Zaporozhian si è trasformato in in un forzato politico e militare forte che ha sfidato l'autorità della Polonia-Lituania, l'impero del Ottoman ed il relativo vassal, nel Khanate della Crimea e nel Tsardom della Russia.  L'ospite ha subito una sequenza dei conflitti e delle alleanze che coinvolgono le tre alimentazioni prima del essere distruttoe verso la fine del diciottesimo secolo dall'impero russo.</Italian>
        <Spanish>[TAB]Los Cossacks de Zaporozhian eran los Cossacks que vivieron en Zaporizhya, una región en Ucrania central.  El anfitrión de Zaporozhian creció rápidamente en el décimo quinto siglo por los siervos que escapaban la Commonwealth lituana polaca.  La base y la fortaleza de los Cossacks eran el Zaporozhian Sich, que fue construido originalmente en el área conocida como Zaporizhia.  Durante el curso del décimosexto, el 17mo y bien en el décimo octavo siglo, los Cossacks de Zaporozhian se convirtió en un forzado político y militar fuerte que desafió la autoridad de la Polonia-Lituania, el imperio del otomano y su vassal, el Khanate crimeo, y el Tsardom de Rusia.  El anfitrión experimentó una secuencia de los conflictos y de las alianzas que implicaban las tres energías antes de ser destruido en el último décimo octavo siglo por el imperio ruso.</Spanish>
    </TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>
