<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by lcollins (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- Copyright Firaxis Games 2005 -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text - New -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_MARAE</Tag>
		<English>Marae</English>
		<French>Marae</French>
		<German>Marae</German>
		<Italian>Marae</Italian>
		<Spanish>Marae</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
        <TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_MARAE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]A marae is a sacred place which served for both religious and social purposes in pre-Christian Polynesian societies.  In all Polynesian languages, any variant of this word means "cleared, free of weeds, trees, etc."  It generally consists of an area of cleared land roughly rectangular, bordered with stones or wooded posts.  In the Maori of New Zealand, the marae is still a vital part of everyday life.  However, in most other Polynesian societies, most marae were destroyed or abandoned with the arrival of Christianity.  Despite all this, marae were built and still considered as a holy place and nobody would build on it.  [PARAGRAPH: 1] In Maori society, the marae is a place where the culture can be celebrated.  Various intertribal ceremonies were also practiced in the marae.  In Maori usage, marae is technically the enclosed space in front of a meeting house.  However, it is usually used to describe the marae itself and the surrounded complex.  The meeting house is the setting for important meetings, sleepovers, and craft and cultural activities.  The wharakeai, dining hall, is sued primarily for communal meals.  Many of the words associated with marae in tropical Polynesia are kept in the Maori context.</English>
		<French>[TAB] Un marae est un lieu sacré qui servait à la fois pour des raisons sociales et religieuses dans le préprimaire Christian sociétés polynésiennes. Dans toutes les langues polynésiennes, une variante de ce mot signifie "nettoyés, exempts de mauvaises herbes, les arbres, etc" Elle est généralement constituée d'une zone de terres déminées à peu près rectangulaire, bordés de pierres ou d'arbres postes. Dans les Maori de la Nouvelle-Zélande, les marae est toujours une partie essentielle de la vie quotidienne. Toutefois, dans la plupart des autres sociétés polynésiennes, la plupart des marae ont été détruits ou abandonnés avec l'arrivée du christianisme. Malgré tout cela, marae ont été construits et toujours considéré comme un lieu saint et personne ne s'appuierait sur elle. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Dans la société maorie, les marae est un lieu où la culture peut être célébré. Diverses cérémonies intertribaux ont également été pratiquée dans les marae. En Maoris utilisation, marae est techniquement un espace clos devant une réunion de maison. Cependant, il est souvent utilisé pour décrire les marae lui-même et le milieu complexe. La réunion maison est le cadre de réunions importantes, sleepovers, et de l'artisanat et des activités culturelles. Le wharakeai, réfectoire, est poursuivi principalement pour des repas communaux. Beaucoup des mots associés à marae en Polynésie tropicales sont conservées dans le contexte des Maoris.</French>
		<German>[TAB] Ein marae ist ein heiliger Ort, der für beide serviert religiösen und sozialen Zwecken in der vorchristlichen polynesischen Gesellschaften. In allen polynesischen Sprachen, jede Variante dieses Wort bedeutet "geräumt, frei von Unkraut, Bäume, usw." Es besteht aus einem allgemeinen Bereich der geräumten Flächen rund rechteckig, grenzt mit Steinen oder bewaldeten Stellen. In den Maori in Neuseeland, die marae ist nach wie vor ein wesentlicher Bestandteil des täglichen Lebens. Aber auch in den meisten anderen polynesischen Gesellschaften, die meisten marae wurden zerstört oder aufgegeben mit der Ankunft des Christentums. Trotz all dieser marae gebaut wurden und noch immer als ein heiliger Ort, und niemand würde auf sie. [ABSATZ: 1] In Maori Gesellschaft, die marae ist ein Ort, wo die Kultur gefeiert werden kann. Verschiedene intertribal Zeremonien wurden auch geübt in der marae. In Maori Nutzung, marae ist technisch der geschlossenen Raum vor der Sitzung. Allerdings ist es in der Regel zur Beschreibung der marae selbst und der umgeben komplex. Die Sitzung ist die Einstellung für den wichtigen Sitzungen, sleepovers, und handwerklichen und kulturellen Aktivitäten. Die wharakeai, Speiseraum, verklagt ist in erster Linie für gemeinsames Essen. Viele der Wörter im Zusammenhang mit marae in tropischen Polynesien werden in der Maori.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB] Un marae è un luogo sacro, che è servita sia per scopi religiosi e sociali nel pre- cristiano Polinesia società. In tutte le lingue della Polinesia, qualsiasi variante di questa parola significa ", però, la libera di erbacce, alberi, ecc" Essa consiste in genere di una zona di terra eliminato circa rettangolare, confinante con pietre o boschive post. Nel Maori della Nuova Zelanda, il marae è ancora una parte vitale della vita quotidiana. Tuttavia, nella maggior parte delle altre società polinesiana, la maggior parte marae sono state distrutte o abbandonate con l'arrivo del cristianesimo. Nonostante tutto questo, marae sono stati costruiti e ancora considerato come un luogo sacro, e nessuno potrebbe costruire su di essa. [PARAGRAFO: 1] Nel Maori società, il marae è un luogo in cui la cultura può essere celebrato. Diversi intertribal cerimonie sono state praticate anche nel marae. In Maori uso, marae è tecnicamente il spazio chiuso di fronte a una riunione casa. Tuttavia, è di solito usato per descrivere la marae stesso e circondato il complesso. La riunione casa è l'impostazione di riunioni importanti, sleepovers, e artigianali e le attività culturali. Il wharakeai, sala da pranzo, è citato in primo luogo per i pasti in comune. Molte delle parole associate con marae nella Polinesia tropicali sono conservate nel contesto Maori.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB] Una marae es un lugar sagrado, que sirve tanto para fines religiosos y sociales en los polinesios antes de las sociedades cristianas. En todos los idiomas polinesios, cualquier variante de esta palabra significa "limpia, libre de malezas, árboles, etc" Generalmente consta de un área de terreno despejado, aproximadamente rectangulares, bordeado con piedras o arbolado puestos. En los maoríes de Nueva Zelandia, el marae sigue siendo una parte vital de la vida cotidiana. Sin embargo, en la mayoría de las otras sociedades de Polinesia, la mayoría de marae fueron destruidos o abandonados con la llegada del cristianismo. A pesar de todo esto, marae se construyeron y aún considerado como un lugar sagrado y nadie puede construir sobre ella. [APARTADO: 1] En la sociedad maorí, el marae es un lugar donde la cultura puede ser celebrado. Varios intertribales ceremonias también se practica en los marae. En uso de los maoríes, es técnicamente el marae espacio cerrado delante de una casa de reunión. Sin embargo, es generalmente utilizado para describir el mismo y el marae rodeado complejo. En la reunión se casa es el escenario de importantes reuniones, sleepovers, y en la artesanía y las actividades culturales. El wharakeai, comedor, es demandado principalmente para las comidas comunales. Muchas de las palabras asociadas con marae tropicales en la Polinesia se mantienen en el contexto maoríes.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
        <TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_MARAE_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Marae[COLOR_REVERT], the Polynesian replacement for the [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Colosseum[COLOR_REVERT], offers bonus culture.</English>
		<French>Le [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]marae[COLOR_REVERT], équivalent polynésien du [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]colisée[COLOR_REVERT], offre un bonus de culture.</French>
		<German>Die [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Marae[COLOR_REVERT], die Polynesische Ersatz für die [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Colosseum[COLOR_REVERT], bietet bonus kultur.</German>
		<Italian>L'[COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Marae[COLOR_REVERT], la sostituzione polinesiana per il [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Colosseo[COLOR_REVERT], offre bonus di cultura.</Italian>
		<Spanish> El [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Marae[COLOR_REVERT], la sustitución de polinesiano para el [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Coliseo[COLOR_REVERT], ofrece bono de la cultura. </Spanish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>