<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by lcollins (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- Copyright Firaxis Games 2005 -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text - New -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_LLYWELYN</Tag>
		<English>Llywelyn</English>
		<French>Llywelyn</French>
		<German>Llywelin</German>
		<Italian>Llywelyn</Italian>
		<Spanish>Llywelyn</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_LLYWELYN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Llywelyn the Great[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Prince of Gwynedd[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived:[\BOLD]c.1173  - 1240[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:1][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Llywelyn Fawr, or Llywelyn the Great, was born in Dolwyddelan Castle in North Wales.  Although Llywelyn had many family connections to royalty, it would not offer him any more of a chance to gain a position of power.  In his early years, Llywelyn's primary enemy would be his uncle, Dafydd.  Dafydd had already killed his own brother and seized control of Gwynedd in Northwest Wales by the time Llywelyn was 22.  However, Dafydd gained many enemies throughout his ordeals.  Llywelyn led a successful revolution against Dafydd and defeated him in a battle at Aberconwy.  Llywelyn was not selfish, and showed early signs of his diplomatic skills by sharing the power of Gwynedd with is cousins.  Llywelyn ruled Dafydd's lands east of the Conwy River. [PARAGRAPH: 1] In the year 1200, Llywelyn's cousin Gruffud died.  Llywelyn now felt he had the power to move against Maredudd, his other cousin, and claimed to be the overlord of the whole of North Wales by expelling him from Llyn and capturing a strategic castle.  Llywelyn lead another invasion into Southern Powys, a territory of Gwenwynwyn, another Welsh opponent. [PARAGRAPH: 1] By 1205, King John of England recognized the power of the Welsh prince, and offered his daughter Joan in marriage.  The alliance caused the arrest of Gwenwynwyn, enabling Llywelyn to seize control of his lands.  The King eventually realized he had gone too far in his support of Llywelyn.  Llywelyn then attacked the lands of the Early of Chester, and King John was forced to go to war with Llywelyn.  The Welsh troops used guerilla tactics and took the English troop's food, leaving King John no choice but to return to England. [PARAGRAPH: 1] However, King John returned to Wales with a greater army.  The English Army cut right into the heart of Gwynedd, forcing Llywelyn to send his wife to negotiate for peace.  The terms of the peace were a serious set back for Llywelyn and he lost the right to lands east of the Conwy River. He was also made to forfeit 20,000 cattle and 40 horses to the English.  King John made other moves to prove his takeover of Whales, and the Welsh, under Llywelyn, captured all the English Forts to free themselves of the English. [PARAGRAPH: 1] After the English Barons were plotting against King John, he sought the help of the Welsh.  The Welsh gave no support to the king.  Llywelyn took the side of the enemies, and took over South Wales.  An Alliance between the Welsh and the Anglo Normans make certain that there would be peace on the borders would be maintained.  After King John died, his son King Henry III made a treaty with Llywelyn.  Llywelyn knew that maintaining the whole of Wales would be difficult, so put other Princes and overlords in charge of districts, but still keeping the position of Overlord for himself.  Disputes with the Earl of Pembroke weakened Llywelyn, and only ended when the new Early of Pembroke formed an alliance with the Welsh.  [PARAGRAPH: 1] The treaties signed kept a peace in Wales until his death in 1240, at the age of 68.  He died at the abbey of Aberconwy and was buried there.  </English>
		<French>[H1]Llywelyn le Grand[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Prince de Gwynedd[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Vécu:[\BOLD]c.1173  - 1240[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:1][BOLD]Fond:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Llywelyn Fawr, ou Llywelyn le Grand, est né en Dolwyddelan Castle dans le nord du pays de Galles. Bien que l'Inde avait de nombreux liens avec la famille royale, il ne serait pas lui offrir plus d'une chance d'acquérir une position de pouvoir. Dans ses premières années, Llywelyn le principal ennemi serait son oncle, Dafydd. Dafydd avait déjà tué son frère et a pris le contrôle de Gwynedd, au nord-ouest du pays de Galles au moment Llywelyn était 22. Toutefois, de nombreux ennemis Dafydd acquise tout au long de ses épreuves. Llywelyn il a réussi un Dafydd révolution contre lui et défait dans une bataille à Aberconwy. Llywelyn n'était pas égoïste, et a montré des signes précoces de ses talents de diplomate en partageant le pouvoir de Gwynedd est avec des cousins. Llywelyn statué Dafydd les terres de l'est de la rivière Conwy. [PARAGRAPH: 1] En l'an 1200, Llywelyn cousin Gruffud décédés. Llywelyn maintenant estimé qu'il avait le pouvoir d'aller contre Maredudd, son autre cousine, et prétend être le maître de l'ensemble du nord du pays de Galles par l'expulsion de Llyn et de la capture stratégique château. Llywelyn entraîner une autre invasion du sud du Powys, un territoire de Gwenwynwyn, un autre adversaire gallois. [PARAGRAPH: 1] En 1205, le roi Jean d'Angleterre a reconnu le pouvoir du prince-évêque gallois, et il a offert sa fille en mariage Joan. L'alliance provoqué l'arrestation de Gwenwynwyn, Llywelyn permettant de s'emparer de ses terres. Le Roi finalement rendu compte qu'il était allé trop loin dans son soutien de Llywelyn. Llywelyn ensuite attaqué les terres de la petite de Chester, et le roi Jean a été forcé d'entrer en guerre avec Llywelyn. Le Welsh troupes utilisé des tactiques de guérilla et a pris les Anglais fournissent la nourriture, John King laissant pas d'autre choix que de retourner en Angleterre. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Toutefois, le Roi John a regagné le Pays de Galles avec une plus grande armée. L'anglais Armée coupe droite dans le coeur de Gwynedd, Llywelyn forcer à envoyer sa femme à négocier pour la paix. Les termes de la paix ont été un grave revers pour le Maroc et il a perdu le droit à des terres est de la rivière Conwy. Il a également été fait pour confisquer 20.000 bovins et 40 chevaux à l'anglais. John King fait d'autres coups de prouver son rachat de baleines, et le gallois, en vertu de Llywelyn, capturé tous les Français Forts de se libérer de l'anglais. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Après l'anglais Barons ont comploté contre le roi Jean, il a demandé l'aide de la Welsh. Le Welsh a donné aucun soutien au roi. Llywelyn a pris le parti de leurs ennemis, et a pris la relève du Sud. Une Alliance entre le gallois et l'Anglo Normands faire certains qu'il n'y aura de paix sur les frontières serait maintenu. Après John King est mort, son fils Henri III fait un traité avec l'Inde. Llywelyn savait que le maintien de l'ensemble du pays de Galles serait difficile, pour mettre les autres Princes et overlords en charge des quartiers, mais en gardant la position de Overlord pour lui-même. Différends avec le comte de Pembroke Llywelyn affaibli, et seulement pris fin lorsque le nouveau début de Pembroke formé une alliance avec le gallois. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Les traités de paix signés conservés au Pays de Galles jusqu'à sa mort, en 1240, à l'âge de 68. Il est décédé à l'abbaye d'Aberconwy et a été enterré.</French>
		<German>[H1]Llywelyn das Große[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Prinz von Gwynedd[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Gelebt:[\BOLD]c.1173  - 1240[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:1][BOLD]Hintergrund:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Llywelyn Fawr oder Llywelyn der Große, war geboren in der Dolwyddelan Schloss in North Wales. Obwohl Llywelyn Familie hatte viele Verbindungen zu Lizenzgebühren, wäre es ihm nicht mehr eine Chance, zu einer Position der Macht. In seinen frühen Jahren, in erster Linie Llywelyn Feind würde sein Onkel, Dafydd. Dafydd hatte bereits seinen eigenen Bruder getötet und beschlagnahmt Kontrolle von Gwynedd im Nordwesten von Wales Llywelyn der Zeit wurde 22. Allerdings Dafydd sich viele Feinde in seiner bestehen. Llywelyn führte eine erfolgreiche Revolution gegen Dafydd und besiegt ihn in der Schlacht bei Aberconwy. Llywelyn war nicht egoistisch, und zeigte erste Anzeichen seiner diplomatischen Fähigkeiten durch die Aufteilung der Macht von Gwynedd mit Vettern ist. Dafydd Llywelyn entschieden, die Grundstücke östlich des Conwy River. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Im Jahr 1200, Llywelyn's Cousin Gruffud gestorben. Llywelyn jetzt fühlte er hatte die Macht, sich gegen Maredudd, seine anderen Cousin, und behauptet, dass der Oberherr der gesamten North Wales durch die Ausweisung von ihm Llyn und Aufzeichnung einer strategischen Burg. Llywelyn führen anderen Invasion in Southern Powys, ein Gebiet von Gwenwynwyn, Welsh anderen Gegner. [PARAGRAPH: 1] 1205, König Johann von England anerkannte die Macht des walisischen Prinzen, und bot seine Tochter Joan in der Ehe. Die Allianz führte zur Festnahme von Gwenwynwyn, damit Llywelyn zu ergreifen, die Kontrolle über seine Grundstücke. Der König schließlich realisierte er zu weit gegangen in seiner Unterstützung von Llywelyn. Llywelyn dann angegriffen dem Boden in der Frühe von Chester, und König John war gezwungen, in den Krieg mit Llywelyn. Die walisische Truppen verwendet Guerilla-Taktik und nahm die englische Truppenstärke der Nahrung, so dass King John keine andere Wahl, als die Rückkehr nach England. [PARAGRAPH: 1] jedoch, King John zurück nach Wales mit einer größeren Armee. Die englische Armee Schnitt rechts in die Herzen von Gwynedd, Llywelyn zwingen zu senden seiner Frau für den Frieden zu verhandeln. Die Bedingungen des Friedens waren eine schwere Rückschlag für Llywelyn und verlor er das Recht auf Land östlich des Flusses Conwy. Er wurde auch zu verfallen 20.000 Rinder und 40 Pferde, die Englisch. King John aus anderen zieht um seine Übernahme der Wale, und der Welsh, unter Llywelyn, gefangen aller englischen Forts, die sich der englischen. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Nach der englischen Barons wurden Verschwörung gegen König John, suchte er die Hilfe der Waliser. Der Waliser hat keine Unterstützung für den König. Llywelyn nahm der Seite der Feinde, und übernahm South Wales. Eine Allianz zwischen dem Waliser und der Anglo Normannen stellen sicher, dass es den Frieden auf die Grenzen würde beibehalten werden. Nach King John starb, wurde sein Sohn König Heinrich III, die einen Vertrag mit Llywelyn. Llywelyn wusste, dass die Aufrechterhaltung der gesamten Wales wäre schwierig, so dass die anderen Fürsten und Herren in der Stadtteile, aber noch halten die Position von Overlord für sich. Streitigkeiten mit den Earl of Pembroke Llywelyn geschwächt, und erst beendet, wenn der neue Early von Pembroke ein Bündnis mit der walisischen. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Die Verträge unterzeichnet haben eine Frieden in Wales bis zu seinem Tod im Jahre 1240, im Alter von 68. Er starb in der Abtei von Aberconwy und wurde dort begraben.</German>
		<Italian>[H1]Llywelyn il Grande[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Principe di Gwynedd[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Vivo:[\BOLD]c.1173  - 1240[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:1][BOLD]Priorità bassa:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Llywelyn Fawr, o Llywelyn il Grande, è nato in Dolwyddelan Castle nel nord del Galles. Sebbene Llywelyn avuto molti collegamenti con la famiglia di royalties, che non offrono alcun lui più di una possibilità di conquistare una posizione di potere. Nei suoi primi anni, il principale nemico Llywelyn sarebbe suo zio, Dafydd. Dafydd aveva già ucciso suo fratello e il controllo di Gwynedd sequestrate nel Galles nordoccidentale, al momento Llywelyn è stato 22. Tuttavia, Dafydd guadagnato molti nemici per tutta la sua prove. Llywelyn ha portato con successo contro la rivoluzione Dafydd e lo sconfitto in una battaglia a Aberconwy. Llywelyn non era egoista, e ha mostrato i primi segnali della sua abilità diplomatica per la condivisione del potere con Gwynedd è cugini. Llywelyn statuito Dafydd di terre ad est del fiume Conwy. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Nel 1200, Llywelyn cugino Gruffud morto. Llywelyn ora aveva sentito il potere di spostare Maredudd contro, il suo altro cugino, e sosteneva di essere il overlord di tutto il nord del Galles da espellere da lui Llyn e strategica acquisizione di un castello. Llywelyn condurre un'altra invasione in Powys Meridionale, un territorio di Gwenwynwyn, un altro gallese avversario. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Per 1205, re d'Inghilterra Giovanni riconosciuto il potere del principe del Galles, e ha offerto la sua figlia Joan nel matrimonio. L'alleanza ha causato l'arresto di Gwenwynwyn, Llywelyn consentendo di riprendere il controllo delle sue terre. Il Re eventualmente realizzato era andato troppo in là nel suo sostegno di Llywelyn. Llywelyn poi attaccato le terre dei primi di Chester, e King John, che è stato costretto a scendere in guerra con Llywelyn. Il gallese truppe usato tattiche di guerriglia e ha preso l'inglese truppe del cibo, lasciando Re Giovanni scelta, ma non per tornare in Inghilterra. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Tuttavia, Re Giovanni ritornò in Galles con un maggiore esercito. L'esercito inglese tagliare nel cuore di Gwynedd, costringendo Llywelyn per inviare la moglie a negoziare per la pace. I termini dell'accordo di pace sono stati un grave arretrato per Llywelyn e ha perso il diritto di terre ad est del fiume Conwy. E 'stato anche fatto incamerata 20.000 bovini e 40 cavalli per la lingua inglese. Re Giovanni fatto altre mosse per provare la sua acquisizione di balene, e il gallese, sotto Llywelyn, catturato tutti gli inglesi forti di liberarsi della lingua inglese. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Dopo gli inglesi sono stati Baroni complottare contro il re Giovanni, che egli ha sempre cercato l'aiuto del gallese. Il gallese ha dato alcun sostegno per il re. Llywelyn ha preso il lato dei nemici, e ha assunto Galles del Sud. Un'Alleanza tra i gallesi e la Anglo Normanni rendere certo che ci sarebbe la pace alle frontiere sarebbe mantenuto. Dopo il Re Giovanni morì, suo figlio Enrico III fatto un trattato con Llywelyn. Llywelyn sapeva che il mantenimento di tutto il Galles sarebbe difficile, in modo da mettere in altri Principi e padroni responsabili dei quartieri, ma sempre mantenendo la posizione di Overlord per se stesso. Controversie con il Conte di Pembroke Llywelyn indebolita, e si è conclusa solo quando il nuovo formato di Pembroke Early un'alleanza con il gallese. [PARAGRAPH: 1] I trattati di pace firmati conservati in Galles, fino alla sua morte nel 1240, all'età di 68. Morì a abbazia di Aberconwy e fu sepolto.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[H1]Llywelyn el Grande[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Príncipe de Gwynedd[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Vivido:[\BOLD]c.1173  - 1240[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:1][BOLD]Fondo:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Llywelyn Fawr, o Llywelyn el Grande, nació en Dolwyddelan Castle en el norte de Gales. Aunque Llywelyn había muchas conexiones con la familia de regalías, que no le ofrecen más de una oportunidad para obtener una posición de poder. En sus primeros años, Llywelyn principal del enemigo sería su tío, Dafydd. Dafydd ya habían asesinado a su propio hermano y tomado el control de Gwynedd en el noroeste de Gales por el momento Llywelyn fue 22. Sin embargo, Dafydd ganado muchos enemigos en todo su pruebas. Llywelyn encabezó una exitosa revolución contra Dafydd y le derrotó en una batalla en Aberconwy. Llywelyn no era egoísta, y mostró los primeros indicios de su capacidad diplomática por compartir el poder de Gwynedd es con primos. Llywelyn dictaminó Dafydd tierras del este del río Conwy. [PARAGRAPH: 1] En el año 1200, Llywelyn del primo Gruffud murió. Llywelyn ahora sentía que él tenía el poder de mover contra Maredudd, su otro primo, y se ha afirmado que a evitar la de todo el Norte de Gales por expulsión de Llyn y estratégico de la captura de un castillo. Llywelyn conducir otra invasión en el sur de Powys, un territorio de Gwenwynwyn, otro galés oponente. [PARAGRAPH: 1] En 1205, el rey Juan de Inglaterra reconoció el poder del príncipe de Gales, y ofreció a su hija Joan en el matrimonio. La alianza provocó la detención de Gwenwynwyn, lo que permite Llywelyn a tomar el control de sus tierras. El Rey cuenta de que el tiempo había ido demasiado lejos en su apoyo de Llywelyn. Llywelyn luego atacaron las tierras de los Temprana de Chester, y el Rey Juan se vio obligado a ir a la guerra con Llywelyn. El galés tropas utilizan tácticas de guerrilla y la toma de alimentos que aportan Inglés, dejando a King John no tiene más opción que regresar a Inglaterra. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Sin embargo, el Rey Juan regresó a Gales con un mayor del ejército. El corte Inglés Ejército de la derecha en el corazón de Gwynedd, lo que obligó a Llywelyn enviar a su esposa a negociar por la paz. Las condiciones de la paz son un serio retroceso para Llywelyn y perdió el derecho a las tierras al este del río Conwy. También fue obligado a renunciar a 20.000 bovinos y 40 caballos al Inglés. King John hecho otros movimientos para probar su toma de Ballenas, y la galesa, en virtud de Llywelyn, a todos los capturados Inglés Forts a liberarse del Inglés. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Después de la Barons Inglés estaban tramando en contra de John King, buscó la ayuda de los galeses. El galés negaron su apoyo al rey. Llywelyn tomó el lado de los enemigos, y se hizo cargo de Gales del Sur. Una alianza entre el galés y el Anglo normandos asegurarse de que no habría paz en las fronteras se mantendrían. Después de King John murió, su hijo el rey Enrique III hizo un tratado con Llywelyn. Llywelyn sabía que el mantenimiento de la totalidad de Gales sería difícil, de modo que los demás príncipes feudales y encargado de los barrios, pero aún se mantiene la posición de Overlord para sí mismo. Controversias con el conde de Pembroke debilitado Llywelyn, y sólo terminó cuando el nuevo temprana de Pembroke formado una alianza con los galeses. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Los tratados firmados mantenido una paz en el País de Gales hasta su muerte en 1240, a la edad de 68. Murió en la abadía de Aberconwy y fue enterrado allí.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_LLYWELYN_1</Tag>
		<English>Good day, I am [OUR_NAME] of the [OUR_EMPIRE].  I offer you my hostility!</English>
		<French>Bonne journée, j'ai un nom, [OUR_NAME], de même que mon empire, [OUR_EMPIRE]. J'ai mais deux souhaits, un est d'être dans la paix avec toi. La seconde est que vous ne devez jamais, d'être irrespectueuse en ma présence.</French>
		<German>Guter Tag, habe ich einen Namen, [OUR_NAME], wie mein Reich, [OUR_EMPIRE]. Ich habe, aber zwei Wünsche, man ist, im Frieden mit dir zu sein. Die Sekunde ist, daß du nie mußt, in meiner Anwesenheit disrespectful zu sein.</German>
		<Italian>Buon giorno, ho un nome, [OUR_NAME], come il mio impero, [OUR_EMPIRE]. Ho ma due desideri, uno è di essere nella pace con voi. Il secondo è che non dovete mai, di essere disrespectful nella mia presenza.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Buen día, tengo un nombre, [OUR_NAME], al igual que mi imperio, [OUR_EMPIRE]. Tengo pero dos deseos, uno son estar en paz con ti. El segundo es que nunca debes, ser irrespetuoso en mi presencia.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>							
</Civ4GameText>