<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by lcollins (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- Copyright Firaxis Games 2005 -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text - New -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_PILIAKALNIS</Tag>
		<English>Piliakalnis</English>
		<French>Piliakalnis</French>
		<German>Piliakalnis</German>
		<Italian>Piliakalnis</Italian>
		<Spanish>Piliakalnis</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
        <TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_PILIAKALNIS_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB] Piliakalniai are hill forts in ancient and medieval Lithuania.  The first piliakalniai are dated to the 1st millennium BC.  Most forts were refortified in later centuries against the constant invasions of the Teutonic Knights.  Most of the forts were located on the banks of a river, or where two rivers met.  The hill was often sculpted for defense, with flattened tops and steeper slopes.  The fortifications also were typically wooden, though some had stone or brick walls.  During the early years of the Grand Duchy of Lithuania, piliakalniai played a major role in battles against the Livonian Order and Teutonic Knights.  During that time, their construction decreased but they became stronger.  Their effectiveness decreased as firearms and cannons developed, and their numbers began to decline.</English>
		<French>[TAB] Piliakalniai sont collines fortifiées dans l'Antiquité et au Moyen Lituanie. La première piliakalniai sont à la date du 1er millénaire avant notre ère. Les plus forts sont refortified siècles plus tard, en constante contre les invasions des chevaliers teutoniques. La plupart des ouvrages sont situés sur les rives d'un fleuve, ou lorsque deux rivières remplies. La colline était souvent sculpté de la défense, avec des sommets aplatis et pentes plus raides. Les fortifications sont aussi généralement en bois, même si certains ont des murs de pierre ou de brique. Au cours des premières années du Grand-Duché de Lituanie, piliakalniai joué un rôle majeur dans les batailles contre l'Ordre livonien et les chevaliers teutoniques. Pendant ce temps, leur construction a augmenté, mais elles sont devenues plus fortes. Leur efficacité diminue à mesure que les armes à feu et de canons développés, et leur nombre a commencé à diminuer.</French>
		<German>[TAB] Piliakalniai Hügel sind Festungen in der Antike und Mittelalter Litauen. Die erste piliakalniai sind datiert auf das 1. Jahrtausend v. Chr.. Die meisten refortified Festungen wurden in späteren Jahrhunderten gegen die ständigen Invasionen der Deutschen Ritterorden. Die meisten Forts befanden sich am Ufer eines Flusses, wo zwei Flüsse oder erfüllt werden. Der Hügel wurde oft Skulpturen für Verteidigung, mit abgeflachtem Tops und steiler Hänge. Die Festung wurde in der Regel auch aus Holz, aber einige hatten Stein oder Ziegelwände. Während der frühen Jahre des Großfürstentums Litauen, piliakalniai spielte eine wichtige Rolle in der Schlacht gegen den Livländischen Ordens und Deutschen Ritterorden. Während dieser Zeit, deren Bau aber sie erhöht wurde stärker. Ihre Wirksamkeit zurückgegangen als Schusswaffen und Kanonen entwickelt, und ihre Zahl begann zu sinken.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB] Piliakalniai sono collina e antiche fortificazioni medievali e Lituania. Il primo piliakalniai sono datati al 1 ° millennio aC. La maggior parte delle fortezze erano refortified nei secoli successivi la costante contro le invasioni dei Cavalieri Teutonico. La maggior parte delle fortezze erano situato sulle rive di un fiume, o dove ha incontrato due fiumi. La collina è stata spesso scolpito per la difesa, con cime appiattite e pendenze. Anche le fortificazioni sono stati in genere di legno, anche se ha avuto alcuni muri in pietra o in mattoni. Durante i primi anni del Granducato di Lituania, piliakalniai svolto un ruolo importante nella battaglia contro la Livonian Ordine Teutonico e Cavalieri. Durante quel tempo, la loro costruzione è aumentato, ma è diventata più forte. La loro efficacia è diminuita, come armi da fuoco e cannoni sviluppato, e il loro numero ha iniziato a declinare.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB] Piliakalniai son fuertes en la colina de la antigua y medieval de Lituania. La primera fecha se piliakalniai a la 1 ª milenio antes de Cristo. Los más fuertes fueron refortified siglos más tarde en contra de las invasiones constantes Teutónica de los Caballeros. La mayoría de las fortalezas se encuentra en la orilla de un río, o en los que se reunió dos ríos. La colina era a menudo esculpida para la defensa, con cimas aplanadas y escarpadas laderas. Las fortificaciones fueron también típicamente de madera, aunque había algunos muros de piedra o ladrillo. Durante los primeros años de la Gran Ducado de Lituania, piliakalniai desempeñado un papel importante en las batallas contra el Livonian Orden Teutónica y Caballeros. Durante ese tiempo, el aumento de su construcción, sino que se convirtió en más fuerte. Su efectividad se redujo como las armas de fuego y cañones desarrollados, y su número empezó a disminuir.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
        <TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_PILIAKALNIS_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Piliakalnis[COLOR_REVERT], the Lithuanian replacement for the [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Castle[COLOR_REVERT], offers bonus health.</English>
		<French>Le [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]piliakalnis[COLOR_REVERT], équivalent lituanien du [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]château[COLOR_REVERT], procure un bonus de santé.</French>
		<German>Die [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Piliakalnis[COLOR_REVERT], die Litauische Ersatz für die [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Schloss[COLOR_REVERT], bietet bonus gesundheit.</German>
		<Italian>L'[COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Piliakalnis[COLOR_REVERT], la sostituzione Lituano per il [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Castello[COLOR_REVERT], offre bonus di salute.</Italian>
		<Spanish> El [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Piliakalnis[COLOR_REVERT], la sustitución de Lituano para el [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Castillo[COLOR_REVERT], ofrece bono de la salud. </Spanish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>