<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- Copyright Firaxis Games 2005 -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text Civilopedia CivLeaders -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<!-- CIVILIZATION INFOS -->
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_VENEZIA_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Venetian Empire</English>
		<French>Empire vénitien</French>
		<German>Venetian Empire</German>
		<Italian>Venetian Empire</Italian>
		<Spanish>Venetian Empire</Spanish>
	</TEXT>	
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_VENEZIA_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Venice</English>
		<French>Venice</French>
		<German>Venice</German>
		<Italian>Venice</Italian>
		<Spanish>Venice</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_VENEZIA_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Venetian</English>
		<French>Vénitien</French>
		<German>Venetian</German>
		<Italian>Venetian</Italian>
		<Spanish>Venetian</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_VENEZIA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The city of Venice originated as a collection of lagoon communities banded together for mutual defence from the Lombards, Huns and other barbarians as the power of the Romans dwindled in northern Italy. Sometime in the first decades of the eighth century, the people of the lagoon elected their first leader Ursus, who was confirmed by Byzantium and given the titles of hypatus and dux. He was the first historical "Doge" of Venice. Tradition, however, first attested in the early 11th century, states that the Venetians first proclaimed one Anafestus Paulicius doge in 697, though this story dates to no earlier than the chronicle of John the Deacon. Whatever the case, the first doges had their power base in Heraclea.[PARAGRAPH:1]In the High Middle Ages, Venice became extremely wealthy through its control of trade between Europe and the Levant, and began to expand into the Adriatic Sea and beyond. In 1084, Domenico Selvo personally led a fleet against the Normans, but he was defeated and lost 9 great galleys, the largest and most heavily armed ships in the Venetian war fleet. Venice was involved in the Crusades almost from the very beginning; 200 Venetian ships assisted in capturing the coastal cities of Syria after the First Crusade, and in 1123 they were granted virtual autonomy in the Kingdom of Jerusalem through the Pactum Warmundi. In 1110, Ordelafo Faliero personally commanded a Venetian fleet of 100 ships to assist Baldwin I of Jerusalem in capturing the city of Sidon. In the 12th century, the Venetians also gained extensive trading privileges in the Byzantine Empire and their ships often provided the Empire with a navy. In 1182 there was an anti-Western riot in Constantinople, of which the Venetians were the main targets. Many in the Empire had become jealous of Venetian power and influence, and thus, when in 1182 the pretender Andronikos I Komnenos marched on Constantinople, Venetian property was seized and the owners imprisoned or banished, an act which humiliated, and angered the Republic. The Venetian fleet was crucial to the transportation of the Fourth Crusade, but when the crusaders could not pay for the ships, the cunning and manipulative Doge Enrico Dandolo quickly exploited the situation and offered transport to the crusaders if they were to capture the Christian Dalmatian city of Zadar (Italian: Zara), which had rebelled against the Venetian rule in 1183, placed itself under the dual protection of the Papacy and King Emeric of Hungary and had proven too well fortified to retake for Venice alone. Upon accomplishing this the crusade was again diverted to Constantinople, the capital of the Byzantine Empire, another rival of Venice in revenge for the 1182 massacre of Venetian citizens living in Constantinople. The city was captured and sacked in 1204 in a daring sea attack; the sack has been described as one of the most profitable and disgraceful sacks of a city in history.  For the following six decades, the latins held sway in Constantinople, ruling it.  The Byzantine Empire, which until 1204 had resisted several attacks and kept the Islamic invaders out of Western Anatolia and the Balkans, was re-established in 1261 by Michael VIII Palaiologos but never recovered its previous power. The Venetians, who accompanied the crusader fleet, claimed much of the plunder, including the famous four bronze horses which were brought back to adorn Basillica San Marco. As a result of the subsequent partition of the Byzantine Empire, Venice gained a great deal of territory in the Aegean Sea (three-eighths of the Byzantine Empire), including the islands of Crete and Euboea. The Aegean islands came to form the Venetian Duchy of the Archipelago. In 1295, Pietro Gradenigo sent a fleet of 68 ships to attack a Genoese fleet at Alexandretta, then another fleet of 100 ships were sent to attack the Genoese in 1299. From 1350 to 1381, Venice fought an intermittent war with the Genoese. Initially defeated, they devastated the Genoese fleet at the Battle of Chioggia in 1380 and retained their prominent position in eastern Mediterranean affairs at the expense of Genoa's declining empire. [PARAGRAPH:1]In the early fifteenth century, the Venetians also began to expand in Italy, as well as along the Dalmatian coast from Istria to Albania, which was acquired from King Ladislas of Naples during the civil war in Hungary. Ladislas was about to lose the conflict and had decided to escape to Naples, but before doing so he agreed to sell his now practically forfeit rights on the Dalmatian cities for a meager sum of 100,000 Ducati. Venice exploited the situation and quickly installed nobility to govern the area, for example, Count Filippo Stipanov in Zadar. This move by the Venetians was a response to the threatening expansion of Giangaleazzo Visconti, Duke of Milan. Control over the north-east main land routes was also a necessity for the safety of the trades. By 1410, Venice had a navy of 3,300 ships (manned by 36,000 men) and taken over most of Venetia, including such important cities as Verona, Vicenza and Padua. The situation in Dalmatia had been settled in 1408 by a truce with King Sigismund of Hungary but the difficulties of Hungary finally granted to the Republic the consolidation of its Adriatic dominions. At the expiration of the truce, Venice immediately invaded the Patriarchate of Aquileia, and subjected Traù, Spalato, Durazzo and other Dalmatian cities. In February 1489, the island of Cyprus, previously a crusader state (the Kingdom of Cyprus), was annexed to Venice. The Battle of Lepanto, on 7 October 1571, ensued when a galley fleet of the Holy League, a coalition of Spain (including their territories of Naples, Sicily and Sardinia), the Republic of Venice, the Papacy (under St. Pope Pius V), the Republic of Genoa, the Duchy of Savoy, the Knights Hospitaller and others, decisively defeated the main fleet of Ottoman war galleys.  The Venetian forces fought brilliantly and were the driving force behind the crucial victory that turned the tide against the Ottoman Empire for good.  The five-hour battle was fought at the northern edge of the Gulf of Patras, off western Greece, where the Ottoman forces sailing westwards from their naval station in Lepanto met the Holy League forces, which had come from Messina. [PARAGRAPH:1]In December 1714, the Turks declared war when the Peloponnese (the Morea) was "without any of those supplies which are so desirable even in countries where aid is near at hand which are not liable to attack from the sea". The Turks took the islands of Tinos and Aegina, crossed the isthmus and took Corinth. Daniele Dolfin, commander of the Venetian fleet, thought it better to save the fleet than risk it for the Morea. When he eventually arrived on the scene, Nauplia, Modon, Corone and Malvasia had fallen. Levkas in the Ionian islands, and the bases of Spinalonga and Suda on Crete which still remained in Venetian hands, were abandoned. The Turks finally landed on Corfù, but its defenders managed to throw them back. In the meantime, the Turks had suffered a grave defeat by the Austrians at Battle of Petrovaradin on 5 August 1716. Venetian naval efforts in the Aegean and the Dardanelles in 1717 and 1718, however, met with little success. With the Treaty of Passarowitz (21 July 1718), Austria made large territorial gains, but Venice lost the Morea, for which its small gains in Albania and Dalmatia were little compensation. This was the last war with the Ottoman Empire. By the year 1792, the once great Venetian merchant fleet had declined to a mere 309 merchantmen. [PARAGRAPH:1]By 1796, the Republic of Venice could no longer defend itself since its war fleet numbered only 4 galleys and 7 galliots. In spring 1796, Piedmont fell and the Austrians were beaten from Montenotte to Lodi. The army under Bonaparte crossed the frontiers of neutral Venice in pursuit of the enemy. By the end of the year the French troops were occupying the Venetian state up to the Adige. Vicenza, Cadore and Friuli were held by the Austrians. With the campaigns of the next year, Napoleon aimed for the Austrian possessions across the Alps. Napoleans forces moved into Venezia without firing a shot, and the city's 1,000 year empire collapsed as an independent entity.  In the preliminaries to the Peace of Leoben, the terms of which remained secret, the Austrians were to take the Venetian possessions as the price of peace (18 April 1797).</English>
		<French>[TAB]La ville de Venise doit son origine à la réunion de plusieurs communautés sur la lagune s'unissant pour faire défense commune face aux Lombards, Huns and autres barbares alors que déclinait le pouvoir romain en Italie du Nord. Au cours des premières décades du 8ème siècle, le peuple de la lagune élut son premier leader, Ursus, qui fut confirmé par les Byzantins qui lui accordèrent les titres d'hypatus et de dux. Il fut le premier "doge" historique de Venise. La tradition, toutefois, attestée pour la première fois au début du 11ème siècle, rapporte que les Vénitiens proclamèrent pour la première fois doge un certain Anafestus Paulicius en 697, bien que cette histoire ne soit pas relatée avant les chroniques de Jean Diacre. Quel que soit la vérité, le premier doge avait son pouvoir basé à Héracléa.[PARAGRAPH:1]Au Moyen-Age, Venise devient extrêmement riche grâce à son contrôle sur le commerce entre l'Europe et l'Orient, et commença son expansion en Mer Adriatique et au delà. En 1084, Domenico Selvo commanda personnellement une flotte contre les Normands, mais fut vaincu et perdit 9 grandes galères, les navires les plus larges et les plus lourdement armés de la flotte vénitienne. Venise fut impliquée dans les croisades dès leur début. Ainsi, 200 navires vénitiens contribuèrent à la capture des cités costales de Syrie après la 1ère Croisade, et en 1123, ils accordèrent une autonomie virtuelle au royaume de Jérusalem grâce au Warmundi. En 1110, Ordelafo Faliero commanda une flotte vénitienne de 100 navires pour aider Beaudouin Ier de Jérusalem à capturer la ville de Sidon. Au 12ème siècle, les  Vénitiens obtinrent des privilèges commerciaux étendus avec l'Empire Byzantin et leurs navires soutenaient régulièrement la flotte byzantine. En 1182, il y eu un soulèvement anti-occidental à Constantinople, dont les Vénitiens furent la principale cible. Beaucoup, au sein de l'Empire, étaient jaloux du pouvoir et de l'influence vénitienne. Aussi, lorsqu'en 1182, le prétendant au trône Andronikos I Komnenos marcha sur Constantinople, les biens vénitiens furent saisis et leurs propriétaires emprisonnés ou bannis. Ce fut un acte qui humilia et mit en colère la République. La flotte vénitienne était cruciale au transport de la 4ème Croisade, mais lorsque les croisés ne purent payer les navires, le malin et manipulateur doge Enrico Dandolo exploita rapidement la situation et offrit le transport aux croisés en échange de la capture de la ville chrétienne dalmate de Zara (actuellement Zadar en Croatie), qui s'était rebellée contre les vénitiens en 1183, se plaçant sous la double protection de la Papauté et du roi Emeric de Hongrie et qui était bien trop fortifiée pour les Vénitiens puissent la reprendre seuls. Après l'accomplissement de cette tâche, la croisade fut déroutée vers Constantinople, la capitale de l'Empire Byzantin, en vengeance du massacre des citoyens vénitiens vivants dans la ville en 1182. La ville fut capturée et mise à sac en 1204 grâce à une attaque navale osée. Le pillage de la ville fut décrit comme étant l'un des plus honteux et profitables pillage de l'Histoire. Au cours des six décades suivantes, les occidentaux tinrent Constantinople en la gouvernant. L'Empire Byzantin, qui avait résisté depuis 1204 à plusieurs attaques et tenus en échec les invasions islamiques en Anatolie occidentale et dans les Balkans, fut rétablit en 1261 par Michel VIII Paléologue mais ne retrouva jamais sa puissance antérieure. Les Vénitiens, qui accompagnaient la flotte croisée, réclamèrent la majeure partie du butin, dont notamment les fameux chevaux en bronze qui ornent la Basilique Saint Marc. En conséquence de la partition de l'Empire Byzantin, Venise récupéra de grands territoires en Mer Egée (les 3/8 de l'Empire Byzantin), dont les îles de Crète et d'Eubée. Les îles égéennes formèrent le Duché Vénitien de l'Archipel. En 1295, Pietro Gradenigo envoya une flotte de 68 navires attaquer la flotte génoise à Alexandretta, puis une nouvelle flotte de 100 navires furent envoyée attaquer les Génois en 1299. De 1350 à 1381, Venise se battit lors de plusieurs guerres contre les Génois pour le contrôle du commerce oriental. Défait initialement, ils dévastèrent la flotte génoise à la bataille de Chioggia en 1380 et gardèrent leur position dominante dans le commerce en Méditerranée occidentale aux dépends de l'empire génois, désormais déclinant. [PARAGRAPH:1]Au début du 15ème siècle, les Vénitiens commencèrent à s'étendre aussi en Italie, ainsi que le long de côte dalmatienne de l'Istrie jusqu'à l'Albanie, qui avait été acquise du roi Ladislas de Naples pendant la guerre civile en Hongrie. Ladislas était sur le point de perdre le conflit et avait décidé de s'enfuir à Naples, mais avant de le faire il accepta de vendre ses droits quasiment perdus sur les cités dalmates pour la maigre somme de 100 000 ducats. Venise exploita la situation et installa rapidement une noblesse pour gouverner la région, comme par exemple le comte Filippo Stipanov à Zara. Ce mouvement était la réponse vénitienne à l'expansion menaçante de Giangaleazzo Visconti, duc de Milan, car le contrôle des principales routes du nord-est était aussi une nécessité pour la sauvegarde du commerce. En 1410, Venise disposait d'une marine de 3300 navires (armés de 36 000 hommes) et avait prit le contrôle de la majeure partie de la Vénétie, dont les importantes villes de Vérone, Vicenza et Padoue. La situation en Dalmatie avait été réglée en 1408 par un cessez-le-feu avec le roi Sigismond de Hongrie mais les difficultés hongroises accordèrent finalement à la République un plein et entier contrôle sur ses possessions adriatiques. Dès la fin du cessez-le-feu, Venise envahit immédiatement le patriarcat d'Aquilée et soumit Traù, Spalato, Durazzo et les autres cités dalmates. En février 1489, l'île de Chypre, anciennement état croisé (le royaume de Chypre), fut annexé par Venise. La bataille de Lépante, le 7 octobre 1571, opposa la flotte de galères de la Sainte Ligue, une coalition comprenant l'Espagne (ainsi que ses territoires de Naples, Sicile et Sardaigne), la République de Venise, la Papauté (sous le pape Pie V), la République de Gênes, le duché de Savoie, les Chevaliers Hospitaliers et d'autres, et la flotte principale ottomane composée de galères de guerre. Les forces vénitiennes combattirent brillamment et furent l'atout majeur de la victoire cruciale qui arrêta la marche de l'Empire Ottoman. La bataille, qui dura 5 heures, se déroula au nord du golfe de Patras, en Grèce occidentale, alors que les forces ottomanes faisaient voiles vers l'ouest depuis leur port de Lépante où elles rencontrèrent les forces de la Sainte Ligue qui venaient de Messine. [PARAGRAPH:1]En décembre 1714, les Turcs déclarèrent la guerre lorsque le Péloponnèse (la Morée) était "sans aucun de ces soutiens qui sont si désirables même dans les pays où l'aide est à portée de main mais qui sont pas assujettis à une attaque par la mer". Les Turcs prirent les îles de Tinos et d'Aegina, traversèrent l'isthme et prirent Corinthe. Daniele Dolfin, commandant de la flotte vénitienne, pensa qu'il valait mieux sauver la flotte que de la risquer pour la Morée. Lorsqu'il arriva finalement sur place, Nauplia, Modon, Corone et Malvasia étaient déjà tombées. Levkas, dans les îles Ioniennes, ainsi que les bases de Spinalonga et de Suda en Crète furent abandonnées bien qu'elles fussent restées dans les mains vénitiennes. Les Turcs débarquèrent finalement à Corfou, mais les défenseurs réussirent à les repousser. Dans le même temps, les Turcs souffrirent une violente défaite par les Autrichiens à la bataille de Petrovaradin le 5 août 1716. Les efforts navals vénitiens en Mer Egée et dans les Dardanelles en 1717 et 1718, cependant, rencontrèrent quelques succès. Par le traité de Passarowitz (signé le 21 juillet 1718), l'Autriche obtint de substantiels gains territoriaux mais Venise perdit la Morée, pour laquelle en comparaison les petits gains en Albanie et Dalmatie furent une piètre compensation. Ce fut la dernière guerre avec l'Empire Ottoman. En 1792, la flotte marchande vénitienne qui fut jadis si grande, déclina jusqu'à 309 navires. [PARAGRAPH:1]En 1796, la République de Venise n'était plus capable de se défendre seule puisque sa flotte de guerre ne comptait plus que 4 galères et 7 galiotes. Au cours du printemps 1796, le Piémont tomba et les Autrichiens furent vaincus de Montenotte jusqu'à Lodi. L'armée de Bonaparte traversa les frontières de Venise, pourtant neutre, à la poursuite de l'ennemi. A la fin de l'année les troupes françaises occupèrent l'état vénitien jusqu'à l'Adige. Les villes de Vicenza, Cadore et Friule étaient tenus, elles, par les Autrichiens. Lors des campagnes de l'année suivante, Napoléon visa les possessions autrichiennes au delà des Alpes. Les forces napoléoniennes firent mouvement en Vénétie sans tirer aucun coup de feu, et la cité d'un empire vieux de 1000 ans perdit son indépendance. En préliminaires à la paix de Leoben, dans des termes qui devaient rester secrets, les Autrichiens devaient récupérer les possessions vénitiennes en échange de la paix (18 April 1797).</French>
		<German>[TAB]The city of Venice originated as a collection of lagoon communities banded together for mutual defence from the Lombards, Huns and other barbarians as the power of the Romans dwindled in northern Italy. Sometime in the first decades of the eighth century, the people of the lagoon elected their first leader Ursus, who was confirmed by Byzantium and given the titles of hypatus and dux. He was the first historical "Doge" of Venice. Tradition, however, first attested in the early 11th century, states that the Venetians first proclaimed one Anafestus Paulicius doge in 697, though this story dates to no earlier than the chronicle of John the Deacon. Whatever the case, the first doges had their power base in Heraclea.[PARAGRAPH:1]In the High Middle Ages, Venice became extremely wealthy through its control of trade between Europe and the Levant, and began to expand into the Adriatic Sea and beyond. In 1084, Domenico Selvo personally led a fleet against the Normans, but he was defeated and lost 9 great galleys, the largest and most heavily armed ships in the Venetian war fleet. Venice was involved in the Crusades almost from the very beginning; 200 Venetian ships assisted in capturing the coastal cities of Syria after the First Crusade, and in 1123 they were granted virtual autonomy in the Kingdom of Jerusalem through the Pactum Warmundi. In 1110, Ordelafo Faliero personally commanded a Venetian fleet of 100 ships to assist Baldwin I of Jerusalem in capturing the city of Sidon. In the 12th century, the Venetians also gained extensive trading privileges in the Byzantine Empire and their ships often provided the Empire with a navy. In 1182 there was an anti-Western riot in Constantinople, of which the Venetians were the main targets. Many in the Empire had become jealous of Venetian power and influence, and thus, when in 1182 the pretender Andronikos I Komnenos marched on Constantinople, Venetian property was seized and the owners imprisoned or banished, an act which humiliated, and angered the Republic. The Venetian fleet was crucial to the transportation of the Fourth Crusade, but when the crusaders could not pay for the ships, the cunning and manipulative Doge Enrico Dandolo quickly exploited the situation and offered transport to the crusaders if they were to capture the Christian Dalmatian city of Zadar (Italian: Zara), which had rebelled against the Venetian rule in 1183, placed itself under the dual protection of the Papacy and King Emeric of Hungary and had proven too well fortified to retake for Venice alone. Upon accomplishing this the crusade was again diverted to Constantinople, the capital of the Byzantine Empire, another rival of Venice in revenge for the 1182 massacre of Venetian citizens living in Constantinople. The city was captured and sacked in 1204 in a daring sea attack; the sack has been described as one of the most profitable and disgraceful sacks of a city in history.  For the following six decades, the latins held sway in Constantinople, ruling it.  The Byzantine Empire, which until 1204 had resisted several attacks and kept the Islamic invaders out of Western Anatolia and the Balkans, was re-established in 1261 by Michael VIII Palaiologos but never recovered its previous power. The Venetians, who accompanied the crusader fleet, claimed much of the plunder, including the famous four bronze horses which were brought back to adorn Basillica San Marco. As a result of the subsequent partition of the Byzantine Empire, Venice gained a great deal of territory in the Aegean Sea (three-eighths of the Byzantine Empire), including the islands of Crete and Euboea. The Aegean islands came to form the Venetian Duchy of the Archipelago. In 1295, Pietro Gradenigo sent a fleet of 68 ships to attack a Genoese fleet at Alexandretta, then another fleet of 100 ships were sent to attack the Genoese in 1299. From 1350 to 1381, Venice fought an intermittent war with the Genoese. Initially defeated, they devastated the Genoese fleet at the Battle of Chioggia in 1380 and retained their prominent position in eastern Mediterranean affairs at the expense of Genoa's declining empire. [PARAGRAPH:1]In the early fifteenth century, the Venetians also began to expand in Italy, as well as along the Dalmatian coast from Istria to Albania, which was acquired from King Ladislas of Naples during the civil war in Hungary. Ladislas was about to lose the conflict and had decided to escape to Naples, but before doing so he agreed to sell his now practically forfeit rights on the Dalmatian cities for a meager sum of 100,000 Ducati. Venice exploited the situation and quickly installed nobility to govern the area, for example, Count Filippo Stipanov in Zadar. This move by the Venetians was a response to the threatening expansion of Giangaleazzo Visconti, Duke of Milan. Control over the north-east main land routes was also a necessity for the safety of the trades. By 1410, Venice had a navy of 3,300 ships (manned by 36,000 men) and taken over most of Venetia, including such important cities as Verona, Vicenza and Padua. The situation in Dalmatia had been settled in 1408 by a truce with King Sigismund of Hungary but the difficulties of Hungary finally granted to the Republic the consolidation of its Adriatic dominions. At the expiration of the truce, Venice immediately invaded the Patriarchate of Aquileia, and subjected Traù, Spalato, Durazzo and other Dalmatian cities. In February 1489, the island of Cyprus, previously a crusader state (the Kingdom of Cyprus), was annexed to Venice. The Battle of Lepanto, on 7 October 1571, ensued when a galley fleet of the Holy League, a coalition of Spain (including their territories of Naples, Sicily and Sardinia), the Republic of Venice, the Papacy (under St. Pope Pius V), the Republic of Genoa, the Duchy of Savoy, the Knights Hospitaller and others, decisively defeated the main fleet of Ottoman war galleys.  The Venetian forces fought brilliantly and were the driving force behind the crucial victory that turned the tide against the Ottoman Empire for good.  The five-hour battle was fought at the northern edge of the Gulf of Patras, off western Greece, where the Ottoman forces sailing westwards from their naval station in Lepanto met the Holy League forces, which had come from Messina. [PARAGRAPH:1]In December 1714, the Turks declared war when the Peloponnese (the Morea) was "without any of those supplies which are so desirable even in countries where aid is near at hand which are not liable to attack from the sea". The Turks took the islands of Tinos and Aegina, crossed the isthmus and took Corinth. Daniele Dolfin, commander of the Venetian fleet, thought it better to save the fleet than risk it for the Morea. When he eventually arrived on the scene, Nauplia, Modon, Corone and Malvasia had fallen. Levkas in the Ionian islands, and the bases of Spinalonga and Suda on Crete which still remained in Venetian hands, were abandoned. The Turks finally landed on Corfù, but its defenders managed to throw them back. In the meantime, the Turks had suffered a grave defeat by the Austrians at Battle of Petrovaradin on 5 August 1716. Venetian naval efforts in the Aegean and the Dardanelles in 1717 and 1718, however, met with little success. With the Treaty of Passarowitz (21 July 1718), Austria made large territorial gains, but Venice lost the Morea, for which its small gains in Albania and Dalmatia were little compensation. This was the last war with the Ottoman Empire. By the year 1792, the once great Venetian merchant fleet had declined to a mere 309 merchantmen. [PARAGRAPH:1]By 1796, the Republic of Venice could no longer defend itself since its war fleet numbered only 4 galleys and 7 galliots. In spring 1796, Piedmont fell and the Austrians were beaten from Montenotte to Lodi. The army under Bonaparte crossed the frontiers of neutral Venice in pursuit of the enemy. By the end of the year the French troops were occupying the Venetian state up to the Adige. Vicenza, Cadore and Friuli were held by the Austrians. With the campaigns of the next year, Napoleon aimed for the Austrian possessions across the Alps. Napoleans forces moved into Venezia without firing a shot, and the city's 1,000 year empire collapsed as an independent entity.  In the preliminaries to the Peace of Leoben, the terms of which remained secret, the Austrians were to take the Venetian possessions as the price of peace (18 April 1797).</German>
		<Italian>[TAB]The city of Venice originated as a collection of lagoon communities banded together for mutual defence from the Lombards, Huns and other barbarians as the power of the Romans dwindled in northern Italy. Sometime in the first decades of the eighth century, the people of the lagoon elected their first leader Ursus, who was confirmed by Byzantium and given the titles of hypatus and dux. He was the first historical "Doge" of Venice. Tradition, however, first attested in the early 11th century, states that the Venetians first proclaimed one Anafestus Paulicius doge in 697, though this story dates to no earlier than the chronicle of John the Deacon. Whatever the case, the first doges had their power base in Heraclea.[PARAGRAPH:1]In the High Middle Ages, Venice became extremely wealthy through its control of trade between Europe and the Levant, and began to expand into the Adriatic Sea and beyond. In 1084, Domenico Selvo personally led a fleet against the Normans, but he was defeated and lost 9 great galleys, the largest and most heavily armed ships in the Venetian war fleet. Venice was involved in the Crusades almost from the very beginning; 200 Venetian ships assisted in capturing the coastal cities of Syria after the First Crusade, and in 1123 they were granted virtual autonomy in the Kingdom of Jerusalem through the Pactum Warmundi. In 1110, Ordelafo Faliero personally commanded a Venetian fleet of 100 ships to assist Baldwin I of Jerusalem in capturing the city of Sidon. In the 12th century, the Venetians also gained extensive trading privileges in the Byzantine Empire and their ships often provided the Empire with a navy. In 1182 there was an anti-Western riot in Constantinople, of which the Venetians were the main targets. Many in the Empire had become jealous of Venetian power and influence, and thus, when in 1182 the pretender Andronikos I Komnenos marched on Constantinople, Venetian property was seized and the owners imprisoned or banished, an act which humiliated, and angered the Republic. The Venetian fleet was crucial to the transportation of the Fourth Crusade, but when the crusaders could not pay for the ships, the cunning and manipulative Doge Enrico Dandolo quickly exploited the situation and offered transport to the crusaders if they were to capture the Christian Dalmatian city of Zadar (Italian: Zara), which had rebelled against the Venetian rule in 1183, placed itself under the dual protection of the Papacy and King Emeric of Hungary and had proven too well fortified to retake for Venice alone. Upon accomplishing this the crusade was again diverted to Constantinople, the capital of the Byzantine Empire, another rival of Venice in revenge for the 1182 massacre of Venetian citizens living in Constantinople. The city was captured and sacked in 1204 in a daring sea attack; the sack has been described as one of the most profitable and disgraceful sacks of a city in history.  For the following six decades, the latins held sway in Constantinople, ruling it.  The Byzantine Empire, which until 1204 had resisted several attacks and kept the Islamic invaders out of Western Anatolia and the Balkans, was re-established in 1261 by Michael VIII Palaiologos but never recovered its previous power. The Venetians, who accompanied the crusader fleet, claimed much of the plunder, including the famous four bronze horses which were brought back to adorn Basillica San Marco. As a result of the subsequent partition of the Byzantine Empire, Venice gained a great deal of territory in the Aegean Sea (three-eighths of the Byzantine Empire), including the islands of Crete and Euboea. The Aegean islands came to form the Venetian Duchy of the Archipelago. In 1295, Pietro Gradenigo sent a fleet of 68 ships to attack a Genoese fleet at Alexandretta, then another fleet of 100 ships were sent to attack the Genoese in 1299. From 1350 to 1381, Venice fought an intermittent war with the Genoese. Initially defeated, they devastated the Genoese fleet at the Battle of Chioggia in 1380 and retained their prominent position in eastern Mediterranean affairs at the expense of Genoa's declining empire. [PARAGRAPH:1]In the early fifteenth century, the Venetians also began to expand in Italy, as well as along the Dalmatian coast from Istria to Albania, which was acquired from King Ladislas of Naples during the civil war in Hungary. Ladislas was about to lose the conflict and had decided to escape to Naples, but before doing so he agreed to sell his now practically forfeit rights on the Dalmatian cities for a meager sum of 100,000 Ducati. Venice exploited the situation and quickly installed nobility to govern the area, for example, Count Filippo Stipanov in Zadar. This move by the Venetians was a response to the threatening expansion of Giangaleazzo Visconti, Duke of Milan. Control over the north-east main land routes was also a necessity for the safety of the trades. By 1410, Venice had a navy of 3,300 ships (manned by 36,000 men) and taken over most of Venetia, including such important cities as Verona, Vicenza and Padua. The situation in Dalmatia had been settled in 1408 by a truce with King Sigismund of Hungary but the difficulties of Hungary finally granted to the Republic the consolidation of its Adriatic dominions. At the expiration of the truce, Venice immediately invaded the Patriarchate of Aquileia, and subjected Traù, Spalato, Durazzo and other Dalmatian cities. In February 1489, the island of Cyprus, previously a crusader state (the Kingdom of Cyprus), was annexed to Venice. The Battle of Lepanto, on 7 October 1571, ensued when a galley fleet of the Holy League, a coalition of Spain (including their territories of Naples, Sicily and Sardinia), the Republic of Venice, the Papacy (under St. Pope Pius V), the Republic of Genoa, the Duchy of Savoy, the Knights Hospitaller and others, decisively defeated the main fleet of Ottoman war galleys.  The Venetian forces fought brilliantly and were the driving force behind the crucial victory that turned the tide against the Ottoman Empire for good.  The five-hour battle was fought at the northern edge of the Gulf of Patras, off western Greece, where the Ottoman forces sailing westwards from their naval station in Lepanto met the Holy League forces, which had come from Messina. [PARAGRAPH:1]In December 1714, the Turks declared war when the Peloponnese (the Morea) was "without any of those supplies which are so desirable even in countries where aid is near at hand which are not liable to attack from the sea". The Turks took the islands of Tinos and Aegina, crossed the isthmus and took Corinth. Daniele Dolfin, commander of the Venetian fleet, thought it better to save the fleet than risk it for the Morea. When he eventually arrived on the scene, Nauplia, Modon, Corone and Malvasia had fallen. Levkas in the Ionian islands, and the bases of Spinalonga and Suda on Crete which still remained in Venetian hands, were abandoned. The Turks finally landed on Corfù, but its defenders managed to throw them back. In the meantime, the Turks had suffered a grave defeat by the Austrians at Battle of Petrovaradin on 5 August 1716. Venetian naval efforts in the Aegean and the Dardanelles in 1717 and 1718, however, met with little success. With the Treaty of Passarowitz (21 July 1718), Austria made large territorial gains, but Venice lost the Morea, for which its small gains in Albania and Dalmatia were little compensation. This was the last war with the Ottoman Empire. By the year 1792, the once great Venetian merchant fleet had declined to a mere 309 merchantmen. [PARAGRAPH:1]By 1796, the Republic of Venice could no longer defend itself since its war fleet numbered only 4 galleys and 7 galliots. In spring 1796, Piedmont fell and the Austrians were beaten from Montenotte to Lodi. The army under Bonaparte crossed the frontiers of neutral Venice in pursuit of the enemy. By the end of the year the French troops were occupying the Venetian state up to the Adige. Vicenza, Cadore and Friuli were held by the Austrians. With the campaigns of the next year, Napoleon aimed for the Austrian possessions across the Alps. Napoleans forces moved into Venezia without firing a shot, and the city's 1,000 year empire collapsed as an independent entity.  In the preliminaries to the Peace of Leoben, the terms of which remained secret, the Austrians were to take the Venetian possessions as the price of peace (18 April 1797).</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB]The city of Venice originated as a collection of lagoon communities banded together for mutual defence from the Lombards, Huns and other barbarians as the power of the Romans dwindled in northern Italy. Sometime in the first decades of the eighth century, the people of the lagoon elected their first leader Ursus, who was confirmed by Byzantium and given the titles of hypatus and dux. He was the first historical "Doge" of Venice. Tradition, however, first attested in the early 11th century, states that the Venetians first proclaimed one Anafestus Paulicius doge in 697, though this story dates to no earlier than the chronicle of John the Deacon. Whatever the case, the first doges had their power base in Heraclea.[PARAGRAPH:1]In the High Middle Ages, Venice became extremely wealthy through its control of trade between Europe and the Levant, and began to expand into the Adriatic Sea and beyond. In 1084, Domenico Selvo personally led a fleet against the Normans, but he was defeated and lost 9 great galleys, the largest and most heavily armed ships in the Venetian war fleet. Venice was involved in the Crusades almost from the very beginning; 200 Venetian ships assisted in capturing the coastal cities of Syria after the First Crusade, and in 1123 they were granted virtual autonomy in the Kingdom of Jerusalem through the Pactum Warmundi. In 1110, Ordelafo Faliero personally commanded a Venetian fleet of 100 ships to assist Baldwin I of Jerusalem in capturing the city of Sidon. In the 12th century, the Venetians also gained extensive trading privileges in the Byzantine Empire and their ships often provided the Empire with a navy. In 1182 there was an anti-Western riot in Constantinople, of which the Venetians were the main targets. Many in the Empire had become jealous of Venetian power and influence, and thus, when in 1182 the pretender Andronikos I Komnenos marched on Constantinople, Venetian property was seized and the owners imprisoned or banished, an act which humiliated, and angered the Republic. The Venetian fleet was crucial to the transportation of the Fourth Crusade, but when the crusaders could not pay for the ships, the cunning and manipulative Doge Enrico Dandolo quickly exploited the situation and offered transport to the crusaders if they were to capture the Christian Dalmatian city of Zadar (Italian: Zara), which had rebelled against the Venetian rule in 1183, placed itself under the dual protection of the Papacy and King Emeric of Hungary and had proven too well fortified to retake for Venice alone. Upon accomplishing this the crusade was again diverted to Constantinople, the capital of the Byzantine Empire, another rival of Venice in revenge for the 1182 massacre of Venetian citizens living in Constantinople. The city was captured and sacked in 1204 in a daring sea attack; the sack has been described as one of the most profitable and disgraceful sacks of a city in history.  For the following six decades, the latins held sway in Constantinople, ruling it.  The Byzantine Empire, which until 1204 had resisted several attacks and kept the Islamic invaders out of Western Anatolia and the Balkans, was re-established in 1261 by Michael VIII Palaiologos but never recovered its previous power. The Venetians, who accompanied the crusader fleet, claimed much of the plunder, including the famous four bronze horses which were brought back to adorn Basillica San Marco. As a result of the subsequent partition of the Byzantine Empire, Venice gained a great deal of territory in the Aegean Sea (three-eighths of the Byzantine Empire), including the islands of Crete and Euboea. The Aegean islands came to form the Venetian Duchy of the Archipelago. In 1295, Pietro Gradenigo sent a fleet of 68 ships to attack a Genoese fleet at Alexandretta, then another fleet of 100 ships were sent to attack the Genoese in 1299. From 1350 to 1381, Venice fought an intermittent war with the Genoese. Initially defeated, they devastated the Genoese fleet at the Battle of Chioggia in 1380 and retained their prominent position in eastern Mediterranean affairs at the expense of Genoa's declining empire. [PARAGRAPH:1]In the early fifteenth century, the Venetians also began to expand in Italy, as well as along the Dalmatian coast from Istria to Albania, which was acquired from King Ladislas of Naples during the civil war in Hungary. Ladislas was about to lose the conflict and had decided to escape to Naples, but before doing so he agreed to sell his now practically forfeit rights on the Dalmatian cities for a meager sum of 100,000 Ducati. Venice exploited the situation and quickly installed nobility to govern the area, for example, Count Filippo Stipanov in Zadar. This move by the Venetians was a response to the threatening expansion of Giangaleazzo Visconti, Duke of Milan. Control over the north-east main land routes was also a necessity for the safety of the trades. By 1410, Venice had a navy of 3,300 ships (manned by 36,000 men) and taken over most of Venetia, including such important cities as Verona, Vicenza and Padua. The situation in Dalmatia had been settled in 1408 by a truce with King Sigismund of Hungary but the difficulties of Hungary finally granted to the Republic the consolidation of its Adriatic dominions. At the expiration of the truce, Venice immediately invaded the Patriarchate of Aquileia, and subjected Traù, Spalato, Durazzo and other Dalmatian cities. In February 1489, the island of Cyprus, previously a crusader state (the Kingdom of Cyprus), was annexed to Venice. The Battle of Lepanto, on 7 October 1571, ensued when a galley fleet of the Holy League, a coalition of Spain (including their territories of Naples, Sicily and Sardinia), the Republic of Venice, the Papacy (under St. Pope Pius V), the Republic of Genoa, the Duchy of Savoy, the Knights Hospitaller and others, decisively defeated the main fleet of Ottoman war galleys.  The Venetian forces fought brilliantly and were the driving force behind the crucial victory that turned the tide against the Ottoman Empire for good.  The five-hour battle was fought at the northern edge of the Gulf of Patras, off western Greece, where the Ottoman forces sailing westwards from their naval station in Lepanto met the Holy League forces, which had come from Messina. [PARAGRAPH:1]In December 1714, the Turks declared war when the Peloponnese (the Morea) was "without any of those supplies which are so desirable even in countries where aid is near at hand which are not liable to attack from the sea". The Turks took the islands of Tinos and Aegina, crossed the isthmus and took Corinth. Daniele Dolfin, commander of the Venetian fleet, thought it better to save the fleet than risk it for the Morea. When he eventually arrived on the scene, Nauplia, Modon, Corone and Malvasia had fallen. Levkas in the Ionian islands, and the bases of Spinalonga and Suda on Crete which still remained in Venetian hands, were abandoned. The Turks finally landed on Corfù, but its defenders managed to throw them back. In the meantime, the Turks had suffered a grave defeat by the Austrians at Battle of Petrovaradin on 5 August 1716. Venetian naval efforts in the Aegean and the Dardanelles in 1717 and 1718, however, met with little success. With the Treaty of Passarowitz (21 July 1718), Austria made large territorial gains, but Venice lost the Morea, for which its small gains in Albania and Dalmatia were little compensation. This was the last war with the Ottoman Empire. By the year 1792, the once great Venetian merchant fleet had declined to a mere 309 merchantmen. [PARAGRAPH:1]By 1796, the Republic of Venice could no longer defend itself since its war fleet numbered only 4 galleys and 7 galliots. In spring 1796, Piedmont fell and the Austrians were beaten from Montenotte to Lodi. The army under Bonaparte crossed the frontiers of neutral Venice in pursuit of the enemy. By the end of the year the French troops were occupying the Venetian state up to the Adige. Vicenza, Cadore and Friuli were held by the Austrians. With the campaigns of the next year, Napoleon aimed for the Austrian possessions across the Alps. Napoleans forces moved into Venezia without firing a shot, and the city's 1,000 year empire collapsed as an independent entity.  In the preliminaries to the Peace of Leoben, the terms of which remained secret, the Austrians were to take the Venetian possessions as the price of peace (18 April 1797).</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<!-- BUILDING INFOS -->
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_ARSENAL</Tag>
		<English>Arsenal</English>
		<French>Arsenal</French>
		<German>Arsenal</German>
		<Italian>Arsenal</Italian>
		<Spanish>Arsenal</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_ARSENAL_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The Venetian Arsenal (Italian: Arsenale di Venezia) is a shipyard and naval depot that played a leading role in Venetian empire-building. It was one of the most important areas of Venice, lying in the Castello sestiere.[PARAGRAPH:1]The Byzantine-style establishment may have existed as early as the eighth century, though the present structure is usually said to have been begun in 1104 during the reign of Ordelafo Faliero, although there is no evidence for such a precise date. It definitely existed by the early thirteenth century and is mentioned in Dante's Inferno. The name probably comes from Arabic Dar al Sina’a ("Dockyard") and the concept was clearly Islamic as much as Byzantine. [PARAGRAPH:1]Initially the state dockyard worked merely to maintain naval ships built privately, but in 1320 the Arsenal Nuovo was built, much larger than the original. It enabled all the state's navy and the larger merchant ships to be both constructed and maintained in one place. The Arsenal incidentally became an important centre for rope manufacture, while housing for the arsenal workers grew up outside its walls. [PARAGRAPH:1]Venice developed methods of mass-producing warships in the Arsenal, including the frame-first system to replace the Roman hull-first practice. The new system was much faster and required less wood. At the peak of its efficiency in the early sixteenth century, the Arsenal employed some 16,000 people who apparently were able to produce nearly one ship each day, and could fit out, arm, and provision a newly-built galley with standardized parts on a production-line basis not seen again until the Industrial Revolution. [PARAGRAPH:1]The staff of the Arsenal also developed new firearms at an early date, beginning with bombards in the 1370s and numerous small arms against the Genoese a few years later. Improvements in handguns led to their muzzle velocity (and therefore their ability to penetrate armor) exceeding that of the crossbow. The Venetian condottieri leader, Bartolomeo Colleoni, is usually given credit as being the first to mount the Arsenal's new lighter-weight artillery on mobile carriages for field use. [PARAGRAPH:1]The Arsenal's main gate, the Porta Magna, was built in about 1460 and was the first Classical revival structure to be built in Venice. It was perhaps built by Antonio Gambello from a design by Jacopo Bellini. Two lions taken from Greece situated beside it were added in 1687. One of the lions, known as the Piraeus Lion, is notable for having been defaced with lengthy runic inscriptions carved in the eleventh century by Scandinavian mercenary soldiers. [PARAGRAPH:1]The Arsenal Novissimo was begun in 1473. It enabled the creation of a system similar to an assembly line, in which hulls were constructed in the newer areas of the Arsenal before being fitted out in the old Arsenal. In the late sixteenth century, the Arsenal's designers experimented with larger ships as platforms for heavy naval guns. The most impressive was the galleass, already used at Lepanto, and developed from the old merchanting "great galley". It was huge, with sails as well as oars, and was virtually a floating fortress, with guns mounted on wheeled carriages along the sides in the modern fashion. It was slow and unwieldy in battle, however, and few were ever built. The galleon, also developed at the Arsenal, was an armed sailing ship, a slimmer version of the merchant "round ship". It was useful in major naval battles, but not in the small bays and off the frequent lee shores of the Dalmatian coast. [PARAGRAPH:1]Significant parts of the Arsenal were destroyed under Napoleonic rule, and later rebuilt to enable the Arsenal's present use as a naval base. It is also used as a research centre, an exhibition venue during the Venice Biennale and is home to a historic boat preservation centre.</English>
		<French>[TAB]L'Arsenal de Venise (en italien : Arsenale di Venezia) est un dépôt et un chantier naval qui joua un rôle primordial dans la construction de l'empire vénitien. Il fut l'un des quartiers les plus importants de Venise, s'étendant dans le Castello sestiere.[PARAGRAPH:1]Ce bâtiment de style byzantin peut avoir existé depuis le 8ème siècle, bien qu'on date habituellement le début de la construction de la structure actuelle à 1104 pendant le règne d'Ordelafo Faliero, bien qu'il n'y ait aucune preuves d'une date aussi précise. Il existe avec certitude depuis le début de 13ème siècle et est mentionné dans l'Enfer de Dante. Le nom provient probablement de l'arabe Dar al Sina’a ("chantier naval") et le concept est clairement arabe beaucoup plus que byzantin. [PARAGRAPH:1]Originellement, le chantier naval ne travaillait quasiment qu'à entretenir et construire les navires privés, mais en 1320 l'Arsenal Nuovo fut bâti, plus grand que le précédent. Il permit à toute la marine de l'état et aux navires marchants les plus importants d'être tous ensembles construits et entretenus dans un seul endroit. L'Arsenal devint incidemment un centre importent de la manufacture de cordes, tandis que les quartiers en dehors des murs de la ville s'agrandissaient pour accueillir les travailleurs de l'Arsenal. [PARAGRAPH:1]Venise développa des méthodes de production de masse de navires dans l'Arsenal, notamment le système de construction en premier de la charpente venant remplacer l'ancienne méthode de construction de la coque en premier inventée par les Romains. Ce nouveau système permettait de construire plus vite et demandait moins de bois. Au maximum de son efficacité au début du 16ème siècle, l'Arsenal employa jusqu'à 16 000 personnes qui étaient apparemment capable de produire presque un navire par jour et pouvaient équiper, armer et provisionner une galère nouvellement construire grâce à des méthodes standardisées dans une ligne de production qui ne sera pas égalée avant la révolution industrielle. [PARAGRAPH:1]Le personnel de l'Arsenal développa aussi de nouvelles armes à feu dès le début, commençant par des bombardes vers 1370 et de nombreuses petites armes à feu utilisées contre les Génois quelques années plus tard. Les améliorations des armes de poings augmentèrent la vélocité de balles en sortie de canon (et par là, leur capacité à pénétrer des armures) excédant celle des arbalètes. On attribue généralement le crédit au chef des condottieri vénitien, Bartolomeo Colleoni, d'avoir monté les nouvelles pièces d'artillerie légère de l'Arsenal sur des chariots mobiles pour un usage sur le champ de bataille. [PARAGRAPH:1]La principale porte de l'Arsenal, la Porta Magna, fut construite aux environs de 1460 et fut la première structure du renouveau classique à Venise. Elle fut peut-être construite par Antonio Gambello d'après des plans de Jacopo Bellini. Deux statues de lion prises en Grèce situées à coté furent ajoutées en 1687. Un des lions, connu sous le nom de Lion de Pirée, fut dégradé notablement par de longues inscriptions runiques gravées au 11ème siècle par des soldats mercenaires vikings. [PARAGRAPH:1]La construction de l'Arsenal Novissimo commença en 1473. Il permit la création d'un système proche des chaînes d'assemblage, dans lequel les coques étaient construites dans les quartiers du nouvel Arsenal avant d'être aménagées dans l'ancien arsenal. A la fin du 16ème siècle, les ingénieurs de l'Arsenal expérimentèrent de larges navires en tant que plateformes pour des canons navals lourds. La plus impressionnante fut la galéasse, utilisée à Lépante, et développée à partir des grandes galères marchandes. Elle était gigantesque, avec des voiles aussi bien que des rames, et était virtuellement une forteresse flottante, avec des canons montés sur chariots le long des flancs. Cependant, elle était lente et difficile à manier, et peu furent finalement construites. Le galion, lui aussi développé à l'Arsenal, était un navire à voiles armé, une version plus légère des gros navires marchands. Il fut largement utilisé dans les principales batailles navales, mais jamais dans les petites baies et les fréquents bancs de sables de la cote dalmatienne. [PARAGRAPH:1]Des parties signifiantes de l'Arsenal furent détruites sous le régime napoléonien, et rebâties plus tard pour permettre à l'Arsenal actuel son utilisation en tant que base navale. Il est aussi utilisé comme centre de recherche, comme lieu d'exposition pendant la biennale vénitienne et comme centre de préservation des navires historiques.</French>
		<German>[TAB]The Venetian Arsenal (Italian: Arsenale di Venezia) is a shipyard and naval depot that played a leading role in Venetian empire-building. It was one of the most important areas of Venice, lying in the Castello sestiere.[PARAGRAPH:1]The Byzantine-style establishment may have existed as early as the eighth century, though the present structure is usually said to have been begun in 1104 during the reign of Ordelafo Faliero, although there is no evidence for such a precise date. It definitely existed by the early thirteenth century and is mentioned in Dante's Inferno. The name probably comes from Arabic Dar al Sina’a ("Dockyard") and the concept was clearly Islamic as much as Byzantine. [PARAGRAPH:1]Initially the state dockyard worked merely to maintain naval ships built privately, but in 1320 the Arsenal Nuovo was built, much larger than the original. It enabled all the state's navy and the larger merchant ships to be both constructed and maintained in one place. The Arsenal incidentally became an important centre for rope manufacture, while housing for the arsenal workers grew up outside its walls. [PARAGRAPH:1]Venice developed methods of mass-producing warships in the Arsenal, including the frame-first system to replace the Roman hull-first practice. The new system was much faster and required less wood. At the peak of its efficiency in the early sixteenth century, the Arsenal employed some 16,000 people who apparently were able to produce nearly one ship each day, and could fit out, arm, and provision a newly-built galley with standardized parts on a production-line basis not seen again until the Industrial Revolution. [PARAGRAPH:1]The staff of the Arsenal also developed new firearms at an early date, beginning with bombards in the 1370s and numerous small arms against the Genoese a few years later. Improvements in handguns led to their muzzle velocity (and therefore their ability to penetrate armor) exceeding that of the crossbow. The Venetian condottieri leader, Bartolomeo Colleoni, is usually given credit as being the first to mount the Arsenal's new lighter-weight artillery on mobile carriages for field use. The Arsenal's main gate, the Porta Magna, was built in about 1460 and was the first Classical revival structure to be built in Venice. It was perhaps built by Antonio Gambello from a design by Jacopo Bellini. Two lions taken from Greece situated beside it were added in 1687. One of the lions, known as the Piraeus Lion, is notable for having been defaced with lengthy runic inscriptions carved in the eleventh century by Scandinavian mercenary soldiers. [PARAGRAPH:1]The Arsenal Novissimo was begun in 1473. It enabled the creation of a system similar to an assembly line, in which hulls were constructed in the newer areas of the Arsenal before being fitted out in the old Arsenal. In the late sixteenth century, the Arsenal's designers experimented with larger ships as platforms for heavy naval guns. The most impressive was the galleass, already used at Lepanto, and developed from the old merchanting "great galley". It was huge, with sails as well as oars, and was virtually a floating fortress, with guns mounted on wheeled carriages along the sides in the modern fashion. It was slow and unwieldy in battle, however, and few were ever built. The galleon, also developed at the Arsenal, was an armed sailing ship, a slimmer version of the merchant "round ship". It was useful in major naval battles, but not in the small bays and off the frequent lee shores of the Dalmatian coast. [PARAGRAPH:1]Significant parts of the Arsenal were destroyed under Napoleonic rule, and later rebuilt to enable the Arsenal's present use as a naval base. It is also used as a research centre, an exhibition venue during the Venice Biennale and is home to a historic boat preservation centre.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB]The Venetian Arsenal (Italian: Arsenale di Venezia) is a shipyard and naval depot that played a leading role in Venetian empire-building. It was one of the most important areas of Venice, lying in the Castello sestiere.[PARAGRAPH:1]The Byzantine-style establishment may have existed as early as the eighth century, though the present structure is usually said to have been begun in 1104 during the reign of Ordelafo Faliero, although there is no evidence for such a precise date. It definitely existed by the early thirteenth century and is mentioned in Dante's Inferno. The name probably comes from Arabic Dar al Sina’a ("Dockyard") and the concept was clearly Islamic as much as Byzantine. [PARAGRAPH:1]Initially the state dockyard worked merely to maintain naval ships built privately, but in 1320 the Arsenal Nuovo was built, much larger than the original. It enabled all the state's navy and the larger merchant ships to be both constructed and maintained in one place. The Arsenal incidentally became an important centre for rope manufacture, while housing for the arsenal workers grew up outside its walls. [PARAGRAPH:1]Venice developed methods of mass-producing warships in the Arsenal, including the frame-first system to replace the Roman hull-first practice. The new system was much faster and required less wood. At the peak of its efficiency in the early sixteenth century, the Arsenal employed some 16,000 people who apparently were able to produce nearly one ship each day, and could fit out, arm, and provision a newly-built galley with standardized parts on a production-line basis not seen again until the Industrial Revolution. [PARAGRAPH:1]The staff of the Arsenal also developed new firearms at an early date, beginning with bombards in the 1370s and numerous small arms against the Genoese a few years later. Improvements in handguns led to their muzzle velocity (and therefore their ability to penetrate armor) exceeding that of the crossbow. The Venetian condottieri leader, Bartolomeo Colleoni, is usually given credit as being the first to mount the Arsenal's new lighter-weight artillery on mobile carriages for field use. The Arsenal's main gate, the Porta Magna, was built in about 1460 and was the first Classical revival structure to be built in Venice. It was perhaps built by Antonio Gambello from a design by Jacopo Bellini. Two lions taken from Greece situated beside it were added in 1687. One of the lions, known as the Piraeus Lion, is notable for having been defaced with lengthy runic inscriptions carved in the eleventh century by Scandinavian mercenary soldiers. [PARAGRAPH:1]The Arsenal Novissimo was begun in 1473. It enabled the creation of a system similar to an assembly line, in which hulls were constructed in the newer areas of the Arsenal before being fitted out in the old Arsenal. In the late sixteenth century, the Arsenal's designers experimented with larger ships as platforms for heavy naval guns. The most impressive was the galleass, already used at Lepanto, and developed from the old merchanting "great galley". It was huge, with sails as well as oars, and was virtually a floating fortress, with guns mounted on wheeled carriages along the sides in the modern fashion. It was slow and unwieldy in battle, however, and few were ever built. The galleon, also developed at the Arsenal, was an armed sailing ship, a slimmer version of the merchant "round ship". It was useful in major naval battles, but not in the small bays and off the frequent lee shores of the Dalmatian coast. [PARAGRAPH:1]Significant parts of the Arsenal were destroyed under Napoleonic rule, and later rebuilt to enable the Arsenal's present use as a naval base. It is also used as a research centre, an exhibition venue during the Venice Biennale and is home to a historic boat preservation centre.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB]The Venetian Arsenal (Italian: Arsenale di Venezia) is a shipyard and naval depot that played a leading role in Venetian empire-building. It was one of the most important areas of Venice, lying in the Castello sestiere.[PARAGRAPH:1]The Byzantine-style establishment may have existed as early as the eighth century, though the present structure is usually said to have been begun in 1104 during the reign of Ordelafo Faliero, although there is no evidence for such a precise date. It definitely existed by the early thirteenth century and is mentioned in Dante's Inferno. The name probably comes from Arabic Dar al Sina’a ("Dockyard") and the concept was clearly Islamic as much as Byzantine. [PARAGRAPH:1]Initially the state dockyard worked merely to maintain naval ships built privately, but in 1320 the Arsenal Nuovo was built, much larger than the original. It enabled all the state's navy and the larger merchant ships to be both constructed and maintained in one place. The Arsenal incidentally became an important centre for rope manufacture, while housing for the arsenal workers grew up outside its walls. [PARAGRAPH:1]Venice developed methods of mass-producing warships in the Arsenal, including the frame-first system to replace the Roman hull-first practice. The new system was much faster and required less wood. At the peak of its efficiency in the early sixteenth century, the Arsenal employed some 16,000 people who apparently were able to produce nearly one ship each day, and could fit out, arm, and provision a newly-built galley with standardized parts on a production-line basis not seen again until the Industrial Revolution. [PARAGRAPH:1]The staff of the Arsenal also developed new firearms at an early date, beginning with bombards in the 1370s and numerous small arms against the Genoese a few years later. Improvements in handguns led to their muzzle velocity (and therefore their ability to penetrate armor) exceeding that of the crossbow. The Venetian condottieri leader, Bartolomeo Colleoni, is usually given credit as being the first to mount the Arsenal's new lighter-weight artillery on mobile carriages for field use. The Arsenal's main gate, the Porta Magna, was built in about 1460 and was the first Classical revival structure to be built in Venice. It was perhaps built by Antonio Gambello from a design by Jacopo Bellini. Two lions taken from Greece situated beside it were added in 1687. One of the lions, known as the Piraeus Lion, is notable for having been defaced with lengthy runic inscriptions carved in the eleventh century by Scandinavian mercenary soldiers. [PARAGRAPH:1]The Arsenal Novissimo was begun in 1473. It enabled the creation of a system similar to an assembly line, in which hulls were constructed in the newer areas of the Arsenal before being fitted out in the old Arsenal. In the late sixteenth century, the Arsenal's designers experimented with larger ships as platforms for heavy naval guns. The most impressive was the galleass, already used at Lepanto, and developed from the old merchanting "great galley". It was huge, with sails as well as oars, and was virtually a floating fortress, with guns mounted on wheeled carriages along the sides in the modern fashion. It was slow and unwieldy in battle, however, and few were ever built. The galleon, also developed at the Arsenal, was an armed sailing ship, a slimmer version of the merchant "round ship". It was useful in major naval battles, but not in the small bays and off the frequent lee shores of the Dalmatian coast. [PARAGRAPH:1]Significant parts of the Arsenal were destroyed under Napoleonic rule, and later rebuilt to enable the Arsenal's present use as a naval base. It is also used as a research centre, an exhibition venue during the Venice Biennale and is home to a historic boat preservation centre.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>
