<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by lcollins (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- Copyright Firaxis Games 2005 -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text - New -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_HURRIANS_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Hurrian Empire</English>
		<French>Peuple hourrite</French>
		<German>Hurriter Reich</German>
		<Italian>Hurriti Impero</Italian>
		<Spanish>Hurrita Imperio</Spanish>
	</TEXT>	
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_HURRIANS_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Hurri</English>
		<French>Hourrites</French>
		<German>Hurri</German>
		<Italian>Hurri</Italian>
		<Spanish>Hurri</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_HURRIANS_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Hurrian</English>
    <French>
      <Text>hourrite:hourrite:hourrites:hourrites</Text>
      <Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
      <Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
    </French>
		<German>Hurriter</German>
		<Italian>Hurriti</Italian>
		<Spanish>Hurrita</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_HURRIANS_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB] Like many aspects of Hurrian culture, their origins are still a mystery.  By 2400 BC, the Hurrians may have expanded from the foothills of the Caucasus to northern Mesopotamia.  The Khabur River Valley became the heart of the Hurrian lands for a millennium.  The first known Hurrian kingdom was centered on the city of Urkesh during the third millennium BC.  The end of the Akkadian Empire enabled the Hurrians to gain control of the area.  Now the Hurrians could benefit from the previous wealthy cultures living there and organize their own advanced city-state.  Urkesh had some powerful neighbors.  Their neighbors included the powerful Amorite kingdom of Mari and the capital of an Old Assyrian kingdom called Shubat-Enlil was founded some distance from Urkesh at another Hurrian settlement in the Khabur River Valley. [PARAGRAPH: 1] The Hurrians also migrated west, and by 1725 BC their remnants can be found in northern Syria.  Early Hurrian kingdoms, such as Kizzuwatna, flourished during this time.  However, many of them eventually found themselves subdued by the Hittites, whom were influenced by the Hurrian culture for centuries.  The destruction of the Babylonian kingdom by the Hittites allowed a powerful Hurrian dynasty to rise.  A legendary king, Kirta, founded the kingdom of Mitanni around 1500 BC.  Mitanni gradually grew from the region around the Khabur Valley and became the most powerful kingdom of the Near East in the 1400s and 1300s BC. [PARAGRAPH: 1] King Barattarna of Mitanni expanded the Mitanni kingdom greatly, and the nation grew even stronger under the reign of Shaushtatar.  Other Hurrian kingdoms, such as Kizzuwatna and Ishuwa, proved powerful allies against the hostile Hittites.  Several wars with the Pharaohs over the control of Syria caused the Mitanni and Egyptians to form an alliance.  During Shaushtatar's reign, Mitanni grew to its zenith.  After the death of Shuttarna, Mitanni was ravaged by a war of succession.  After a king finally claimed the throne, Mitanni had been weakened considerably.  At this same time, both the Hittite and Assyrian power increased, bringing a greater thread to Mitanni.  In the capital Washukanni a new power struggle broke out.  Eventually, after wars with the Hittites and Assyrians, Mitanni was weakened greatly and was eventually annexed by the Assyrian king Shalmaneser in the 13th century BC. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Another Hurrian kingdom also benefited from the demise of Babylonian power in the sixteenth century BC.  The Hurrians now inhabited the region northeast of the Tigris River.  The kingdom that emerged here was Arrapha.  Excavations at one of Arrapha's chief cities, Nuzi, proved to be an important source of information about the Hurrians.  Eventually, this kingdom was destroyed by the Assyrians in the fourteenth century BC. [PARAGRAPH: 1] By the thirteenth century BC, all the Hurrian states had been vanquished by other peoples.  The heart of the Hurrian lands, the Khabur River Valley, became an Assyrian province.  The Hurrian population in Syria seems to have given up their language in favor the Assyrian dialect of Akkadian, or, more likely, Aramaic.</English>
		<French>[TAB] À l'instar de nombreux aspects de la culture hourrite, leurs origines sont encore un mystère. En 2400 avant J.-C., les Hourrites peuvent avoir étendu de la contreforts du Caucase au nord de la Mésopotamie. La vallée du fleuve Khabour est devenu le coeur de la hourrite terres pour un millénaire. Le premier royaume connu hourrite est centrée sur la ville de Urkesh au cours du troisième millénaire av. La fin de l'Empire d'Akkad permis à la Hourrites de prendre le contrôle de la zone. Maintenant, les Hourrites pourraient bénéficier de la précédente riches cultures qui y vivent et à organiser leurs propres programmes d'état-ville. Urkesh a quelques puissants voisins. Leurs voisins compris le puissant royaume Amorrite de Mari et la capitale d'un vieux royaume assyrien appelé Shubat-Enlil fut fondée une certaine distance de Urkesh hourrite à un autre règlement dans la vallée du fleuve Khabour. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Les Hourrites aussi migré ouest, et 1725 avant J.-C. par leurs restes se trouvent dans le nord de la Syrie. Early kingdoms hourrite, comme Kizzuwatna, a prospéré pendant cette période. Cependant, beaucoup d'entre eux se sont retrouvés finalement vaincu par les Hittites, qui ont été influencés par la culture hurrienne pendant des siècles. La destruction du royaume babylonien par les Hittites permis une puissante dynastie hourrite à la hausse. Un roi légendaire, Kirta, fonda le royaume de Mitaniens alentours de 1500 av. Mitaniens progressivement passé de la région autour de la vallée du Khabour et est devenue le plus puissant royaume du Proche-Orient dans les années 1300 et 1400 avant JC. [PARAGRAPH 1] roi Barattarna de Mitaniens élargi le royaume Mitaniens grandement, et la nation a augmenté encore plus sous le règne de Shaushtatar. Hourrite autres royaumes, comme la Kizzuwatna et Ishuwa, révélés de puissants alliés contre les Hittites hostiles. Plusieurs guerres avec les Pharaons sur le contrôle de la Syrie et causé la Mitaniens Égyptiens pour former une alliance. Pendant le règne de Shaushtatar, Mitaniens a grandi à son apogée. Après la mort de Shuttarna, Mitaniens a été ravagé par une guerre de succession. Après un roi finalement revendiqué le trône, Mitaniens avait été considérablement affaiblie. À ce même moment, à la fois le hittite et assyrienne puissance accrue, qui entraîne une plus forte au fil Mitaniens. Dans la capitale Washukanni une nouvelle lutte pour le pouvoir a éclaté. Finalement, après les guerres avec les Hittites et les Assyriens, Mitaniens a été grandement affaibli et a finalement été annexé par le roi assyrien Salmanasar au 13ème siècle avant JC. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Un autre royaume hourrite également bénéficié de la disparition de la puissance babylonienne dans le seizième siècle av. Les Hourrites maintenant habité la région nord-est du Tigre. Le royaume qui a vu le jour ici Arrapha. Fouilles à l'une de ses principales villes Arrapha, Nuzi, s'est révélée être une source importante d'informations sur les Hourrites. En fin de compte, ce royaume a été détruit par les Assyriens au XIVe siècle av. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Par le XIIIe siècle avant J.-C., les Hourrites tous les Etats ont été vaincus par d'autres peuples. Le coeur de la hourrite terres, la vallée du fleuve Khabour, est devenu une province assyrienne. La population Hourrites en Syrie semble avoir renoncé à leur langue au profit du dialecte de l'akkadien assyrien, ou, plus probablement, araméen.</French>
		<German>[TAB] Wie viele andere Aspekte der Hurrian Kultur, ihre Ursprünge sind noch immer ein Geheimnis. Mit 2400 v. Chr., die Hurrians Mai erweitert haben von den Ausläufern des Kaukasus zu den nördlichen Mesopotamien. Die Khabur River Valley wurde im Herzen der Hurrian Land für ein Jahrtausend. Die erste bekannte Hurrian Reich wurde zentriert auf die Stadt Urkesh im dritten Jahrtausend v. Chr.. Das Ende des Reiches konnten die Akkadisch Hurrians zu gewinnen, die Kontrolle über das Gebiet. Nun könnte die Hurrians profitieren von den früheren Kulturen reichen die dort leben und organisieren ihre eigenen fortschrittlichen Stadt-Staat. Urkesh hatte einige mächtige Nachbarn. Ihre Nachbarn waren die mächtigen Amorite Reich der Mari und der Hauptstadt des assyrischen Reiches namens Old Shubat-Enlil gegründet Urkesh aus einiger Entfernung an einem anderen Hurrian Abrechnung in der Khabur River Valley. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Die Hurrians auch migriert Westen und von 1725 v. Chr., ihre Reste finden sich in Nord-Syrien. Early Hurrian Königreiche, wie Kizzuwatna, blühte während dieser Zeit. Aber viele von ihnen fanden sich schließlich gedämpft durch die Hethiter, die geprägt waren von der Hurrian Kultur seit Jahrhunderten. Die Zerstörung des babylonischen Reiches durch die Hethiter erlaubt eine mächtige Dynastie Hurrian steigen. Ein legendärer König, Kirta, gründete das Reich von Mitanni um 1500 v. Chr.. Mitanni wuchs Schritt für Schritt aus der Region rund um den Khabur Valley und wurde zum mächtigsten Reich der Nahe Osten in den 1400er und 1300er v. Chr.. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Barattarna König von Mitanni erweitert die Mitanni Reich stark, und die Nation wuchs noch stärker unter der Herrschaft von Shaushtatar. Andere Hurrian Königreiche, wie Kizzuwatna und Ishuwa, erwies sich mächtige Verbündete gegen die feindlichen Hethiter. Mehrere Kriege mit den Pharaonen über die Kontrolle von Syrien verursacht die Mitanni und Ägypter zu einer Allianz. Während der Herrschaft Shaushtatar, Mitanni stieg auf seinen Höhepunkt. Nach dem Tod von Shuttarna, Mitanni verwüstet wurde von einem Erbfolgekrieg. Nach einem König schließlich beansprucht den Thron, Mitanni wurde erheblich geschwächt. In dieser Zeit, die beide der hethitischen und assyrischen Macht erhöht, wodurch eine größere thread zu Mitanni. In der Hauptstadt Washukanni einen neuen Machtkampf brach. Schließlich, nach dem Kriege mit den Hethitern und Assyrern, Mitanni war stark geschwächt und wurde schließlich durch den Anhang assyrischen König Salmanassar im 13. Jahrhundert v. Chr.. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Ein weiteres Hurrian Reich auch in den Genuss der Niedergang der babylonischen Macht in der sechzehnten Jahrhundert v. Chr.. Die Hurrians jetzt bewohnt die Region im Nordosten des Tigris. Das Reich war, die sich hier Arrapha. Grabungen an einem Arrapha Chef Städte, Nuzi, erwies sich als eine wichtige Quelle für Informationen über die Hurrians. Schließlich ist diese Reich zerstört wurde durch die Assyrer im vierzehnten Jahrhundert v. Chr.. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Mit dem dreizehnten Jahrhundert v. Chr., die alle Staaten der Hurrian worden Besiegten von anderen Völkern. Das Herz der Hurrian Länder, die Khabur River Valley, wurde ein assyrische Provinz. Die Hurrian Bevölkerung in Syrien zu haben scheint aufgegeben, ihre Sprache zu Gunsten der assyrischen Dialekt des Akkadisch, oder, was wahrscheinlicher ist, Aramäisch.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB] Come molti aspetti della cultura Hurrian, le loro origini sono ancora un mistero. Dal 2400 aC, la Hurrians può avere ampliato da colline del Caucaso settentrionale alla Mesopotamia. Il Khabur River Valley è diventato il cuore del Hurrian terreni per un millennio. La prima nota Hurrian regno era centrata sulla città di Urkesh nel corso del terzo millennio aC. La fine della Impero accadico consentito alla Hurrians per ottenere il controllo della zona. Ora il Hurrians potrebbe trarre vantaggio dal precedente ricchi culture che vi abitano e organizzare le proprie avanzate città-stato. Urkesh avuto alcuni potenti vicini. I loro vicini di casa inclusi i potenti Amorite regno dei mari e la capitale di un regno assiro Old chiamato Shubat-Enlil è stata fondata da una certa distanza Urkesh a un altro Hurrian insediamento nella valle del fiume Khabur. [PARAGRAPH: 1] La Hurrians anche migrati ovest, e dal 1725 aC loro resti si trovano nel nord della Siria. Early Hurrian regni, come Kizzuwatna, fiorirono durante questo tempo. Tuttavia, molti di loro si sono trovati poi sottomessa dai Ittiti, che sono stati influenzati dalla cultura Hurrian per secoli. La distruzione del regno babilonese dalla Ittiti consentito una potente dinastia Hurrian a salire. Un leggendario re, Kirta, fondò il regno di Mitanni intorno al 1500 aC. Mitanni è gradualmente cresciuto dalla regione intorno al Khabur Valley e divenne il più potente regno del Vicino Oriente nel 1400 e 1300 aC. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Barattarna re di Mitanni ampliato il regno di Mitanni notevolmente, e la nazione è cresciuta ancora di più, sotto il regno di Shaushtatar. Hurrian altri regni, come Kizzuwatna e Ishuwa, dimostrato potenti alleati contro gli Ittiti ostile. Diverse le guerre con i faraoni per il controllo della Siria, ha causato il Mitanni e egiziani a formare un'alleanza. Durante il regno Shaushtatar, Mitanni è cresciuto al suo zenit. Dopo la morte di Shuttarna, Mitanni è stato devastato da una guerra di successione. Dopo un re infine rivendicato il trono, Mitanni era stata notevolmente indebolita. Al tempo stesso, sia la ittita e assira maggiore potenza, portando ad una maggiore thread Mitanni. Nella capitale Washukanni una nuova lotta di potere scoppiata. Alla fine, dopo le guerre con gli Ittiti e Assiri, Mitanni era notevolmente indebolita e fu infine annessa dal re assiro Shalmaneser nel 13 ° secolo aC. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Un altro Hurrian regno ha beneficiato anche la scomparsa di potenza babilonese nel XVI secolo aC. Il Hurrians ora abitato la regione nord-est del fiume Tigri. Il regno che è stato Arrapha qui emerse. Scavi presso uno dei Arrapha città capoluogo, Nuzi, dimostrato di essere un importante fonte di informazioni circa la Hurrians. Infine, questo regno fu distrutta dal assiri e il XIV secolo aC. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Con il tredicesimo secolo aC, tutti gli Stati Hurrian era stato sconfitto da altri popoli. Il cuore della Hurrian terre, il Khabur River Valley, divenne provincia assira. Hurrian la popolazione in Siria sembra aver dato loro la lingua in favore di accado assira dialetto, o, più probabilmente, l'aramaico.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB] Al igual que muchos aspectos de la cultura Hurrita, sus orígenes son aún un misterio. En 2400 aC, los hurritas puede haber ampliado de las faldas de la cordillera del Cáucaso al norte de Mesopotamia. El valle del río Jabur se convirtió en el corazón de los hurritas tierras para un milenio. El primer reino conocido Hurrita se centra en la ciudad de Urkesh durante el tercer milenio antes de Cristo. El final del Imperio acadio permitido a los hurritas a hacerse con el control de la zona. Ahora los hurritas podrían beneficiarse de las ricas culturas anteriores que viven allí y organizar su propia ciudad-estado avanzado. Urkesh había algunos poderosos vecinos. Sus vecinos incluyen los poderosos Amorite reino de Mari y la capital de un reino llamado Antiguo asirio-Shubat Enlil fue fundada a cierta distancia de Urkesh hurritas en otro asentamiento en el valle del río Jabur. [PARAGRAPH: 1] El hurritas también emigraron al oeste, y por el 1725 aC sus restos se encuentran en el norte de Siria. Los primeros reinos hurritas, como Kizzuwatna, florecieron durante este tiempo. Sin embargo, muchos de ellos se encuentran moderada por los hititas, los cuales son influenciados por la cultura Hurrita durante siglos. La destrucción del reino de Babilonia por los hititas permitido una poderosa dinastía hurritas aumentando. Un legendario rey, Kirta, fundó el reino de Mitanni alrededor de 1500 aC. Mitanni gradualmente creció de la región en todo el Valle del Khabur y se convirtió en el reino más poderoso de Oriente Próximo en el 1400 y 1300 antes de Cristo. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Rey Barattarna de Mitanni amplió el reino Mitanni mucho, y de la nación creció aún más fuerte bajo el reinado de Shaushtatar. Hurrita otros reinos, como Kizzuwatna y Ishuwa, demostrado poderosos aliados contra los hititas hostil. Varias guerras con los faraones por el control de Siria causó la Mitanni y egipcios para formar una alianza. Durante el reinado de Shaushtatar, Mitanni creció a su cenit. Después de la muerte de Shuttarna, Mitanni fue asolado por una guerra de sucesión. Después de un rey alegó finalmente el trono, Mitanni se había debilitado considerablemente. En este mismo tiempo, tanto el hitita y asiria aumento de potencia, con lo que un mayor flujo de Mitanni. En la capital Washukanni una nueva lucha de poder estalló. Eventualmente, después de las guerras con los hititas y los asirios, Mitanni se debilitó mucho y fue anexada por el rey asirio Shalmaneser en el siglo 13 antes de Cristo. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Otro hurritas reino también se benefició de la desaparición del poder de Babilonia en el siglo XVI antes de Cristo. El hurritas ahora habitado la región noreste del río Tigris. El reino que surgió aquí fue Arrapha. Las excavaciones en uno de Arrapha jefe de las ciudades, Nuzi, demostró ser una importante fuente de información acerca de los hurritas. Eventualmente, este reino fue destruido por los asirios en el siglo XIV aC. [PARAGRAPH: 1] En el siglo XIII antes de Cristo, todos los estados hurritas habían sido vencidos por otros pueblos. El corazón de los hurritas tierras, el valle del río Jabur, se convirtió en una provincia asiria. La población hurritas en Siria parece haber renunciado a su idioma en favor de los asirios dialecto acadio, o, más probable, arameo.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>	