<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by lcollins (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- Copyright Firaxis Games 2005 -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text - New -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_BORU</Tag>
		<English>Boru</English>
		<French>Boru</French>
		<German>Boru</German>
		<Italian>Boru</Italian>
		<Spanish>Boru</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_BORU_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Brian Boru[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]High King of Ireland[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived:[\BOLD] 941 - 1014[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Brian Boru was likely born in 941, though some sources state that he was born as early as 926.  He was born near Killaloe, a town in the region of Thomond where his father, Cenn&#233;tig mac Lorc&#225;in was king.  When Brian's father died, the kingship of Thomond passed to his older brother, Mathgamain.  When Mathgamain was killed in 976, Brian replaced him and became the King of the entire kingdom of Munster.  Brian Boru belonged to the D&#225;l Cais who occupied a territory across the River Shannon, a territory that would later be known as the Kingdom of Thomond and today encompasses the counties Clare and Limerick.  The Shannon served as an easy route by which raids could be made against the provinces of Connacht and Meath. Brian Boru participated in these early raids along with his brother and father. [PARAGRAPH: 1] After Mathgamain captured the province of Munster, the E&#243;ganacht King organized an anti-Dalcassian alliance.  At the Battle of Sulchoid, the Dalcassian army led by Mathgamain and Boru resolutely defeated the Hiberno Norse army of Limerick and looted the city.  In 976, Mathgamain attended a supposedly peaceful meeting where he was murdered.  Thus, Brian Boru became the new leader of the Dalcassians.  In order to avenge his brother's death, Brian Boru reestablished the Dalcassian control over Munster.  By the end, he had killed several rulers involved in the anti-Dalcassian alliance. [PARAGRAPH: 1] After having rule of the Province of Munster, Brian then set out to extend his authority to the provinces of Leinster and Connacht.  In doing so, he came into conflict with the High King M&#225;el Sechnaill mac Domnaill whose power base was in the Province of Meath.  For the next fifteen years, the high King M&#225;el repeatedly lead armies into Leinster and Boru led his naval forces up the River Shannon to attack Connacht and Meath.  Boru developed a military strategy that used the forces on both land and water that would serve him well throughout his career.  In 966, Boru managed to control the Province of Leinster and Munster, while M&#225;el Sechnaill was still in control of the Provinces of Meath, Connacht, and Ulster.  After deposing the King of Leinster, Brian Boru's selected ruler for Munster rebelled against him.  The opposing sides of the armies fought the Battle of Glen Mama.  Brian's army was victorious and captured and sacked the enemy's city. [PARAGRAPH: 1] In the year 1000, King Brian Boru lead a combined Munster-Leinster-Dublin army on an attack on the High King M&#225;el Sechnaill mac Domnaill's home in the Province of Meath.  Meath's most important ally was the Province of Connacht.  However, the two provinces were separated by a river giving Boru's naval forces an advantage.   In response to this problem, M&#225;el Sechnaill built two bridges to serve as obstacles and a connection between the Provinces of Meath and Connacht.  In 1002, M&#225;el Sechnaill surrendered his title to Brian Boru.  In order to use the title High King not only as a name but a reliable title, Boru had to extend his authority to the Province of Ulster.  Ulster's geographical location presented a great challenge against Boru's army.  It took Boru ten years of campaigning to achieve his goal.  But gaining entry to the Province of Ulster brought him only halfway to his goal. Brian systematically defeated each of the regional rulers who defied him, forcing them to recognize him as their overlord. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Brian Boru received support from an important monastery in Ireland, Armagh.  Armagh gave him financial support after Brian Boru generously donated gold to the monastery and declared it the religious capital of Ireland.  M&#225;el M&#243;rda mac Murchada of Leinster rose in rebellion in 1012.  M&#225;el M&#243;rda sought out allies with which to defy the High King.  Together, they attacked the Province of Meath and in 1013, Boru led a force from Munster and southern Connacht into Leinster.  The city of Dublin was blockaded by Boru's army.  His army was forced to abandon the siege when they ran out of supplies before the army of M&#225;el M&#243;rda.  M&#225;el M&#243;rda was relying on the thought that if he defied Boru, the rulers of the other Provinces would aid him.  He was wrong, however, with a sole ruler from Ulster providing support.  When Boru returned in 1014, M&#225;el had no other choice but to send his cousin, Sigtrygg, overseas to seek aid. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Sigtrygg sailed to Orkeney Island and the Isle of Man.  All of the men here were in the service of M&#225;el M&#243;rda.  Boru's troops were from Munster and southern Connacht.  Boru lost the support of the King of Meath after a disagreement and was thus at a loss in the battle.  The fighting took place just north of Dublin, at Clontarf.  The Battle of Clontarf resulted in the death of Brian Boru.  There are many legends concerning his death, from dying in a heroic man-to-man combat to being killed fleeing Viking mercenary Brodir while praying in his tent.  It is said that Boru is buried in the grounds of St. Patrick's Cathedral in the city of Armagh.</English>
		<French>[H1]Brian Boru[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Ard ri &#201;renn[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Dates :[\BOLD] 941 - 1014[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Biographie :[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Brian Boru était probablement né en 941, même si certaines sources indiquent que il est né dès 926. Il est né près de Killaloe, une ville située dans la région de Thomond où son père, Cenneétig mac, Lorcáin est roi. Brian Lorsque le père est mort, la royauté de Thomond passa à son frère aîné, Mathgamain. Quand Mathgamain a été tué en 976, Brian remplacé lui et devint roi de l'ensemble du royaume de Munster. Brian Boru appartenait à la Dál Cais qui occupe un territoire à travers la rivière Shannon, un territoire qui serait plus tard connu sous le nom de Royaume de Thomond et englobe aujourd'hui les comtés de Clare et de Limerick. Le Shannon a servi d'itinéraire facile par des raids qui pourraient être formulées contre les provinces de Connacht et Meath. Brian Boru participé à ces premières descentes avec son frère et son père. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Après Mathgamain capturé la province de Munster, le Eógnacht Roi a organisé une antipersonnel Dalcassian d'alliance. Lors de la bataille de Sulchoid, le Dalcassian armée dirigée par Mathgamain et résolument Boru défait l'armée Hiberno scandinave de Limerick et pillé la ville. En 976, Mathgamain assisté à une réunion prétendument pacifique, où il a été assassiné. Ainsi, Brian Boru est devenu le nouveau chef du Dalcassians. Afin de venger la mort de son frère, Brian Boru rétabli la Dalcassian contrôle de Munster. À la fin, il a tué plusieurs dirigeants impliqués dans la lutte contre la Dalcassian d'alliance. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Après avoir primauté de la Province de Munster, Brian expose ensuite d'étendre son autorité aux provinces du Leinster et le Connacht. Ce faisant, il entre en conflit avec le Haut Roi Máel Sechnaill mac, Domnaill dont le pouvoir de base a été, dans la province de Meath. Pour les quinze prochaines années, le grand roi Máel reprises armées en plomb et le Leinster Boru a conduit ses forces navales de la rivière Shannon et à l'attaque Connacht Meath. Boru mis au point une stratégie militaire utilisée que les forces des deux terres et en eau qui servira bien tout au long de sa carrière. En 966, Boru est parvenu à contrôler la Province de Leinster et le Munster, tandis que Máel Sechnaill était encore dans le contrôle des provinces de Meath, Connacht et Ulster. Après le renversement du roi de Leinster, Brian Boru's sélectionnés pour le dirigeant de Munster se sont rebellés contre lui. Les parties adverses ont combattu les armées de la bataille de Glen Mama. Brian victorieuse de l'armée et a été capturé et mis à sac l'ennemi de la ville. [PARAGRAPH: 1] En l'an 1000, le roi Brian Boru mener une combinés Munster - Leinster - Dublin armée sur une attaque contre le Haut Roi Mael Sechnaill mac, Domnaill domicile, dans la province de Meath. Meath allié le plus important est de la province de Connacht. Toutefois, les deux provinces ont été séparés par une rivière donnant Boru's forces navales un avantage. En réponse à ce problème, Máel Sechnaill construit deux ponts à servir comme des obstacles et d'une connexion entre les Provinces de Meath et Connacht. En 1002, Máel Sechnaill remis son titre pour Brian Boru. Afin de porter le titre de Grand Roi, non seulement comme un nom mais un titre fiable, Boru a dû étendre son autorité à la province de l'Ulster. Emplacement géographique de l'Ulster a présenté un grand défi contre Boru's armée. Il a fallu Boru dix années de la campagne pour atteindre leur but. Mais accéder à la province de l'Ulster lui a apporté la moitié seulement de son but. Brian systématiquement défaits chacun des dirigeants régionaux qui ont défié lui, les forçant à reconnaître comme leur maître. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Brian Boru bénéficié de l'appui d'un important monastère en Irlande, Armagh. Armagh lui a donné un appui financier après Brian Boru a généreusement fait don au monastère d'or et déclaré qu'elle était la capitale religieuse de l'Irlande. Máel M + rda mac, Murchada de Leinster a augmenté dans la rébellion en 1012. Máel M + rda cherché des alliés avec qui défient le Haut Roi. Ensemble, ils ont attaqué la Province de Meath et en 1013, Boru a conduit une force de Munster et dans le sud du Connacht Leinster. La ville de Dublin a été bloqué par l'armée Boru. Son armée a été contrainte d'abandonner le siège lorsqu'ils ont manqué de fournitures de l'armée avant de Máel M + rda. Máel M + rda se fondait sur l'idée que s'il a défié Boru, les dirigeants des autres provinces aiderait lui. Il a eu tort, cependant, avec une seule règle de l'Ulster fournir un appui. Quand Boru retournés dans 1014, Má n'avait pas d'autre choix que d'envoyer son cousin, Sigtrygg, étranger à solliciter des aides. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Sigtrygg navigué à Orkeney Island et l'île de Man. Tous les hommes sont ici au service de Máel M + rda. Boru's troupes sont de Munster et dans le sud du Connacht. Boru perdu le soutien du roi de Meath après un désaccord et était donc à perte dans la bataille. Les combats ont eu lieu juste au nord de Dublin, à Clontarf. La bataille de Clontarf entraîné la mort de Brian Boru. Il existe de nombreuses légendes concernant sa mort, de mourir dans un héroïque man-to-man combat pour être tué fuyant Viking mercenaire Brodir en priant dans sa tente. Il est dit que Boru est enterré dans l'enceinte de la cathédrale Saint Patrick dans la ville d'Armagh.</French>
		<German>[H1]Brian Boru[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Irische Hochk&#246;nige[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lebte:[\BOLD] 941 - 1014[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Hintergrund:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Brian Boru war wahrscheinlich geboren in 941, obwohl einige Quellen, dass er geboren wurde so früh wie 926. Er wurde geboren in der Nähe Killaloe, eine Stadt in der Region Thomond, wo sein Vater, Cenneétig Mac Lorcáin war König. Als Brian's Vater starb, das Königtum von Thomond an seinem älteren Bruder, Mathgamain. Wenn Mathgamain wurde in 976, Brian ersetzt ihn und wurde zum König des gesamten Königreich Munster. Brian Boru gehörte zu den Dál Cais besetzt, die ein Gebiet über den Fluss Shannon, ein Gebiet, das später als das Königreich Thomond und umfasst heute die Grafschaften Clare und Limerick. Die Shannon als eine einfache Weg für die Überfälle könnte gegen den Provinzen Connacht und Meath. Brian Boru an diese frühen Überfälle zusammen mit seinem Bruder und Vater. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Nach Mathgamain gefangen der Provinz Munster, die Eógnacht King organisierte gegen Dalcassian Allianz. In der Schlacht von Sulchoid, die Dalcassian Armee unter Mathgamain und Boru entschlossen gegen die Wikinger Hiberno Armee von Limerick und geplündert der Stadt. In 976, Mathgamain an einem angeblich friedlichen Treffen, wo er ermordet wurde. So, Brian Boru wurde der neue Führer der Dalcassians. Um Rache für den Tod seines Bruders, Brian Boru wieder die Dalcassian Kontrolle über Munster. Am Ende hatte er getötet, mehrere Herrscher an der Bekämpfung der Dalcassian Allianz. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Nachdem der Regel in der Provinz Munster, Brian dann zu erweitern, seine Autorität in die Provinzen Leinster und Connacht. Dabei kam er in Konflikt mit dem Hohen König Máel Sechnaill Mac Domnaill, dessen Macht in der Provinz Meath. Für die nächsten fünfzehn Jahren, die hohe König Máel wiederholt führen Armeen in Leinster und Boru führte seine Seestreitkräfte der Shannon zum Angriff Connacht und Meath. Boru entwickelt eine militärische Strategie, die das Kräfte an Land und Wasser, würde ihm auch in seiner Karriere. In 966, Boru gelungen, die Kontrolle der Provinz Leinster und Munster, während Máel Sechnaill noch in die Kontrolle der Provinzen Meath, Connacht und Ulster. Nach der Absetzung des Königs von Leinster, Brian Boru's ausgewählte Lineal für Munster rebelliert gegen ihn. Die gegnerischen Seiten der Armeen gekämpft der Schlacht von Glen Mama. Brians Armee war siegreich und gefangen genommen und entlassen, der den Feind Stadt. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Im Jahr 1000, King Brian Boru führen eine kombinierte Munster - Leinster - Dublin Armee einen Angriff auf den Hohen König Mael Sechnaill Mac Domnaill zu Hause in der Provinz Meath. Meath wichtigster Verbündeter war die Provinz Connacht. Allerdings sind die beiden Provinzen wurden getrennt durch einen Fluss geben Boru's Seestreitkräfte von Vorteil. Als Reaktion auf dieses Problem zu lösen, Máel Sechnaill gebaut zwei Brücken, die als Hindernisse und eine Verbindung zwischen den Provinzen Meath und Connacht. In 1002, Máel Sechnaill verzichtet seinen Titel an Brian Boru. Um den Titel High King nicht nur als Name, sondern eine zuverlässige Titel, Boru hatte, seine Autorität in der Provinz Ulster. Ulster die geografische Lage eine große Herausforderung gegen Boru's Armee. Es dauerte Boru zehn Jahren Kampagnen sein Ziel zu erreichen. Aber gewinnen Eintrag in der Provinz Ulster brachte ihn nur auf halbem Weg zu seinem Ziel. Brian systematisch gegen jede der regionalen Herrscher, trotzte ihm, dass sie gezwungen sind, erkennen ihn als ihr Oberherr. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Brian Boru erhielt Unterstützung von einer wichtigen Kloster in Irland, Armagh. Armagh gab ihm finanzielle Unterstützung nach Brian Boru großzügig gespendeten Gold, das Kloster und erklärte, es den religiösen Hauptstadt von Irland. Máel M + rda Mac Murchada Leinster stieg in Rebellion im 1012. Máel M + rda suchte Verbündete, mit denen zu trotzen dem Hohen König. Gemeinsam griffen sie der Provinz Meath und in 1013, Boru führte eine Kraft aus Munster und südlichen Connacht in Leinster. Die Stadt Dublin wurde blockiert durch Boru's Armee. Seine Armee war gezwungen, die Belagerung aufgeben, wenn sie lief aus, bevor die Armee von Máel M + rda. Máel M + rda wurde unter Berufung auf den Gedanken, dass, wenn er trotzte Boru, der Herrscher der anderen Bundesländer würde ihm. Er war falsch, allerdings mit einem einzigen Herrscher von Ulster Unterstützung. Wenn Boru wieder in 1014, Má hatte keine andere Wahl, als zu senden sein Cousin, Sigtrygg, Übersee um Hilfe. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Sigtrygg segelte zu Orkeney Island und der Isle of Man. Alle hier waren die Männer in den Dienst der Máel M + rda. Boru's Truppen aus Munster und südlichen Connacht. Boru verlor die Unterstützung des Königs von Meath nach einem Streit und wurde damit zu einem Verlust in der Schlacht. Die Kämpfe fanden nur nördlich von Dublin, bei Clontarf. Die Schlacht bei Clontarf führte zu dem Tod von Brian Boru. Es gibt viele Legenden über seinen Tod, von Sterben in einer heroischen von Mann zu Mann zu bekämpfen getötet Flucht Viking Söldneraktivitäten Brodir während beten in seinem Zelt. Es wird gesagt, dass Boru begraben liegt auf dem Gelände des St. Patrick's Cathedral in der Stadt Armagh.</German>
		<Italian>[H1]Brian Boru[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Grand re di Irlanda[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Vita:[\BOLD] 941 - 1014[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Informazioni:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Brian Boru era probabilmente nato nel 941, anche se alcune fonti affermano che egli è nato già nel 926. Era nato vicino a Killaloe, una città nella regione di Thomond dove suo padre, Cenneétig Mac Lorcáin era re. Brian, quando il padre morì, il regno di Thomond passò a suo fratello, Mathgamain. Quando Mathgamain è stato ucciso nel 976, Brian sostituito lui, e divenne il re di tutto il regno di Munster. Brian Boru apparteneva alla Dál Cais che ha occupato un territorio attraverso il fiume Shannon, un territorio che, in seguito, essere conosciuto come il Regno di Thomond e oggi comprende le contee di Clare e di Limerick. La Shannon è servita come un facile percorso attraverso il quale può essere effettuato incursioni contro le province di Connacht e Meath. Brian Boru partecipato a questi primi raid insieme al fratello e padre. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Dopo Mathgamain catturato provincia di Munster, il Eógnacht re organizzato un antidumping Dalcassian alleanza. Nella Battaglia di Sulchoid, il Dalcassian esercito guidato da Mathgamain e Boru risolutamente sconfitto il Hiberno norvegese esercito di Limerick e saccheggiato la città. Nel 976, Mathgamain hanno partecipato a un incontro presumibilmente pacifica, dove è stato assassinato. Così, Brian Boru è diventato il nuovo leader della Dalcassians. Al fine di vendicare la morte di suo fratello, Brian Boru ristabilita la Dalcassian il controllo su di Munster. Entro la fine, di aver ucciso diversi governanti coinvolti nella lotta Dalcassian alleanza. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Dopo aver regola della Provincia di Munster, di cui Brian poi di estendere la sua autorità per le province di Leinster e Connacht. In tal modo, egli è entrato in conflitto con l'Alto Re Máel Sechnaill Mac Domnaill la cui base di potere è stato in provincia di Meath. Per i prossimi quindici anni, l'alto re Máel ripetutamente portare le forze armate in Leinster e Boru ha portato la sua forze navali il fiume Shannon per attaccare Connacht e Meath. Boru sviluppato una strategia militare che le forze utilizzati su entrambi i terreni e di acqua che potrebbe servire lui e per tutta la sua carriera. Nel 966, Boru gestita per il controllo della provincia di Leinster e Munster, mentre Máel Sechnaill era ancora in fase di controllo delle Province di Meath, Connacht e Ulster. Dopo deponendo il re di Leinster, Brian Boru's selezionati righello per Munster ribellato contro di lui. Le opposizioni degli eserciti combattuta la battaglia di Glen Mama. Brian esercito vittorioso è stato catturato e saccheggiata e il nemico della città. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Nel 1000, il re Brian Boru condurre una combinata Leinster Munster - Dublino - esercito in un attacco contro la High re di Mael Sechnaill Mac Domnaill casa in provincia di Meath. Meath alleato più importante è stata la Provincia di Connacht. Tuttavia, le due province sono stati separati da un fiume dando Boru forze navali di un vantaggio. In risposta a questo problema, Máel Sechnaill costruito due ponti a servire come ostacoli e di un collegamento tra le Province di Meath e Connacht. Nel 1002, Máel Sechnaill rinuncia titolo a Brian Boru. Al fine di utilizzare il titolo di Re non solo come un nome ma un titolo affidabile, Boru era di estendere la sua autorità per la Provincia di Ulster. Ulster la posizione geografica ha presentato una grande sfida contro l'esercito di Boru. Boru ci sono voluti dieci anni di campagne di raggiungere il suo obiettivo. Ma di entrare alla Provincia di Ulster lo portò soltanto a metà per il suo obiettivo. Brian sistematicamente sconfitti ciascuno dei governanti regionali che hanno sfidato lui, costringendoli a riconoscerlo come loro overlord. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Brian Boru ricevuto il sostegno di un importante monastero in Irlanda, Armagh. Armagh ha dato sostegno finanziario dopo Brian Boru generosamente donato oro per il monastero e ha dichiarato che la capitale religiosa d'Irlanda. Máel M + rda Mac Murchada di Leinster insorsero nel 1012. Máel M + rda cercato alleati con cui sfidare l'Alto Re. Insieme, hanno attaccato la Provincia di Meath e nel 1013, Boru ha portato una forza da Munster e meridionale in Connacht Leinster. La città di Dublino, è stato bloccato dalla Boru l'esercito. Il suo esercito è stato costretto ad abbandonare l'assedio, quando uscì la prima delle forniture esercito di Máel M + rda. Máel M + rda era far valere il pensiero che, se egli sfidato Boru, il governo delle altre Province che lo aiuti. Era sbagliato, tuttavia, con un unico governante da Ulster fornendo sostegno. Quando Boru restituiti nel 1014, Má non ha avuto altra scelta se non quella di inviare il cugino, Sigtrygg, oltremare, a cercare aiuto. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Sigtrygg navigato per Orkeney Island e l'Isola di Man. Tutti gli uomini qui sono stati al servizio del Máel M + rda. Boru le truppe sono state da Munster e Connacht meridionale. Boru perso l'appoggio del re di Meath, dopo un disaccordo ed è stato quindi a una perdita in battaglia. I combattimenti hanno avuto luogo a nord di Dublin, a Clontarf. La battaglia di Clontarf causato la morte di Brian Boru. Ci sono molte leggende sulla sua morte, di morire in un eroico uomo a uomo combattere ad essere uccisi in fuga Viking mercenari Brodir mentre pregava nella sua tenda. Si dice che Boru è sepolto nella motivazione della St Patrick's Cathedral nella città di Armagh.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[H1]Brian Boru[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Gran rey de Irlanda[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Vivi&#243;:[\BOLD] 941 - 1014[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Historia:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Brian Boru probablemente nació en 941, aunque algunas fuentes afirman que él nació ya en 926. Él nació cerca de Killaloe, una ciudad en la región de Thomond donde su padre, Cenneétig Mac Lorcáin fue rey. Cuando murió el padre de Brian, el reinado de Thomond pasó a su hermano mayor, Mathgamain. Cuando Mathgamain fue asesinado en 976, Brian lo reemplazó y se convirtió en el rey de todo el reino de Munster. Brian Boru pertenecían a la Dál Cais que ocuparon un territorio a través del río Shannon, un territorio que más tarde sería conocido como el Reino de Thomond y en la actualidad abarca los condados de Limerick y de Clare. The Shannon sirvió como un recorrido fácil por la que podría hacerse redadas en contra de las provincias de Connacht y Meath. Brian Boru participó en las incursiones a lo largo de estos primeros con su hermano y su padre. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Después de Mathgamain capturaron la provincia de Munster, la Eógnacht King organizó una lucha contra la Dalcassian alianza. En la Batalla de Sulchoid, la Dalcassian ejército dirigido por Mathgamain y Boru resueltamente derrotó al ejército de Norse Hiberno Limerick y saquearon la ciudad. En 976, Mathgamain asistió a una reunión supuestamente pacíficos, donde fue asesinado. Así, Brian Boru se convirtió en el nuevo líder de la Dalcassians. Con el fin de vengar la muerte de su hermano, Brian Boru restablecido el Dalcassian control de Munster. Al final, que había asesinado a varios gobernantes que participan en la lucha contra la Dalcassian alianza. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Después de haber estado de la provincia de Munster, Brian entonces establecido para extender su autoridad a las provincias de Leinster y Connacht. Al hacerlo, entró en conflicto con el Alto Rey Máel Sechnaill Mac Domnaill cuya base de poder es en la provincia de Meath. Para los próximos quince años, la alta Rey Máel repetidamente conducir ejércitos en Leinster y dirigió a su Boru fuerzas navales hasta el río Shannon a atacar Connacht y Meath. Boru desarrollado una estrategia militar que utilizan las fuerzas de la tierra y el agua que sirva lo mejor en toda su carrera. En 966, Boru logrado controlar la provincia de Leinster y Munster, mientras que Máel Sechnaill todavía estaba en el control de las provincias de Meath, Connacht y Ulster. Después de deponer al rey de Leinster, Brian Boru's seleccionados gobernante de Munster se rebeló contra él. Las partes enfrentadas de los ejércitos lucho en la Batalla de Glen Mama. Brian's ejército victorioso y fue capturado y saquearon la ciudad del enemigo. [PARAGRAPH: 1] En el año 1000, King Brian Boru dirigir un combinado Munster - Leinster - Dublin ejército en un ataque en el Alto Rey Mael Sechnaill Mac Domnaill la casa en la provincia de Meath. Meath el aliado más importante fue la provincia de Connacht. Sin embargo, las dos provincias separadas por un río que Boru's fuerzas navales una ventaja. En respuesta a este problema, Máel Sechnaill construido dos puentes para actuar como obstáculos y una conexión entre las provincias de Meath y Connacht. En 1002, Máel Sechnaill entregó su título a Brian Boru. Con el fin de utilizar el título de Alto Rey, no sólo como un nombre, sino un título fiable, Boru tuvo que extender su autoridad a la Provincia de Ulster. La ubicación geográfica de Ulster presenta un gran desafío contra el ejército de Boru. Tomó Boru diez años de campaña para conseguir su objetivo. Pero ingresar a la Provincia de Ulster le llevó sólo a mitad de camino a su meta. Brian derrotado sistemáticamente cada uno de los gobernantes regionales que desafiaron a él, obligándoles a reconocer él como sus a evitar. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Brian Boru recibido el apoyo de un importante monasterio en Irlanda, Armagh. Armagh le dio apoyo financiero después de Brian Boru oro donado generosamente al monasterio y declaró que la capital religiosa de Irlanda. Máel M + rda Mac Murchada de Leinster aumentó en rebelión en 1012. Máel M + rda buscado aliados con los que desafían el Alto Rey. Juntos, atacaron la provincia de Meath y, en 1013, Boru encabezó una fuerza de Munster y en el sur de Connacht Leinster. La ciudad de Dublín fue bloqueado por el ejército de Boru. Su ejército se vio obligado a abandonar el sitio cuando se acabó de suministros antes de que el ejército de Máel M + rda. Máel M + rda se basaba en la idea de que si él desafiado Boru, los gobernantes de las otras provincias que le ayuda. Él estaba equivocado, sin embargo, con un único soberano del imperio de la prestación de apoyo Ulster. Boru Cuando volvió en 1014, Má no tenían otra opción que enviar su primo, Sigtrygg, en el exterior a buscar ayuda. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Sigtrygg navegó a Orkeney Isla y la Isla de Man. Todos los hombres estaban aquí en el servicio de Máel M + rda. Boru's tropas de Munster y el sur de Connacht. Boru perdió el apoyo del rey de Meath después de un desacuerdo y, por ende, a una pérdida en la batalla. Los combates tuvieron lugar al norte de Dublin, en Clontarf. La batalla de Clontarf resultó en la muerte de Brian Boru. Se dice que Boru es enterrado en el recinto de la catedral de San Patricio en la ciudad de Armagh.</Spanish>	
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_BORU_1</Tag>
		<English>Greetings, [CT_NAME]! I hope we will be allies, for in our togetherness, castles are built.</English>
		<French>Salutations, [CT_NAME] ! J'espère que nous serons alliés, et durant notre rassemblement, des châteaux seront construits.</French>
		<German>Grüße, [CT_NAME]! Ich hoffe, wir werden Verbündeten, in unserem Miteinander, Burgen gebaut werden.</German>
		<Italian>Saluti, [CT_NAME]! Spero che saremo alleati, per il nostro stare insieme, i castelli sono costruiti.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Saludos, [CT_NAME]! Espero que seamos aliados, en nuestra unidad, se construyen castillos.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>