<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by lcollins (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- Copyright Firaxis Games 2005 -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text - New -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_KHAZARIA_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Khazar Empire</English>
		<French>Peuple khazar</French>
		<German>Chasar Reich</German>
		<Italian>Cazar Impero</Italian>
		<Spanish>Jazar Imperio</Spanish>
	</TEXT>	
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_KHAZARIA_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Khazaria</English>
		<French>Khazars</French>
		<German>Chasaria</German>
		<Italian>Cazaria</Italian>
		<Spanish>Jazaria</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_KHAZARIA_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Khazar</English>
		<French>
	    <Text>khazar:khazare:khazars:khazares</Text>
	    <Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
	    <Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
    </French>
		<German>Chasar</German>
		<Italian>Cazar</Italian>
		<Spanish>Jazar</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_KHAZARIA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]In the seventh century, in the region between the Black Sea and the Caspian Sea, a free Jewish state was established.  Its people were a mix of Khazar Turks, whom were part of the Gok Turkic Migration, the Huns, the Bulgars, and the Caucasians.  The story of the Khazar Empire begins when the infant-empire Khagan Bulan heard from an Arab mullah, a Christian priest, and a Jewish rabbi on the reasons why Khazaria should adopt each of their religions.  After much thought, Bulan decided to adopt the Jewish faith.  Nowhere else in the world, has a non-Jewish nation undergone such a conversion as Bulan faced the Muslim expansion of the South, and the Christian expansion to the west.  A few wars between the Khazars and Arabs prevented Islam from spreading across all of eastern Europe at a time when Islam was attracting many followers.  It also became a place of safety and refuge for the Jewish people, as the rest of the world were persecuted.[PARAGRAPH: 1]Khazar power begins at about 650 BC, when the Turkic kingdom formed after the breakup of the Gok Turks and the collapse of their rival the Avars.  Khazar culture was molded around the Gok Turks, with the Khagan holding supreme power and the Khagan Bek being the military power.  The Khazars used a runic script that originated in Mongolia as their language.  Most of the Turkish groups of the period used the same type of language.[PARAGRAPH: 1]Arab scholars of the time provide the most knowledge of the Khazars.  An 11th century Muslim chronicler elaborated on the man who brought the Jewish faith to Khazaria.  His writings explain how a single Khazar Jew, who had a high military rank, converted all the other Khazars to Judaism.  The chronicler went on to explain how the Khazars observed Judaism.  Obadiah, one of Bulan's descendants, consolidated the newly-adopted religion with the construction of synogogues and invited Jewish scholars to confine other doubters among the aristocracy.  However, it was not only the military elite and the nobles who were converted.  The common people embraced the new religion with open arms.  Pagan shamanism was the Khazar's original religion, remained in place as were other religions.  Incredibly, a seven-strong Supreme Court with representatives of all faiths was established to ensure fair hearing for all people.  Such religious tolerance was unheard of.[PARAGRAPH: 1]Although the Khazars were nomadic people, the conversion to Judaism rapidly opted for a more settled existence with Khazaria prospering from farming, the production of goods, and trading.  Khazaria also did play a role in the defeat of Persia in the 7th century, allying it self with the Turks and the Byzantines.  There were also a series of wars in the 8th century against the Arabs that established Khazaria's southern borders at the Caucasus Mountains.  However, the Khazars are associated with a period of peace along the steppe because they were more concerned with commerce than warfare.[PARAGRAPH: 1]The Khazars were very cooperative with their neighbors such that the Byzantines build a wall for them at the city of Sarkel along the Don River.  Byzantine emperors Justinian II and Constantine V both took a Khazar wife.  Khazar also brought many new technologies in since Jews from all over the world came in search of a Jewish beacon.  All this helped to strengthen Khazaria and make it into a cosmopolitan and a progressive civilization.[PARAGRAPH: 1]At the empires greatest extent at 850, it stretched from the Black to the Caspian sea.  The waterways were trading links and the Khazars built the city of Kiev, later becoming its capital.  The most enduring of Khazar capitals was Itil.  It had a trading post, an administrative center, and religious hearland for the Jews.  It also had an Islamic mosque to serve the Muslim population.  Khazar power ended under Svyatoslav, the ruler of Kiev.  Khazaria was then taken over by the neighboring Pechenegs, Oghuz, and Byzantine peoples.  Khazar traders faced difficult circumstances during these times and all mention of them ends.  The Penchenegs who had much of Khazar land did not focus on trade, and disrupted the trade with Eastern Europe.</English>
		<French>[TAB]Au septième siècle, dans la région entre la Mer Noire et la mer caspienne, un état juif libre a été établi. Ses personnes étaient un mélange des Turcs de Khazar, qui faisaient partie de la migration de Gok Turkic, les huns, le Bulgars, et les Caucasiens. L'histoire de l'empire de Khazar commence quand l'enfant en bas âge-empire Khagan Bulan reçu des nouvelles un mollah arabe, un prêtre chrétien, et un rabbin juif sur les raisons pour lesquelles Khazaria devrait adopter chacune de leurs religions. Après beaucoup de pensée, Bulan a décidé d'adopter la foi juive. Nulle part autrement dans le monde, a une nation non-Juive subie une telle conversion que Bulan a fait face à l'expansion musulmane des sud, et l'expansion chrétienne à l'ouest. Quelques guerres entre le Khazars et les Arabes ont empêché l'Islam d'écarter à travers toute l'Europe de l'Est à un moment où l'Islam attirait beaucoup de disciples. C'est également devenu un endroit de la sûreté et refuge pour les personnes juives, pendant que le reste du monde étaient persécutés. [PARAGRAPH: 1] La puissance de Khazar commence à environ 650 AVANT JÉSUS CHRIST, quand le royaume de Turkic a formé après la dissolution des Turcs de Gok et l'effondrement de leur rival l'Avars. La culture de Khazar a été moulée autour des Turcs de Gok, avec le Khagan tenant la puissance suprême et le Khagan Bek étant la puissance militaire. Le Khazars a employé un manuscrit runic qui a provenu de la Mongolie en tant que leur langue. La plupart des groupes turcs de la période ont employé le même type de langue. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Les disciples arabes du temps fournissent la plupart de connaissance du Khazars. Un chroniqueur musulman du 11ème siècle a élaboré sur l'homme qui a apporté la foi juive à Khazaria. Ses écritures expliquent comment un juif simple de Khazar, qui a eu un rang élevé de militaires, a converti tout autre Khazars en judaïsme. Le chroniqueur a continué pour expliquer comment le Khazars a observé le judaïsme. Obadiah, un des descendants de Bulan, a consolidé la religion nouveau-adoptée avec la construction des synogogues et a invité les disciples juifs au confince d'autres douteurs parmi l'aristocratie. Cependant, c'était non seulement l'élite militaire et les nobles qui ont été convertis. Les gens du commun ont embrassé la nouvelle religion avec les bras ouverts. Le shamanism païen était la religion originale du Khazar, restée en place de même que d'autres religions. Incredibely, une cour suprême sept-forte avec des représentants de toutes les fois a été établi pour assurer l'audition juste pour toutes les personnes. Une telle tolérance religieuse était inconnue. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Bien que le Khazars aient été des personnes de nomadiv, la conversion en judaïsme a rapidement opté pour un existance plus arrangé avec Khazaria prospérant de l'affermage, de la production des marchandises, et du commerce. Khazaria également a joué un rôle dans la défaite de Perse au 7ème siècle, l'alliant individu avec les Turcs et le Byzantines. Là wer également qu'une série de guerres dans le 8ème centurey contre les Arabes qui ont établi le souther de Khazaria encadre aux montagnes de Caucase. Cependant, le Khazars sont associés à une période de paix le long de la steppe parce qu'elles davantage ont été concernées par le commerce que la guerre. [PARAGRAPH : 1] Le Khazars étaient très coopertive avec leurs voisins tels que la construction de Byzantines un mur pour eux à la ville de Sarkel le long du fleuve de Don. Les emporors bizantins Justinian II et Constantine V tous les deux ont pris une épouse de Khazar. Khazar également a apporté beaucoup de nouvelles technologies dedans puisque les juifs de sont partout dans le monde venus à la recherche d'une balise juive. Tout ceci a aidé à renforcer Khazaria et à le transformer en une civilisation cosmopolite et progressive. [PARAGRAPH : 1] À la plus grande ampleur d'empires à 850, il s'est étendu du noir à la mer caspienne. Les voies d'eau commerçaient des liens et le Khazars a construit la ville de Kiev, devenant plus tard son capital. La résistance des capitaux de Khazar était Itil. Elle a eu un comptoir commercial, un centre administratif, et le hearland religieux pour les juifs. Elle a également eu une mosquée islamique pour servir la population musulmane. La puissance de Khazar a fini sous Svyatoslav, la règle de Kiev. Khazaria a été alors succédé par le Pechenegs voisin, l'Oghuz, et les peuples bizantins. Les commerçants de Khazar ont fait face à des circonstances difficiles pendant ces périodes et toute la mention de elles des extrémités. Le Penchenegs qui a eu beaucoup de terre de Khazar ne s'est pas concentré sur le commerce, et distrupted le commerce avec l'Europe de l'Est.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Im 7. Jahrhundert in der Region zwischen dem Schwarzen Meer und dem kaspischen Meer, wurde ein freier jüdischer Zustand hergestellt. Seine Leute waren eine Mischung der Khazar Türken, die ein Teil der Gok Turkic Migration, die Hunnen, das Bulgars und die Kaukasier waren. Die Geschichte des Khazar Reiches fängt wenn das Kindreich Khagan Bulan an, das von einem arabischen Mulla, von einem christlichen Priester und von einem jüdischen Rabbiner auf den Gründen gehört wird, warum Khazaria jede ihrer Religionen annehmen sollte. Nach vielem Gedanken entschied Bulan, den jüdischen Glauben anzunehmen. Nirgendwo sonst in der Welt, hat eine nicht-Jüdische Nation, die solch einer Umwandlung durchgemacht wird, der Bulan die moslemische Expansion des Südens gegenüberstellte, und der christlichen Expansion zum Westen. Einige Kriege zwischen dem Khazars und den Arabern verhinderten Islam am Verbreiten über den ganzen Osteuropa, zu einer Zeit als Islam viele Nachfolger anzog. Es wurde auch ein Ort der Sicherheit und Schutz für die jüdischen Leute, während der Rest der Welt verfolgt wurden. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Khazar Energie fängt an ungefähr 650 BC an, als das Turkic Königreich nach dem Auseinanderbrechen der Gok Türken und dem Einsturz ihres Rivalen das Avars sich bildete. Khazar Kultur wurde um die Gok Türken geformt, wenn das Khagan Oberste Energie hält und dem Khagan Bek, das die militärische Energie ist. Das Khazars benutzte einen runic Index, der in Mongolei als ihre Sprache entstand. Die meisten türkischen Gruppen der Periode benutzten die gleiche Art der Sprache. [PARAGRAPH: 3] Arabische Gelehrte der Zeit stellen das meiste Wissen des Khazars zur Verfügung. Ein moslemischer Chronist des 11. Jahrhunderts arbeitete auf dem Mann aus, der Khazaria den jüdischen Glauben holte. Seine Schreiben erklären, wie ein einzelner Khazar Jude, der einen hohen Militärrank hatte, alles andere Khazars in Judentum umwandelte. Der Chronist fuhr fort, zu erklären, wie das Khazars Judentum beobachtete. Obadiah, einer von Nachkommen Bulans, vereinigte die neu-angenommene Religion mit dem Aufbau von synogogues und lud jüdische Gelehrte zum confince andere Zweifler unter der Aristokratie ein. Jedoch war es nicht nur die militärische Auslese und die Adligen, die umgewandelt wurden. Die gewöhnlichen Leute umfaßten die neue Religion mit den geöffneten Armen. Heidnisches shamanism war die des Khazars ursprüngliche Religion, an der richtigen Stelle geblieben, wie andere Religionen. Incredibely, ein sieben-starkes Höchstes Gericht mit Repräsentanten aller Glauben wurde hergestellt, um angemessene Hörfähigkeit für alle Leute sicherzustellen. Solche fromme Toleranz war von ungehört. [PARAGRAPH: 4] Obgleich das Khazars nomadiv Leute waren, entschied die Umwandlung zum Judentum schnell für ein vereinbartes existance mit Khazaria, das vom Bewirtschaften, von der Produktion von Waren und vom Handeln sich erweitert. Khazaria auch spielte eine Rolle in der Niederlage von Persien im 7. Jahrhundert und verband sie Selbst mit den Türken und dem Byzantines. Dort wer, auch, das eine Reihe Kriege im 8. centurey gegen die Araber, die souther Khazarias herstellten, an den Kaukasus Bergen einfaßt. Jedoch sind das Khazars mit einer Periode des Friedens entlang der Steppe verbunden, weil sie mehr mit Handel als Kriegsführung betroffen wurden. [PARAGRAPH: 5] Das Khazars waren mit ihren Nachbarn so daß der Byzantines Bau eine Wand für sie an der Stadt von Sarkel entlang dem anziehenfluß sehr coopertive. Byzantinische emporors Justinian II und Constantine V beide nahmen eine Khazar Frau. Khazar holte auch viele neue Technologien innen, da Juden von auf der ganzen Erde auf der Suche nach einem jüdischen Leuchtfeuer kamen. Alles half dieses, Khazaria zu verstärken und es in eine Welt- und progressive Zivilisation zu bilden. [PARAGRAPH: 6] Am größten Umfang der Reiche bei 850, dehnte er vom Schwarzen zum kaspischen Meer aus. Die Wassern-Strasse handelten Verbindungen und das Khazars errichtete die Stadt von Kiew und später wurde sein Kapital. Das Aushalten der Khazar Kapitalien war Itil. Es hatte einen handelnden Pfosten, eine Verwaltungsstelle und frommes hearland für die Juden. Es hatte auch eine islamische Moschee, zum der moslemischen Bevölkerung zu dienen. Khazar Energie beendete unter Svyatoslav, die Lehre von Kiew. Khazaria wurde dann vom benachbarten Pechenegs, vom Oghuz und von den byzantinischen Völkern übernommen. Khazar Händler stellten schwierige Umstände während dieser Zeiten und aller Erwähnung von ihnen Enden gegenüber. Das Penchenegs, das viel von Khazar Land hatte, konzentrierte nicht auf Handel und distrupted den Handel mit Osteuropa.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB]Nel settimo secolo, nella regione fra il Mar Nero ed il mare caspico, un ebreo libero dichiara è stato stabilito. La relativa gente era una miscela dei Turchi di Khazar, quale facevano parte dell'espansione di Gok Turkic, i Huns, il Bulgars ed i Caucasians. La storia dell'impero di Khazar comincia quando l'infante-impero Khagan Bulan ascoltato di un mullah arabo, di un priest cristiano e di un rabbi ebreo sulle ragioni per le quali Khazaria dovrebbe adottare ciascuna delle loro religioni. Dopo molto pensiero, Bulan ha deciso adottare la fede ebrea. In nessun posto altrimenti nel mondo, ha una nazione non-Ebrea subita una tal conversione come Bulan ha affrontato l'espansione musulmana del sud e l'espansione cristiana all'ovest. Alcune guerre fra il Khazars e gli arabi hanno impedito l'Islam la diffusione attraverso tutta l'Europa Orientale in un momento in cui l'Islam stava attraendo molti seguicamme. Inoltre si è trasformato in in un posto di sicurezza ed in rifugio per la gente ebrea, mentre il resto del mondo persecuted. [PARAGRAPH: 2] L'alimentazione di Khazar comincia BC a circa 650, quando il regno di Turkic ha formato dopo il disfacimento dei Turchi di Gok ed il crollo del loro rivale il Avars. La coltura di Khazar è stata modellata intorno ai Turchi di Gok, con l'alimentazione suprema della tenuta di Khagan e il Khagan Bek che è l'alimentazione militare. Il Khazars ha usato uno scritto runic che ha provenuto in Mongolia come loro lingua. La maggior parte dei gruppi turchi del periodo hanno usato lo stesso tipo di lingua. [PARAGRAPH: 3] Gli eruditi arabi del tempo forniscono la maggior parte della conoscenza del Khazars. Un chronicler musulmano di undicesimo secolo ha elaborato sull'uomo che ha portato la fede ebrea a Khazaria. Le sue scritture spiegano come un singolo ebreo di Khazar, che ha avuto un alto Rank dei militari, ha convertito tutto il altro Khazars in Judaism. Il chronicler ha continuato a spiegare come il Khazars ha osservato il Judaism. Obadiah, uno dei discendenti del Bulan, ha consolidato la religione nuovo-adottata con la costruzione degli synogogues ed ha invitato gli eruditi ebrei al confince altri doubters fra il aristocracy. Tuttavia, era non solo l'elite militare ed i nobili che sono stati convertiti. La gente comune ha abbracciato la nuova religione con le armi aperte. Lo shamanism Pagan era la religione originale del Khazar, rimasta sul posto come erano altre religioni. Incredibely, una Corte suprema sette-forte con i rappresentanti di tutta la fede è stato stabilito per accertare l'udienza giusta per tutta la gente. Tale tolleranza religiosa era unheard di. [PARAGRAPH: 4] Anche se il Khazars era la gente del nomadiv, la conversione a Judaism ha optato velocemente per un existance depositato con Khazaria che prospera dall'agricoltura, dalla produzione delle merci e dal commercio. Khazaria inoltre ha svolto un ruolo nella sconfitta della Persia nel settimo secolo, alleante lo auto con i Turchi e il Byzantines. Là wer inoltre che una serie di guerre nell'ottavo centurey contro gli arabi che hanno stabilito il souther del Khazaria borders alle montagne del Caucaso. Tuttavia, il Khazars è associato con un periodo di pace lungo la steppa perché di più sono state interessate del commercio che la guerra. [PARAGRAPH: 5] Il Khazars era molto coopertive con i loro vicini tali che la configurazione di Byzantines una parete per loro alla città di Sarkel lungo il fiume di indoss. I emporors Byzantine Justinian II e Constantine V entrambi hanno preso una moglie di Khazar. Khazar inoltre ha portato molte nuove tecnologie dentro poiché gli ebrei da dappertutto sono venuto alla ricerca di un falò ebreo. Tutto questo ha contribuito a rinforzare Khazaria e trasformarlo una civilizzazione cosmopolita e progressiva. [PARAGRAPH: 6] Al limite più grande degli imperi a 850, ha allungato dal nero al mare caspico. I canali navigabili stavano commerciando i collegamenti e il Khazars ha costruito la città di Kiev, successivamente trasformantesi nel relativo capitale. Resistere dei capitali di Khazar era Itil. Ha avuto un alberino di commercio, un centro amministrativo e hearland religioso per gli ebrei. Inoltre ha avuto un mosque islamico per servire la popolazione musulmana. L'alimentazione di Khazar si è conclusa sotto Svyatoslav, il righello di Kiev. Khazaria allora è stato rilevato dal Pechenegs vicino, dal Oghuz e dalla gente Byzantine. I commercianti di Khazar hanno affrontato le circostanze difficili durante questi periodi e tutta la menzione di loro estremità. Il Penchenegs che ha avuto molta della terra di Khazar non ha messo a fuoco su commercio e distrupted il commercio con l'Europa Orientale.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB]En el séptimo siglo, en la región entre el Mar Negro y el mar caspio, un estado judío libre fue establecido. Su gente era una mezcla de los turcos de Khazar, que eran parte de la migración de Gok Turkic, los Huns, el Bulgars, y los caucásicos. La historia del imperio de Khazar comienza cuando el infante-imperio Khagan Bulan recibido noticias un mullah árabe, un sacerdote cristiano, y un rabino judío en las razones por las que Khazaria debe adoptar cada uno de sus religiones. Después de mucho pensamiento, Bulan decidía a adoptar la fe judía. En ninguna parte en el mundo, tiene una nación no-Judía experimentada una conversión tal que Bulan hizo frente a la extensión musulmana del sur, y la extensión cristiana al oeste. Algunas guerras entre el Khazars y los árabes evitaron que el Islam se separara a través de toda la Europa Oriental en un momento en que el Islam atraía muchos seguidores. También se convirtió en un lugar de la seguridad y refugio para la gente judía, mientras que el resto del mundo fue perseguido. [PARAGRAPH: 2] La energía de Khazar comienza aproximadamente 650 A.C., cuando el reino de Turkic formó después de la desintegración de los turcos de Gok y del derrumbamiento de su rival el Avars. La cultura de Khazar fue moldeada alrededor de los turcos de Gok, con el Khagan llevando a cabo energía suprema y el Khagan Bek que era la energía militar. El Khazars utilizó una escritura runic que originó en Mongolia como su lengua. La mayor parte de los grupos turcos del período utilizaron el mismo tipo de lengua. [PARAGRAPH: 3] Los eruditos árabes del tiempo proporcionan la mayoría del conocimiento del Khazars. Un cronista musulmán del 11mo siglo elaboró en el hombre que trajo la fe judía a Khazaria. Sus escrituras explican cómo un solo judío de Khazar, que tenía una alta fila de los militares, convirtió todo el otro Khazars al judaísmo. El cronista se encendió explicar cómo el Khazars observó judaísmo. Obadiah, uno de los descendientes de Bulan, consolidó la religión nuevo-adoptada con la construcción de synogogues e invitó a eruditos judíos al confince otros doubters entre la aristocracia. Sin embargo, era no sólo la élite militar y los nobles que fueron convertidos. El pueblo abrazó la nueva religión con los brazos abiertos. El shamanism Pagan era la religión original del Khazar, permanecida en lugar al igual que otras religiones. Incredibely, un Tribunal Supremo siete-fuerte con los representantes de todas las fes fue establecido para asegurar la audiencia justa para toda la gente. Tal tolerancia religiosa era unheard de. [PARAGRAPH: 4] Aunque el Khazars era gente del nomadiv, la conversión al judaísmo optó rápidamente por un existance colocado con Khazaria que prosperaba de cultivar, de la producción de mercancías, y de negociar. Khazaria también desempeñó un papel en la derrota de Persia en el 7mo siglo, aliándolo uno mismo con los turcos y el Byzantines. Allí wer también que una serie de guerras en el 8vo centurey contra los árabes que establecieron el souther de Khazaria confina en las montañas del Cáucaso. Sin embargo, el Khazars se asocia a un período de la paz a lo largo de la estepa porque fueron referidas más a comercio que la guerra. [PARAGRAPH: 5] El Khazars era muy coopertive con sus vecinos tales que la estructura de Byzantines una pared para ellos en la ciudad de Sarkel a lo largo del río del poner. Los emporors Byzantine Justinian II y Constantina V ambos tomaron a esposa de Khazar. Khazar también trajo muchas nuevas tecnologías adentro puesto que los judíos de por todo el mundo vinieron en busca de un faro judío. Todo el esto ayudó a consolidar Khazaria y a hacerlo en una civilización cosmopolita y progresiva. [PARAGRAPH: 6] En el grado más grande de los imperios en 850, estiró del negro al mar caspio. Los canales negociaban acoplamientos y el Khazars construyó la ciudad de Kiev, convirtiéndose en más adelante su capital. El aguantar de los capitales de Khazar era Itil. Tenía un poste que negociaba, un centro administrativo, y hearland religioso para los judíos. También tenía una mezquita islámica para servir a la población musulmana. La energía de Khazar terminó debajo de Svyatoslav, la regla de Kiev. Khazaria entonces fue asumido el control por el Pechenegs vecino, el Oghuz, y la gente Byzantine. Los comerciantes de Khazar hicieron frente a circunstancias difíciles durante estas épocas y toda la mención de ellas los extremos. El Penchenegs que tenía mucha de tierra de Khazar no se centró en comercio, y distrupted el comercio con Europa Oriental.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>	