<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_AKKADIAN_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Akkadian Empire</English>
		<French>Akkadian Empire</French>
		<German>Akkadian Empire</German>
		<Italian>Akkadian Empire</Italian>
		<Spanish>Akkadian Empire</Spanish>
	</TEXT>	
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_AKKADIAN_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Akkad</English>
		<French>Akkad</French>
		<German>Akkad</German>
		<Italian>Akkad</Italian>
		<Spanish>Akkad</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_AKKADIAN_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Akkadian</English>
		<French>Akkadian</French>
		<German>Akkadian</German>
		<Italian>Akkadian</Italian>
		<Spanish>Akkadian</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_SARGON</Tag>
		<English>Sargon</English>
		<French>Sargon</French>
		<German>Sargon</German>
		<Italian>Sargon</Italian>
		<Spanish>Sargon</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_ENHEDUANNA</Tag>
		<English>Enheduanna</English>
		<French>Enheduanna</French>
		<German>Enheduanna</German>
		<Italian>Enheduanna</Italian>
		<Spanish>Enheduanna</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_AKKADIAN_COMPOSITE_BOWMAN</Tag>
		<English>Composite Bowman</English>
		<French>Composite Bowman</French>
		<German>Composite Bowman</German>
		<Italian>Composite Bowman</Italian>
		<Spanish>Composite Bowman</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_AKKADIAN_TEMPLE_ISHTAR</Tag>
		<English>Temple of Ishtar</English>
		<French>Temple of Ishtar</French>
		<German>Temple of Ishtar</German>
		<Italian>Temple of Ishtar</Italian>
		<Spanish>Temple of Ishtar</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
<!--
	Note from Jecrell:
	The following text references use several kinds
	of custom tags for special text effects. Here's
	a few of them.
	[H1]Text[\H1] - Header
	[BOLD]Text[\BOLD] - Makes text bold
	[NEWLINE] - Makes a new line (Emulates Enter Key)
	[TAB] - Creates indentation (Emulates Tab key)
	[PARAGRAPH:2] - Creates a paragraph and indents it.
-->
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_AKKADIAN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The rise of the Akkadian Empire marked the first time in history that the entire region of Mesopotamia was united under one ruler, the king of Agade (Akkad). The conquests of these kings of Akkad marked a break with the previous Sumerian Early Dynastic period; however, the culture of the region under the Akkadian rulers did not differ much from that of their Sumerian predecessors. The main difference was that of the language of the ruling authority: the Akkadians replaced the Sumerian language with their Semitic language. Indeed, because the two civilizations were in very close contact for centuries and their languages borrowed many words from each other, it is difficult to distinguish the two during their coexistence in the Early Dynastic period, before the Akkadians consolidated their power over Sumer.[PARAGRAPH:2]Sargon, the first ruler of the dynasty of Agade, came to power in 2334 BC and expanded his rule over the cities of Mesopotamia, conquering the Sumerians. The Akkadians also campaigned quite far to the east and west - by their own accounts, all the way to the Mediterranean. These large military conquests marked a shift from the parochial ruling style of the Sumerians.[PARAGRAPH:2]Many remarkable artifacts have been recovered from the Akkadian empire, including a 160 kilogram piece of a solid copper statue of a male figure and a life-size copper head, likely a representation of the king Naram-Sin. Both pieces show naturalism and fine workmanship. The most famous Akkadian artifact is Naram-Sin's Victory Stele, recording his victory over the Lullubi tribe in western Iran.[PARAGRAPH:2]The Akkadian Empire began to collapse under pressure from neighboring tribes during the reign of Shar-kali-sharri (r.2217-2193). According to the Sumerian King List, the empire deteriorated into a state of anarchy after his reign:[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][TAB][TAB]"Who was king? Was Nanum king? Was Imi king? Was Elulu king? The four of[NEWLINE][TAB][TAB]them were kings and reigned three years."[PARAGRAPH:2]The last kings of Agade were Dudu and Shu-durul. By the time of their reigns, the city states to the south, including Lagash, had gained their independence, and the empire had been reduced to the region just around Agade.</English>
		<French>[TAB]The rise of the Akkadian Empire marked the first time in history that the entire region of Mesopotamia was united under one ruler, the king of Agade (Akkad). The conquests of these kings of Akkad marked a break with the previous Sumerian Early Dynastic period; however, the culture of the region under the Akkadian rulers did not differ much from that of their Sumerian predecessors. The main difference was that of the language of the ruling authority: the Akkadians replaced the Sumerian language with their Semitic language. Indeed, because the two civilizations were in very close contact for centuries and their languages borrowed many words from each other, it is difficult to distinguish the two during their coexistence in the Early Dynastic period, before the Akkadians consolidated their power over Sumer.[PARAGRAPH:2]Sargon, the first ruler of the dynasty of Agade, came to power in 2334 BC and expanded his rule over the cities of Mesopotamia, conquering the Sumerians. The Akkadians also campaigned quite far to the east and west - by their own accounts, all the way to the Mediterranean. These large military conquests marked a shift from the parochial ruling style of the Sumerians.[PARAGRAPH:2]Many remarkable artifacts have been recovered from the Akkadian empire, including a 160 kilogram piece of a solid copper statue of a male figure and a life-size copper head, likely a representation of the king Naram-Sin. Both pieces show naturalism and fine workmanship. The most famous Akkadian artifact is Naram-Sin's Victory Stele, recording his victory over the Lullubi tribe in western Iran.[PARAGRAPH:2]The Akkadian Empire began to collapse under pressure from neighboring tribes during the reign of Shar-kali-sharri (r.2217-2193). According to the Sumerian King List, the empire deteriorated into a state of anarchy after his reign:[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][TAB][TAB]"Who was king? Was Nanum king? Was Imi king? Was Elulu king? The four of[NEWLINE][TAB][TAB]them were kings and reigned three years."[PARAGRAPH:2]The last kings of Agade were Dudu and Shu-durul. By the time of their reigns, the city states to the south, including Lagash, had gained their independence, and the empire had been reduced to the region just around Agade.</French>
		<German>[TAB]The rise of the Akkadian Empire marked the first time in history that the entire region of Mesopotamia was united under one ruler, the king of Agade (Akkad). The conquests of these kings of Akkad marked a break with the previous Sumerian Early Dynastic period; however, the culture of the region under the Akkadian rulers did not differ much from that of their Sumerian predecessors. The main difference was that of the language of the ruling authority: the Akkadians replaced the Sumerian language with their Semitic language. Indeed, because the two civilizations were in very close contact for centuries and their languages borrowed many words from each other, it is difficult to distinguish the two during their coexistence in the Early Dynastic period, before the Akkadians consolidated their power over Sumer.[PARAGRAPH:2]Sargon, the first ruler of the dynasty of Agade, came to power in 2334 BC and expanded his rule over the cities of Mesopotamia, conquering the Sumerians. The Akkadians also campaigned quite far to the east and west - by their own accounts, all the way to the Mediterranean. These large military conquests marked a shift from the parochial ruling style of the Sumerians.[PARAGRAPH:2]Many remarkable artifacts have been recovered from the Akkadian empire, including a 160 kilogram piece of a solid copper statue of a male figure and a life-size copper head, likely a representation of the king Naram-Sin. Both pieces show naturalism and fine workmanship. The most famous Akkadian artifact is Naram-Sin's Victory Stele, recording his victory over the Lullubi tribe in western Iran.[PARAGRAPH:2]The Akkadian Empire began to collapse under pressure from neighboring tribes during the reign of Shar-kali-sharri (r.2217-2193). According to the Sumerian King List, the empire deteriorated into a state of anarchy after his reign:[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][TAB][TAB]"Who was king? Was Nanum king? Was Imi king? Was Elulu king? The four of[NEWLINE][TAB][TAB]them were kings and reigned three years."[PARAGRAPH:2]The last kings of Agade were Dudu and Shu-durul. By the time of their reigns, the city states to the south, including Lagash, had gained their independence, and the empire had been reduced to the region just around Agade.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB]The rise of the Akkadian Empire marked the first time in history that the entire region of Mesopotamia was united under one ruler, the king of Agade (Akkad). The conquests of these kings of Akkad marked a break with the previous Sumerian Early Dynastic period; however, the culture of the region under the Akkadian rulers did not differ much from that of their Sumerian predecessors. The main difference was that of the language of the ruling authority: the Akkadians replaced the Sumerian language with their Semitic language. Indeed, because the two civilizations were in very close contact for centuries and their languages borrowed many words from each other, it is difficult to distinguish the two during their coexistence in the Early Dynastic period, before the Akkadians consolidated their power over Sumer.[PARAGRAPH:2]Sargon, the first ruler of the dynasty of Agade, came to power in 2334 BC and expanded his rule over the cities of Mesopotamia, conquering the Sumerians. The Akkadians also campaigned quite far to the east and west - by their own accounts, all the way to the Mediterranean. These large military conquests marked a shift from the parochial ruling style of the Sumerians.[PARAGRAPH:2]Many remarkable artifacts have been recovered from the Akkadian empire, including a 160 kilogram piece of a solid copper statue of a male figure and a life-size copper head, likely a representation of the king Naram-Sin. Both pieces show naturalism and fine workmanship. The most famous Akkadian artifact is Naram-Sin's Victory Stele, recording his victory over the Lullubi tribe in western Iran.[PARAGRAPH:2]The Akkadian Empire began to collapse under pressure from neighboring tribes during the reign of Shar-kali-sharri (r.2217-2193). According to the Sumerian King List, the empire deteriorated into a state of anarchy after his reign:[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][TAB][TAB]"Who was king? Was Nanum king? Was Imi king? Was Elulu king? The four of[NEWLINE][TAB][TAB]them were kings and reigned three years."[PARAGRAPH:2]The last kings of Agade were Dudu and Shu-durul. By the time of their reigns, the city states to the south, including Lagash, had gained their independence, and the empire had been reduced to the region just around Agade.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB]The rise of the Akkadian Empire marked the first time in history that the entire region of Mesopotamia was united under one ruler, the king of Agade (Akkad). The conquests of these kings of Akkad marked a break with the previous Sumerian Early Dynastic period; however, the culture of the region under the Akkadian rulers did not differ much from that of their Sumerian predecessors. The main difference was that of the language of the ruling authority: the Akkadians replaced the Sumerian language with their Semitic language. Indeed, because the two civilizations were in very close contact for centuries and their languages borrowed many words from each other, it is difficult to distinguish the two during their coexistence in the Early Dynastic period, before the Akkadians consolidated their power over Sumer.[PARAGRAPH:2]Sargon, the first ruler of the dynasty of Agade, came to power in 2334 BC and expanded his rule over the cities of Mesopotamia, conquering the Sumerians. The Akkadians also campaigned quite far to the east and west - by their own accounts, all the way to the Mediterranean. These large military conquests marked a shift from the parochial ruling style of the Sumerians.[PARAGRAPH:2]Many remarkable artifacts have been recovered from the Akkadian empire, including a 160 kilogram piece of a solid copper statue of a male figure and a life-size copper head, likely a representation of the king Naram-Sin. Both pieces show naturalism and fine workmanship. The most famous Akkadian artifact is Naram-Sin's Victory Stele, recording his victory over the Lullubi tribe in western Iran.[PARAGRAPH:2]The Akkadian Empire began to collapse under pressure from neighboring tribes during the reign of Shar-kali-sharri (r.2217-2193). According to the Sumerian King List, the empire deteriorated into a state of anarchy after his reign:[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][TAB][TAB]"Who was king? Was Nanum king? Was Imi king? Was Elulu king? The four of[NEWLINE][TAB][TAB]them were kings and reigned three years."[PARAGRAPH:2]The last kings of Agade were Dudu and Shu-durul. By the time of their reigns, the city states to the south, including Lagash, had gained their independence, and the empire had been reduced to the region just around Agade.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_SARGON_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Sargon the Great[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Emperor of the Akkadian Empire[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD]c.2334 - c.2215 BC[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Sargon of Akkad was one of the earliest of the world's great empire builders, conquering all of southern Mesopotamia as well as parts of Syria, Anatolia, and Elam (western Iran). He established the region's first Semitic dynasty and was considered the founder of the Mesopotamian military tradition.  Sargon is known almost entirely from the legends and tales that followed his reputation through 2,000 years of cuneiform Mesopotamian history, and not from documents that were written during his lifetime. The lack of contemporary record is explained by the fact that the capital city of Agade, which he built, has never been located and excavated. It was destroyed at the end of the dynasty that Sargon founded and was never again inhabited, at least under the name of Agade.  According to a folktale, Sargon was a self-made man of humble origins; a gardener, having found him as a baby floating in a basket on the river, brought him up in his own calling. His father is unknown; his own name during his childhood is also unknown; his mother is said to have been a priestess in a town on the middle Euphrates. Rising, therefore, without the help of influential relations, he attained the post of cupbearer to the ruler of the city of Kish, in the north of the ancient land of Sumer. The event that brought him to supremacy was the defeat of Lugalzaggisi of Uruk (biblical Erech, in central Sumer). Lugalzaggisi had already united the city-states of Sumer by defeating each in turn and claimed to rule the lands not only of the Sumerian city-states but also those as far west as the Mediterranean. Thus, Sargon became king over all of southern Mesopotamia, the first great ruler for whom, rather than Sumerian, the Semitic tongue known as Akkadian was natural from birth, although some earlier kings with Semitic names are recorded in the Sumerian king list. Victory was ensured, however, only by numerous battles, since each city hoped to regain its independence from Lugalzaggisi without submitting to the new overlord. It may have been before these exploits, when he was gathering followers and an army, that Sargon named himself Sharru-kin ("Rightful King") in support of an accession not achieved in an old-established city through hereditary succession. Historical records are still so meager, however, that there is a complete gap in information relating to this period.  Not content with dominating this area, his wish to secure favorable trade with Agade throughout the known world, together with an energetic temperament, led Sargon to defeat cities along the middle Euphrates to northern Syria and the silver-rich mountains of southern Anatolia. He also dominated Susa, capital city of the Elamites, in the Zagros Mountains of western Iran, where the only truly contemporary record of his reign has been uncovered. Such was his fame that some merchants in an Anatolian city, probably in central Turkey, begged him to intervene in a local quarrel, and, according to the legend, Sargon, with a band of warriors, made a fabulous journey to the still-unlocated city of Burushanda (Purshahanda), at the end of which little more than his appearance was needed to settle the dispute.  As the result of Sargon's military prowess and ability to organize, as well as of the legacy of the Sumerian city-states that he had inherited by conquest and of previously existing trade of the old Sumerian city-states with other countries, commercial connections flourished with the Indus Valley, the coast of Oman, the islands and shores of the Persian Gulf, the lapis lazuli mines of Badakhshan, the cedars of Lebanon, the silver-rich Taurus Mountains, Cappadocia, Crete, and perhaps even Greece.

During Sargon's rule Akkadian became adapted to the script that previously had been used in the Sumerian language, and the new spirit of calligraphy that is visible upon the clay tablets of this dynasty is also clearly seen on contemporary cylinder seals, with their beautifully arranged and executed scenes of mythology and festive life. Even if this new artistic feeling is not necessarily to be attributed directly to the personal influence of Sargon, it shows that, in his new capital, military and economic values were not alone important.  Because contemporary record is lacking, no sequence can be given for the events of his reign. Neither the number of years during which he lived nor the point in time at which he ruled can be fixed exactly; 2334 BC is now given as a date on which to hang the beginning of the dynasty of Agade, and, according to the Sumerian king list, he was king for 56 years.  2334 BC is now given as a date on which to hang the beginning of the dynasty of Agade, and, according to the Sumerian king list, he was king for 56 years.  The latter part of his reign was troubled with rebellions, which later literature ascribes, predictably enough, to sacrilegious acts that he is supposed to have committed; but this can be discounted as the standard cause assigned to all disasters by Sumerians and Akkadians alike. The troubles, in fact, were probably caused by the inability of one man, however energetic, to control so vast an empire without a developed and well-tried administration. There is no evidence to suggest that he was particularly harsh, nor that the Sumerians disliked him for being a Semite. The empire did not collapse totally, for Sargon's successors were able to control their legacy, and later generations thought of him as being perhaps the greatest name in their history.  Attributing his success to the patronage of the goddess Ishtar, in whose honor Agade was erected, Sargon of Akkad became the first great empire builder. Two later Assyrian kings were named in his honor. Although the briefly recorded information of his predecessor Lugalzaggisi shows that expansion beyond the Sumerian homeland had already begun, later Mesopotamians looked to Sargon as the founder of the military tradition that runs through the history of their people.</English>
		<French>[H1]Sargon the Great[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Emperor of the Akkadian Empire[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD]c.2334 - c.2215 BC[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Sargon of Akkad was one of the earliest of the world's great empire builders, conquering all of southern Mesopotamia as well as parts of Syria, Anatolia, and Elam (western Iran). He established the region's first Semitic dynasty and was considered the founder of the Mesopotamian military tradition.  Sargon is known almost entirely from the legends and tales that followed his reputation through 2,000 years of cuneiform Mesopotamian history, and not from documents that were written during his lifetime. The lack of contemporary record is explained by the fact that the capital city of Agade, which he built, has never been located and excavated. It was destroyed at the end of the dynasty that Sargon founded and was never again inhabited, at least under the name of Agade.  According to a folktale, Sargon was a self-made man of humble origins; a gardener, having found him as a baby floating in a basket on the river, brought him up in his own calling. His father is unknown; his own name during his childhood is also unknown; his mother is said to have been a priestess in a town on the middle Euphrates. Rising, therefore, without the help of influential relations, he attained the post of cupbearer to the ruler of the city of Kish, in the north of the ancient land of Sumer. The event that brought him to supremacy was the defeat of Lugalzaggisi of Uruk (biblical Erech, in central Sumer). Lugalzaggisi had already united the city-states of Sumer by defeating each in turn and claimed to rule the lands not only of the Sumerian city-states but also those as far west as the Mediterranean. Thus, Sargon became king over all of southern Mesopotamia, the first great ruler for whom, rather than Sumerian, the Semitic tongue known as Akkadian was natural from birth, although some earlier kings with Semitic names are recorded in the Sumerian king list. Victory was ensured, however, only by numerous battles, since each city hoped to regain its independence from Lugalzaggisi without submitting to the new overlord. It may have been before these exploits, when he was gathering followers and an army, that Sargon named himself Sharru-kin ("Rightful King") in support of an accession not achieved in an old-established city through hereditary succession. Historical records are still so meager, however, that there is a complete gap in information relating to this period.  Not content with dominating this area, his wish to secure favorable trade with Agade throughout the known world, together with an energetic temperament, led Sargon to defeat cities along the middle Euphrates to northern Syria and the silver-rich mountains of southern Anatolia. He also dominated Susa, capital city of the Elamites, in the Zagros Mountains of western Iran, where the only truly contemporary record of his reign has been uncovered. Such was his fame that some merchants in an Anatolian city, probably in central Turkey, begged him to intervene in a local quarrel, and, according to the legend, Sargon, with a band of warriors, made a fabulous journey to the still-unlocated city of Burushanda (Purshahanda), at the end of which little more than his appearance was needed to settle the dispute.  As the result of Sargon's military prowess and ability to organize, as well as of the legacy of the Sumerian city-states that he had inherited by conquest and of previously existing trade of the old Sumerian city-states with other countries, commercial connections flourished with the Indus Valley, the coast of Oman, the islands and shores of the Persian Gulf, the lapis lazuli mines of Badakhshan, the cedars of Lebanon, the silver-rich Taurus Mountains, Cappadocia, Crete, and perhaps even Greece.

During Sargon's rule Akkadian became adapted to the script that previously had been used in the Sumerian language, and the new spirit of calligraphy that is visible upon the clay tablets of this dynasty is also clearly seen on contemporary cylinder seals, with their beautifully arranged and executed scenes of mythology and festive life. Even if this new artistic feeling is not necessarily to be attributed directly to the personal influence of Sargon, it shows that, in his new capital, military and economic values were not alone important.  Because contemporary record is lacking, no sequence can be given for the events of his reign. Neither the number of years during which he lived nor the point in time at which he ruled can be fixed exactly; 2334 BC is now given as a date on which to hang the beginning of the dynasty of Agade, and, according to the Sumerian king list, he was king for 56 years.  2334 BC is now given as a date on which to hang the beginning of the dynasty of Agade, and, according to the Sumerian king list, he was king for 56 years.  The latter part of his reign was troubled with rebellions, which later literature ascribes, predictably enough, to sacrilegious acts that he is supposed to have committed; but this can be discounted as the standard cause assigned to all disasters by Sumerians and Akkadians alike. The troubles, in fact, were probably caused by the inability of one man, however energetic, to control so vast an empire without a developed and well-tried administration. There is no evidence to suggest that he was particularly harsh, nor that the Sumerians disliked him for being a Semite. The empire did not collapse totally, for Sargon's successors were able to control their legacy, and later generations thought of him as being perhaps the greatest name in their history.  Attributing his success to the patronage of the goddess Ishtar, in whose honor Agade was erected, Sargon of Akkad became the first great empire builder. Two later Assyrian kings were named in his honor. Although the briefly recorded information of his predecessor Lugalzaggisi shows that expansion beyond the Sumerian homeland had already begun, later Mesopotamians looked to Sargon as the founder of the military tradition that runs through the history of their people.</French>
		<German>[H1]Sargon the Great[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Emperor of the Akkadian Empire[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD]c.2334 - c.2215 BC[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Sargon of Akkad was one of the earliest of the world's great empire builders, conquering all of southern Mesopotamia as well as parts of Syria, Anatolia, and Elam (western Iran). He established the region's first Semitic dynasty and was considered the founder of the Mesopotamian military tradition.  Sargon is known almost entirely from the legends and tales that followed his reputation through 2,000 years of cuneiform Mesopotamian history, and not from documents that were written during his lifetime. The lack of contemporary record is explained by the fact that the capital city of Agade, which he built, has never been located and excavated. It was destroyed at the end of the dynasty that Sargon founded and was never again inhabited, at least under the name of Agade.  According to a folktale, Sargon was a self-made man of humble origins; a gardener, having found him as a baby floating in a basket on the river, brought him up in his own calling. His father is unknown; his own name during his childhood is also unknown; his mother is said to have been a priestess in a town on the middle Euphrates. Rising, therefore, without the help of influential relations, he attained the post of cupbearer to the ruler of the city of Kish, in the north of the ancient land of Sumer. The event that brought him to supremacy was the defeat of Lugalzaggisi of Uruk (biblical Erech, in central Sumer). Lugalzaggisi had already united the city-states of Sumer by defeating each in turn and claimed to rule the lands not only of the Sumerian city-states but also those as far west as the Mediterranean. Thus, Sargon became king over all of southern Mesopotamia, the first great ruler for whom, rather than Sumerian, the Semitic tongue known as Akkadian was natural from birth, although some earlier kings with Semitic names are recorded in the Sumerian king list. Victory was ensured, however, only by numerous battles, since each city hoped to regain its independence from Lugalzaggisi without submitting to the new overlord. It may have been before these exploits, when he was gathering followers and an army, that Sargon named himself Sharru-kin ("Rightful King") in support of an accession not achieved in an old-established city through hereditary succession. Historical records are still so meager, however, that there is a complete gap in information relating to this period.  Not content with dominating this area, his wish to secure favorable trade with Agade throughout the known world, together with an energetic temperament, led Sargon to defeat cities along the middle Euphrates to northern Syria and the silver-rich mountains of southern Anatolia. He also dominated Susa, capital city of the Elamites, in the Zagros Mountains of western Iran, where the only truly contemporary record of his reign has been uncovered. Such was his fame that some merchants in an Anatolian city, probably in central Turkey, begged him to intervene in a local quarrel, and, according to the legend, Sargon, with a band of warriors, made a fabulous journey to the still-unlocated city of Burushanda (Purshahanda), at the end of which little more than his appearance was needed to settle the dispute.  As the result of Sargon's military prowess and ability to organize, as well as of the legacy of the Sumerian city-states that he had inherited by conquest and of previously existing trade of the old Sumerian city-states with other countries, commercial connections flourished with the Indus Valley, the coast of Oman, the islands and shores of the Persian Gulf, the lapis lazuli mines of Badakhshan, the cedars of Lebanon, the silver-rich Taurus Mountains, Cappadocia, Crete, and perhaps even Greece.

During Sargon's rule Akkadian became adapted to the script that previously had been used in the Sumerian language, and the new spirit of calligraphy that is visible upon the clay tablets of this dynasty is also clearly seen on contemporary cylinder seals, with their beautifully arranged and executed scenes of mythology and festive life. Even if this new artistic feeling is not necessarily to be attributed directly to the personal influence of Sargon, it shows that, in his new capital, military and economic values were not alone important.  Because contemporary record is lacking, no sequence can be given for the events of his reign. Neither the number of years during which he lived nor the point in time at which he ruled can be fixed exactly; 2334 BC is now given as a date on which to hang the beginning of the dynasty of Agade, and, according to the Sumerian king list, he was king for 56 years.  2334 BC is now given as a date on which to hang the beginning of the dynasty of Agade, and, according to the Sumerian king list, he was king for 56 years.  The latter part of his reign was troubled with rebellions, which later literature ascribes, predictably enough, to sacrilegious acts that he is supposed to have committed; but this can be discounted as the standard cause assigned to all disasters by Sumerians and Akkadians alike. The troubles, in fact, were probably caused by the inability of one man, however energetic, to control so vast an empire without a developed and well-tried administration. There is no evidence to suggest that he was particularly harsh, nor that the Sumerians disliked him for being a Semite. The empire did not collapse totally, for Sargon's successors were able to control their legacy, and later generations thought of him as being perhaps the greatest name in their history.  Attributing his success to the patronage of the goddess Ishtar, in whose honor Agade was erected, Sargon of Akkad became the first great empire builder. Two later Assyrian kings were named in his honor. Although the briefly recorded information of his predecessor Lugalzaggisi shows that expansion beyond the Sumerian homeland had already begun, later Mesopotamians looked to Sargon as the founder of the military tradition that runs through the history of their people.</German>
		<Italian>[H1]Sargon the Great[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Emperor of the Akkadian Empire[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD]c.2334 - c.2215 BC[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Sargon of Akkad was one of the earliest of the world's great empire builders, conquering all of southern Mesopotamia as well as parts of Syria, Anatolia, and Elam (western Iran). He established the region's first Semitic dynasty and was considered the founder of the Mesopotamian military tradition.  Sargon is known almost entirely from the legends and tales that followed his reputation through 2,000 years of cuneiform Mesopotamian history, and not from documents that were written during his lifetime. The lack of contemporary record is explained by the fact that the capital city of Agade, which he built, has never been located and excavated. It was destroyed at the end of the dynasty that Sargon founded and was never again inhabited, at least under the name of Agade.  According to a folktale, Sargon was a self-made man of humble origins; a gardener, having found him as a baby floating in a basket on the river, brought him up in his own calling. His father is unknown; his own name during his childhood is also unknown; his mother is said to have been a priestess in a town on the middle Euphrates. Rising, therefore, without the help of influential relations, he attained the post of cupbearer to the ruler of the city of Kish, in the north of the ancient land of Sumer. The event that brought him to supremacy was the defeat of Lugalzaggisi of Uruk (biblical Erech, in central Sumer). Lugalzaggisi had already united the city-states of Sumer by defeating each in turn and claimed to rule the lands not only of the Sumerian city-states but also those as far west as the Mediterranean. Thus, Sargon became king over all of southern Mesopotamia, the first great ruler for whom, rather than Sumerian, the Semitic tongue known as Akkadian was natural from birth, although some earlier kings with Semitic names are recorded in the Sumerian king list. Victory was ensured, however, only by numerous battles, since each city hoped to regain its independence from Lugalzaggisi without submitting to the new overlord. It may have been before these exploits, when he was gathering followers and an army, that Sargon named himself Sharru-kin ("Rightful King") in support of an accession not achieved in an old-established city through hereditary succession. Historical records are still so meager, however, that there is a complete gap in information relating to this period.  Not content with dominating this area, his wish to secure favorable trade with Agade throughout the known world, together with an energetic temperament, led Sargon to defeat cities along the middle Euphrates to northern Syria and the silver-rich mountains of southern Anatolia. He also dominated Susa, capital city of the Elamites, in the Zagros Mountains of western Iran, where the only truly contemporary record of his reign has been uncovered. Such was his fame that some merchants in an Anatolian city, probably in central Turkey, begged him to intervene in a local quarrel, and, according to the legend, Sargon, with a band of warriors, made a fabulous journey to the still-unlocated city of Burushanda (Purshahanda), at the end of which little more than his appearance was needed to settle the dispute.  As the result of Sargon's military prowess and ability to organize, as well as of the legacy of the Sumerian city-states that he had inherited by conquest and of previously existing trade of the old Sumerian city-states with other countries, commercial connections flourished with the Indus Valley, the coast of Oman, the islands and shores of the Persian Gulf, the lapis lazuli mines of Badakhshan, the cedars of Lebanon, the silver-rich Taurus Mountains, Cappadocia, Crete, and perhaps even Greece.

During Sargon's rule Akkadian became adapted to the script that previously had been used in the Sumerian language, and the new spirit of calligraphy that is visible upon the clay tablets of this dynasty is also clearly seen on contemporary cylinder seals, with their beautifully arranged and executed scenes of mythology and festive life. Even if this new artistic feeling is not necessarily to be attributed directly to the personal influence of Sargon, it shows that, in his new capital, military and economic values were not alone important.  Because contemporary record is lacking, no sequence can be given for the events of his reign. Neither the number of years during which he lived nor the point in time at which he ruled can be fixed exactly; 2334 BC is now given as a date on which to hang the beginning of the dynasty of Agade, and, according to the Sumerian king list, he was king for 56 years.  2334 BC is now given as a date on which to hang the beginning of the dynasty of Agade, and, according to the Sumerian king list, he was king for 56 years.  The latter part of his reign was troubled with rebellions, which later literature ascribes, predictably enough, to sacrilegious acts that he is supposed to have committed; but this can be discounted as the standard cause assigned to all disasters by Sumerians and Akkadians alike. The troubles, in fact, were probably caused by the inability of one man, however energetic, to control so vast an empire without a developed and well-tried administration. There is no evidence to suggest that he was particularly harsh, nor that the Sumerians disliked him for being a Semite. The empire did not collapse totally, for Sargon's successors were able to control their legacy, and later generations thought of him as being perhaps the greatest name in their history.  Attributing his success to the patronage of the goddess Ishtar, in whose honor Agade was erected, Sargon of Akkad became the first great empire builder. Two later Assyrian kings were named in his honor. Although the briefly recorded information of his predecessor Lugalzaggisi shows that expansion beyond the Sumerian homeland had already begun, later Mesopotamians looked to Sargon as the founder of the military tradition that runs through the history of their people.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[H1]Sargon the Great[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Emperor of the Akkadian Empire[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD]c.2334 - c.2215 BC[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Sargon of Akkad was one of the earliest of the world's great empire builders, conquering all of southern Mesopotamia as well as parts of Syria, Anatolia, and Elam (western Iran). He established the region's first Semitic dynasty and was considered the founder of the Mesopotamian military tradition.  Sargon is known almost entirely from the legends and tales that followed his reputation through 2,000 years of cuneiform Mesopotamian history, and not from documents that were written during his lifetime. The lack of contemporary record is explained by the fact that the capital city of Agade, which he built, has never been located and excavated. It was destroyed at the end of the dynasty that Sargon founded and was never again inhabited, at least under the name of Agade.  According to a folktale, Sargon was a self-made man of humble origins; a gardener, having found him as a baby floating in a basket on the river, brought him up in his own calling. His father is unknown; his own name during his childhood is also unknown; his mother is said to have been a priestess in a town on the middle Euphrates. Rising, therefore, without the help of influential relations, he attained the post of cupbearer to the ruler of the city of Kish, in the north of the ancient land of Sumer. The event that brought him to supremacy was the defeat of Lugalzaggisi of Uruk (biblical Erech, in central Sumer). Lugalzaggisi had already united the city-states of Sumer by defeating each in turn and claimed to rule the lands not only of the Sumerian city-states but also those as far west as the Mediterranean. Thus, Sargon became king over all of southern Mesopotamia, the first great ruler for whom, rather than Sumerian, the Semitic tongue known as Akkadian was natural from birth, although some earlier kings with Semitic names are recorded in the Sumerian king list. Victory was ensured, however, only by numerous battles, since each city hoped to regain its independence from Lugalzaggisi without submitting to the new overlord. It may have been before these exploits, when he was gathering followers and an army, that Sargon named himself Sharru-kin ("Rightful King") in support of an accession not achieved in an old-established city through hereditary succession. Historical records are still so meager, however, that there is a complete gap in information relating to this period.  Not content with dominating this area, his wish to secure favorable trade with Agade throughout the known world, together with an energetic temperament, led Sargon to defeat cities along the middle Euphrates to northern Syria and the silver-rich mountains of southern Anatolia. He also dominated Susa, capital city of the Elamites, in the Zagros Mountains of western Iran, where the only truly contemporary record of his reign has been uncovered. Such was his fame that some merchants in an Anatolian city, probably in central Turkey, begged him to intervene in a local quarrel, and, according to the legend, Sargon, with a band of warriors, made a fabulous journey to the still-unlocated city of Burushanda (Purshahanda), at the end of which little more than his appearance was needed to settle the dispute.  As the result of Sargon's military prowess and ability to organize, as well as of the legacy of the Sumerian city-states that he had inherited by conquest and of previously existing trade of the old Sumerian city-states with other countries, commercial connections flourished with the Indus Valley, the coast of Oman, the islands and shores of the Persian Gulf, the lapis lazuli mines of Badakhshan, the cedars of Lebanon, the silver-rich Taurus Mountains, Cappadocia, Crete, and perhaps even Greece.

During Sargon's rule Akkadian became adapted to the script that previously had been used in the Sumerian language, and the new spirit of calligraphy that is visible upon the clay tablets of this dynasty is also clearly seen on contemporary cylinder seals, with their beautifully arranged and executed scenes of mythology and festive life. Even if this new artistic feeling is not necessarily to be attributed directly to the personal influence of Sargon, it shows that, in his new capital, military and economic values were not alone important.  Because contemporary record is lacking, no sequence can be given for the events of his reign. Neither the number of years during which he lived nor the point in time at which he ruled can be fixed exactly; 2334 BC is now given as a date on which to hang the beginning of the dynasty of Agade, and, according to the Sumerian king list, he was king for 56 years.  2334 BC is now given as a date on which to hang the beginning of the dynasty of Agade, and, according to the Sumerian king list, he was king for 56 years.  The latter part of his reign was troubled with rebellions, which later literature ascribes, predictably enough, to sacrilegious acts that he is supposed to have committed; but this can be discounted as the standard cause assigned to all disasters by Sumerians and Akkadians alike. The troubles, in fact, were probably caused by the inability of one man, however energetic, to control so vast an empire without a developed and well-tried administration. There is no evidence to suggest that he was particularly harsh, nor that the Sumerians disliked him for being a Semite. The empire did not collapse totally, for Sargon's successors were able to control their legacy, and later generations thought of him as being perhaps the greatest name in their history.  Attributing his success to the patronage of the goddess Ishtar, in whose honor Agade was erected, Sargon of Akkad became the first great empire builder. Two later Assyrian kings were named in his honor. Although the briefly recorded information of his predecessor Lugalzaggisi shows that expansion beyond the Sumerian homeland had already begun, later Mesopotamians looked to Sargon as the founder of the military tradition that runs through the history of their people.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_ENHEDUANNA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Enheduanna[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Akkadian Princess[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD]c.2285 - c.2250 BC[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background: [\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Enheduanna, also known as Enheduana or Enheduanna, meaning "lord or lady ornament of An" or "high priestess ornament of An" (An being "the sky" or "heaven") was an Akkadian princess as well as high priestess of the Moon god Nanna (Sin) in Ur. She was the first known holder of the title, 'En Priestess', a role of great political importance which often was held by royal daughters.

Regarded by literary and historical scholars as the earliest known author and poet, she served as an En Priestess during the Third Millennium BC. She was appointed to the role by her Father, Sargon of Akkad. She has left behind a corpus of literary works definitively ascribed to her, including many personal devotions to the goddess Inanna and a collection of Hymns known as the 'Sumerian Temple Hymns' which are regarded as one of the first attempts at a systematic theology. In addition scholars , such as Hallo and Van Dijk, suggest that certain texts which have not been ascribed to her may also be her work.  Enheduanna was appointed to the role of En Priestess at Ur by her Father King Sargon of Akkad, in a move considered to be a shrewd political move by the Akkadian Sargon to help cement power in the Sumerian south, in which the City of Ur was located. She continued to hold office during the reign of Rimush her brother. It was during the reign of Rimush that she was involved in some form of political turmoil and expelled from the role and eventually reinstated. This is detailed in her composition 'The Exaltation of Inanna" details her expulsion from Ur and eventual reinstatement.  This correlates with with 'The Curse of Akkade' in which Naram-Sin, under whom Enheduanna may have also served, is cursed and cast out by Enlil. After her death Enheduanna continued to be remembered as an important figure, perhaps even attaining semi-divine status.</English>
		<French>[H1]Enheduanna[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Akkadian Princess[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD]c.2285 - c.2250 BC[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background: [\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Enheduanna, also known as Enheduana or Enheduanna, meaning "lord or lady ornament of An" or "high priestess ornament of An" (An being "the sky" or "heaven") was an Akkadian princess as well as high priestess of the Moon god Nanna (Sin) in Ur. She was the first known holder of the title, 'En Priestess', a role of great political importance which often was held by royal daughters.

Regarded by literary and historical scholars as the earliest known author and poet, she served as an En Priestess during the Third Millennium BC. She was appointed to the role by her Father, Sargon of Akkad. She has left behind a corpus of literary works definitively ascribed to her, including many personal devotions to the goddess Inanna and a collection of Hymns known as the 'Sumerian Temple Hymns' which are regarded as one of the first attempts at a systematic theology. In addition scholars , such as Hallo and Van Dijk, suggest that certain texts which have not been ascribed to her may also be her work.  Enheduanna was appointed to the role of En Priestess at Ur by her Father King Sargon of Akkad, in a move considered to be a shrewd political move by the Akkadian Sargon to help cement power in the Sumerian south, in which the City of Ur was located. She continued to hold office during the reign of Rimush her brother. It was during the reign of Rimush that she was involved in some form of political turmoil and expelled from the role and eventually reinstated. This is detailed in her composition 'The Exaltation of Inanna" details her expulsion from Ur and eventual reinstatement.  This correlates with with 'The Curse of Akkade' in which Naram-Sin, under whom Enheduanna may have also served, is cursed and cast out by Enlil. After her death Enheduanna continued to be remembered as an important figure, perhaps even attaining semi-divine status.</French>
		<German>[H1]Enheduanna[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Akkadian Princess[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD]c.2285 - c.2250 BC[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background: [\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Enheduanna, also known as Enheduana or Enheduanna, meaning "lord or lady ornament of An" or "high priestess ornament of An" (An being "the sky" or "heaven") was an Akkadian princess as well as high priestess of the Moon god Nanna (Sin) in Ur. She was the first known holder of the title, 'En Priestess', a role of great political importance which often was held by royal daughters.

Regarded by literary and historical scholars as the earliest known author and poet, she served as an En Priestess during the Third Millennium BC. She was appointed to the role by her Father, Sargon of Akkad. She has left behind a corpus of literary works definitively ascribed to her, including many personal devotions to the goddess Inanna and a collection of Hymns known as the 'Sumerian Temple Hymns' which are regarded as one of the first attempts at a systematic theology. In addition scholars , such as Hallo and Van Dijk, suggest that certain texts which have not been ascribed to her may also be her work.  Enheduanna was appointed to the role of En Priestess at Ur by her Father King Sargon of Akkad, in a move considered to be a shrewd political move by the Akkadian Sargon to help cement power in the Sumerian south, in which the City of Ur was located. She continued to hold office during the reign of Rimush her brother. It was during the reign of Rimush that she was involved in some form of political turmoil and expelled from the role and eventually reinstated. This is detailed in her composition 'The Exaltation of Inanna" details her expulsion from Ur and eventual reinstatement.  This correlates with with 'The Curse of Akkade' in which Naram-Sin, under whom Enheduanna may have also served, is cursed and cast out by Enlil. After her death Enheduanna continued to be remembered as an important figure, perhaps even attaining semi-divine status.</German>
		<Italian>[H1]Enheduanna[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Akkadian Princess[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD]c.2285 - c.2250 BC[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background: [\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Enheduanna, also known as Enheduana or Enheduanna, meaning "lord or lady ornament of An" or "high priestess ornament of An" (An being "the sky" or "heaven") was an Akkadian princess as well as high priestess of the Moon god Nanna (Sin) in Ur. She was the first known holder of the title, 'En Priestess', a role of great political importance which often was held by royal daughters.

Regarded by literary and historical scholars as the earliest known author and poet, she served as an En Priestess during the Third Millennium BC. She was appointed to the role by her Father, Sargon of Akkad. She has left behind a corpus of literary works definitively ascribed to her, including many personal devotions to the goddess Inanna and a collection of Hymns known as the 'Sumerian Temple Hymns' which are regarded as one of the first attempts at a systematic theology. In addition scholars , such as Hallo and Van Dijk, suggest that certain texts which have not been ascribed to her may also be her work.  Enheduanna was appointed to the role of En Priestess at Ur by her Father King Sargon of Akkad, in a move considered to be a shrewd political move by the Akkadian Sargon to help cement power in the Sumerian south, in which the City of Ur was located. She continued to hold office during the reign of Rimush her brother. It was during the reign of Rimush that she was involved in some form of political turmoil and expelled from the role and eventually reinstated. This is detailed in her composition 'The Exaltation of Inanna" details her expulsion from Ur and eventual reinstatement.  This correlates with with 'The Curse of Akkade' in which Naram-Sin, under whom Enheduanna may have also served, is cursed and cast out by Enlil. After her death Enheduanna continued to be remembered as an important figure, perhaps even attaining semi-divine status.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[H1]Enheduanna[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Akkadian Princess[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD]c.2285 - c.2250 BC[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background: [\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Enheduanna, also known as Enheduana or Enheduanna, meaning "lord or lady ornament of An" or "high priestess ornament of An" (An being "the sky" or "heaven") was an Akkadian princess as well as high priestess of the Moon god Nanna (Sin) in Ur. She was the first known holder of the title, 'En Priestess', a role of great political importance which often was held by royal daughters.

Regarded by literary and historical scholars as the earliest known author and poet, she served as an En Priestess during the Third Millennium BC. She was appointed to the role by her Father, Sargon of Akkad. She has left behind a corpus of literary works definitively ascribed to her, including many personal devotions to the goddess Inanna and a collection of Hymns known as the 'Sumerian Temple Hymns' which are regarded as one of the first attempts at a systematic theology. In addition scholars , such as Hallo and Van Dijk, suggest that certain texts which have not been ascribed to her may also be her work.  Enheduanna was appointed to the role of En Priestess at Ur by her Father King Sargon of Akkad, in a move considered to be a shrewd political move by the Akkadian Sargon to help cement power in the Sumerian south, in which the City of Ur was located. She continued to hold office during the reign of Rimush her brother. It was during the reign of Rimush that she was involved in some form of political turmoil and expelled from the role and eventually reinstated. This is detailed in her composition 'The Exaltation of Inanna" details her expulsion from Ur and eventual reinstatement.  This correlates with with 'The Curse of Akkade' in which Naram-Sin, under whom Enheduanna may have also served, is cursed and cast out by Enlil. After her death Enheduanna continued to be remembered as an important figure, perhaps even attaining semi-divine status.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_AKKADIAN_COMPOSITE_BOWMAN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]The Composite Bow[\H1][PARAGRAPH:2]The Akkadians probably invented the composite bow during the reign of Naram-Sin (2254-2218). A stele from this period shows Naram-Sin holding a composite bow, which is its first appearance in history, suggesting an Akkadian origin.[PARAGRAPH:2]The structure of the composite bow allows a smaller sized bow to pack greater power. The curve of the bow creates a higher draw-weight, releasing more total energy when the arrow is fired. The higher power allowed arrows to pierce leather armor, and possibly even bronze armor, from a great distance. The smaller size makes the composite bow more suitable for use on horseback or chariots. The disadvantage is that a composite bow takes much more time and effort to make than a regular bow, and because it necessitates gluing materials together, it is susceptible to water and humidity.</English>
		<French>[H1]The Composite Bow[\H1][PARAGRAPH:2]The Akkadians probably invented the composite bow during the reign of Naram-Sin (2254-2218). A stele from this period shows Naram-Sin holding a composite bow, which is its first appearance in history, suggesting an Akkadian origin.[PARAGRAPH:2]The structure of the composite bow allows a smaller sized bow to pack greater power. The curve of the bow creates a higher draw-weight, releasing more total energy when the arrow is fired. The higher power allowed arrows to pierce leather armor, and possibly even bronze armor, from a great distance. The smaller size makes the composite bow more suitable for use on horseback or chariots. The disadvantage is that a composite bow takes much more time and effort to make than a regular bow, and because it necessitates gluing materials together, it is susceptible to water and humidity.</French>
		<German>[H1]The Composite Bow[\H1][PARAGRAPH:2]The Akkadians probably invented the composite bow during the reign of Naram-Sin (2254-2218). A stele from this period shows Naram-Sin holding a composite bow, which is its first appearance in history, suggesting an Akkadian origin.[PARAGRAPH:2]The structure of the composite bow allows a smaller sized bow to pack greater power. The curve of the bow creates a higher draw-weight, releasing more total energy when the arrow is fired. The higher power allowed arrows to pierce leather armor, and possibly even bronze armor, from a great distance. The smaller size makes the composite bow more suitable for use on horseback or chariots. The disadvantage is that a composite bow takes much more time and effort to make than a regular bow, and because it necessitates gluing materials together, it is susceptible to water and humidity.</German>
		<Italian>[H1]The Composite Bow[\H1][PARAGRAPH:2]The Akkadians probably invented the composite bow during the reign of Naram-Sin (2254-2218). A stele from this period shows Naram-Sin holding a composite bow, which is its first appearance in history, suggesting an Akkadian origin.[PARAGRAPH:2]The structure of the composite bow allows a smaller sized bow to pack greater power. The curve of the bow creates a higher draw-weight, releasing more total energy when the arrow is fired. The higher power allowed arrows to pierce leather armor, and possibly even bronze armor, from a great distance. The smaller size makes the composite bow more suitable for use on horseback or chariots. The disadvantage is that a composite bow takes much more time and effort to make than a regular bow, and because it necessitates gluing materials together, it is susceptible to water and humidity.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[H1]The Composite Bow[\H1][PARAGRAPH:2]The Akkadians probably invented the composite bow during the reign of Naram-Sin (2254-2218). A stele from this period shows Naram-Sin holding a composite bow, which is its first appearance in history, suggesting an Akkadian origin.[PARAGRAPH:2]The structure of the composite bow allows a smaller sized bow to pack greater power. The curve of the bow creates a higher draw-weight, releasing more total energy when the arrow is fired. The higher power allowed arrows to pierce leather armor, and possibly even bronze armor, from a great distance. The smaller size makes the composite bow more suitable for use on horseback or chariots. The disadvantage is that a composite bow takes much more time and effort to make than a regular bow, and because it necessitates gluing materials together, it is susceptible to water and humidity.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_AKKADIAN_COMPOSITE_BOWMAN_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Composite Bowman[COLOR_REVERT] (the Akkadian replacement for the [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Archer[COLOR_REVERT]) start with Shock 1 and get an extra first strike chance.</English>
		<French>The [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Composite Bowman[COLOR_REVERT] (the Akkadian replacement for the [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Archer[COLOR_REVERT]) start with Shock 1 and get an extra first strike chance.</French>
		<German>The [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Composite Bowman[COLOR_REVERT] (the Akkadian replacement for the [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Archer[COLOR_REVERT]) start with Shock 1 and get an extra first strike chance.</German>
		<Italian>The [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Composite Bowman[COLOR_REVERT] (the Akkadian replacement for the [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Archer[COLOR_REVERT]) start with Shock 1 and get an extra first strike chance.</Italian>
		<Spanish>The [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Composite Bowman[COLOR_REVERT] (the Akkadian replacement for the [COLOR_UNIT_TEXT]Archer[COLOR_REVERT]) start with Shock 1 and get an extra first strike chance.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_AKKADIAN_TEMPLE_ISHTAR_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Temple of Ishtar[\H1][PARAGRAPH:2]Ishtar is a goddess of fertility, love, war, and sex.  In the Babylonian pantheon, she "was the divine personification of the planet Venus."  Ishtar was above all associated with sexuality: her cult involved sacred prostitution.  Her holy city Uruk was called the "town of the sacred courtesans"; and she herself was the "courtesan of the gods."</English>
		<French>[H1]Temple of Ishtar[\H1][PARAGRAPH:2]Ishtar is a goddess of fertility, love, war, and sex.  In the Babylonian pantheon, she "was the divine personification of the planet Venus."  Ishtar was above all associated with sexuality: her cult involved sacred prostitution.  Her holy city Uruk was called the "town of the sacred courtesans"; and she herself was the "courtesan of the gods."</French>
		<German>[H1]Temple of Ishtar[\H1][PARAGRAPH:2]Ishtar is a goddess of fertility, love, war, and sex.  In the Babylonian pantheon, she "was the divine personification of the planet Venus."  Ishtar was above all associated with sexuality: her cult involved sacred prostitution.  Her holy city Uruk was called the "town of the sacred courtesans"; and she herself was the "courtesan of the gods."</German>
		<Italian>[H1]Temple of Ishtar[\H1][PARAGRAPH:2]Ishtar is a goddess of fertility, love, war, and sex.  In the Babylonian pantheon, she "was the divine personification of the planet Venus."  Ishtar was above all associated with sexuality: her cult involved sacred prostitution.  Her holy city Uruk was called the "town of the sacred courtesans"; and she herself was the "courtesan of the gods."</Italian>
		<Spanish>[H1]Temple of Ishtar[\H1][PARAGRAPH:2]Ishtar is a goddess of fertility, love, war, and sex.  In the Babylonian pantheon, she "was the divine personification of the planet Venus."  Ishtar was above all associated with sexuality: her cult involved sacred prostitution.  Her holy city Uruk was called the "town of the sacred courtesans"; and she herself was the "courtesan of the gods."</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_AKKADIAN_TEMPLE_ISHTAR_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>A [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Temple of Ishtar[COLOR_REVERT] is a [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Brothel[COLOR_REVERT] that allows two Priests.</English>
		<French>A [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Temple of Ishtar[COLOR_REVERT] is a [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Brothel[COLOR_REVERT] that allows two Priests.</French>
		<German>A [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Temple of Ishtar[COLOR_REVERT] is a [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Brothel[COLOR_REVERT] that allows two Priests.</German>
		<Italian>A [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Temple of Ishtar[COLOR_REVERT] is a [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Brothel[COLOR_REVERT] that allows two Priests.</Italian>
		<Spanish>A [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Temple of Ishtar[COLOR_REVERT] is a [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Brothel[COLOR_REVERT] that allows two Priests.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
<!--
	Note from Jecrell:
	The following lines are represent text used
	in your leader's diplomacy routine. Here's a few
	special tags used in diplomacy.
	[OUR_NAME] - Your leader's name.
	[OUR_EMPIRE] - Your leader's empire.
	[OUR_CIV_SHORT] - Your leader's civ's short name.
	[OUR_CIV_ADJ] - Your leader's civ's adjective.
	[CT_NAME] - The player's name
	[CT_EMPIRE] - The player's empire.
	[CT_CIV_SHORT] - The player's empire's short name.
	[CT_CIV_ADJ] - The player's empire's adjective.
-->		
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_SARGON_1</Tag>
		<English>Greetings! I am [OUR_NAME], the true king of Akkad. No, really, I mean it. Did somebody tell you something else? True king, seriously.</English>
		<French>Salutations ! Je suis [OUR_NAME], je r&#232;gne sur l'[OUR_EMPIRE]. Je souhaite que nos deux grands peuples puissent vivre en paix.</French>
		<German>Seid gegr&#252;&#223;t! Ich bin [OUR_NAME], Staatsoberhaupt des [OUR_EMPIRE:3]es. Ich hoffe, unsere gro&#223;artigen V&#246;lker werden in Frieden zusammenleben.</German>
		<Italian>Saluti! Io sono [OUR_NAME] dell'[OUR_EMPIRE]. Spero che i nostri due grandi popoli possano vivere in pace.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Saludos. &#161;Soy [OUR_NAME], del [OUR_EMPIRE]! Espero que nuestros dos grandes pueblos puedan vivir en paz.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>	
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_ENHEDUANNA_1</Tag>
		<English>Ah, welcome [CT_NAME].  I have just finished the most perfect poem, care to hear it?</English>
		<French>Salutations ! Je suis [OUR_NAME], je r&#232;gne sur l'[OUR_EMPIRE]. Je souhaite que nos deux grands peuples puissent vivre en paix.</French>
		<German>Seid gegr&#252;&#223;t! Ich bin [OUR_NAME], Staatsoberhaupt des [OUR_EMPIRE:3]es. Ich hoffe, unsere gro&#223;artigen V&#246;lker werden in Frieden zusammenleben.</German>
		<Italian>Saluti! Io sono [OUR_NAME] dell'[OUR_EMPIRE]. Spero che i nostri due grandi popoli possano vivere in pace.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Saludos. &#161;Soy [OUR_NAME], del [OUR_EMPIRE]! Espero que nuestros dos grandes pueblos puedan vivir en paz.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>	
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_REFUSE_TO_TALK_LEADER_SARGON_1</Tag>
		<English>You wish to speak? I will listen to you when you are dead, [CT_NAME]!</English>
		<French>Vos bavardages incessants ne nous amusent pas, [CT_NAME] !</French>
		<German>Euer bedeutungsloses Geschwafel am&#252;siert uns ganz und gar nicht, [CT_NAME]!</German>
		<Italian>I tuoi balbettii senza senso non sono affatto divertenti, [CT_NAME]!</Italian>
		<Spanish>&#161;No nos hace gracia vuestra ch&#225;chara absurda, [CT_NAME]!</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_NO_PEACE_LEADER_SARGON_1</Tag>
		<English>Coward! There will be peace only when your hapless empire is overrun by mighty Akkad!</English>
		<French>La guerre est tr&#232;s d&#233;plaisante, mais parfois n&#233;cessaire. Il appara&#238;t que nous sommes dans cette situation, aussi devons-nous rejeter votre requ&#234;te. Cette entrevue est termin&#233;e.</French>
		<German>Kriege sind eine h&#246;chst unangenehme Sache, manchmal aber auch unumg&#228;nglich. Und wie ich h&#246;re, ist das in diesem Fall so, deshalb muss ich Euer Anliegen zur&#252;ckweisen. Diese Unterhaltung ist beendet!</German>
		<Italian>La guerra non &#232; per niente piacevole, ma a volte &#232; necessaria. Questa &#232; una di quelle volte, perci&#242; dobbiamo respingere le tue suppliche. L'udienza termina qui.</Italian>
		<Spanish>La guerra es harto desagradable, pero a veces resulta necesaria. Nos informan de que &#233;sta es una de esas veces, as&#237; que debemos rechazar vuestras s&#250;plicas. La audiencia ha terminado.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FR_LEADER_SARGON_1</Tag>
		<English>My dear friend, [CT_NAME], to what do I owe this visit? Shall we go to battle together and feast upon the flesh of our enemies? Or we could have a cup of tea, if you'd rather.</English>
		<French>Je vous souhaite la bienvenue ! Venez, allons d&#233;truire nos ennemis du haut de nos chars et laissons cinquante mille cadavres sur le champ de bataille pour le festin des corbeaux !</French>
		<German>Willkommen! Lasst uns unsere Streitwagen anspannen und unsere Feinde vernichten! M&#246;gen die Gefallenen auf dem Schlachtfeld ein Festmahl f&#252;r die Geier sein!</German>
		<Italian>Salve, ti do il benvenuto! Montiamo sulle bighe e distruggiamo i nemici, lasceremo sul campo di battaglia solamente i cadaveri perch&#233; se ne sfamino i corvi!</Italian>
		<Spanish>&#161;Os saludamos, camarada! Venga, montemos en los carros, destruyamos a nuestros enemigos y dejemos cincuenta mil cad&#225;veres pudri&#233;ndose en el campo de batalla como pasto para los cuervos.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_GREETINGS_ATT_FUR_LEADER_SARGON_1</Tag>
		<English>Oh, how wonderf - oh, excuse me, [CT_NAME]. I saw your ugly head and for a moment I thought my soldiers were carrying it in on a pole.</English>
		<French>Bonjour, [CT_NAME]. A quoi devons-nous cette interruption inattendue ?</French>
		<German>Guten Tag, [CT_NAME]. Was beschert mir diese unerwartete St&#246;rung?</German>
		<Italian>Buongiorno a te, [CT_NAME]. A cosa dobbiamo questa interruzione inaspettata?</Italian>
		<Spanish>Buenos d&#237;as teng&#225;is, [CT_NAME]. &#191;A qu&#233; debemos esta interrupci&#243;n tan inesperada?</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_WEAKER_SARGON_1</Tag>
		<English>Poor, sweet, innocent [OUR_CIV_SHORT] needs your help, [CT_NAME].</English>
		<French>Les [CT_CIV_ADJ] sont dans le besoin, [CT_NAME]. J'esp&#232;re que vous ne les d&#233;cevrez pas.</French>
		<German>Das [CT_CIV_ADJ:3] Volk befindet sich in einer &#252;blen Notlage, [CT_NAME]! Entt&#228;uscht uns nicht!</German>
		<Italian>Il popolo [CT_CIV_ADJ:1] vive nell'indigenza, [CT_NAME]. Non deluderci.</Italian>
		<Spanish>El pueblo [CT_CIV_ADJ:1] tiene una gran necesidad, [CT_NAME]. No nos decepcion&#233;is.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_EQUAL_SARGON_1</Tag>
		<English>We have needs, [CT_NAME]. Please comply.</English>
		<French>Nous avons des besoins, [CT_NAME]. Veuillez les satisfaire.</French>
		<German>Auch wir haben Bed&#252;rfnisse, [CT_NAME]! Und es ist an Euch, sie zu befriedigen!</German>
		<Italian>Abbiamo delle necessit&#224;, [CT_NAME]. Ti preghiamo di accettarle.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Tenemos necesidades, [CT_NAME]. Satisfacedlas, por favor.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_DEMAND_TRIBUTE_POWER_STRONGER_SARGON</Tag>
		<English>We all have to make sacrifices. By 'we all,' I mean specifically you.</English>
		<French>Donnez aux [CT_CIV_SHORT] ce qui leur revient, [CT_NAME] ! Nous ne vous le demanderons pas deux fois.</French>
		<German>Gebt [CT_CIV_SHORT], was ihm zusteht, [CT_NAME]! Wir werden Euch kein zweites Mal darum bitten!</German>
		<Italian>Dona ci&#242; che ti richiede [CT_CIV_SHORT:2], [CT_NAME]! Non te lo chiederemo una seconda volta!</Italian>
		<Spanish>&#161;Dadle a [CT_CIV_SHORT] lo que le corresponde, [CT_NAME]! No os lo pediremos otra vez.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>		
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_AGADE</Tag>
		<English>Agade</English>
		<French>Agade</French>
		<German>Agade</German>
		<Italian>Agade</Italian>
		<Spanish>Agade</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_SIMURRUM</Tag>
		<English>Simurrum</English>
		<French>Simurrum</French>
		<German>Simurrum</German>
		<Italian>Simurrum</Italian>
		<Spanish>Simurrum</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>	
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_DER</Tag>
		<English>Der</English>
		<French>Der</French>
		<German>Der</German>
		<Italian>Der</Italian>
		<Spanish>Der</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>	
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_URUA</Tag>
		<English>Urua</English>
		<French>Urua</French>
		<German>Urua</German>
		<Italian>Urua</Italian>
		<Spanish>Urua</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>	
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_MARI</Tag>
		<English>Mari</English>
		<French>Mari</French>
		<German>Mari</German>
		<Italian>Mari</Italian>
		<Spanish>Mari</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>	
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_HAHHUM</Tag>
		<English>Hahhum</English>
		<French>Hahhum</French>
		<German>Hahhum</German>
		<Italian>Hahhum</Italian>
		<Spanish>Hahhum</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>	
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_TUTTUL</Tag>
		<English>Tuttul</English>
		<French>Tuttul</French>
		<German>Tuttul</German>
		<Italian>Tuttul</Italian>
		<Spanish>Tuttul</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>	
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_EBLA</Tag>
		<English>Ebla</English>
		<French>Ebla</French>
		<German>Ebla</German>
		<Italian>Ebla</Italian>
		<Spanish>Ebla</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>	
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_YARMUTI</Tag>
		<English>Yarmuti</English>
		<French>Yarmuti</French>
		<German>Yarmuti</German>
		<Italian>Yarmuti</Italian>
		<Spanish>Yarmuti</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>	
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_PURUSKHANDA</Tag>
		<English>Puruskhanda</English>
		<French>Puruskhanda</French>
		<German>Puruskhanda</German>
		<Italian>Puruskhanda</Italian>
		<Spanish>Puruskhanda</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>	
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_MARHASHI</Tag>
		<English>Marhashi</English>
		<French>Marhashi</French>
		<German>Marhashi</German>
		<Italian>Marhashi</Italian>
		<Spanish>Marhashi</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>	
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_ANSHAN</Tag>
		<English>Anshan</English>
		<French>Anshan</French>
		<German>Anshan</German>
		<Italian>Anshan</Italian>
		<Spanish>Anshan</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>	
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_MAGAN</Tag>
		<English>Magan</English>
		<French>Magan</French>
		<German>Magan</German>
		<Italian>Magan</Italian>
		<Spanish>Magan</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>	
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_DILMUN</Tag>
		<English>Dilmun</English>
		<French>Dilmun</French>
		<German>Dilmun</German>
		<Italian>Dilmun</Italian>
		<Spanish>Dilmun</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>	
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_ZAHARA</Tag>
		<English>Zahara</English>
		<French>Zahara</French>
		<German>Zahara</German>
		<Italian>Zahara</Italian>
		<Spanish>Zahara</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>	
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_SUBARTU</Tag>
		<English>Subartu</English>
		<French>Subartu</French>
		<German>Subartu</German>
		<Italian>Subartu</Italian>
		<Spanish>Subartu</Spanish>
	</TEXT>	
	<TEXT>	
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CITY_NAME_ARMANUM</Tag>
		<English>Armanum</English>
		<French>Armanum</French>
		<German>Armanum</German>
		<Italian>Armanum</Italian>
		<Spanish>Armanum</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>
