<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by lcollins (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- Copyright Firaxis Games 2005 -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text - New -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_CHE_BONG_NGA</Tag>
		<English>Che Bong Nga</English>
		<French>Che Bong Nga</French>
		<German>Che Bong Nga</German>
		<Italian>Che Bong Nga</Italian>
		<Spanish>Che Bong Nga</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_CHE_BONG_NGA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Che Bong Nga[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]King of Champa[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Reigned:[\BOLD] c.1360 - 1390 AD [PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Che Bong Nga, also known as the Red King in Vietnamese stories, is one of the great kings of Champa.  He was a remarkable general who attempted to reconquer the Cham provinces to the north of Vijaya.  Vijaya was under Vietnamese control at the time.  During these campaigns, Che Bong Nga sacked Hanoi, at the time known as Thang Long, three times and drove the Vietnamese Court into hiding.  The first sackings of Hanoi were in 1372 and in 1377.  The last attack occurred in 1388, which was checked by the Vietnamese General Jo Quy Ly, the future founder of the Ho Dynasty in Vietnam.  These campaigns were a major crisis in the history of the Dai Viet and spelled the end of the Tran Dynasty in Vietnam.  Despite all the success of Che Bong Nga, his successors had much less success holding together the new Champa.</English>
		<French>[H1]Che Bong Nga[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Roi de Champa[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]A regne:[\BOLD]vers 1360 - 1390 av. J.C.[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Biographie :[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Che Bong Nga, également connu sous le nom de roi rouge dans des histoires vietnamiennes, est l'un des grands rois de Champa. Il était un général remarquable qui a essayé au reconquer les provinces de Cham au nord de Vijaya. Vijaya était sous la commande vietnamienne alors. Pendant ces campagnes, Che Bong Nga a renvoyé Hanoï, alors connu sous le nom de Thang longtemps, trois fois et a conduit la cour vietnamienne dans se cacher. Les premiers sackings de Hanoï avaient lieu en 1372 et en 1377. La dernière attaque s'est produite en 1388, qui a été vérifié par le Général vietnamien Jo Quy Ly, le futur fondateur de la dynastie de Ho au Vietnam. Ces campagnes étaient une crise importante dans l'histoire du Dai Viet et ont orthographié la fin de la dynastie de Tran au Vietnam. En dépit de tout succès de Che Bong Nga, ses successeurs ont eu beaucoup moins de succès liant le nouveau Champa.</French>
		<German>[H1]Che Bong Nga[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]K&#246;nig von Champa[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Ordnete an:[\BOLD] ca. 1360 - 1390 v. Chr.[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Hintergrund:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Che Bong Nga, alias der rote König in den vietnamesischen Geschichten, ist einer der großen Könige von Champa. Er war ein bemerkenswerter General, der zum reconquer die Champrovinzen zum Norden von Vijaya versuchte. Vijaya war unter vietnamesischer Steuerung zu der Zeit. Während dieser Kampagnen sacked Che Bong Nga Hanoi, zu der Zeit lang bekannt als Thang, dreimal und fuhr das vietnamesische Gericht in das Verstecken. Die ersten sackings von Hanoi waren 1372 und 1377. Der letzte Angriff trat 1388, das vom vietnamesischen General Jo Quy Ly überprüft wurde, der zukünftige Gründer der Ho Dynastie in Vietnam auf. Diese Kampagnen waren eine Hauptkrise in der Geschichte des Dai Viet und buchstabierten das Ende der Tran Dynastie in Vietnam. Trotz alles Erfolges von Che Bong Nga, hatten seine Nachfolger viel weniger Erfolg das neue Champa zusammenhalten.</German>
		<Italian>[H1]Che Bong Nga[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Re di Champa[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Ha regolato:[\BOLD] ca. 1360 - 1390 a.C.[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Informazioni:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Che Bong Nga, anche conosciuto come il re rosso nelle storia vietnamite, è uno dei re grandi di Champa. Era un General notevole che ha tentato a reconquer le province del Cham al nord di Vijaya. Vijaya era allora sotto controllo vietnamita. Durante queste campagne, Che Bong Nga sacked Hanoi, allora conosciuta lungamente come Thang, tre volte ed ha guidato la corte vietnamita nel nascondersi. I primi sackings di Hanoi avevano luogo in 1372 e in 1377. L'ultimo attacco si è presentato in 1388, che è stato controllato dal General vietnamita Jo Quy Ly, il fondatore futuro del Dynasty di Ho nel Vietnam. Queste campagne erano una crisi importante nella storia del Dai Viet ed hanno ortografato la conclusione del Dynasty di Tran nel Vietnam. Malgrado tutto il successo di Che Bong Nga, i suoi successori hanno avuti molto meno successo che tengono insieme il nuovo Champa.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[H1]Che Bong Nga[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Rey de Champa[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Goberno:[\BOLD] c. 1360 - 1390 a. C.[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Historia:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Che Bong Nga, también conocido como el rey rojo en historias vietnamitas, es uno de los grandes reyes de Champa. Él era un general notable que procuró al reconquer las provincias del Cham al norte de Vijaya. Vijaya estaba bajo control vietnamita en ese entonces. Durante estas campañas, Che Bong Nga sacked Hanoi, conocida en ese entonces como Thang de largo, tres veces y condujo la corte vietnamita en ocultar. Los primeros sackings de Hanoi eran en 1372 y en 1377. El ataque pasado ocurrió en 1388, que fue comprobado por el general vietnamita Jo Quy Ly, el fundador futuro de la dinastía de Ho en Vietnam. Estas campañas eran una crisis importante en la historia del Dai Viet y deletrearon el final de la dinastía de Tran en Vietnam. A pesar de todo el éxito de Che Bong Nga, sus sucesores tenían mucho menos éxito que ligaban el Champa nuevo.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_CHE_BONG_NGA_1</Tag>
		<English>Greetings to you, [CT_NAME].  I am [OUR_NAME] and remind you that opportunity knocks but once.  What favors do you bring with you?</English>
		<French>Salutations à toi, [CT_NAME]. Je suis [OUR_NAME] et vous rappelle que l'occasion ne frappe qu'une fois. Quelles faveurs apportez-vous ?</French>
		<German>Grüße zu dir, [CT_NAME]. Ich bin [OUR_NAME] und erinnere dich, daß Gelegenheit aber einmal klopft. Welche Bevorzugungen holst du mit dir?</German>
		<Italian>Saluti a voi, [CT_NAME]. Sono [OUR_NAME] e gli ricordo che l'occasione batte ma una volta. Che favori portate con voi?</Italian>
		<Spanish>Saludos a ti, [CT_NAME]. Soy [OUR_NAME] y te recuerdo que la oportunidad golpea pero una vez. ¿Qué favores traes con ti?</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>