<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by lcollins (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- Copyright Firaxis Games 2005 -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text - New -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_MENARA</Tag>
		<English>Menara</English>
		<French>Menara</French>
		<German>Menara</German>
		<Italian>Menara</Italian>
		<Spanish>Menara</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_MENARA_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>The [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Menara[COLOR_REVERT], the Cham replacement for the [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Castle[COLOR_REVERT], provides a free priest in city.</English>
		<French>Le [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]menara[COLOR_REVERT], l'équivalent cham du [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]château[COLOR_REVERT], procure un prêtre gratuit dans la ville.</French>
		<German>Das [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Menara [COLOR_REVERT], der Chamwiedereinbau für das [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Schloß[COLOR_REVERT], liefert ein Hauptglück in deiner Stadt</German>
		<Italian>Il[COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Menara [COLOR_REVERT], il rimontaggio del Cham per il castillo [COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT] castillo  [COLOR_REVERT], fornisce una felicità importante nella vostra città</Italian>
		<Spanish>El[COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]Menara [COLOR_REVERT], el reemplazo del Cham para el[COLOR_BUILDING_TEXT]castillo  [COLOR_REVERT], proporciona una felicidad importante en tu ciudad</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
   	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_BUILDING_MENARA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The Cham Empire was a religious empire, and built many temples.  A common feature of these temples is that there are towers, or menaras, in these temples.  The most famous temples of the Cham are the temples at My Son.  Other temples with towers are Po Klaung, Po Nagar, and Pho Hai.  In the village of Khuong My in the Vietnamese province of Quang Nam stands a group of three Cham towers dating from the 10th century. [PARAGRAPH: 1] The Po Nagar towers once stood at the entrance to a river. The Po Nagar towers complex was built between the 7th and 12th century. The most beautiful towers were built in the year 813 and 817. Most were destroyed and only four towers are still standing. Each tower is a shrine to a different deity.  There are eight towers at Binh Dinh which are commonly used to study Champa.</English>
		<French>[TAB]L'empire de Cham était un empire religieux, et a construit beaucoup de temples. Un dispositif commun de ces temples est qu'il y a des tours dans des ces temples. Les temples les plus célèbres du Cham sont les temples à mon fils. D'autres temples avec des tours sont PO Klaung, PO Nagar, et Pho Hai. Dans le village de Khuong mon dedans la province vietnamienne de Quang Nam tient un groupe de trois tours de Cham datant du 10ème siècle. [PARAGRAPH : 1] Le PO Nagar domine une fois tenu à l'entrée à un fleuve. Le complexe de tours de PO Nagar a été établi entre le 7ème et 12ème siècle. Les tours les plus belles ont été construites en l'année 813 et 817. Les la plupart ont été détruites et seulement quatre tours se tiennent toujours. Chaque tour est un tombeau à une déité différente. Il y a huit tours chez Binh Dinh qui sont utilisées généralement pour étudier Champa.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Das cham-Reich war ein frommes Reich und errichtete viele Bügel. Eine allgemeine Eigenschaft dieser Bügel ist, daß es Aufsätze in diesen Bügeln gibt. Die berühmtesten Bügel des Cham sind die Bügel an meinem Sohn. Andere Bügel mit Aufsätzen sind PO Klaung, PO Nagar und Pho Hai. Im Dorf von Khuong meinem innen steht die vietnamesische Provinz von Quang Nam eine Gruppe von drei Chamaufsätzen, die vom 10. Jahrhundert datieren. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Das PO Nagar towers einmal gestanden am Eingang zu einem Fluß. Der PO Nagar Aufsatzkomplex wurde zwischen dem 7. und 12. Jahrhundert errichtet. Die schönsten Aufsätze wurden im Jahr 813 und 817 errichtet. Die meisten wurden zerstört und nur vier Aufsätze stehen noch. Jeder Aufsatz ist ein Schrein zu einer anderen Gottheit. Es gibt acht Aufsätze bei Binh Dinh, die allgemein verwendet sind, Champa zu studieren.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB]L'impero del Cham era un impero religioso ed ha costruito molte tempie. Una caratteristica comune di queste tempie è che ci sono torrette in queste tempie. Le tempie più famose del Cham sono le tempie al mio figlio. Altre tempie con le torrette sono Po Klaung, Po Nagar e Pho Hai. Nel villaggio di Khuong mio dentro la provincia vietnamita di Quang Nam si leva in piedi un gruppo di tre torrette del Cham che datano dal decimo secolo. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Il Po Nagar torreggia su levato in piedi una volta all'entrata ad un fiume. Il complesso delle torrette di Po Nagar è stato sviluppato fra il settimo e dodicesimo secolo. Le torrette più belle sono state costruite durante gli anni 813 e 817. La maggior parte sono stati distrutti e soltanto quattro torrette ancora stanno levando in piedi. Ogni torretta è uno shrine ad un deity differente. Ci sono otto torrette a Binh Dinh che sono comunemente usate studiare Champa.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB]El imperio del Cham era un imperio religioso, y construyó muchos templos. Una característica común de estos templos es que hay torres en estos templos. Los templos más famosos del Cham son los templos en mi hijo. Otros templos con las torres son Po Klaung, Po Nagar, y Pho Hai. En la aldea de Khuong mi adentro la provincia vietnamita de Quang Nam está parado un grupo de tres torres del Cham que fechan a partir del 10mo siglo. [PARAGRAPH: 1] El Po Nagar se eleva estado parado una vez en la entrada a un río. El complejo de las torres del Po Nagar fue construido entre el 7mo y 12mo siglo. Las torres más hermosas fueron construidas en el año 813 y 817. La mayoría fueron destruidas y solamente cuatro torres todavía están estando paradas. Cada torre es una capilla a un diverso deity. Hay ocho torres en Binh Dinh que son de uso general estudiar Champa.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>