<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by lcollins (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- Copyright Firaxis Games 2005 -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text - New -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
        <TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_ANGLO_SAXON_HUSCARL</Tag>
		<English>Huskarl</English>
		<French>Huskarl</French>
		<German>Huskarl</German>
		<Italian>Huskarl</Italian>
		<Spanish>Huskarl</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
        <TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_ANGLO_SAXON_HUSCARL_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>In Anglo-Saxon England there may have been as many as 3,000 royal housecarls, and a special tax was levied to provide pay in coin. They were housed and fed at the king's expense. They formed a standing army of professional soldiers and also had some administrative duties in peacetime as the King's representatives. The term was often used in contrast to the non-professional fyrd. These Housecarls used a tactic called the shieldwall. In this tactic the Housecarls formed a line with their shields locked blocking the invaders or enemies from penetrating their lines. The Saxons were an aggressive force, and did not like defending. Thus, this battle tactic was not used for a long time. Huscarls were often the only professional soldiers in the kingdom, the rest of the army being made up of militia called the fyrd, peasant levy, and occasionally mercenaries. They were usually armed with the long Danish axe and had shields and mail armour.</English>
		<French>in French</French>
		<German>in German</German>
		<Italian>in Italian</Italian>
		<Spanish>in Spanish</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_UNIT_ANGLO_SAXON_HUSCARL_STRATEGY</Tag>
		<English>THe Huskarl is the Anglo-Saxon replacement for the Swordsman. It is excellent against archery units.</English>
		<French>Le huskarl est l'équivalent anglo-saxon du spadassin. Il est très puissant contre les unités à l'arc.</French>
		<German>in German</German>
		<Italian>in Italian</Italian>
		<Spanish>in Spanish</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>