<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by lcollins (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- Copyright Firaxis Games 2005 -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text - New -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_JOGAILA</Tag>
		<English>Jogaila</English>
		<French>Jogaila</French>
		<German>Jogaila</German>
		<Italian>Jogaila</Italian>
		<Spanish>Jogaila</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_JOGAILA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Jogaila[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Grand Duke of Lithuania, King of Poland[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived:[\BOLD] 1362 - 1434 AD[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Jogaila was born to Algirdas, Grand Duke of Lithuania, and his second wife, Uliana, daughter of Alexander I, Grand Prince of Tver.  When Jogaila succeeded to the throne in 1377, Lithuania contained two different nationalities and two political systems: ethnic Lithuania in the northwest and the vast Ruthenian territories of the former Kievan Rus', comprising lands of modern Ukraine, Belarus, and parts of western Russia.  At first, Jogaila based his rule in southern and eastern territories in Lithuania, while his uncle continued to rule the northwestern region. [PARAGRAPH: 1] At the beginning of his reign, Jogaila confronted unrest in the Lithuanian Rus' lands.  In the northwest, Lithuania faced constant thread from the monastic state of the Teutonic Order, which was founded in 1226 to fight and convert the pagan Baltic tries of Prussians, Yotvingians, and Lithuanians.  In return for the Order's backing against Jogaila's uncle, Jogaila agreed to the Christianization of Lithuania.  However, Jogaila's uncle discovered the plan, seized Vilnius, overthrew Jogaila, and pronounced himself Grand Duke in his place.  Jogaila's uncle, with the help of his son Vytautas, entered Jogaila's encampment in Vilnius.  The uncle was later murdered, and Vytautas escaped.  Jogaila conducted further talks with the Teutonic Order, but later was betrayed by them.  Jogaila then allied himself with Vytautas to, in retaliation, loot and attack several Prussian castles. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Jogaila's choice to marry a Christian wife was evident, and he therefore married the young Queen Jadwiga of Poland.  Jogaila also signed a treaty with Poland agreeing to his Christianization and the returning of the lands taken from Poland by its neighbors.  Another agreement concerning a union between Lithuania and Poland was also signed when the marriage took place.  When Jogaila was baptized in 1386, Lithuania's Christianization began. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Jogaila and Jadwiga reigned as co-monarchs, and Jadwiga made several contributions to Poland's political and cultural life.  Jogaila then passed several laws unifying the two legal systems of Poland and Lithuania that achieved a lasting influence on history.  During the following years, he faced continuous challenges.  The Teutonic Knights failed to end their crusades claiming Jogaila's conversion to Christianity was false.  Jogaila and Jadwiga sponsored the creation of the Diocese of Vilnius and other religious reforms.  Jogaila faced a revived challenge from Vytautas, who resented the power given to Skirgaila in Lithuania at the expense of his own patrimony.  In 1390, Vytautas and the Teutonic Knights laid siege to Vilnius and destroyed the outer city.  In order to gain peace with Vytautas, Jogaila handed over the throne of Lithuania to him.  However, Vytautas continued to demand Lithuania's separation from Poland.  Later, after being crushed by the Timurids in a battle, Vytautas was forced to give in to Jogaila's protection once again. [PARAGRAPH: 1] In 1399, Jadwiga died while giving birth, leaving Jogaila the sole ruler of Poland without an heir.  In 1401, Vytautas was recognized as Grand Duke under Jogaila's overlordship, also allowing Jogaila's heirs, rather than those of Vytautas, to succeed to the throne.  If no heirs were born, the Lithuanian boyars would elect a new monarch.  This act forged an alliance between Poland and Lithuania, strengthening both for another war against the Teutonic Order.  However, after problems within borders, Jogaila was defeated after a war with the Teutonic Order, and gave in to their demands.  In 1408, Jogaila and Vytautas held strategic talks in Navahrudak, where they decided to revolt against Teutonic rule in portions of Lithuania.  The Order declared war against Poland that same year. [PARAGRAPH: 1] The castles on the northern border were easily captured by the Teutonic Knights, and both sides prepared for a major confrontation that winter.  Both sides received support from various European countries.  However, after one of the largest and most ferocious battles of the Middle Ages, Jogaila and his army were victors.  Jogaila, however, hesitated to move on to the capital of Marienburg, and thus suffered a loss at the city.  The war ended in 1411 in which neither Poland nor Lithuania returned home with all of what they hoped to earn.  Lithuania regained much of its territory after the war, but the Polish people began to revive their distrust of Jogaila.  Jogaila made several attempts to strengthen his relations with the Polish people, including permanently forming a union between Poland and Lithuania. [PARAGRAPH: 1] A new war broke out between the Knights and Poland, but ended in nothing, as both sides were still worn out from the last war.  Jogaila continued to be questioned and scandalized by his people, and lost the popularity he once had.  In 1422, Jogaila fought another war against the Teutonic Order, defeating them in under two months.  Further sporadic wars broke out between Poland and the Knights between 1431 and 1435.  Jogaila died in 1434, leaving Poland to his elder son and Lithuania to his younger, both were minors at the time.</English>
		<French>[H1]Jogaila[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Grand-Duc de Lituanie, Roi de Pologne[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Dates :[\BOLD] 1362 - 1434 ap. J.C.[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Biographie :[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Jogaila est né à Algirdas, Grand-Duc de Lituanie, et de sa seconde épouse, Uliana, fille d'Alexandre Ier, le Grand Prince de Tver. Quand Jogaila a succédé sur le trône en 1377, la Lituanie contenait deux nationalités différentes et de deux systèmes politiques: Lituanie ethniques dans le nord-ouest et la grande ruthène territoires de l'ancienne Kievan Rus', qui comprend les terres moderne de l'Ukraine, la Biélorussie, et des parties de l'ouest de la Russie. Au début, les Jagellon fondé son règne dans le sud et l'est du territoire en Lituanie, tandis que son oncle continué de gouverner la région nord-ouest. [PARAGRAPH 1] Au début de son règne, Jagellon confrontés troubles dans le lituanien Rus' terres. Dans le nord-ouest, la Lituanie font face à de constantes fil de l'état monastique de l'Ordre teutonique, qui a été fondée en 1226 à se battre et à convertir les païens Baltique essaie de Prussiens, Yotvingians, et les Lituaniens. En retour de l'Ordre soutien contre l'oncle de Jagellon, Ladislas II Jagellon convenu de la christianisation de la Lituanie. Toutefois, l'oncle de Jagellon découvert ce plan, à la saisie de Vilnius, a renversé Jagellon, et se prononce Grand-Duc à sa place. Jogaila son oncle, avec l'aide de son fils, Vytautas, est entré Jagellon de cantonnement à Vilnius. L'oncle a été assassiné plus tard, et Vytautas échappé. Jogaila mené de nouvelles discussions avec l'Ordre teutonique, mais plus tard a été trahi par eux. Jagellon puis s'allie avec Vytautas, en représailles, de piller et d'attaquer plusieurs châteaux de Prusse. [PARAGRAPH 1] Jagellon son choix d'épouser une chrétienne épouse était évident, et il a donc épousé la jeune reine Jadwiga de Pologne. Jogaila a également signé un traité avec la Pologne acceptant sa christianisation et de la restitution de terres de la prise de la Pologne par ses voisins. Un autre accord concernant l'union entre la Lituanie et la Pologne a également été signé lorsque le mariage a eu lieu. Quand Jagellon fut baptisé en 1386, la Lituanie a commencé christianisation. [PARAGRAPH 1] Jagellon et Jadwiga régna en tant que co-monarques, et Jadwiga fait plusieurs contributions à la Pologne de la vie politique et culturelle. Jogaila ensuite adopté plusieurs lois sur l'unification des deux systèmes juridiques, de la Pologne et la Lituanie, qui a obtenu une influence durable sur l'histoire. Au cours des années suivantes, il continue défis rencontrés. Les chevaliers teutoniques pas réussi à mettre fin à leurs croisades Jagellon revendiquant la conversion au christianisme était fausse. Jagellon et Jadwiga parrainé la création du diocèse de Vilnius et d'autres réformes religieuses. Jogaila relancé face à un défi de Vytautas, qui a ressenti le pouvoir donné à Skirgaila en Lituanie, au détriment de son propre patrimoine. En 1390, Vytautas et de l'Ordre teutonique assiégé à Vilnius et détruit l'extérieur ville. Afin de gagner la paix avec Vytautas, Ladislas II Jagellon remis le trône de la Lituanie auprès de lui. Toutefois, Vytautas Lituanie a continué d'exiger la séparation de la Pologne. Plus tard, après avoir été écrasé par le Timurids dans une bataille, Vytautas a été forcé de céder à la protection Jagellon une fois de plus. [PARAGRAPH 1] En 1399, Jadwiga est mort tout en donnant naissance, laissant Jagellon le seul dirigeant de la Pologne, sans un héritier. En 1401, a été reconnue comme Vytautas le Grand-Duc Jogaila sous l'overlordship, en autorisant également les héritiers de Ladislas II Jagellon, plutôt que celles de Vytautas, pour succéder au trône. Si les héritiers ne sont nés, les boyards lituanien serait élire un nouveau monarque. Cet acte forgé une alliance entre la Pologne et la Lituanie, renforçant à la fois pour une nouvelle guerre contre l'Ordre teutonique. Cependant, après des problèmes au sein de frontières, les Jagellon a été vaincu après une guerre avec l'Ordre teutonique, et cédé à leurs exigences. En 1408, Ladislas II Jagellon et Vytautas tenue stratégique pourparlers à Navahrudak, où ils ont décidé de se révolter contre Teutonique règle dans certaines parties de la Lituanie. L'Ordre a déclaré la guerre contre la Pologne, la même année. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Les châteaux sur la frontière nord sont facilement capturés par les chevaliers teutoniques, et les deux parties ont préparé pour une confrontation majeure que l'hiver. Les deux parties ont reçu le soutien de plusieurs pays européens. Toutefois, après l'un des plus grands et des plus féroces batailles du Moyen Age, Jagellon et son armée ont été vainqueurs. Ladislas II Jagellon, cependant, hésité à passer à la capitale de Marienburg, et donc subi une perte lors de la ville. La guerre a pris fin en 1411 dans lequel ni la Pologne, ni la Lituanie rentre à la maison avec tous ce qu'ils espéraient gagner. Lituanie a retrouvé une grande partie de son territoire après la guerre, mais le peuple polonais a commencé à raviver leur méfiance à l'égard des Jagellon. Jogaila tente à plusieurs reprises de renforcer ses relations avec le peuple polonais, y compris la formation d'une union permanente entre la Pologne et la Lituanie. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Une nouvelle guerre a éclaté entre les Chevaliers et de la Pologne, mais a pris fin en rien, car les deux parties étaient encore usé de la dernière guerre. Jogaila a continué d'être question et scandalisé par son peuple, et a perdu la popularité, il a une fois. En 1422, Ladislas II Jagellon combattu une autre guerre contre l'Ordre teutonique, les vaincre en moins de deux mois. D'autres guerres sporadiques ont éclaté entre la Pologne et les Chevaliers entre 1431 et 1435. Jagellon mourut en 1434, laissant la Pologne à son fils aîné et de la Lituanie à son jeune, les deux étaient mineurs à l'époque.</French>
		<German>[H1]Jogaila[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Gro&#223;herzog von Litauen, K&#246;nig von Polen[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lebte:[\BOLD] 1362 - 1434 n. Chr. [NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Wladyslaw II. Jagiello, geboren zu Algirdas, Großherzog von Litauen, und seiner zweiten Frau, Uliana, Tochter von Alexander I., Großfürst von Twer. Als Wladyslaw II. Jagiello gelungen, auf den Thron in 1377, Litauen enthielt zwei verschiedene Nationalitäten und zwei politische Systeme: ethnischen Litauen in den Nordwesten und die große ruthenische Gebiete des ehemaligen Kiewer Rus "mit den Ländern der modernen Ukraine, Weißrussland und Teile der westlichen Russland. Auf den ersten, Wladyslaw II. Jagiello stützte seine Herrschaft in den südlichen und östlichen Gebiete in Litauen, während sein Onkel weiter Regel der nordwestlichen Region. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Zu Beginn seiner Regierungszeit, Wladyslaw II. Jagiello konfrontiert Unruhen in der litauischen Rus' landet. Im Nordwesten, Litauen, denen konstant Thread aus der klösterlichen Staat des Deutschen Ordens, der 1226 gegründet wurde und zu bekämpfen und zu konvertieren, die heidnischen baltischen versucht von Preußen, Yotvingians und Litauer. Im Gegenzug für die Unterstützung des Ordens gegen Onkel Wladyslaw II. Jagiello, Wladyslaw II. Jagiello vereinbart, die Christianisierung von Litauen. Allerdings, Wladyslaw II. Jagiello Onkel entdeckte den Plan, beschlagnahmt Vilnius, stürzten Wladyslaw II. Jagiello, und sprach sich Großherzog an seinem Platz ist. Wladyslaw II. Jagiello Onkel, der mit Hilfe von seinem Sohn Vytautas, trat Wladyslaw II. Jagiello's Camp in Vilnius. Der Onkel wurde später ermordet, und Vytautas entkam. Wladyslaw II. Jagiello führte weitere Gespräche mit dem Deutschen Orden, wurde aber später von ihnen verraten. Wladyslaw II. Jagiello, dann verbündete sich mit Vytautas, in der Vergeltung, Beute angegriffen und mehrere preußischen Schlössern. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Wladyslaw II. Jagiello Wahl zu heiraten, eine christliche Frau war offensichtlich, und er daher heiratete die junge Königin Jadwiga von Polen. Wladyslaw II. Jagiello auch einen Vertrag mit Polen die Zustimmung zu seiner Rückkehr und der Christianisierung des Landes, die aus Polen von seinem Nachbarn. Ein weiteres Abkommen über eine Union zwischen Litauen und Polen wurde auch, wenn die Ehe stattfand. Als Wladyslaw II. Jagiello wurde in 1386 getauft, Litauen's Christianisierung begann. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Wladyslaw II. Jagiello Jadwiga und regierte als Co-Monarchen, und Jadwiga aus mehreren Beiträgen zu Polen die politischen und kulturellen Leben. Wladyslaw II. Jagiello dann mehrere Gesetze Vereinheitlichung der beiden Rechtssysteme von Polen und Litauen, einen dauerhaften Einfluss auf die Geschichte. In den folgenden Jahren hat er sich kontinuierlich Herausforderungen. Die Kreuzritter nicht beenden ihre Kreuzzüge behaupten Wladyslaw II. Jagiello die Konvertierung zum Christentum war falsch. Wladyslaw II. Jagiello Jadwiga gesponsert und die Schaffung der Diözese von Vilnius und anderen religiösen Reformen. Wladyslaw II. Jagiello wieder vor einer Herausforderung von Vytautas, übelgenommen, die die Macht an Skirgaila in Litauen auf Kosten seiner eigenen Erbes. In 1390, Vytautas und den Deutschen Ritterorden, die Belagerung zu Wilna und zerstörte den äußeren Stadt. Um zu gewinnen, den Frieden mit Vytautas, Wladyslaw II. Jagiello übergab den Thron von Litauen zu ihm. Allerdings, Vytautas weiterhin Nachfrage Litauen's Trennung von Polen. Später, nachdem er erdrückt von der Timurids in einer Schlacht, Vytautas war gezwungen zu geben und zu Wladyslaw II. Jagiello-Schutz wieder. [PARAGRAPH: 1] In 1399, Jadwiga starb während der Geburt, so dass der alleinige Herrscher Wladyslaw II. Jagiello von Polen ohne Erben. In 1401, Vytautas war als Grand Duke's overlordship unter Wladyslaw II. Jagiello, Wladyslaw II. Jagiello auch die Erben, sondern als die von Vytautas, zur Thronfolge. Wenn keine Erben geboren wurden, die litauischen Bojaren würde wählt einen neuen Monarchen. Dieser Akt schmiedete eine Allianz zwischen Polen und Litauen, die Stärkung sowohl für einen neuen Krieg gegen den Deutschen Orden. Allerdings, nach Problemen innerhalb der Grenzen, Wladyslaw II. Jagiello wurde nach einem Krieg mit dem Deutschen Orden, und gab sich in ihren Forderungen. In 1408, Wladyslaw II. Jagiello und Vytautas hielt strategische Gespräche in Navahrudak, wo sie beschlossen, die Revolte gegen die germanische Regel in Portionen von Litauen. Der Orden den Krieg gegen Polen im selben Jahr. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Die Schlösser an der nördlichen Grenze gefangen genommen wurden leicht durch den Deutschen Ritterorden, und beide Seiten bereit für eine große Konfrontation, die im Winter. Beide Seiten erhielten Unterstützung aus verschiedenen europäischen Ländern. Allerdings, nach einer der größten und wildesten Schlachten des Mittelalters, Wladyslaw II. Jagiello und seine Armee wurden Sieger. Wladyslaw II. Jagiello, aber zögerte, um auf die Hauptstadt der Marienburg, und somit einen Verlust erlitten in der Stadt. Der Krieg endete 1411, in dem weder Polen noch Litauen kehrten nach Hause zurück mit allem, was sie hoffen, zu verdienen. Litauen wieder viel von seinem Hoheitsgebiet nach dem Krieg, sondern das polnische Volk begann zu beleben, sein Misstrauen von Wladyslaw II. Jagiello. Wladyslaw II. Jagiello aus mehreren Versuchen zu stärken, seine Beziehungen mit der polnischen Volkes, einschließlich der Bildung einer Gewerkschaft permanent zwischen Polen und Litauen. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Ein neuer Krieg zwischen den Knights und Polen, aber in nichts beendet, da beide Seiten noch getragen aus dem letzten Krieg. Wladyslaw II. Jagiello fortgesetzt werden und die Frage angeeckt von seinem Volk, und die Popularität verloren, die er einst hatte. In 1422, Wladyslaw II. Jagiello kämpfte einen neuen Krieg gegen den Deutschen Orden, sie zu besiegen, in weniger als zwei Monaten. Weitere sporadisch brachen Kriege zwischen Polen und der Ritter zwischen 1431 und 1435. Wladyslaw II. Jagiello starb 1434, so dass Polen zu seinem älteren Sohn und Litauen bis zu seinem jüngeren, beide wurden von Minderjährigen zu dieser Zeit.</German>
		<Italian>[H1]Jogaila[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Granduca di Lituania, Re di Polonia[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Vita:[\BOLD] 1362 - 1434 d.C. [NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Informazioni:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Jogaila è nato a Algirdas, Granduca di Lituania, e la sua seconda moglie, Uliana, figlia di Alessandro I, Gran Principe di Tver. Quando Jogaila succeduto al trono nel 1377, la Lituania conteneva due nazionalità diverse e due sistemi politici: etnica Lituania nel nord-ovest, e la stragrande ruteni territori della ex Kiev Rus', che comprende le terre della moderna Ucraina, la Bielorussia, e parti della Russia occidentale. In un primo tempo, Jogaila basa la sua regola e meridionale e orientale territori in Lituania, mentre suo zio continuò a governare la regione nord-occidentale. [PARAGRAPH: 1] All'inizio del suo regno, di fronte Jogaila disordini in lituano Rus' terre. Nel nord-ovest, la Lituania fronte costante filo da monastica stato della Teutonico, che è stata fondata nel 1226 per combattere e convertire i pagani baltici cerca di prussiani, Yotvingians, e lituani. In cambio, per l'Ordine di appoggio contro Jogaila's zio, Jogaila accettato la cristianizzazione della Lituania. Tuttavia, Jogaila's zio scoperto il piano, sequestrati Vilnius, Jogaila rovesciato, e una marcata se stesso Granduca al suo posto. Jogaila's zio, con l'aiuto di suo figlio Vytautas, entrato Jogaila's accampamento a Vilnius. Lo zio fu poi assassinato, e Vytautas escape. Jogaila condotti ulteriori colloqui con l'Ordine Teutonico, ma in seguito è stato tradito da loro. Jogaila poi si alleò con Vytautas, per ritorsione, bottino attacco più prussiana e castelli. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Jogaila, la scelta di sposare un cristiano moglie era evidente, e pertanto egli sposò la giovane regina Edvige di Polonia. Jogaila inoltre firmato un trattato con la Polonia, accettando la sua cristianizzazione e il ritorno delle terre prese dalla Polonia con i suoi vicini. Un'altra, relativa ad un accordo di unione tra la Lituania e la Polonia, è stato firmato anche quando il matrimonio ha avuto luogo. Quando Jogaila fu battezzato nel 1386, la Lituania ha iniziato la cristianizzazione. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Jogaila e Jadwiga regnato come co-monarchi, e Jadwiga fatto diversi contributi alla Polonia la vita politica e culturale. Jogaila poi passò varie leggi unificante i due sistemi giuridici di Polonia e Lituania, che ha raggiunto una duratura influenza sulla storia. Negli anni seguenti, ha di fronte sfide continue. Il Cavaliere Teutonico non ha fine il loro crociate Jogaila rivendicando la conversione al cristianesimo era falso. Jogaila e Jadwiga sponsorizzato la creazione della diocesi di Vilnius e di altre riforme religiose. Jogaila dovuto affrontare una sfida rianimato da Vytautas, che risentì il potere dato a Skirgaila in Lituania, a scapito del proprio patrimonio. Nel 1390, Vytautas Teutonico Cavalieri e il cui assedio a Vilnius e distrutto l'esterno della città. Al fine di ottenere la pace con Vytautas, Jogaila consegnato il trono di Lituania a lui. Tuttavia, Vytautas Lituania ha continuato a chiedere la separazione dalla Polonia. Più tardi, dopo essere stato schiacciato dal Timurids in una battaglia, Vytautas è stato costretto a cedere al Jogaila's protezione ancora una volta. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Nel 1399, Jadwiga morì mentre la nascita di un figlio, lasciando Jogaila l'unico governante della Polonia senza un erede. Nel 1401, è stato riconosciuto come Vytautas Granduca Jogaila sotto's overlordship, consentendo anche Jogaila's eredi, piuttosto che quelli di Vytautas, per avere successo al trono. Se non sono nati eredi, il lituano boyars sarebbe eleggere un nuovo monarca. Questo atto forgiato un'alleanza tra la Polonia e la Lituania, il rafforzamento sia per una nuova guerra contro l'Ordine Teutonico. Tuttavia, dopo i problemi all'interno di frontiere, Jogaila è stato sconfitto dopo una guerra con l'Ordine Teutonico, e ha dato e alle loro richieste. Nel 1408, Jogaila e Vytautas terrà colloqui strategici e Navahrudak, dove hanno deciso di rivolta contro Teutonico regola in porzioni di Lituania. L'Ordine ha dichiarato guerra contro la Polonia in quello stesso anno. [PARAGRAPH: 1] I castelli sul confine settentrionale erano facilmente catturato dai Teutonico Cavalieri, e di entrambi i lati preparato per un importante confronto che invernale. Entrambe le parti hanno ricevuto sostegno da vari paesi europei. Tuttavia, dopo una delle più grandi e più feroci battaglie del Medio Evo, Jogaila e il suo esercito sono stati vincitori. Jogaila, tuttavia, esitato a muoversi verso la capitale di Marienburg, e, quindi, subito una perdita in città. La guerra terminò nel 1411, in cui né la Polonia né Lituania tornato a casa con tutto quello che sperava di guadagnare. Lituania riacquistato gran parte del suo territorio, dopo la guerra, ma il popolo polacco ha iniziato a ravvivare la loro diffidenza di Jogaila. Jogaila fatto diversi tentativi di rafforzare le sue relazioni con il popolo polacco, compresi permanentemente formazione di una unione tra la Polonia e la Lituania. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Una nuova guerra scoppiata tra il Cavaliere e la Polonia, ma alla fine nel nulla, in quanto entrambe le parti erano ancora esaurita da l'ultima guerra. Jogaila continuato ad essere scandalizzati dalla questione e il suo popolo, e perde la popolarità che si era una volta. Nel 1422, un altro Jogaila lottato contro la guerra Teutonico, sconfitto in meno di due mesi. Ulteriori sporadici guerre scoppiata tra la Polonia e Cavalieri tra 1431 e 1435. Jogaila morì nel 1434, lasciando la Polonia per il suo figlio maggiore e la Lituania ai suoi giovani, entrambi erano minorenni al momento.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[H1]Jogaila[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Gran Duque de Lituania, Rey de Polonia[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Vivi&#243;:[\BOLD] 1362 - 1434 d. C. [NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Historia:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Jogaila nació a Algirdas, Gran Duque de Lituania, y de su segunda esposa, Uliana, hija de Alejandro I, el Gran Príncipe de Tver. Cuando Jogaila sucesión al trono en 1377, Lituania contiene dos nacionalidades diferentes y dos sistemas políticos: Lituania étnica en el noroeste y la gran rutenio territorios de la antigua Rus de Kiev ", que comprende tierras de la moderna Ucrania, Bielorrusia, y partes del oeste de Rusia. Al principio, Jogaila basa su imperio en el sur y el este de los territorios en Lituania, mientras que su tío siguen gobernando la región noroeste. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Al principio de su reinado, Jogaila enfrentan disturbios en el lituano Rus' tierras. En el noroeste, Lituania se enfrentan constante hilo de la monástica estado de la Orden Teutónica, que se fundó en 1226 para luchar contra la conversión de los paganos y el Báltico trata de prusianos, Yotvingians, y los lituanos. A cambio de la Orden del respaldo contra el tío de Jogaila, Jogaila de acuerdo a la cristianización de Lituania. Sin embargo, el tío de Jogaila descubrió el plan, se apoderó de Vilnius, derrocó Jogaila, y él mismo pronuncia Gran Duque en su lugar. Jogaila del tío, con la ayuda de su hijo Vytautas, entró Jogaila del campamento en Vilnius. El tío fue asesinado más tarde, y Vytautas escapó. Jogaila llevó a cabo nuevas conversaciones con la Orden Teutónica, pero más tarde fue traicionado por ellos. Jogaila entonces aliado a sí mismo con Vytautas, en represalia, el ataque y saqueo de varios castillos prusiana. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Jogaila escogió para casarse con una mujer cristiana era evidente, y por lo tanto, se casó con el joven reina Jadwiga de Polonia. Jogaila también firmó un tratado con Polonia de acuerdo a su cristianización y la devolución de las tierras tomadas de Polonia por sus vecinos. Otro acuerdo relativo a una unión entre Lituania y Polonia también fue firmado cuando el matrimonio se haya celebrado. Jogaila cuando fue bautizado en 1386, se inició la cristianización de Lituania. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Jogaila y Jadwiga reinó como co-monarcas, y Jadwiga hizo varias contribuciones a Polonia en la vida política y cultural. Jogaila entonces pasó varias leyes unificación de los dos sistemas jurídicos de Polonia y Lituania, que logró una duradera influencia en la historia. Durante los siguientes años, se enfrentaba a retos continuos. Los Caballeros no Teutónica a poner fin a sus cruzadas alegando Jogaila la conversión al cristianismo era falsa. Jogaila Jadwiga y patrocinó la creación de la Diócesis de Vilnius y otras reformas religiosas. Jogaila enfrenta desafío de reactivar un Vytautas, resentimiento, que el poder dado a Skirgaila en Lituania a costa de su propio patrimonio. En 1390, Vytautas y la Teutónica Caballeros sitiaron a Vilnius y destruyó la ciudad exterior. A fin de obtener la paz con Vytautas, Jogaila entregó el trono de Lituania a él. Sin embargo, Vytautas seguido de Lituania a la demanda de separación de Polonia. Más tarde, después de haber sido aplastada por la Timurids en una batalla, Vytautas se vio obligado a ceder a la protección Jogaila una vez más. [PARAGRAPH: 1] En 1399, Jadwiga murió al dar a luz, dejando Jogaila el único gobernante de Polonia sin un heredero. En 1401, Vytautas fue reconocido como Gran Duque bajo Jogaila del overlordship, permitiendo también que los herederos de Jogaila, en lugar de los de Vytautas, para tener éxito al trono. Si los herederos no han nacido, el lituano boyars elegirá un nuevo monarca. Este acto forjado una alianza entre Polonia y Lituania, otro tanto para el fortalecimiento de la guerra contra la Orden Teutónica. Sin embargo, después de los problemas dentro de las fronteras, Jogaila fue derrotada después de una guerra con la Orden Teutónica, y dio a sus demandas. En 1408, y Jogaila Vytautas celebró conversaciones estratégicas en Navahrudak, donde se decidió a la revuelta contra la norma Teutónica en porciones de Lituania. La Orden declarado la guerra contra Polonia en el mismo año. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Los castillos en la frontera norte fueron fácilmente capturados por la Teutónica caballeros, y ambas partes prepararon para un importante enfrentamiento que el invierno. Ambas partes recibieron el apoyo de varios países europeos. Sin embargo, después de una de las mayores y más feroces batallas de la Edad Media, Jogaila y su ejército fueron vencedores. Jogaila, sin embargo, dudaban a la hora de pasar a la capital de Marienburg, y, por tanto, sufrió una pérdida en la ciudad. La guerra terminó en 1411 en el que ni Polonia ni Lituania volvió a casa con la totalidad de lo que espera ganar. Lituania recuperó gran parte de su territorio después de la guerra, pero el pueblo polaco comenzó a reactivar su desconfianza de Jogaila. Jogaila hecho varios intentos de fortalecer sus relaciones con el pueblo polaco, incluida la formación de una unión permanente entre Polonia y Lituania. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Una nueva guerra entre los Caballeros y Polonia, pero terminó en la nada, ya que ambas partes estaban todavía desgastado de la última guerra. Jogaila sigue siendo cuestión y escandalizó por su pueblo, y la pérdida de la popularidad que una vez tuvieron. En 1422, luchó Jogaila otra guerra contra la Orden Teutónica, derrotando a ellos en menos de dos meses. Más esporádicas guerras estalló entre Polonia y los Caballeros entre 1431 y 1435. Jogaila murió en 1434, dejando a Polonia a su hijo mayor y Lituania a su más joven, ambos menores de edad en el momento.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_JOGAILA_1</Tag>
		<English>Hello [CT_NAME].  I hope we can help each other, for the person who gives is the person who has.</English>
		<French>Bonjour [CT_NAME]. J'espère que nous pourrons nous aider les uns les autres, pour que celui qui donne soit celui qui possède.</French>
		<German>Hallo [CT_NAME]. Ich hoffe, wir können einander helfen, für die Personen, die von der Person, die hat.</German>
		<Italian>Ciao [CT_NAME]. Spero che si possa aiutare a vicenda, per la persona che dà è la persona che ha.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Hola [CT_NAME]. Espero que podamos ayudar unos a otros, para la persona que se da a la persona que los haya.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>