<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by lcollins (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- Copyright Firaxis Games 2005 -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text - New -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_NUBIA_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Nubian Empire</English>
		<French>Royaume de Nubie</French>
		<German>Nubian Reich</German>
		<Italian>Impero di Nubian</Italian>
		<Spanish>Imperio de Nubian</Spanish>
	</TEXT>	
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_NUBIA_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Nubia</English>
		<French>Nubiens</French>
		<German>Nubia</German>
		<Italian>Nubia</Italian>
		<Spanish>Nubia</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_NUBIA_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Nubian</English>
    <French>
	    <Text>nubien:nubienne:nubiens:nubiennes</Text>
	    <Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
	    <Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
    </French>
		<German>Nubian</German>
		<Italian>Nubian</Italian>
		<Spanish>Nubian</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_NUBIA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The first sign of inhabitants in the land now called Nubia was in the fifth millennium BC.  Various monuments of these early cultures can be found throughout parts of Eastern Africa and the Nile Valley.  Around 3800 BC, the first Nubian culture arose, known as the A Group.  Around 3300 BC, there is evidence of a unified kingdom that maintained interactions with the culture of Naqadan Upper Egypt.  This culture began to decline in the 28th century BC, when the B Group culture appeared.  The B Group is like the A Group, but poorer for reasons believed to be Egyptian invasions.  Nubia was a trade corridor between Egypt and tropical Africa. [PARAGRAPH: 2] In 2300 BC, Nubia was first mentioned in Old Kingdom Egyptian accounts of trade missions.  Trade with Egypt increased Nubia's wealth and stability as a nation.  By the Egyptian 6th Dynasty, Nubia was divided into a series of small kingdoms.  This C Group flourished from 2240 BC to 2150 BC.  During the Egyptian Middle Kingdom, it expanded into Nubia to gain control over the trade routes.  The Egyptians who lived in Nubia seemed to have peaceful relations with the people, but limited contact.  The next culture, the Pan Graves, lived along the East bank of the Nile River. [PARAGRAPH: 2] The first kingdom to unify much of the region arose, the Kingdom of Kerma, which was named after its capital at Kerma.  By 1760 BC, the kings organized various construction projects.  At one point, Kerma even came close to conquering Egypt.  However, as Egyptian power revived under the New Kingdom and expanded into Nubian lands, Kerma was destroyed and the new administrative center, Napata, was built. [PARAGRAPH: 2] When the Egyptians pulled out of Nubia, they left there cultural traditions, that mixed in with the previous traditions.  The Kingdom of Kush was then created, that adopted many Egyptian traditions, such as building pyramids.  Under the leadership of powerful leaders, Kush conquered Egypt and even outlasted it.  Eventually, they were conquered by the Assyrians and forced to migrate further south, establishing the new capital at Meroe.  The people of Meroe preserved many of their distinct customs, while still adapting Egyptian customs.  A famous Meroean incident is when their queen, Candace, held out against Alexander the Great who withdrew his troops.  Other powerful queens held out against the Romans.  Meroe would soon meet defeat by a new kingdom, Aksum, in the south. [PARAGRAPH: 2] After being occupied by the kingdom of Aksum, Nubia was divided into three smaller kingdoms: Nobatia, Makuria, and Alodia.  John of Ephesus records that a priest converted the king and his nobles of Nabatia to Christianity around 545.  He also wrote that Alodia was converted around 569.  The Kingdom of Makuria was apparently converted to Roman Catholicism around the same year.  By the 7th century, Makuria became the dominant power in the region.  It was strong enough to hold out against the southern expansion of Islam when the Arabs took Egypt.  A peace treaty was signed between the new rulers that lasted for six hundred years.  Over time, Islam migrated into Nubia and replaced Christianity.  [PARAGRAPH: 2] In the 14th century, the government collapsed and was dominated by Egypt.  By the end of colonialist, Nubia was divided between Egypt and Sudan.  Nubian villages can now be found north of Aswan and on Elephantine Island.  The Nubian people now live in large cities such as Cairo.</English>
		<French>[TAB]Le premier signe d'habitants de la terre est maintenant appelé Nubie dans la cinquième millénaire av. Divers monuments de ces premiers cultures peuvent être trouvées dans différentes parties de l'Afrique de l'Est et la vallée du Nil. Autour de 3800 avant notre ère, la première nubien se pose la culture, connu sous le nom A Groupe. Autour de 3300 avant J.-C., il existe des preuves d'un royaume unifié maintenu que les interactions avec la culture de Naqadan Haute Égypte. Cette culture a commencé à décliner dans la 28e siècle avant J.-C., lorsque le Groupe B est apparu la culture. Le Groupe B est comme le Groupe A, mais les plus pauvres pour des raisons jugées égyptien des invasions. Nubie était un corridor commercial entre l'Egypte et l'Afrique tropicale. [PARAGRAPH: 2] En 2300 avant J.-C., la Nubie a été mentionnée pour la première fois dans le Vieux Royaume égyptien comptes de missions commerciales. Le commerce avec l'Égypte a augmenté la richesse de la Nubie et de la stabilité en tant que nation. Par égyptien 6e dynastie, la Nubie a été divisé en une série de petits royaumes. Ce groupe C prospéra de 2240 avant J.-C. à 2150 av. Pendant le Moyen Empire égyptien, elle en Nubie élargi à la prise de contrôle de routes commerciales. Les Egyptiens qui vivaient dans la Nubie semblait avoir des relations pacifiques avec les peuples, mais des contacts limités. La prochaine culture, de la Pan Graves, vivaient le long de la rive orientale du Nil. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Le premier royaume à unifier une grande partie de la région ont surgi, le royaume de Kerma, qui a reçu le nom de sa capitale à Kerma. En 1760 avant notre ère, les rois organisé divers projets de construction. À un moment donné, Kerma même venu près de la conquête de l'Egypte. Toutefois, comme le pouvoir égyptien relancée dans le cadre du Nouveau Royaume et élargi en Nubie terres, Kerma a été détruite et le nouveau centre administratif, Napata, a été construit. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Quand les Egyptiens se sont retirés de la Nubie, ils ont laissé là traditions culturelles, qui mélangé avec le précédent dans les traditions. Le Royaume de Koush a été alors créé, qui a adopté un grand nombre de traditions égyptiennes, telles que la construction des pyramides. Sous la direction de puissants chefs, Kush conquis l'Egypte et même survécu. Finalement, ils ont été conquis par les Assyriens et forcés de migrer plus au sud, la mise en place de la nouvelle capitale à Méroé. Les habitants de Méroé conservé beaucoup de leurs coutumes, tout en adaptant les douanes égyptiennes. Un célèbre Meroean incident est lorsque leur reine, Candace, qui a eu lieu à l'encontre d'Alexandre le Grand, qui a retiré ses troupes. Autres reines tenue puissant contre les Romains. Méroé allait bientôt répondre par une nouvelle défaite royaume d'Axoum, dans le sud. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Après avoir été occupés par le royaume d'Axoum, la Nubie a été divisé en trois petits royaumes: Nobatia, Makuria et Alodia. Jean d'Éphèse dossiers qu'un prêtre converti le roi et ses nobles de Nabatia au christianisme autour de 545. Il a également écrit que Alodia fut converti vers 569. Le Royaume de Makuria a apparemment été convertis au catholicisme romain autour de la même année. Par la 7e siècle, Makuria devenus la puissance dominante dans la région. Il a été assez forte pour tenir le coup contre le sud de l'expansion de l'Islam lorsque les Arabes ont pris l'Égypte. Un traité de paix a été signé entre les nouveaux dirigeants qui a duré pendant six cents ans. Au fil du temps, l'Islam a émigré en Nubie et remplacé le christianisme. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Au 14ème siècle, le gouvernement s'est effondré et a été dominé par l'Egypte. À la fin du colonialisme, la Nubie a été divisée entre l'Egypte et le Soudan. Nubien de villages se trouvent maintenant au nord d'Assouan, sur l'île Éléphantine. Le nubien de personnes vivent actuellement dans les grandes villes comme Le Caire.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Die ersten Zeichen der Bewohner in das Land jetzt Nubien genannt wurde in der fünften Jahrtausend v. Chr.. Verschiedene Denkmäler dieser frühen Kulturen kann man in Teilen des östlichen Afrika und dem Nil-Tal. Um 3800 v. Chr., der erste nubische Kultur entstand, bekannt als die A Gruppe. Um 3300 v. Chr., gibt es Anzeichen für ein einheitliches Reich, das gepflegt Wechselwirkungen mit der Kultur der Naqadan Oberägypten. Diese Kultur begann Rückgang im 28. Jahrhundert v. Chr., als die B Gruppe Kultur erschienen. Die Gruppe B ist wie die A Gruppe, sondern ärmer aus Gründen davon aus, dass ägyptische Invasionen. Nubien war ein Handel zwischen Ägypten und tropischen Afrika. [PARAGRAPH: 2] In 2300 BC, Nubien wurde zum ersten Mal im Alten Reich ägyptischen Konten des Handels Missionen. Der Handel mit Ägypten stieg Nubien Reichtum und Stabilität als eine Nation. Nach der ägyptischen 6. Dynastie, Nubien wurde in einer Reihe von kleinen Königreiche. Diese Gruppe C blühte von 2240 v. Chr. bis 2150 v. Chr.. Während der ägyptischen Mittleren Reich, in Nubien erweitert um die Kontrolle über die Handelswege. Der Ägypter lebte in Nubien zu sein schien friedliche Beziehungen mit den Menschen, aber nur Kontakt. Die nächste Kultur, die Pan Graves, lebten entlang der Ufer des East River Nile. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Das erste Reich zu vereinheitlichen viel in der Region entstanden, das Königreich von Kerma, was benannt nach der Hauptstadt Kerma. Nach 1760 v. Chr., die Könige organisiert verschiedene Bauvorhaben. Es gab einen Punkt, Kerma sogar nah an der Eroberung Ägyptens. Doch wie ägyptischen Macht wieder im Rahmen des neuen Königreichs und erweitert in die nubische Grundstücke, Kerma zerstört wurde und der neue administrative Zentrum, Napata, gebaut wurde. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Wenn die Ägypter zog sich aus Nubien, verließen sie es kulturellen Traditionen, die gemischt mit der bisherigen Traditionen. Das Königreich von Kusch war dann, dass viele angenommen ägyptischen Traditionen, wie Gebäude Pyramiden. Unter der Führung von mächtigen Führer, Kush erobert Ägypten und sogar überdauerten. Schließlich wurden sie von den Assyrern erobert und gezwungen, zu migrieren weiter nach Süden, zur Gründung der neuen Hauptstadt Meroe. Die Leute von Meroe erhalten viele ihrer unterschiedlichen Bräuche, während noch die Anpassung ägyptische Zoll. Ein berühmtes Meroean Vorfall ist, wenn ihre Königin, Candace, die sich gegen Alexander dem Großen, der seine Truppen. Andere mächtige Königinnen statt gegen die Römer. Meroe bald treffen Niederlage durch ein neues Reich, Aksum, im Süden des Landes. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Nach der Besetzung durch das Reich von Aksum, Nubien wurde in drei kleinere Königreiche: Nobatia, Makuria und Alodia. Johannes von Ephesus Aufzeichnungen, dass ein Priester konvertiert der König und seine Adeligen von Nabatia zum Christentum rund 545. Er schrieb auch, dass Alodia wurde rund 569. Das Königreich Makuria war offensichtlich zu Katholische Kirche in der gleichen Jahr. Nach dem 7. Jahrhundert, Makuria wurde die dominierende Macht in der Region. Es war stark genug, um sich gegen den südlichen Expansion des Islam, wenn die Araber hat Ägypten. Ein Friedensvertrag unterzeichnet wurde zwischen den neuen Herrscher, das seit sechshundert Jahren. Im Laufe der Zeit, den Islam konvertierten in Nubien und ersetzt das Christentum. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Im 14. Jahrhundert hat die Regierung zusammen und war geprägt von Ägypten. Bis zum Ende des kolonialistischen, Nubien wurde zwischen Ägypten und Sudan. Nubische Dörfer finden sich nun nördlich von Assuan und die Elephantine Island. Die nubische Menschen leben heute in den großen Städten wie Kairo.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB]Il primo segno di abitanti nel paese è stato ora chiamato Nubia nel quinto millennio aC. Diversi di questi primi monumenti culture possono essere trovati in tutta parti di Africa orientale e la Valle del Nilo. Intorno al 3800 aC, il primo Nubian cultura nata, noto come il Gruppo A. Intorno al 3300 aC, non vi è evidenza di un unico regno che mantenuto interazioni con la cultura della Naqadan Egitto. Questa cultura ha cominciato a declinare nel 28o secolo aC, quando il gruppo B è apparso cultura. Il gruppo B è come il gruppo A, ma più poveri, per motivi ritenuti egiziano invasioni. Nubia era un corridoio di scambi tra l'Egitto e l'Africa tropicale. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Nel 2300 aC, Nubia è stata menzionata per la prima volta nel Vecchio Regno egiziano conti di missioni commerciali. Il commercio con l'Egitto Nubia aumento della ricchezza e la stabilità di una nazione. Per l'egiziano 6a Dinastia, Nubia è stato diviso in una serie di piccoli regni. Questo gruppo C fiorì dal 2240 aC al 2150 aC. Durante il Medio Regno egiziano, è espansa in Nubia per ottenere il controllo sulle rotte commerciali. Gli egiziani che hanno vissuto in Nubia sembrava avere relazioni pacifiche con la gente, ma limitato contatto. L'ordine del giorno della cultura, il Pan Graves, vissuta lungo la riva orientale del fiume Nilo. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Il primo regno di unificare gran parte della regione sono sorte, il Regno di Kerma, che è stato chiamato dopo la sua capitale a Kerma. Dal 1760 aC, il re organizzato diversi progetti di costruzione. Ad un certo punto, anche Kerma venuto vicino a conquistare l'Egitto. Tuttavia, come egiziano potere rilanciato sotto la nuova e ampliata nel Regno Nubiano terre, Kerma è stato distrutto e il nuovo centro amministrativo, Napata, è stato costruito. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Quando gli egiziani tirato fuori della Nubia, a sinistra ci sono tradizioni culturali, che miscelato con il precedente tradizioni. Il Regno di Kush è stato quindi creato, che ha adottato molte tradizioni egiziane, come la costruzione delle piramidi. Sotto la guida del potente leader, Kush conquistato l'Egitto e anche outlasted. Alla fine, sono stati conquistati dalla Assiri e costretti a migrare più a sud, che istituisce la nuova capitale a Meroe. La gente di Meroe conservati molti di loro distinte doganali, mentre ancora adattando egiziano doganali. Un famoso Meroean incidente è quando la loro regina, Candace, svoltasi contro Alessandro Magno, che ha ritirato le sue truppe. Altri potenti regine detenuti contro i Romani. Meroe sarebbe presto incontrare sconfitta da un nuovo regno, Aksum, nel sud. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Dopo essere stato occupato dal regno di Aksum, Nubia è stato diviso in tre piccoli regni: Nobatia, Makuria, e Alodia. Giovanni di Efeso, che registra un sacerdote convertito il re e la sua nobiltà di Nabatia al cristianesimo intorno a 545. Ha anche scritto che Alodia è stato convertito circa 569. Il Regno di Makuria era apparentemente convertiti al cattolicesimo intorno allo stesso anno. Per il 7 ° secolo, Makuria divenne il potere dominante nella regione. E 'stato abbastanza forte da tenere contro il sud di espansione dell'Islam, quando gli arabi hanno preso Egitto. Un trattato di pace è stato firmato tra i nuovi governanti, che si è protratta per cento sei anni. Nel corso del tempo, l'Islam è migrato in Nubia e sostituito cristianesimo. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Nel 14 ° secolo, il governo è crollato ed è stato dominato da Egitto. Entro la fine del colonialista, Nubia è stata suddivisa tra l'Egitto e il Sudan. Nubian villaggi può essere trovato a nord di Assuan e sulla Elefantini Island. Nubiano persone ora vive in grandi città come il Cairo.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB]La primera señal de habitantes en la tierra, ahora llamado Nubia fue en el quinto milenio antes de Cristo. Varios monumentos de las culturas de estos principios se puede encontrar en toda partes del África oriental y del valle del Nilo. Alrededor de 3800 aC, la primera surgió la cultura de Nubia, conocido como el Grupo A. Alrededor de 3300 aC, hay evidencia de un reino unificado que mantiene la interacción con la cultura de Naqadan Alto Egipto. Esta cultura empezó a disminuir en el 28 siglo AC, cuando el Grupo B parecía cultura. El Grupo B es como el Grupo A, más pobres, pero por razones de Egipto cree que las invasiones. Nubia era un corredor de comercio entre Egipto y el Africa tropical. [PARAGRAPH: 2] En 2300 a. de C., Nubia fue mencionada por primera vez en el Viejo Reino de Egipto cuentas de las misiones comerciales. El comercio con Egipto Nubia aumento de la riqueza y la estabilidad como nación. Por el egipcio 6 ª dinastía, Nubia se dividió en una serie de pequeños reinos. Este Grupo C florecido desde 2240 AC a 2150 AC. En el Reino Medio de Egipto, en Nubia ampliado para ganar el control sobre las rutas comerciales. Los egipcios que vivían en Nubia parecía tener relaciones pacíficas con la gente, pero un contacto limitado. El próximo cultura, el Pan Graves, vivió a lo largo de la ribera del East River Nile. [PARAGRAPH: 2] El primer reino de unificar gran parte de la región se produjo, el Reino de Kerma, que fue el nombre de su capital en Kerma. En 1760 a. de C., los reyes organizado diversos proyectos de construcción. En un momento dado, Kerma incluso estuvo cerca de conquistar Egipto. Sin embargo, como el poder de Egipto revivió en el marco del Nuevo Reino y ampliado en las tierras de Nubia, Kerma fue destruido y el nuevo centro administrativo, Napata, fue construido. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Cuando los egipcios se retiraron de Nubia, que la izquierda hay tradiciones culturales, que mezcla con la tradición anterior. El Reino de Kush fue entonces creado, que aprobó muchas tradiciones egipcias, como la construcción de las pirámides. Bajo la dirección de líderes poderosos, Kush conquistó Egipto e incluso outlasted. Eventualmente, que fueron conquistados por los asirios y obligadas a emigrar más al sur, el establecimiento de la nueva capital en Meroe. El pueblo de Meroe conservado muchas de sus diferentes costumbres, a la vez que la adaptación de las aduanas egipcias. Un famoso Meroean incidente es cuando su reina, Candace, que se celebró en contra de Alejandro Magno, que retiró sus tropas. Otras reinas poderosos celebrada en contra de los romanos. Meroe pronto satisfacer derrota por un nuevo reino de Axum, en el sur. [PARAGRAPH: 2] Después de ser ocupado por el reino de Axum, Nubia estaba dividida en tres reinos: Nobatia, Makuria, y Alodia. Juan de Éfeso registros que un sacerdote convertido el rey y sus nobles de Nabatia al cristianismo alrededor de 545. También escribió que Alodia se convirtió en torno a 569. El Reino de Makuria aparentemente se convirtió al catolicismo romano en todo el mismo año. Por el siglo 7, Makuria se convirtió en el poder dominante en la región. Es lo suficientemente fuerte como para resistir contra el sur de la expansión del Islam, cuando los árabes tomaron Egipto. Un tratado de paz fue firmado entre los nuevos gobernantes que duró seiscientos años. Con el tiempo, el islam emigrado en Nubia y se sustituirá el cristianismo. [PARAGRAPH: 2] En el siglo 14, el gobierno se derrumbó y fue dominado por Egipto. A finales de colonialista, Nubia estaba dividida entre Egipto y Sudán. Nubian aldeas ya se encuentra al norte de Asuán y en la isla Elefantina. El pueblo nubio ahora viven en las grandes ciudades como El Cairo.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>	