<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by lcollins (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- Copyright Firaxis Games 2005 -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text - New -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_SCOTLAND_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Scottish Empire</English>
		<French>Écosse</French>
		<German>Schotten Reich</German>
		<Italian>Scozzese Impero</Italian>
		<Spanish>Escocés Imperio</Spanish>
	</TEXT>	
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_SCOTLAND_SHORT_DESC</Tag>
		<English>Scotland</English>
		<French>Écossais</French>
		<German>Schottland</German>
		<Italian>Scozia</Italian>
		<Spanish>Escocia</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_SCOTLAND_ADJECTIVE</Tag>
		<English>Scottish</English>
    <French>
      <Text>écossais:écossaise:écossais:écossaises</Text>
      <Gender>Male:Female:Male:Female</Gender>
      <Plural>0:0:1:1</Plural>
    </French>
		<German>Schotten</German>
		<Italian>Scozzese</Italian>
		<Spanish>Escocés</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_SCOTLAND_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[TAB]The earliest settlement in Scotland may date from as early as 4000 B.C.  Many large structures remain from the later part of the New Stone Age.  The Romans attempted to suppress the militaristic northern tribes.  Eventually, they withdrew south of Hadrian's Wall, which they completed in the year 128 across northern England.  The Picts and Scots, along the Britons, Angles, and the Vikings, all contributed to the establishment of a Scottish kingdom by the 10th and 11th centuries.  [PARAGRAPH: 1] The early years of Scotland's kingdom was characterized by violence.  Shakespeare's "Macbeth" is an example.  In the story, the Scottish king Duncan I is killed by his general Macbeth and his son, Malcolm III, succeeds to the throne.  The 13th century was more peaceful.  However, in 1290, Scottish lords fought over the succession to the throne.  England's King Edward tried but failed to install a king into the Scottish throne.  He then invaded Scotland and declared himself overlord.  The Scots rose against Edward I under the leadership of a great hero, Sir William Wallace.  After Wallace's execution, the revolt continued under the leadership of Robert the Bruce, the leading candidate for the throne.  He was crowned King Robert I in 1306.  He defeated the English at Bannockburn in 1314, and in 1328, the English signed a treaty recognizing Scotland's independence.  [PARAGRAPH: 1] Robert's son David II died childless.  Several nobles struggled for the throne, and the Stuart noble family won.  Robert II, the first Stuart king, was crowned in 1371.  A later Stuart king, James I, and his son James II strengthened the central government.  During this time, trade flourished and universities were founded.  Scotland was usually allied with France against England during these years.  In 1502, James IV tried to strengthen Scotland's ties with England by marrying Margaret Tudor.  Margaret was the daughter of King Henry VII.  But conflicts between James and Henry VIII led to border war.  James was killed at the Battle of Flodden Field in 1513 and was succeeded by his son, James V. [PARAGRAPH: 1] One of Scotland's most famous rulers, Mary, Queen of Scots, James V's daughter, ruled at this time.  She was the last monarch of a separate Scottish kingdom.  In 1603 her son James VI succeeded to the throne of England and Ireland as James I.  With the Act of Union in 1707, England, Ireland, and Scotland were united under one parliament and ruler.  Wales was already under English rule at this time.  Meanwhile, the Scots continued to maintain their own identity. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Ever since the Scots ceased to govern themselves, generations of Scottish nationalists have called for an independent state.  More moderate people have supported devolution, which would return power over to local affairs to an elected Scottish legislature in Edinburgh while leaving foreign affairs in the hands of the British parliament.  A vote on devolution failed in 1979, but another succeeded overwhelmingly in 1997 and home rule was finally approved.  Elections to the new Scottish Parliament were scheduled in 1999.</English>
		<French>[TAB]Les premiers règlement en Ecosse Mai date dès 4000 avant JC Beaucoup de grandes structures restent de la dernière partie du Nouvel Âge de la pierre. Les Romains ont tenté de réprimer les tribus du nord militariste. Éventuellement, ils se retirent au sud du Mur d'Hadrien, qu'ils ont terminé en l'an 128 dans le nord de l'Angleterre. Les Pictes et les Scots, le long des Britanniques, des Angles, et les Vikings, ont tous contribué à la création d'un royaume écossais par les 10e et 11e siècles. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Les premières années du règne de l'Écosse est caractérisée par la violence. Shakespeare's "Macbeth" en est un exemple. Dans l'histoire, le roi écossais Duncan I est tué par ses généraux Macbeth et son fils, Malcolm III, succède sur le trône. Le 13ème siècle a été plus pacifique. Toutefois, en 1290, les seigneurs écossais a combattu sur la succession au trône. England's King Edward tenté mais n'a pas réussi à installer un roi sur le trône écossais. Il a ensuite envahi l'Ecosse et s'est déclaré maître. L'écossais est levée contre Edward I, sous la direction d'un grand héros, Sir William Wallace. Après l'exécution de Wallace, la révolte a continué sous la direction de Robert de Bruce, le premier candidat pour le trône. Il fut couronné roi Robert Ier en 1306. Il a battu les anglais à Bannockburn en 1314, et en 1328, le Français signe un traité reconnaissant l'indépendance de l'Ecosse. [PARAGRAPH 1] Robert II, le fils de David meurt sans enfant. Plusieurs nobles sont battus pour le trône, et à la famille noble Stuart gagné. Robert II, le premier roi Stuart, a été couronné en 1371. A côté Stuart roi Jacques Ier, et son fils Jacques II de renforcer le gouvernement central. Pendant ce temps, le commerce a prospéré et les universités ont été fondées. Ecosse était habituellement alliée avec la France contre l'Angleterre au cours de ces années. En 1502, James IV essayé de renforcer les liens de l'Écosse avec l'Angleterre en épousant Margaret Tudor. Margaret était la fille du roi Henri VII. Mais les conflits entre James et Henry VIII conduit à la guerre frontalière. James a été tué à la bataille de Flodden Field en 1513 et a été succédé par son fils, James V. [POINT: 1] Une des plus célèbres Ecosse gouvernants, Mary Queen of Scots, la fille de James V, a statué en ce moment. Elle a été le dernier monarque d'un royaume distinct écossais. En 1603, son fils Jacques VI a succédé sur le trône d'Angleterre et l'Irlande comme James I. Avec l'Acte d'Union en 1707, l'Angleterre, l'Irlande et l'Ecosse ont été réunis sous un parlement et une règle. Pays de Galles était déjà sous domination anglaise pour le moment. Pendant ce temps, les écossais ont continué à maintenir leur propre identité. [PARAGRAPH 1] Depuis l'écossais cessé de se gouverner eux-mêmes, des générations de nationalistes écossais ont appelé à un État indépendant. Plus modéré, les gens ont appuyé la déconcentration, ce qui reviendrait à pouvoir sur les affaires locales à un législateur élu écossais à Édimbourg, tout en laissant les affaires étrangères entre les mains du parlement britannique. Un vote sur la décentralisation a échoué en 1979, mais un autre a réussi une écrasante majorité en 1997 et la maison règle a été finalement approuvée. Élections du nouveau Parlement écossais étaient prévues en 1999.</French>
		<German>[TAB]Die ältesten Siedlung in Schottland Mai stammen aus so früh wie 4000 v. Chr. Viele große Strukturen bleiben aus der später ein Teil der New Stone Age. Die Römer versuchten zu unterdrücken, die militaristische nördlichen Stämme. Schließlich zog sie südlich von Hadrian's Wall, die sie im Jahr 128 in Nordengland. Die Pikten und Schotten, entlang der Briten, Winkel, und die Wikinger, die alle einen Beitrag zur Schaffung eines schottischen Reich durch die 10. und 11. Jahrhundert. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Die frühen Jahre der schottischen Reiches ist geprägt von Gewalt. Shakespeares "Macbeth" ist ein Beispiel. In der Geschichte, den schottischen König Duncan I getötet von seinem allgemeinen Macbeth und sein Sohn, Malcolm III, die Nachfolge auf den Thron. Das 13. Jahrhundert war eher ruhig. Doch in 1290, Scottish Fürsten kämpfte über die Thronfolge. England's King Edward versucht, die Installation eines Königs in den schottischen Thron. Er erobert Schottland und erklärte sich Oberherr. Die Schotten stieg gegen Edward I unter der Führung eines großen Helden, Sir William Wallace. Nach der Hinrichtung Wallace, der Aufstand unter der Führung von Robert the Bruce, der führende Kandidat für den Thron. Er wurde zum König gekrönt Robert I und 1306. Er besiegte die Engländer bei Bannockburn in 1314 und in 1328, der englische unterzeichnete einen Vertrag zu erkennen, die Unabhängigkeit Schottlands. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Robert's Sohn David II. starb kinderlos. Mehrere Adlige kämpften für den Thron, und der adeligen Familie Stuart gewonnen. Robert II., der erste König Stuart, der 1371 gekrönt wurde. Ein später Stuart König James I., und sein Sohn James II der Zentralregierung gestärkt. Während dieser Zeit, der Handel blühte und Universitäten wurden gegründet. Schottland in der Regel zusammen mit Frankreich gegen England in diesen Jahren. In 1502, James IV versucht, die Beziehungen zu stärken Schottland England durch Heirat mit Margaret Tudor. Margaret war die Tochter von König Heinrich VII.. Aber Konflikte zwischen James und Henry VIII führte zur Grenze Krieg. James umgebracht wurde in der Schlacht von Flodden Field in 1513 gelungen, und wurde von seinem Sohn, James V. [PARAGRAPH: 1] One of Scotland's bekannteste Herrscher, Mary, Queen of Scots, James V's Tochter, entschieden, zu diesem Zeitpunkt. Sie war die letzte Monarch einer eigenen schottischen Reich. In 1603 ihren Sohn James VI erfolgreich auf den Thron von England und Irland als James I. Mit dem Act of Union in 1707, England, Irland und Schottland waren vereint unter einem Parlament und Lineal. Wales war bereits in der Regel Englisch zu dieser Zeit. Unterdessen setzte die Schotten um ihre eigene Identität. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Schon seit den Schotten nicht mehr sich selbst zu regieren, Generationen von schottischen Nationalisten forderten einen unabhängigen Staat. Mehr moderaten Menschen unterstützt haben, Dezentralisierung, die Rückkehr zur Macht über lokale Angelegenheiten zu einer Legislaturperiode gewählt schottischen Edinburgh, während er in der Außenpolitik in den Händen der britischen Parlament. Eine Abstimmung über die Dezentralisierung im Jahr 1979 gescheitert, sondern einem anderen gelang 1997 mit überwältigender Mehrheit in der Regel zu Hause und wurde schließlich genehmigt. Die Wahlen zum neuen schottischen Parlament wurden im Jahr 1999 geplant.</German>
		<Italian>[TAB]I primi insediamenti in Scozia maggio data fin dal 4000 aC Molte grandi strutture di rimanere il più tardi da parte di New Stone Age. Romani ha tentato di sopprimere la militarista tribù del nord. Infine, si ritirò a sud del Vallo di Adriano, che hanno completato l'anno 128 in tutta l'Inghilterra settentrionale. Pitti e scozzese, lungo i britannici, Angles, e la Vichinghi, tutti hanno contribuito alla creazione di un regno scozzese dal 10 ° e 11 ° secolo. [PARAGRAPH: 1] I primi anni del regno di Scozia è caratterizzata dalla violenza. Shakespeare's "Macbeth" è un esempio. E la storia, il re scozzese Duncan I viene ucciso dai suoi generali di Macbeth e di suo figlio, Malcolm III, succede al trono. Il 13 ° secolo è stata più tranquilla. Tuttavia, nel 1290, oltre scozzese signori combattuto la successione al trono. England's King Edward cercato, ma non è riuscita a installare un re in trono scozzese. Egli ha poi invaso la Scozia e si è dichiarato overlord. La rosa scozzese contro Edoardo I, sotto la guida di un grande eroe, Sir William Wallace. Dopo Wallace's esecuzione, la rivolta continuato sotto la guida di Robert il Bruce, il principale candidato per il trono. Egli fu incoronato re Roberto I nel 1306. Egli ha sconfitto gli inglesi a Bannockburn nel 1314, e nel 1328, l'inglese ha firmato un trattato di riconoscere l'indipendenza della Scozia. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Robert figlio di David II morì senza figli. Diversi nobili lottato per il trono, e la nobile famiglia Stuart ha vinto. Robert II, il primo re Stuart, fu incoronato nel 1371. A più tardi Stuart re Giacomo I, e suo figlio Giacomo II rafforzato il governo centrale. Durante questo tempo, il commercio fiorì e università sono state fondate. Scozia era solito alleò con la Francia contro l'Inghilterra nel corso di questi anni. Nel 1502, James IV cercato di rafforzare i legami con la Scozia, Inghilterra sposando Margherita Tudor. Margaret era la figlia del re Enrico VII. Ma i conflitti tra Enrico VIII e James ha portato a guerra di confine. James è stato ucciso nella battaglia di Flodden Field nel 1513 ed è stato succeduto da suo figlio, James V. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Uno dei più famosi Scozia governanti, Maria, Regina di Scozia, la figlia di James V, stabilito in questo momento. Fu l'ultimo monarca di un regno separato scozzese. Nel 1603 suo figlio Giacomo VI, succeduto al trono d'Inghilterra e in Irlanda, come James I. Con l'Atto di Unione nel 1707, in Inghilterra, Irlanda, Scozia, e sono stati uniti sotto un unico parlamento e righello. Galles era già in inglese regola in questo momento. Nel frattempo, gli scozzesi hanno continuato a mantenere la propria identità. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Fin dalla scozzese cessato di governare se stessi, generazioni di nazionalisti scozzesi hanno chiesto uno stato indipendente. Più moderato persone hanno sostenuto devoluzione, che oltre a riprendere il potere locale affari di uno scozzese eletto legislatore a Edimburgo, lasciando la politica estera nelle mani del parlamento britannico. Un voto sulla devolution venuta meno nel 1979, ma un altro riuscito ampiamente nel 1997 e home regola è stata finalmente approvata. Elezioni per il nuovo Parlamento scozzese sono stati programmati nel 1999.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[TAB]Los primeros asentamientos en Escocia fecha a partir de Mayo ya en 4000 aC Muchas grandes estructuras de la parte posterior de la Nueva Edad de Piedra. Los romanos trataron de reprimir la militarista norte de las tribus. Finalmente, se retiraron al sur de la Muralla de Adriano, que se completó en el año 128 a través del norte de Inglaterra. Imágenes y el escocés, a lo largo de los británicos, Angles, y de los vikingos, todos contribuyeron a la creación de un reino de Escocia por la 10 ª y 11 siglos. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Los primeros años del reino de Escocia se caracteriza por la violencia. Shakespeare "Macbeth" es un ejemplo. En la historia, el rey Duncan I de Escocia es asesinado por sus generales Macbeth y su hijo, Malcolm III, sucede en el trono. El siglo 13 fue más pacífico. Sin embargo, en 1290, el escocés luchó más de los señores de la sucesión al trono. England's King Edward intentado, pero no para instalar un rey en el trono de Escocia. A continuación, invadió Escocia, y se declaró jefe supremo. El escocés levanta contra Edward I, bajo la dirección de un gran héroe, Sir William Wallace. Después de la ejecución de Wallace, la rebelión continuó bajo la dirección de Robert de Bruce, el principal candidato para el trono. Fue coronado Rey Robert I en 1306. Él derrotó al Inglés en Bannockburn en 1314, y en 1328, el Inglés firmaron un tratado reconociendo la independencia de Escocia. [PARAGRAPH: 1] el hijo de David Robert II murió sin hijos. Varios nobles lucharon por el trono, y de la noble familia de Stuart ganó. Robert II, el primer rey Stuart, fue coronado en 1371. Un rey Stuart más tarde, Jaime I, y su hijo Jaime II el fortalecimiento de la administración central. Durante este tiempo, el comercio floreció y se fundaron las universidades. Escocia fue generalmente aliado con Francia contra Inglaterra en estos años. En 1502, James IV trató de fortalecer los vínculos de Escocia con Inglaterra por matrimonio con Margaret Tudor. Margarita era hija del rey Enrique VII. Sin embargo, los conflictos entre James y Enrique VIII llevó a la guerra fronteriza. James fue asesinado en la Batalla de Flodden Field en 1513 y fue sucedido por su hijo, James V. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Uno de Escocia más famosa de los gobernantes, María, Reina de escocés, la hija de James V, se pronunció en este momento. Fue el último monarca de un reino de Escocia. En 1603 su hijo James VI de la sucesión al trono de Inglaterra e Irlanda como James I. Con el Acta de Unión en 1707, Inglaterra, Irlanda y Escocia se unieron bajo un solo parlamento y gobernante. País de Gales ya está en Inglés imperio en este momento. Mientras tanto, el escocés siguió manteniendo su propia identidad. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Desde el escocés dejó de gobernarse a sí mismo, generaciones de los nacionalistas escoceses han pedido un estado independiente. Más moderado personas han apoyado la descentralización, que volvería a poder sobre los asuntos locales a un legislador electo de Escocia en Edimburgo, dejando los asuntos exteriores en manos del parlamento británico. Una votación de la devolución no en 1979, sino otro logrado por abrumadora mayoría en 1997 y la regla de origen fue finalmente aprobado. Las elecciones para el nuevo Parlamento escocés se había previsto en 1999.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>	