<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by lcollins (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- Copyright Firaxis Games 2005 -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text - New -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_MARIA_THERESA</Tag>
		<English>Maria Theresa</English>
		<French>Marie-Thérèse</French>
		<German>Maria Theresia</German>
		<Italian>Maria Teresa</Italian>
		<Spanish>María Teresa</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_MARIA_THERESA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Maria Theresa[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Archduchess of Austria[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD]1717 - 1780[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:1][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Maria Theresa was the eldest daughter of Elisabeth Christine of Brunswick-Wolfenbuttel and Emperor Charles VI who allowed her to succeed the Habsburg Monarchy.  Her transition to the throne was all but simple.  Opposition to her succession to the throne led to the War of the Austrian Succession in 1740.  After Emperor Charles VII, who claimed the throne, died in 1745, Maria Theresa claimed the throne for her husband, Francis I.  She was technically the empress consort, but was the de facto ruler of the nation.  In 1745, she also began styling herself as the Holy Roman Empress. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Maria Theresa helped commence financial and educational reforms, promoted commerce, agriculture, and reorganized the army.  Many of her actions strengthened Austria as a whole and its resources.  After a continuous conflict with Prussia, the Seven Years' War and eventually to the War of the Bavarian Succession.  She became the dowager empress after the death of Francis and succession of her son Joseph as emperor in 1765.  Maria Theresa brought unity to the Habsburg Monarchy and is considered one of its most talented rulers. [PARAGRAPH: 1] While Bavaria and France posed a continuous threat to Austria, it was Frederick the Great who became Maria's primary foe during her reign.  Maria Theresa focused the majority of her policies towards the defeat or Prussia.  Because of these reforms, the Treaty of Aix-la-Chapelle gave the Austrian Netherlands back to Maria Theresa.  In exchange, Maria ceded Parma, Piacenza, and Guastalla to the Infante Philip of Spain.  After being defeated in the First and Second Silesian Wars, Maria Theresa began to modernize her realms with the assistance of Freidrich Wilhelm Graf von Gaugwitz.  Of her many reforms, she increased the size of the army by 200% and increased taxes to guarantee a steady income for the military.  She also centralized the government by combining the Austrian and Bohemian chancelleries into one administrative office. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Like other Habsburgs, Maria Theresa was a devout Roman Catholic.  She was educated by Jesuits at Mariazell, and in later life was short of the religious pessimism of other royal figures of her time.  Her conservative outlook involved a poor view of other faiths.  In 1741, she expelled the Jewish people from Prague.  [PARAGRAPH: 1] Maria Theresa dropped Great Britain as an ally and allied herself with Russia and France.  When she felt her army was strong enough, she prepared an attack on Prussia in 1756.  However, it was Frederick II who attacked first, invading Saxony and starting the Seven Years' War.  When Maria Theresa signed the Treaty of Hubertsburg in 1763, the war ended recognizing Prussia as the owner of most of Silesia. [PARAGRAPH: 1] After her husband's death in 1765, Maria Theresa became separated from her people.  Her focus changed to maintaining peace, rather than regaining Silesia.  She named her son, Joseph II, as coregent and Emperor.  However, he received limited powers because she felt he was too haughty for the full responsibilities.  In 1767, Maria Theresa was infected with smallpox.  However, she recovered and became a strong supporter of inoculation.  In her later years, she focused on reforming laws along the lines of enlightened absolutism. [PARAGRAPH: 1] In 1771, she and Joseph II issued to Robot Patent, a reform that regulated the serf's payments in her lands.  Other reforms included outlawing witch-burning and torture, and taking capital punishment the off the penal code.  In 1772, Maria Theresa founded the Imperial and Royal Academy of Science and Literature in Brussels.  Mandatory education was introduced in 1774 in order to form an educated class of citizens, from which civil servants were recruited.  Maria Theresa continued issuing various police laws throughout Austria.  She died in 1780 in Vienna, being the only female to rule the Habsburg Dynasty, which lasted 650 years.  Her son Joseph II was her successor.</English>
		<French>[H1]Marie-Thérèse[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Archiduchesse d'Autriche[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Dates :[\BOLD]1717 - 1780[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:1][BOLD]Biographie :[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Maria Theresa est la fille aînée de Christine Elisabeth de Brunswick Wolfenbuttel, et l'empereur Charles VI, qui lui a permis de réussir la monarchie des Habsbourg. Sa transition vers le trône était tout sauf simples. L'opposition à sa succession au trône conduit à la guerre de Succession d'Autriche en 1740. Après l'empereur Charles VII, qui a revendiqué le trône, est mort en 1745, Maria Theresa revendiqué le trône à son mari, François I. Elle était techniquement consort de l'impératrice, mais était de facto le dirigeant de la nation. En 1745, elle a aussi commencé style elle-même comme la Sainte impératrice romaine. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Maria Theresa aidé commencer financières et les réformes de l'éducation, de promouvoir le commerce, l'agriculture, et réorganisation de l'armée. Beaucoup de ses actions de renforcement de l'Autriche dans son ensemble et de ses ressources. Au terme d'un conflit avec la Prusse, la guerre de Sept Ans et, finalement, à la guerre de Succession de Bavière. Elle est devenue la dowager impératrice après la mort de François et de la succession de son fils Joseph empereur en 1765. Maria Theresa unité portées à la monarchie des Habsbourg et est considéré comme l'un de ses dirigeants les plus talentueux. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Alors que la Bavière et la France fait peser une menace continue à l'Autriche, il a été Frédéric le Grand, qui est devenu le principal ennemi Maria durant son règne. Maria Theresa concentré la majorité de ses politiques en faveur de la défaite ou la Prusse. En raison de ces réformes, le traité d'Aix-la-Chapelle a donné les Pays-Bas autrichiens retour à Marie Thérèse. En échange, Maria cède Parme, Plaisance, Guastalla et à l'Infante Philip de l'Espagne. Après avoir été battu lors des Première et Deuxième Guerres de Silésie, Maria Theresa a commencé à moderniser son royaume avec l'aide de Freidrich Wilhelm von Gaugwitz. De ses nombreuses réformes, elle a augmenté les effectifs de l'armée de 200% et une augmentation des impôts pour assurer un revenu stable pour les militaires. Elle a également centralisé, le gouvernement autrichien en combinant les chancelleries et de Bohême dans un bureau administratif. [PARAGRAPH: 1] À l'instar d'autres Habsbourg, Maria Theresa était une fervente catholique. Elle a été instruite par les Jésuites à Mariazell, et en fin de vie a été de courte de la religieuse pessimisme des autres personnalités royales de son temps. Ses perspectives conservatrices impliqué une mauvaise opinion des autres religions. EN 1741, elle a expulsé le peuple juif de Prague. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Maria Theresa chuté Grande-Bretagne comme des alliés et s'est alliée avec la Russie et la France. Quand elle a senti son armée est assez forte, elle a préparé une attaque contre la Prusse en 1756. Toutefois, il a été Frédéric II, qui a attaqué en premier, envahissent la Saxe et de commencer la guerre de Sept Ans. Lorsque Maria Theresa signé le Traité de Hubertsburg en 1763, la guerre a pris fin en reconnaissant la Prusse en tant que propriétaire de la majeure partie de la Silésie. [PARAGRAPH: 1] Après le décès de son mari en 1765, Maria Theresa devient séparée de son peuple. Sa tendance a changé pour le maintien de la paix, plutôt que de reconquérir la Silésie. Elle a nommé son fils, Joseph II, comme coregent et de l'empereur. Cependant, il a reçu des pouvoirs limités, car elle a estimé qu'il était trop arrogant pour la totalité des responsabilités. En 1767, Maria Theresa a été infecté par la variole. Toutefois, elle a récupéré et est devenu un fervent partisan de l'inoculation. Dans ses dernières années, elle s'est concentrée sur la réforme des lois allant dans le sens de l'absolutisme éclairé. [PARAGRAPH: 1] En 1771, elle et Joseph II brevets délivrés aux robots, une réforme qui régissaient le serf dans ses paiements de terres. D'autres réformes figurent proscrivant sorcières brûlant et de la torture, et prenant le large de la peine capitale du code pénal. En 1772, Maria Theresa fondé l'Académie royale et impériale de la science et de la littérature à Bruxelles. L'enseignement obligatoire a été introduite en 1774 afin de former une classe de citoyens instruits, dont les fonctionnaires ont été recrutés. Maria Theresa continué délivrance différentes lois de police dans toute l'Autriche. Elle est décédée en 1780 à Vienne, étant la seule femme à la règle de la dynastie des Habsbourg, qui a duré 650 ans. Son fils Joseph II était son successeur.</French>
		<German>[H1]Maria Theresia[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Erzherzogin von Österreich[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lebte:[\BOLD]1717 - 1780[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:1][BOLD]Hintergrund:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Maria Theresia war die älteste Tochter von Elisabeth Christine von Braunschweig - Wolfenbüttel und Kaiser Karl VI, der sich ihr Erfolg der Habsburger Monarchie. Ihrem Übergang zum Thron war aber einfach. Widerspruch zu ihrem Thronfolge führte zu dem Krieg des österreichischen Erbfolgekrieg 1740. Nach Kaiser Karl VII., die behauptet, den Thron, starb 1745, Maria Theresia beansprucht den Thron für ihren Mann, Franz I. Sie war technisch die Kaiserin Gefährtin, war aber der de facto Herrscher des Landes. Im Jahre 1745, begann sie auch Styling selbst als das Heilige Römische Kaiserin. [ABSATZ: 1] Maria Theresia geholfen beginnen finanzielle und pädagogische Reformen, gefördert Handel, Landwirtschaft und der Armee reorganisiert. Viele ihrer Aktionen gestärkt werden Österreich als Ganzes und ihrer Ressourcen. Nach einem ständigen Konflikt mit Preußen, des Siebenjährigen Krieges und schließlich zu dem Krieg der Bayerischen Erbfolgekrieg. Sie wurde die Kaiserin Witwe nach dem Tod des Franziskus und der Abfolge von ihrem Sohn Joseph als Kaiser in 1765. Maria Theresia brachte Einheit in der Habsburger Monarchie und gilt als einer der talentiertesten Herrscher. [ABSATZ: 1] Während Bayern und Frankreich stellte eine ständige Bedrohung für Österreich, es war Friedrich der Große, Maria wurde in erster Linie Feind während ihrer Regierungszeit. Maria Theresia konzentrierte sich die Mehrheit ihrer Politik gegenüber der Niederlage oder Preußen. Aufgrund dieser Reformen, den Vertrag von Aix la Chapelle gab der österreichischen Niederlande zurück zu Maria Theresia. Im Gegenzug, Maria abgetretenen Parma, Piacenza und Guastalla an den Infanten Philipp von Spanien. Nach der Niederlage im Ersten und Zweiten Schlesischen Kriege, Maria Theresia begann zu modernisieren, ihre Bereiche mit Hilfe von Freidrich Wilhelm Graf von Gaugwitz. Ihrer vielen Reformen, sie erhöht die Größe der Armee um 200% und höhere Steuern zu garantieren, ein geregeltes Einkommen für das Militär. Sie auch zentral die Regierung durch die Kombination der österreichischen und böhmischen Kanzleien in einer Verwaltungsbehörde. [ABSATZ: 1] Wie andere Habsburger, Maria Theresia war ein gläubiger römisch-katholisch. Sie wurde von den Jesuiten in Mariazell, und im späteren Leben war kurz der religiösen Pessimismus der anderen königlichen Zahlen ihrer Zeit. Ihre konservativen Ausblick an einen schlechten Blick auf andere Religionen. IN 1741, sie trieben die Juden aus Prag. [ABSATZ: 1] Maria Theresia ging Großbritannien als Verbündeter und verbündeten sich mit Russland und Frankreich. Wenn sie das Gefühl hatte, ihre Armee sei stark genug, sie bereit, einen Angriff auf die Preußen 1756. Allerdings war es Friedrich II., der erste Angriff, der Invasion Sachsen und Starten des Siebenjährigen Krieges. Wenn Maria Theresia unterzeichnet den Vertrag von Hubertsburg 1763 endete der Krieg in Anerkennung Preußen als Eigentümer der meisten Schlesien. [ABSATZ: 1] Nach dem Tod ihres Mannes im 1765, Maria Theresia wurde getrennt von ihren Menschen. Ihr Schwerpunkt auf die Erhaltung des Friedens, anstatt wieder in Schlesien. Sie benannt ihrem Sohn, Joseph II., Kaiser und Mitregenten. Allerdings erhielt er beschränkte Befugnisse, weil sie das Gefühl hatte, er war zu stolz für die volle Verantwortung. Im Jahre 1767, Maria Theresia wurde mit Pocken infiziert. Doch sie erholte sich und wurde ein starker Befürworter der Impfung. In ihren späteren Jahren hat sie sich auf die Reform der Gesetze im Sinne des aufgeklärten Absolutismus. [ABSATZ: 1] In 1771, die sie und Joseph II. ausgestellt Robot Patent, eine Reform, reguliert die Leibeigener der Zahlungen in ihrem Land. Weitere Reformen sind Verbot Hexe - Brennen und Folter, die Todesstrafe und die aus dem Strafgesetzbuch. Im Jahre 1772, Maria Theresia gegründet, die Imperial und Königliche Akademie der Wissenschaften und Literatur in Brüssel. Obligatorische Ausbildung wurde im Jahre 1774 im Hinblick auf eine gebildete Klasse der Bürger, von denen Beamte wurden eingestellt. Maria Theresia setzte die Ausstellung verschiedene Gesetze Polizei in ganz Österreich. Sie starb im Jahre 1780 in Wien, die einzige weibliche Regel Dynastie der Habsburger, die seit 650 Jahren. Ihr Sohn Joseph II. war ihr Nachfolger.</German>
		<Italian>[H1]Maria Teresa[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Arciduchessa d'Austria[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Vita:[\BOLD]1717 - 1780[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:1][BOLD]Informazioni:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]Maria Teresa è stata la figlia maggiore di Elisabeth Christine di Brunswick - Wolfenbuttel e Carlo VI, che hanno permesso di riuscire Monarchia degli Asburgo. La sua transizione verso il trono, ma è stato tutto semplice. Opposizione alla sua successione al trono ha portato alla guerra di successione austriaca nel 1740. Dopo l'imperatore Carlo VII, che hanno rivendicato il trono, morì nel 1745, Maria Teresa rivendicato il trono di suo marito, Francesco I. Era tecnicamente l'imperatrice consorte, ma de facto, è stato il dominatore della nazione. Nel 1745, ha iniziato Styling anche se stessa come il Sacro Romano imperatrice. [PARAGRAFO: 1] Maria Teresa contribuito a cominciare finanziaria e le riforme educative, di promozione del commercio, dell'agricoltura, e riorganizzato l'esercito. Molte delle sue azioni rafforzato l'Austria nel suo complesso e delle sue risorse. Dopo un continuo conflitto con la Prussia, il Sette Anni 'Guerra e infine alla guerra di successione bavarese. Ella divenne il dowager imperatrice dopo la morte di Francesco e la successione del figlio Giuseppe come imperatore nel 1765. Maria Teresa unità portato alla Habsburg Monarchia ed è considerato uno dei più dotati governanti. [PARAGRAFO: 1] Mentre Baviera e la Francia pone una continua minaccia per l'Austria, è stato Federico il Grande, che è diventato il principale nemico Maria durante il suo regno. Maria Teresa concentrata la maggior parte della sua politica verso la sconfitta o di Prussia. A causa di queste riforme, il trattato di Aix -la Chapelle - Paesi Bassi ha dato l'austriaco torna a Maria Teresa. In cambio, Maria ceduto Parma, Piacenza e Guastalla a Filippo Infante di Spagna. Dopo essere stato sconfitto nella prima e seconda guerra Silesiana, Maria Teresa ha iniziato a modernizzare il suo regno con l'assistenza di Freidrich Wilhelm von Gaugwitz. Molte delle sue riforme, ha aumentato le dimensioni dell 'esercito del 200% e un aumento delle imposte per garantire un reddito stabile per il militare. Ha anche centralizzato combinando il governo austriaco e boemo cancellerie in un ufficio amministrativo. [PARAGRAFO: 1] Come altri Asburgo, Maria Teresa era una devota cattolica romana. E 'stata istruita da gesuiti a Mariazell, e più tardi nella vita è stata breve pessimismo dei religiosi di altre cifre reali del suo tempo. La sua prospettiva conservatrice ha coinvolto una scarsa considerazione di altre fedi. NEL 1741, ha espulso il popolo ebraico di Praga. [PARAGRAFO: 1] Maria Teresa abbandonato la Gran Bretagna come un alleato e si allearono con la Russia e la Francia. Quando ha sentito il suo esercito è stato abbastanza forte, ha preparato un attacco alla Prussia nel 1756. Tuttavia, è stato Federico II, che hanno attaccato in primo luogo, invadendo Sassonia e di partenza dei Sette Anni 'guerra. Quando Maria Teresa firmato il trattato di Hubertsburg nel 1763, la guerra si è conclusa Prussia riconoscere come il proprietario della maggior parte della Slesia. [PARAGRAFO: 1] Dopo la morte del marito nel 1765, Maria Teresa divenne separato dal suo popolo. Cambiato la sua attenzione per il mantenimento della pace, piuttosto che riconquistare la Slesia. Ha il nome di suo figlio, Giuseppe II, come coregent e imperatore. Tuttavia, egli ha ricevuto poteri limitati, perché ha ritenuto che fosse troppo arroganti per la piena responsabilità. Nel 1767, Maria Teresa è stato infettato con il vaiolo. Tuttavia, è guarita ed è diventato un grande sostenitore di inoculazione. Nel suo anno più tardi, ha focalizzato sulla riforma delle leggi sulla falsariga di assolutismo illuminato. [PARAGRAFO: 1] Nel 1771, lei e Giuseppe II del brevetto rilasciato a Robot, una riforma che regolamentato il serf di pagamenti nella sua terre. Altre riforme che proibisce la strega - inclusa la combustione e la tortura, la pena capitale e tenendo spento il codice penale. Nel 1772, Maria Teresa fondata Imperiale e Reale Accademia di Scienza e Letteratura, a Bruxelles. L'istruzione obbligatoria è stata introdotta nel 1774 al fine di formare una classe di cittadini istruiti, da cui i dipendenti pubblici sono stati assunti. Maria Teresa continuato rilascio varie leggi di polizia in tutta l'Austria. Morì nel 1780 a Vienna, essendo l'unica donna a governare la dinastia Asburgo, che è durata 650 anni. Suo figlio Giuseppe II è stato il suo successore.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[H1]María Teresa[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Archiduquesa de Austria[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Vivi&#243;:[\BOLD]1717 - 1780[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:1][BOLD]Historia:[\BOLD][PARAGRAPH:1]María Teresa era la hija mayor de Christine Elisabeth de Brunswick Wolfenbuttel - y el emperador Carlos VI, que le ha permitido tener éxito la monarquía Habsburgo. Su transición al trono, pero era todo sencillo. La oposición a su sucesión al trono llevaron a la Guerra de la Sucesión de Austria en 1740. Después el emperador Carlos VII, que ha reivindicado el trono, murió en 1745, María Teresa reclamado el trono de su marido, Francisco I. Ella era técnicamente la emperatriz consorte, pero de hecho fue el gobernante de la nación. En 1745, ella comenzó también a sí misma como el estilo Holy Roman Empress. [APARTADO: 1] María Teresa ayudó a comenzar financiera y las reformas de la educación, promueve el comercio, la agricultura, y reorganizó el ejército. Muchas de sus acciones de fortalecimiento de Austria en su conjunto y de sus recursos. Después de un continuo conflicto con Prusia, el Seven Years' War y finalmente a la Guerra de la Sucesión Bávara. Se convirtió en la dowager emperatriz después de la muerte de Francisco y de la sucesión de su hijo Joseph como emperador en 1765. Maria Theresa trajo unidad a la monarquía Habsburgo, y se considera uno de sus más talentosos gobernantes. [APARTADO: 1] Si bien Bavaria y Francia que plantea una amenaza continua para Austria, es Federico el Grande, quien se convirtió en su principal enemigo Maria durante su reinado. Maria Theresa centrado la mayoría de sus políticas hacia la derrota o Prusia. Debido a estas reformas, el Tratado de Aix la Chapelle - dieron la vuelta a los Países Bajos de Austria Maria Theresa. A cambio, cedió Maria Parma, Piacenza y Guastalla para el Infante Felipe de España. Después de ser derrotado en la Primera y Segunda Guerras de Silesia, Maria Theresa comenzó a modernizar su reino con la ayuda de Freidrich Wilhelm Graf Von Gaugwitz. Muchas de sus reformas, que aumentó el tamaño del ejército en un 200% y un aumento de los impuestos para garantizar un ingreso constante para los militares. También centralizada por el gobierno austriaco y la combinación de las cancillerías de Bohemia en una oficina administrativa. [APARTADO: 1] Al igual que otros Habsburgo, María Teresa fue un devoto católico romano. Fue educado por los jesuitas en Mariazell, y más tarde en la vida es corta pesimismo de los religiosos de otras cifras reales de su tiempo. Su visión conservadora que participan una mala opinión de otros credos. EN 1741, que expulsó a los judíos de Praga. [APARTADO: 1] Maria Theresa disminuyó Gran Bretaña como aliado y aliados a sí misma con Rusia y Francia. Cuando ella sentía su ejército era lo suficientemente fuerte, se preparó un ataque a Prusia en 1756. Sin embargo, se Frederick II que atacaron primero, invadiendo Sajonia y de iniciar el Seven Years' War. Maria Theresa Cuando firmaron el Tratado de Hubertsburg en 1763, la guerra terminó reconociendo Prusia como propietario de la mayor parte de Silesia. [APARTADO: 1] Después de la muerte de su marido en 1765, María Teresa se convirtió separada de su pueblo. Su cambiado de enfoque para el mantenimiento de la paz, en lugar de recuperar Silesia. Ella nombró a su hijo, Joseph II, como coregent y Emperador. Sin embargo, recibió poderes limitados porque ella sentía que él era demasiado altivo para la plena responsabilidades. En 1767, María Teresa fue infectada con la viruela. Sin embargo, se recuperó y se convirtió en un firme defensor de la inoculación. En sus últimos años, se ha centrado en la reforma de las leyes a lo largo de las líneas de absolutismo ilustrado. [APARTADO: 1] En 1771, ella y José II a los robots de Patentes, una reforma que regula el siervo de los pagos en sus tierras. Otras reformas incluyen la prohibición de la quema de brujas y la tortura, y teniendo frente a la pena capital del Código Penal. En 1772, Maria Theresa Imperial y fundó la Real Academia de Ciencias y Literatura en Bruselas. La educación obligatoria se introdujo en 1774 con el fin de formar una clase de educación de los ciudadanos, a partir de la cual los funcionarios públicos han sido contratados. Maria Theresa siguió la emisión de diferentes leyes de policía en toda Austria. Murió en 1780 en Viena, al ser la única mujer a la regla la dinastía Habsburgo, que duró 650 años. Su hijo Joseph II fue su sucesor.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>AI_DIPLO_FIRST_CONTACT_LEADER_MARIA_THERESA_1</Tag>
		<English>It is a pleasure to meet you, [CT_NAME]. History is constantly teaching, but it does not find many pupils, so look closely at the world around you.</English>
		<French>C'est un plaisir de vous rencontrer, [CT_NAME]. L'histoire ne cesse de nous enseigner, mais elle ne trouve pas beaucoup d'élèves, alors regarde attentivement le monde autour de toi.</French>
		<German>Es ist ein Vergnügen, Sie kennen zu lernen, [CT_NAME]. Die Geschichte ist ständig Lehre, aber es läßt sich nicht finden viele Schüler, so dass sehr genau auf die Welt um sich herum.</German>
		<Italian>E 'un piacere incontrarvi, [CT_NAME]. È in costante insegnamento della storia, ma non trovano molti alunni, in modo da vicino il mondo che vi circonda.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Es un placer conocerte, [CT_NAME]. La historia está en constante enseñanza, pero no encuentra muchos alumnos, por lo que examinar de cerca el mundo que te rodea.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>